<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 04:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Dirac quantum criticality in twisted double bilayer transition metal dichalcogenides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04561</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04561v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the phase diagram of moir\'e double bilayer transition metal dichalcogenides with ABBA stacking as a function of twist angle and applied pressure. At hole filling $\nu = 2$ per moir\'e unit cell, the noninteracting system hosts a Dirac semimetal with graphene-like low-energy bands in the moir\'e Brillouin zone. At small twist angles, the Fermi velocity is reduced and interactions dominate the low-temperature behavior. A strong-coupling analysis identifies insulating ferromagnetic and antiferromagnetic ground-state candidates, characterized by spin-density modulations set by the moir\'e scale. Using a realistic continuum model with long-range Coulomb interactions, we perform self-consistent Hartree-Fock calculations to study the competition between these states. Varying the twist angle or pressure drives a transition from a Dirac semimetal to an antiferromagnetic insulator, which breaks SU(2) spin rotation and two-fold lattice rotation symmetries. This semimetal-to-insulator transition is continuous and belongs to the (2+1)D relativistic Gross-Neveu-Heisenberg universality class with $N = 2$ four-component Dirac fermions. Finite heterostrain, relevant in realistic samples, induces a crossover from Gross-Neveu-Heisenberg universality at intermediate temperatures to conventional (2+1)D Heisenberg criticality at the lowest temperatures. Further decreasing the twist angle can cause a level crossing from the antiferromagnetic insulator into a ferromagnetic insulator with spin-split bands. Our results provide a comprehensive theoretical framework that complements and elucidates recent experiments in twisted double bilayer WSe$_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04561v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Biedermann, Lukas Janssen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconducting pairing symmetries in charge-ordered kagom\'e metals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04571</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04571v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the superconducting state in a kagom\'e lattice, with intertwined charge order and time-reversal symmetry-breaking loop current, using self-consistent Bogoliubov-de Gennes formalism to find the emergent pairing symmetries. Using local and nearest-neighbor attractive interactions, treated within Hartree-Fock mean-field approximation, we obtain all possible pairing symmetries in position space. Our findings indicate that the uniform $s$-wave symmetry, arising in the absence of the charge order and the loop current, modifies to a pair density wave of $s$-wave symmetry of 2$\times$2 lattice periodicity in the presence of the charge order, and a chiral pair density wave of $d_{x^2-y^2}\!+\!id_{xy}$-wave symmetry of the same 2$\times$2 periodicity in the presence of the charge order and loop current order, in both onsite and nearest-neighbor channels. In the absence of inversion symmetry, such as in the thin-film geometry, Rashba spin-orbit coupling appears, inducing an additional nearest-neighbor triplet $p_x\pm ip_y$-wave pairing. The results are relevant to superconductivity found in $A$V$_{3}$Sb$_{5}$ ($A$ = K, Rb, Cs), coexisting with a charge order that breaks time-reversal symmetry. We discuss fingerprints of these different pairing symmetries in scanning tunneling microscopy experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04571v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pujita Das, Parth Bahuguna, Tulika Maitra, Narayan Mohanta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strongly Entangled Kondo and Kagome Lattices and the Emergent Magnetic Ground State in Heavy-Fermion Kagome Metal YbV$_6$Sn$_6$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04641v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Applying angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy and density functional theory calculations, we present compelling spectroscopic evidence demonstrating the intertwining and mutual interaction between the Kondo and kagome sublattices in heavy-fermion intermetallic compound YbV$_6$Sn$_6$. We reveal the Yb 4$f$-derived states near the Fermi level, along with the presence of bulk kagome bands and topological surface states. We unveil strong interactions between the 4$f$ and itinerant electrons, where the kagome bands hosting the Dirac fermions and van Hove singularities predominate. Such findings are well described using a $c$-$f$ hybridization model. On the other hand, our systematic characterization of magnetic properties demonstrates an unusually enhanced antiferromagnetic ordering, where the kagome-derived van Hove singularities near $E_F$ play a vital role in determining the unconventional nature of the Ruderman-Kittel-Kasuya-Yosida interaction and Kondo coupling. These unique kagome-state-mediated exchange interactions have never been reported before and could lead to a novel phase diagram and various quantum critical behaviors in YbV$_6$Sn$_6$ and its siblings. Our results not only expand the family of exotic quantum phases entangled with kagome structure to the strongly correlated regime, but also establish YbV$_6$Sn$_6$ as an unprecedented platform to explore unconventional many-body physics beyond the standard Kondo picture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04641v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/sqbn-vtcj</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Rui Lou, Max Mende, Riccardo Vocaturo, Hao Zhang, Qingxin Dong, Man Li, Pengfei Ding, Erjian Cheng, Zhiguang Liao, Yu Zhang, Junfa Lin, Reza Firouzmandi, Vilmos Kocsis, Laura T. Corredor, Yurii Prots, Oleksandr Suvorov, Anupam Jana, Jun Fujii, Ivana Vobornik, Oleg Janson, Wenliang Zhu, Jeroen van den Brink, Cornelius Krellner, Minghu Pan, Bosen Wang, Tianlong Xia, Jinguang Cheng, Shancai Wang, Claudia Felser, Bernd B\"uchner, Sergey Borisenko, Rong Yu, Denis V. Vyalikh, Alexander Fedorov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermoelectric transport in graphene under strain fields modeled by Dirac oscillators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04704</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04704v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Graphene has emerged as a paradigmatic material in condensed matter physics due to its exceptional electronic, mechanical, and thermal properties. A deep understanding of its thermoelectric transport behavior is crucial for the development of novel nanoelectronic and energy-harvesting devices. In this work, we investigate the thermoelectric transport properties of monolayer graphene subjected to randomly distributed localized strain fields, which locally induce impurity-like perturbations. These strain-induced impurities are modeled via 2D Dirac oscillators, capturing the coupling between pseudorelativistic charge carriers and localized distortions in the lattice. Employing the semiclassical Boltzmann transport formalism, we compute the relaxation time using a scattering approach tailored to the Dirac oscillator potential. From this framework, we derive analytical expressions for the electrical conductivity, Seebeck coefficient, and thermal conductivity. The temperature dependence of the scattering centers density is also investigated. Our results reveal how strain modulates transport coefficients, highlighting the interplay between mechanical deformations and thermoelectric performance in graphene. This study provides a theoretical foundation for strain engineering in thermoelectric graphene-based devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04704v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/3r17-kfy7</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Juan A. Ca\~nas, Daniel A. Bonilla, A. Mart\'in-Ruiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$^{51}$V NMR evidence for interlayer-modulated charge order and a first-order low-temperature transition in CsV$_3$Sb$_5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04724</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04724v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Charge order in the kagome superconductor CsV$_3$Sb$_5$ exhibits a complex three-dimensional organization and intermediate-temperature anomalies whose bulk character has remained unsettled. We use orientation-dependent $^{51}$V NMR as a site-selective probe to determine the stacking of the charge density wave (CDW) state and its thermal evolution. Below $T_{\mathrm{CDW}}\!\approx\!94$~K, the field-linear splitting of the $^{51}$V central transition together with the anisotropy of the Knight-shift tensor identify an interlayer-modulated $3\mathbf{q}$ CDW whose local environments are consistent with a four-layer $2\times2\times4$ stacking with mixed trihexagonal/Star-of-David distortions, in agreement with synchrotron x-ray determinations. For comparison, RbV$_3$Sb$_5$ serves as a reference exhibiting a uniform trihexagonal $2\times2\times2$ stacking, allowing us to isolate features unique to the $2\times2\times4$ state in CsV$_3$Sb$_5$. With $\mathbf{H}_0\!\parallel\!c$, the $^{51}$V quadrupolar satellites through the intermediate temperature scale near $T_{\mathrm{CO}}\!\approx\!65$ K reorganize into two well-resolved electric-field-gradient manifolds that coexist over a finite interval; their relative spectral weights interchange on cooling while the total integrated satellite intensity remains conserved and $\nu_Q$ within each manifold is nearly temperature independent. The coexistence without critical broadening, together with conserved intensity, provides bulk evidence consistent with a first-order charge-order transition near $T_{\mathrm{CO}}$. Our measurements do not resolve whether this lower-temperature transition corresponds to a distinct in-plane order or a reorganization of the $3\mathbf{q}$ state; rather, they delimit this window and provide bulk, site-resolved constraints that connect prior reported anomalies to a thermodynamic first-order transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04724v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoling Wang, Arneil P. Reyes, Hrishit Banerjee, Andrea N. Capa Salinas, Stephen Wilson, Brenden R. Ortiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surface reconstruction and orthogonal decoupling in SrAl4 and EuAl4</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04742</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04742v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Surface-induced symmetry breaking in quantum materials can stabilize exotic electronic phases distinct from those in the bulk, yet its momentum-space manifestations remain elusive due to domain-averaging effects. Here, using angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) and scanning tunneling microscopy (STM), we present a microscopic investigation of the electronic structures of SrAl4 and EuAl4, layered tetragonal intermetallic compounds that exhibit well-characterized incommensurate charge-density-wave (CDW) transitions. Below the CDW transition temperatures, we uncover linearly dispersing electronic states and pronounced unidirectional replica bands orthogonal to the bulk CDW wave vector, evidencing the emergence of an in-plane C4 symmetry-breaking electronic order that is not dictated by the bulk incommensurate CDW. STM measurements further reveal a 1 times 2 surface reconstruction with quasi-one-dimensional modulations and half-unit-cell steps, traced to ordered 50 percent Sr/Eu vacancies, which vanish irreversibly upon thermal cycling, indicating decoupled surface and bulk orders. These findings establish SrAl4 and EuAl4 as model platforms for exploring surface-confined nematicity and emergent low-dimensional phases in quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04742v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tongrui Li, Leiyuan Chen, Jian Yuan, Zhengtai Liu, Yichen Yang, Zhicheng Jiang, Jianyang Ding, Jiayu Liu, Jishan Liu, Zhe Sun, Yanfeng Guo, Tong Zhang, Dawei Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cone-dependent retro and specular Andreev reflections in AA-stacked bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04841</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04841v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We theoretically study the Andreev reflection (AR) in AA-stacked bilayer graphene/superconductor (AABG/SC) junction. AABG has a linear gapless energy band with two shifted Dirac cones and the electronic states are described by the cone indices. The results indicate that the property of AR strongly depends on the cone degree of freedom. In the absence of the inter-layer potential difference, only intra-cone AR and normal reflection (NR) could occur, and the inter-cone process is forbidden. By adjusting the potential, the intra-cone AR can be specular AR (SAR) in one cone and it is retro-AR (RAR) in the other cone. The existence of the inter-layer potential difference would lead to the inter-cone scattering. As a result, double ARs and double NRs can take place between the two cones. The inter-cone SAR could happen in a broad potential region. Furthermore, the inter-cone retro-NR (RNR) could happen as well. The switch between SAR and RAR, and the switch between specular NR (SNR) and RNR can be achieved by regulating the potential. Therefore, different cone carriers can be separated spatially based on the RAR and SAR. The cone-dependent Andreev conductance may be separately measured near the critical values where RAR crosses over to SAR.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04841v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review B 108, 195425 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Tao Lu, Qing-Feng Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coexisting Kagome and Heavy Fermion Flat Bands in YbCr$_6$Ge$_6$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04902</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04902v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Flat bands, emergent in strongly correlated electron systems, stand at the frontier of condensed matter physics, providing fertile ground for unconventional quantum phases. Recent observations of dispersionless bands at the Fermi level in kagome lattice open the possibility of unifying the disjoint paradigms of topology and correlation-driven heavy fermion liquids. Here, we report the unprecedented coexistence of these mechanisms in the layered kagome metal YbCr6Ge6. At high temperatures, an intrinsic kagome flat band-arising from the frustrated hopping on the kagome lattice-dominates the Fermi level. Upon cooling, localized Yb 4f-states hybridize with the topological kagome flat bands, transforming this state into the Kondo resonance states that are nearly dispersionless across the entire Brillouin zone. Crystalline symmetry forbids hybridization along specific high-symmetry lines, which stabilizes Dirac crossings of heavy-fermion character. Topological analysis of the resulting gaps reveals both trivial and nontrivial Z2 invariants, establishing the emergence of a Dirac-Kondo semimetal phase. Taken together, these results identify YbCr6Ge6 as a prototype of a topological heavy-fermion system and a platform where geometric frustration, strong correlations, and topology converge, with broad implications for correlated quantum matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04902v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanoh Lee, Churlhi Lyi, Taehee Lee, Hyeonhui Na, Jinyoung Kim, Sangjae Lee, Younsik Kim, Anil Rajapitamahuni, Asish K. Kundu, Elio Vescovo, Byeong-Gyu Park, Changyoung Kim, Charles H. Ahn, Frederick J. Walker, Ji Seop Oh, Bo Gyu Jang, Youngkuk Kim, Byungmin Sohn, Tuson Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning-Assisted Weak Beam Identification in Dark-Field X-ray Microscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05017</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05017v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dislocations control the mechanical behavior of crystalline materials, yet their quantitative characterization in bulk has remained elusive. Transmission Electron Microscopy provides atomic-scale resolution but is restricted to thin foils, limiting relevance to structural performance. Dark-field X-ray microscopy (DFXM) has recently opened access to three-dimensional, non-destructive imaging of dislocations in macroscopic crystals. A critical bottleneck, however, is the reliable identification of weak- versus strong-beam conditions. Weak-beam imaging enhances dislocation contrast, while strong-beam conditions are dominated by multiple scattering and obscure interpretation. Current practice depends on manual classification by specialists, which is subjective, slow, and incompatible with the scale of modern experiments. Here, we introduce a deep learning framework that automates this task using a lightweight convolutional neural network trained on small, hand-labeled datasets. By enabling robust, rapid, and scalable identification of imaging conditions, this approach transforms DFXM into a high-throughput tool, unlocking statistically significant studies of dislocation dynamics in bulk materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05017v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Benhadjira, C. Detlefs, S. Borgi, V. Favre-Nicolin, C. Yildirim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tuning Magneto-Optical Zero-Reflection via Dual-Channel Hybrid Magnonics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05022v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multi-channel coupling in hybrid systems makes an attractive testbed not only because of the distinct advantages entailed in each constituent mode, but also the opportunity to leverage interference among the various excitation pathways. Here, via combined analytical calculation and experiment, we demonstrate that the phase of the magnetization precession at the interface of a coupled yttrium iron garnet(YIG)/permalloy(Py) bilayer is collectively controlled by the microwave photon field torque and the interlayer exchange torque, manifesting a coherent, dual-channel excitation scheme that effectively tunes the magneto-optic spectrum. The different torque contributions vary with frequency, external bias field, and types of interlayer coupling between YIG and Py, which further results in destructive or constructive interferences between the two excitation channels, and hence, selective suppression or amplification of the hybridized magnon modes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05022v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Christy, Yujie Zhu, Yi Li, Yuzan Xiong, Tao Qu, Frank Tsui, James F. Cahoon, Binbin Yang, Jia-Mian Hu, Wei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supersolidity induced flux magnetism with magnetic atoms in an anti-magic wavelength optical lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05058</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05058v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Supersolidity and magnetism are fundamental phenomena characterizing strongly correlated states of matter. Here, we unveil a mechanism that establishes a direct connection between these quantum regimes and can be experimentally accessed in ultracold atomic systems. Specifically, we exploit the distinctive properties of ultracold magnetic lanthanide atoms trapped in a one dimensional anti-magic wavelength optical lattice. This allows us to design a realistic implementation of a triangular Bose-Hubbard ladder featuring two essential ingredients: strong long-range interactions and tunable gauge fields. Thanks to these unconventional properties, our numerical analysis highlights that, among the others, a robust lattice supersolid regime with finite fluxes in each triangular plaquette occurs. Remarkably, we show that the specific density distribution of the supersolid phase leads to the magnetic ordering of fluxes, which can form ferrimagnetic and ferromagnetic structures. Our results thus discover a fascinating quantum mechanical effect that bridges supersolidity and magnetism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05058v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michele Miotto, Pietro Lombardi, Giovanni Ferioli, Joana Fraxanet, Maciej Lewenstein, Luca Tanzi, Luca Barbiero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Boundary-Modes Localization from Quantum Metric Length</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05114v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The presence of localized boundary modes is an unambiguous hallmark of topological quantum matter. While these modes are typically protected by topological invariants such as the Chern number, here we demonstrate that the {\it quantum metric length} (QML), a quantity inherent in multi-band topological systems, governs the spatial extent of flat-band topological boundary modes. We introduce a framework for constructing topological flat bands from degenerate manifolds with large quantum metric and find that the boundary modes exhibit dual phases of spatial behaviors: a conventional oscillatory decay arising from bare band dispersion, followed by another exponential decay controlled by quantum geometry. Crucially, the QML, derived from the quantum metric of the degenerate manifolds, sets a lower bound on the spatial spread of boundary states in the flat-band limit. Applying our framework to concrete models, we validate the universal role of the QML in shaping the long-range behavior of topological boundary modes. Furthermore, by tuning the QML, we unveil extraordinary non-local transport phenomena, including QML-shaped quantum Hall plateaus and anomalous Fraunhofer patterns. Our theoretical framework paves the way for engineering boundary-modes localization in topological flat-band systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05114v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xing-Lei Ma, Jin-Xin Hu, K. T. Law</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital Ordering in the Charge Density Wave Phases of BaNi$_2$(As$_{1-x}$P$_x$)$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05200v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We use resonant X-ray scattering at the nickel L$_{2,3}$ edges to investigate the interplay between orbital degrees of freedom and charge density waves (CDW) in the superconductor BaNi$_2$(As$_{1-x}$P$_x$)$_2$. Both the incommensurate and commensurate CDWs in this system exhibit strong resonant enhancement with distinct energy and polarization dependencies, indicative of orbital ordering. Azimuthal-angle-dependent measurements reveal a lowering of the local Ni site symmetry, consistent with monoclinic or lower point group symmetry. The scattering signatures of both CDWs are dominated by contributions from Ni d$_{xz,yz}$ orbitals, with similar orbital character despite their distinct wave vectors. These findings point to a shared orbital-driven formation mechanism and provide new insight into the symmetry breaking and orbital/nematic fluctuations in the high-temperature regime of the superconductor BaNi$_2$(As$_{1-x}$P$_x$)$_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05200v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tom Lacmann, Robert Eder, Igor Vinograd, Michael Merz, Mehdi Frachet, Philippa Helen McGuinness, Kurt Kummer, Enrico Schierle, Amir-Abbas Haghighirad, Sofia-Michaela Souliou, Matthieu Le Tacon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlation-driven 3d Heavy Fermion behavior in LiV2O4</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05237v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: LiV2O4 is a spinel-structured compound that stands out as the first known 3d-electron system exhibiting typical heavy fermion behavior. A central question is how such strong mass renormalization emerges in the absence of f-electrons. In this work, we investigate the three-dimensional electronic structure of LiV2O4 thin films using angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES). We identify that an electron-like flat band is derived from a1g orbitals, along with a highly dispersive e'g band strongly coupled with phonons. The overall agreement with dynamical mean-field theory (DMFT) calculations highlights the essential role of inter-orbital Hund's coupling in reducing the a1g bandwidth to 25 meV, approaching a Mott state. Notably, we find that heavy-fermion behavior arises from additional renormalization at the a1g band near the Fermi level, likely driven by many-body interactions at energy scales down to a few meV and potentially linked to geometric frustration inherent to the spinel lattice. These results provide crucial insights into the origin of the heavy fermion behavior in 3d-electron systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05237v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/0256-307X/42/10/100710</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Min-Yi-Nan Lei, Z. H. Chen, H. T. Wang, Y. Fan, N. Guo, T. X. Jiang, Yanwei Cao, T. Zhang, Rui Peng, Haichao Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin dynamics in natural multiferroic pyroxene NaFeSi$_2$O$_6$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05251v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spin dynamics in the natural mineral aegirine, NaFeSi$_2$O$_6$, a member of the pyroxene family, was studied by elastic and inelastic neutron scattering. Magnetization and specific heat measurements as well as single-crystal neutron diffraction maps, taken in the temperature range 2 - 20 K, confirm two successive magnetic transitions at 8.8 and 5.8 K, consistent with previous studies. The observed spin-wave excitations emerge from the incommensurate magnetic Bragg peaks corresponding to the propagation vector $k_{\rm ICM} = (0, 0.77, 0)$, and extend up to energies of about 1.5 meV. In the low-temperature helical phase, the spin dynamics of the Fe$^{3+}$ ions is well described by a simple linear spin-wave model. The observed excitations can be modeled using a spin Hamiltonian that includes three primary exchange interactions - intrachain coupling $J=0.142(2)$ meV, interchain couplings $J_1=0.083(1)$ meV and $J_2=0.186(1)$ meV - and an easy-plane anisotropy $D=0.020(6)$ meV. Our results show that no single exchange interaction dominates the spin dynamics. The similar strengths of the intrachain and interchain couplings point to the fact that the magnetic interactions in aegirine are three-dimensional rather than confined along one direction. As a result, the system cannot be considered quasi-one-dimensional, as previously suggested, and calls for further investigations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05251v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/tb2z-skj1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112 (2025) 094402</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Oleksandr Prokhnenko (Helmholtz-Zentrum Berlin f\H{u}r Materialien und Energie, Berlin, Germany), Stanislav E. Nikitin (PSI Center for Neutron and Muon Sciences, Paul Scherrer Institut, Switzerland), Koji Kaneko (Materials Sciences Research Center, Japan Atomic Energy Agency, Tokai, Japan, Advanced Science Research Center, Japan Atomic Energy Agency, Tokai, Japan), Chihiro Tabata (Materials Sciences Research Center, Japan Atomic Energy Agency, Tokai, Japan, Advanced Science Research Center, Japan Atomic Energy Agency, Tokai, Japan), Yusuke Hirose (Materials Sciences Research Center, Japan Atomic Energy Agency, Tokai, Japan, Advanced Science Research Center, Japan Atomic Energy Agency, Tokai, Japan), Yoshifumi Tokiwa (Advanced Science Research Center, Japan Atomic Energy Agency, Tokai, Japan), Yoshinori Haga (Advanced Science Research Center, Japan Atomic Energy Agency, Tokai, Japan), Masaki Fujita (Institute for Materials Research, Tohoku University, Sendai, Japan), Hiroyuki Nojiri (Institute for Materials Research, Tohoku University, Sendai, Japan), Lawrence M. Anovitz (Chemical Sciences Division, Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Oak Ridge, TN, USA), Andrey Podlesnyak (Neutron Scattering Division, Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Oak Ridge, TN, USA)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulated Laser Cooling and Magneto-Optical Trapping of Group IV Atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04635</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04635v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a scheme for laser cooling and magneto-optical trapping of the Group IV (a.k.a. Group 14 or tetrel) atoms silicon (Si), germanium (Ge), tin (Sn), and lead (Pb). These elements each possess a strong Type-II transition ($J \rightarrow J' = J-1$) between the metastable $s^2p^2 \,^3 P_1$ state and the excited $s^2ps'\, ^3P_0^o$ state at an accessible laser wavelength, making them amenable to laser cooling and trapping. We focus on the application of this scheme to Sn, which has several features that make it attractive for precision measurement applications. We perform numerical simulations of atomic beam slowing, capture into a magneto-optical trap (MOT), and subsequent sub-Doppler cooling and compression in a blue-detuned MOT of Sn atoms. We also discuss a realistic experimental setup for realizing a high phase-space density sample of Sn atoms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04635v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Geoffrey Zheng, Jianwei Wang, Mohit Verma, Qian Wang, Thomas K. Langin, David DeMille</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hot-Ham: an accurate and efficient E(3)-equivariant machine-learning electronic structures calculation framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04875</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04875v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The combinations of machine learning with ab initio methods have attracted much attention for their potential to resolve the accuracy-efficiency dilemma and facilitate calculations for large-scale systems. Recently, equivariant message passing neural networks (MPNNs) that explicitly incorporate symmetry constraints have demonstrated promise for interatomic potential and density functional theory (DFT) Hamiltonian predictions. However, the high-order tensors used to represent node and edge information are coupled through the Clebsch-Gordan tensor product (CGTP), leading to steep increases in computational complexity and seriously hindering the performance of equivariant MPNNs. Here, we develop High-order Tensor machine-learning Hamiltonian (Hot-Ham), an E(3) equivariant MPNN framework that combines two advanced technologies local coordinate transformation and Gaunt tensor product (GTP) to efficiently model DFT Hamiltonians. These two innovations significantly reduce the complexity of tensor products from O(L^6) to O(L^3) or O(L^2 log^2 L) for the max tensor order L, and enhance the performance of MPNNs. Benchmarks on several public datasets demonstrate its state-of-the-art accuracy with relatively few parameters, and the applications to multilayer twisted moir\'e systems, heterostructures and allotropes showcase its generalization ability and high efficiency. Our Hot-Ham method provides a new perspective for developing efficient equivariant neural networks and would be a promising approach for investigating the electronic properties of large-scale materials systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04875v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhixin Liang, Yunlong Wang, Chi Ding, Junjie Wang, Hui-Tian Wang, Dingyu Xing, Jian Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Field-sensitive dislocation bound states in two-dimensional $d$-wave altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.08563</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.08563v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: When a two-dimensional $d$-wave altermagnet is grown on a substrate, the interplay of momentum-dependent spin splittings arising from altermagnetism and Rashba spin-orbit coupling gives rise to a nodal band structure with band degeneracies enforced by a $C_{4z}\mathcal{T}$ symmetry. If we break the $C_{4z}\mathcal{T}$ symmetry by an exchange field, the band degeneracies are found to be immediately lifted, leading to a topological band structure characterized by nontrivial strong and weak topological indices. Remarkably, both the strong topological index and the $Z_{2}$-valued weak topological indices depend sensitively on the direction of the exchange field. As a consequence of the bulk-defect correspondence, we find that the unique dependence of weak topological indices on the exchange field in this system dictates that the presence or absence of topological bound states at lattice dislocations also depends sensitively on the direction of the exchange field. When the substrate is an $s$-wave superconductor, we find that a similar dependence of band topology on the exchange field gives rise to field-sensitive dislocation Majorana zero modes. As topological dislocation bound states are easily detectable by scanning tunneling microscopy, our findings unveil a promising experimental diagnosis of altermagnetic materials among an ever growing list of candidates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.08563v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.165141</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 165141 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Di Zhu, Dongling Liu, Zheng-Yang Zhuang, Zhigang Wu, Zhongbo Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Circular dichroism on the edge of quantum Hall systems: From many-body Chern number to anisotropy measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04639v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum Hall states are characterized by a topological invariant, the many-body Chern number, which determines their quantized Hall conductivity. This invariant also emerges in circular dichroic responses, namely, by applying a circular drive and comparing excitation rates for opposite orientations. This work explores the dichroic response of confined, isolated quantum Hall systems, where bulk and edge contributions cancel exactly: When the edge response is properly isolated, the circular dichroic signal becomes quantized, serving as a direct and elegant probe of the many-body Chern number encoded in the edge physics. We demonstrate that this quantized edge response is entirely captured by low-energy chiral edge modes, allowing for a universal description of this effect based on Wen's edge theory. Its low-energy nature implies that the quantized edge response can be distinguished from the bulk response in the frequency domain. The edge response is also shown to be a sensitive diagnostic of geometric features. This opens the possibility of characterizing the shape of quantum Hall droplets through edge spectroscopic measurements, without requiring knowledge of the system's boundary profile. We illustrate our findings using realistic models of integer and fractional Chern insulators, with different edge geometries, and propose detection schemes suitable for ultracold atoms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04639v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Nur \"Unal, A. Nardin, N. Goldman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Origin of the Unusual Temperature Dependence of the Upper Critical Field of Kagome Superconductor CsV3Sb5: Multiple Bands or van Hove Singularities?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.16625</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.16625v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Van Hove singularities (vHs) located close to the Fermi level in Kagome superconductors AV3Sb5 (A = K, Rb, Cs) have profound influence on their electronic and transport characteristics. Specifically, magneto-transport and susceptibility measurements on CsV3Sb5 reveal an anomalous temperature dependence of the upper critical field H_c2 (T), characterized by a pronounced upward curvature for both in-plane and c-axis magnetic fields, with zero-temperature H_c2 values of ~6.0 T and ~1.2 T, respectively. Our theoretical analysis, using a newly developed single-band model incorporating vHs and gap anisotropy, suggests that the observed upper critical field behavior is predominantly driven by the anisotropy of the Fermi velocity originating from vHs, instead of multi-band effects or gap anisotropy. Increased electron scattering introduced by proton irradiation defects smears out the vHs, reduces anisotropy, and recovers the conventional H_c2 (T) behavior, corroborating our proposed model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.16625v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ramakanta Chapai, Alexei E. Koshelev, Matthew P. Smylie, Duck Young Chung, Asghar Kayani, Khushi Bhatt, Gaurab Rimal, Mercouri G. Kanatzidis, Wai-Kwong Kwok, John Mitchell, Ulrich Welp</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Twist-angle evolution of the intervalley-coherent antiferromagnet in twisted WSe$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11763</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11763v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent experimental reports of correlated physics in twisted homobilayer WSe$_2$ have spurred interest in the interplay of electronic interactions and topology in this system. Here, we explore its phase diagram using the Hartree-Fock approximation within a three-orbital Wannier model of the bilayer. Our analysis reveals a dominant intervalley-coherent antiferromagnetic instability, whose stability in the space of twist angle, interaction strength, out-of-plane displacement field, and hole density is primarily set by nesting and commensurability. At large angles or low interaction-to-bandwidth ratios, the instability arises at hole densities above half filling near a van-Hove line where the strong Fermi surface nesting occurs due to the flatness of the band in a region enclosing the van-Hove and $\kappa$ points. Increasing interaction strength or decreasing the twist angle gradually shifts the ordered phase toward half filling, where the strongest antiferromagnetic order gets pinned due to commensurability effects that enable a full gap opening. The antiferromagnetic order parameter strongly couples to the layer polarization, which makes its transition to the normal state sharp in the strong-coupling limit and carries implications for collective modes. Our Hartree-Fock phase diagram reproduces key aspects of recent experiments and the reconstructed Fermi surfaces and DOS in the antiferromagnetic phase account for subtle transport signatures observed in these studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11763v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/m6c2-yd5j</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Mu\~noz-Segovia, Valentin Cr\'epel, Raquel Queiroz, Andrew J. Millis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charge gap and charge redistribution among copper and oxygen orbitals in the normal state of the Emery model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11161</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.11161v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Unraveling the behavior of the electrons in the copper-oxygen planes of cuprate superconductors remains a challenge. Here we examine the electronic charge redistribution among planar copper and oxygen orbitals and the charge gap using the Emery model in the normal state, solved with cellular dynamical mean-field theory at finite temperature. We quantify the charge redistribution as a function of the onsite Coulomb repulsion on the copper orbitals, the bare copper-oxygen energy difference, and the hole or electron doping. We find that the position relative to the metal to insulator boundary of the Zaanen-Sawatzky-Allen diagram determines the charge redistribution among copper and oxygen orbitals. For a fixed bare Cu-O energy difference, an increase in the Cu electron repulsion leads to a transfer of the electronic charge from Cu to O orbitals. For a fixed charge gap size of the undoped state, as the system evolves from a charge-transfer to a Mott-Hubbard regime, the electronic charge is transferred from Cu to O orbitals. Our findings posit the Coulomb repulsion and the bare charge-transfer energy as key drivers of the microscopic process of charge redistribution in the CuO$_2$ plane. They quantify the anticorrelation between the charge gap size and oxygen hole content. They show that for fixed band-structure parameters, the charge gap and the charge redistribution between Cu and O orbitals provide a way to understand observed trends in cuprates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.11161v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/7bbg-m38l</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 125106 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>G. L. Reaney, N. Kowalski, A. -M. S. Tremblay, G. Sordi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hidden Bose-Einstein Singularities in Correlated Electron Systems: III. Thermodynamic Signals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19211</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19211v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study thermodynamic consequences of the hidden Bose-Einstein singularities, which have been predicted to cause a pseudogap phase, based on quantum field theory of ordered phases. Starting from the Luttinger-Ward functional for the grand thermodynamic potential, we derive expressions of the Helmholtz free energy, internal energy, entropy, and heat capacity in a form suitable for numerical studies. They are applied to the weakly attractive Hubbard model in three dimensions to calculate the thermodynamic potentials numerically and continuously for the normal, pseudogap, and superconducting phases on the same footing. It is shown that the entry into the pseudogap phase is detectable as singularities of thermodynamic potentials, especially a discontinuity in the heat capacity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19211v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.7566/JPSJ.94.104701</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. 94, 104701 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Takafumi Kita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The electronic and transport properties in odd-parity altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09906v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Following recent intensive studies on altermagnets(ALM) characterized by non-relativistic even-parity spin splitting, realizing unconventional odd-parity magnetism has also attracted increasing interest. Here, using symmetry arguments based on spin-group analyses, we elucidate the sufficient condition, the breaking nonmagnetic time reversal symmetry(TRS), for the presence of odd-parity spin splitting in the collinear antiferromagnetic(AFM) systems, which is also proved as a standard odd-parity ALM. Then, we utilize the well-known Haldane-Hubbard model to identify the odd-parity spin splitting in the collinear AFM ground state where the nonmagnetic TRS is broken by sublattice currents coming from the Haldane hopping term. A comprehensive phase diagram involving the Haldane hopping strength and on-site coulomb repulsion is established to elucidate correlation-driven electronic phases. Moreover, we calculate the optical conductivity to illustrate the sublattice current induced odd-parity ALM, displaying a significant spin-degenerate peak in the vicinity of the single-particle energy gap. This work reveals the underlying mechanism for the realization of the unconventional odd-parity ALM in collinear AFM systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09906v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minghuan Zeng, Zheng Qin, Ling Qin, Shiping Feng, Dong-Hui Xu, Rui Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adjudicating Conduction Mechanisms in High Performance Carbon Nanotube Fibers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.20481</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.20481v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The performance of carbon nanotube (CNT) cables, a contender for copper-wire replacement, is tied to its metallic and semi-conducting-like conductivity responses with temperature; the origin of the semi-conducting-like response however is an underappreciated incongruity in literature. With controlled aspect-ratio and doping-degree, over 61 unique cryogenic experiments including anisotropy and Hall measurements, CNT cable performance is explored at extreme temperatures (65 mK) and magnetic fields (60 T). A semi-conducting-like conductivity response with temperature becomes temperature-independent approaching absolute-zero, uniquely demonstrating the necessity of heterogeneous fluctuation induced tunneling; complete de-doping leads to localized hopping, contrasting graphite's pure metallic-like response. High-field magneto-resistance (including +22% longitudinal magneto-resistance near room-temperature) is analyzed with hopping and classical two-band models, both similarly yielding a parameter useful for conductor development. Varying field-orientation angle uncovers two-and four-fold symmetries from Aharonov-Bohm-like corrections to curvature-induced bandgap. Tight-binding calculations using Green's Function formalism model large-scale, coherent transport in commensurate CNT bundles in magnetic field, revealing non-uniform transmission across bundle cross-sections with doping restoring uniformity; independent of doping, transport in bundle-junction-bundle systems are predominantly from CNTs adjacent to the other bundle. The final impact is predicting the ultimate conductivity of heterogeneous CNT cables using temperature and field-dependent transport, surpassing conductivity of traditional metals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.20481v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John Bulmer, Chris Kovacs, Thomas Bullard, Charlie Ebbing, Timothy Haugan, Ganesh Pokharel, Stephen D. Wilson, Fedor F. Balakirev, Oscar A. Valenzuela, Michael A. Susner, David Turner, Pengyu Fu, Teresa Kulka, Jacek Majewski, Irina Lebedeva, Karolina Z. Milowska, Agnieszka Lekawa-Raus, Magdalena Marganska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intricacies of Frustrated Magnetism in the Kondo Metal YbAgGe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02252</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02252v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The combination of localized magnetic moments, their frustration and interaction with itinerant electrons is a key challenge of condensed matter physics. Frustrated magnetic interactions promote degenerate ground states with enhanced fluctuations, a topic that is predominantly studied in magnetic insulators. The coupling between itinerant and localized electrons in metals add complexity to the problem, and presently formulated only for extreme cases in which the itinerant electrons mediate exchange between localized spins (RKKY interaction) or suppress the formation of magnetic moments (Kondo screening). Here, we report an in-depth experimental study of the distorted Kagome metal YbAgGe, unravelling the open questions of how frustration, localized magnetism and itinerant electrons are intertwined in frustrated Kondo metals. We find that coupled itinerant and localized electrons give rise to dynamic magnetic correlations below T* ~ 20 K. At lower temperature, frustrated magnetic interactions establish anisotropic magnetic short-range correlations that culminate into antiferromagnetic long-range order below TN = 0.68 K with a significantly reduced modulated magnetic moment. We show that local moment Hamiltonians can yield limited understanding of the microscopic behaviour in frustrated metals, and prompt the extension of more sophisticated model Hamiltonians incorporating itinerant effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02252v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. G. Mazzone, C. B. Larsen, B. Ueland, X. Boraley, D. M. Pajerowski, Y. Skourski, J. Taylor, B. Fak, S. L. Bud'ko, R. McQueeney, P. C. Canfield, O. Zaharko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gauging Quantum Phases: A Matrix Product State Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14380</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14380v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Utilizing the framework of matrix product states, we investigate gauging as a method for exploring quantum phases of matter. Specifically, we describe how symmetry-protected topological (SPT) phases and spontaneous symmetry breaking (SSB) phases in one-dimensional spin systems behave under twisted gauging, a generalization of the well-known gauging procedure for globally symmetric states. Compared to previous, order parameter-based, approaches our analysis is not limited to the case of maximally non-commutative (MNC) phases and we use our findings to propose a generalization of the Kennedy-Tasaki transformation to the non-MNC setting. A key result of our work is that gauging produces configurations characterized by a combination of MNC order and symmetry breaking, when applied to non-MNC SPT phases. More generally, we conjecture a precise correspondence between SSB and non-MNC SPT phases, possibly enabling the detection of such phases using local and string order parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14380v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/gkh9-lgrk</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 115110 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>David Blanik, Jos\'e Garre-Rubio, Norbert Schuch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum simulation of the Hubbard model on a graphene hexagon: Strengths of IQPE and noise constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05031</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05031v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum computing offers transformative potential for simulating real-world materials, providing a powerful platform to investigate complex quantum systems across quantum chemistry and condensed matter physics. In this work, we leverage this capability to simulate the Hubbard model on a six-site graphene hexagon using Qiskit, employing the Iterative Quantum Phase Estimation (IQPE) and adiabatic evolution algorithms to determine its ground-state properties. Our results show that a single Slater determinant is sufficient to initialize IQPE and accurately recover ground-state energies (GSEs) in small-scale Hubbard systems. In noiseless simulations, IQPE converges within a few iterations to exact GSEs, while adiabatic simulations yield charge and spin densities and correlation functions in excellent agreement with exact diagonalization. However, deploying IQPE and adiabatic evolution on today's noisy quantum hardware remains highly challenging. To investigate these limitations in IQPE, we use the Qiskit Aer simulator with a custom noise model tailored to the characteristics of IBM's real hardware. This model includes realistic depolarizing gate errors, thermal relaxation, and readout noise, allowing us to explore how these factors degrade simulation accuracy. Further, we implement the IQPE algorithm on IBM's ibm_strasbourg and ibm_fez devices for a reduced three-site Hubbard model, enabling direct comparison between simulated and real hardware noise. While ibm_fez runs closely match exact results, discrepancies highlight the gap between modeled and physical noise. This study demonstrates both the IQPE's potential and current limitations for simulating strongly correlated systems under realistic conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05031v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Mirzakhani, Kyungsun Moon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
