<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 04:00:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Theory of Sondheimer magneto-oscillations beyond semiclassical limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14315v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In conducting films subjected to an out-of-plane magnetic field, electron motion along the field direction gives rise to conductance oscillations periodic in field intensity - a phenomenon known as Sondheimer oscillations. Traditionally, these oscillations were understood within the semiclassical framework of kinetic theory. However, their behavior in the quantum regime (i.e. at strong fields and weak disorder) remains unclear, particularly due to potential interference with quantum Shubnikov-de Haas magneto-oscillations. In this work, we develop a comprehensive theory of quantum magnetoconductivity oscillations in metallic films of finite thickness, fully capturing the interplay between the Sondheimer and Shubnikov-de Haas effects beyond the semiclassical limit. By treating surface scattering, in-plane Landau quantization, and dimensional confinement along the magnetic field direction on equal footing, we reveal an intricate hierarchy of oscillation patterns and characterize how their amplitudes and frequencies depend on various physical parameters. Our results pave the way for systematic characterization of thin metallic films with boundary-dominated transport properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14315v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Nikolaenko, Pavel A. Nosov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resonantly enhanced photoemission from topological surface states in MnBi$_6$Te$_{10}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14714</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14714v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The dispersion of topological surface bands in MnBi$_2$Te$_4$-based magnetic topological insulator heterostructures is strongly affected by band hybridization and is spatially inhomogeneous due to varying surface layer terminations on microscopic length scales. Here, we apply micro-focused angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy with tunable photon energy from 18 to 30 eV to distinguish bulk valence and conduction bands from surface bands on the three surface terminations of MnBi$_6$Te$_10$. We observe a strong enhancement of photoemission intensity from the topological surface bands at the Bi O4 absorption edge, which is exploited to visualize a gapless Dirac cone on the MnBi$_2$Te$_4$-terminated surface and varying degrees of hybridization effects in the surface bands on the two distinct Bi$_2$Te$_3$-terminated surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14714v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-648X/ae025b</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. Condens. Matter 37 385501 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Paulina Majchrzak, Alfred J. H. Jones, Klara Volckaert, Xing-Chen Pan, Philip Hofmann, Yong P. Chen, Jill A. Miwa, S{\o}ren Ulstrup</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection of ferroic octupole ordering in $d$-wave altermagnetic rutile-type compounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14716</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14716v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose that X-ray absorption and emission magnetic circular dichroism (XAS-MCD and XES-MCD) are promising measurements to directly detect ferroic higher-rank multipoles as candidate order parameters in altermagnets. Using the sum rules for XES-MCD and connecting them to multipole language, we demonstrate that the expectation value of the magnetic octupole moment is finite in the $d$-wave altermagnetic candidate rutile-type compounds TF$_2$ (T=transition metal). We also perform spectral calculations of XAS-MCD and XES-MCD based on an effective model with a full multiplet approach. While the intensity of the XAS-MCD spectra vanishes, the XES-MCD spectra exhibit finite intensity, whose spectrum becomes opposite by inverting the N\`eel vector. These results clearly indicate ferroic magnetic octupole order in these compounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14716v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masaichiro Mizumaki, Norimasa Sasabe, Takayuki Uozumi, Rikuto Oiwa, Hiroaki Kusunose</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-photon coupling using circular double quantum dots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14813</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14813v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose and analyze a microwave spin-photon interface based on a circular double quantum dot, inspired by recent experimental observations of anisotropic g-factors and ring states in InAs nanowires. We develop an effective theoretical model capturing the interplay of spin-orbit coupling and the magnetic flux through the ring and show how ring states form at crossings of odd and even geometrical parity orbital states. Similar to bonding and antibonding states of conventional double quantum dots, the ring eigenstates can be changed into single dot states by detuning the dots, which enables a high degree of control over the system's properties. Applying a tilted magnetic field induces spin-charge hybridization which enables spin-photon coupling. For low disorder, the photons couple states of simultaneously (almost) opposite spin and angular momentum. With increasing disorder, the spin-photon coupling becomes analogous to the flopping mode mechanism of conventional double quantum dots where the spin is hybridized with the bonding and antibonding orbital states without angular momentum. We show that the system exhibits a second-order charge-noise sweet spot at a specific magnetic field angle, which lowers the system's sensitivity to dephasing while retaining a substantial spin-photon coupling strength. Moreover, the photon coupling mechanism can be switched off either electrically, by detuning to the single-dot regime, or magnetically, by rotating the field to disable the spin-charge hybridization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14813v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ferdinand Omlor, Florinda Vi\~nas Bostr\"om, Martin Leijnse</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sub-tesla on-chip nanomagnetic metamaterial platform for angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15092</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.15092v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetically controlled states in quantum materials are central to their unique electronic and magnetic properties. However, direct momentum-resolved visualization of these states via angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) has been hindered by the disruptive effect of magnetic fields on photoelectron trajectories. Here, we introduce an \textit{in-situ} method that is, in principle, capable of applying magnetic fields up to 1 T. This method uses substrates composed of nanomagnetic metamaterial arrays with alternating polarity. Such substrates can generate strong, homogeneous, and spatially confined fields applicable to samples with thicknesses up to the micron scale, enabling ARPES measurements under magnetic fields with minimal photoelectron trajectory distortion. We demonstrate this minimal distortion with ARPES data taken on monolayer graphene. Our method paves the way for probing magnetic field-dependent electronic structures and studying field-tunable quantum phases with state-of-the-art energy-momentum resolutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.15092v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenxin Li, Wisha Wanichwecharungruang, Mingyang Guo, Ioan-Augustin Chioar, Nileena Nandakumaran, Justin Ramberger, Senlei Li, Zhibo Kang, Jinming Yang, Donghui Lu, Makoto Hashimoto, Chunhui Rita Du, Chris Leighton, Peter Schiffer, Qiong Ma, Ming Yi, Yu He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diagrammatic bosonisation, aspects of criticality, and the Hohenberg-Mermin-Wagner Theorem in parquet approaches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15094</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.15094v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The parquet equations present a cornerstone of some of the most important diagrammatic many-body approximations and methods currently on the market for strongly correlated materials: from non-local extensions of the dynamical mean-field theory to the functional renormalization group. The recently introduced single-boson exchange decomposition of the vertex presents an alternative set of equivalent equations in terms of screened interactions, Hedin vertices, and rest functions. This formulation has garnered much attention for several reasons: opening the door to new approximations, for avoiding vertex divergences associated with local moment formation plaguing the traditional parquet decomposition, and for its interpretative advantage in its built-in diagrammatic identification of bosons without resorting to Hubbard-Stratonovich transformations. In this work, we show how the fermionic diagrams of the particle-particle and particle-hole polarizations can be mapped to diagrammatics of a bosonic self-energy of two respective bosonic theories with pure bosonic constituents, solidifying the identification of the screened interaction with a bosonic propagator. Resorting to a spin-diagonalized basis for the bosonic fields and neglecting the coupling between singlet and triplet components is shown to recover the trace log theory known from Hubbard-Stratonovich transformations. Armed with this concrete mapping, we revisit a conjecture claiming that universal aspects of the parquet approximation coincide with those of the self-consistent screening approximation for a bosonic $O(N)$ model. We comment on the role of the self-energy and crossing symmetry in enforcing the Hohenberg-Mermin-Wagner theorem in parquet-related approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.15094v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aiman Al-Eryani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bichromatic Moir\'{e} Superlattices for Tunable Quadrupolar Trions and Correlated States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15118</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.15118v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Moir\'{e} superlattices in transition metal dichalcogenide heterostructures provide a platform to engineer many-body interactions. Here, we realize a bichromatic moir\'{e} superlattice in an asymmetric WSe$_2$/WS$_2$/WSe$_2$ heterotrilayer by combining R- and H-stacked bilayers with mismatched moir\'{e} wavelengths. This structure hosts fermionic quadrupolar moir\'{e} trions--interlayer excitons bound to an opposite-layer hole--with vanishing dipole moments. These trions arise from hybridized moir\'{e} potentials enabling multiple excitonic orbitals with tunable interlayer coupling, allowing control of excitonic and electronic ground states. We show that an out-of-plane electric field could effectively reshape moir\'{e} excitons and interlayer-intralayer electron correlations, driving a transition from interlayer to intralayer Mott states with enhanced Coulomb repulsion. The asymmetric stacking further enriches excitonic selection rules, broadening opportunities for spin-photon engineering. Our results demonstrate bichromatic moir\'{e} superlattices as a reconfigurable platform for emergent quantum states, where quadrupolar moir\'{e} trion emission may enable coherent and entangled quantum light manipulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.15118v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingfeng Chen, Runtong Li, Haonan Wang, Yuliang Yang, Yiyang Lai, Chaowei Hu, Takashi Taniguchi, Kenji Watanabe, Jiaqiang Yan, Jiun-Haw Chu, Erik Henriksen, Chuanwei Zhang, Li Yang, Xi Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Competing and Intertwined Orders in Boson-Doped Mott Antiferromagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15215</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.15215v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Inspired by the recent experimental advances in cold atom quantum simulators, we explore the experimentally implemented bosonic $t$-$t'$-$J$ model on the square lattice using large-scale density matrix renormalization group simulations. By tuning the doping level $\delta$ and hopping ratio $t'/t$, we uncover six distinct quantum phases, several of which go far beyond the conventional paradigm of phase-coherent superfluidity (SF) expected for bosonic systems. In particular, in the presence of antiferromagnetic (AFM) order, doped holes are tightly bound into pairs, giving rise to a pair density wave (PDW) phase at low doping and small $|t'/t|$, which is suppressed on the $t'&lt;0$ side, resulting in a disordered PDW state that lacks coherence of either individual bosons or pairs. Upon further doping, bosons can regain phase coherence and form a SF* state, characterized by condensation at emergent incommensurate momenta concurrent with an incommensurate magnetic order. On the $t'&gt;0$ side, the sign-induced kinetic frustration inherently disfavors local AFM correlations, leading to a phase separation in which doped holes cluster into ferromagnetic (FM) domains spatially separated by undoped AFM regions. Upon further doping, this inhomogeneous state evolves into a uniform SF + $xy$-FM phase. Finally, we propose a concrete experimental scheme to realize both signs of $t'/t$ in Rydberg tweezer arrays, with an explicit mapping between model parameters and experimentally accessible regimes. Our results reveal competing and intertwined orders in doped antiferromagnets, which are relevant to central issues in high-$T_c$ superconductivity, reflecting the frustrated interplay between doped holes and spin background.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.15215v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Lu, Jia-Xin Zhang, Lukas Homeier, Hong-Chen Jiang, Shou-Shu Gong, D. N. Sheng, Zheng-Yu Weng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Precise correspondence between the p-wave chiral superfluid and the spinless bosonic superfluid in the lowest Landau level</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05243v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish a precise formal correspondence between a spinless p-wave chiral fermionic superfluid and a spinless bosonic superfluid in a strong magnetic field by correctly accounting for superfluid vorticity in the effective theory of the former. In the literature, this vorticity term incompletely manifests as the magnetic field. This paper demonstrates this substitution can be understood as a truncation within the relevant expansion scheme, accompanied by field redefinitions. The components discarded in this truncation are critical for restoring the Berry phase term in the effective theory, encapsulating both systems in the same master Lagrangian. Beyond clarifying the structure of the Berry phase, this formalism allows for solving the bosonic system in the lowest Landau level (LLL) by analogy. Specifically, we show that, in the linear regime, the Maxwell equations governing these systems are identical when the vortex crystal is reformulated using an auxiliary electromagnetic field. This approach offers a unified perspective on these systems and yields solutions that are rotationally covariant, gauge invariants, and physically interpretable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05243v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.7566/JPSJ.94.034601</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. 94, 034601 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Han Hsiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Itinerant electron metamagnetism for lattices with van Hove density-of-states singularities near the Fermi level</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.15748</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.15748v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Itinerant-electron metamagnetism is investigated within the Hubbard model for various lattices having van Hove singularities (vHS) in the electronic spectrum: face-centered cubic and orthorhombic lattices. The remarkable itinerant-electron metamagnetic transition occurs provided that the Fermi level is in the region with a strong positive curvature of the density of electron states typically positioned between two close van Hove singularities. Orthorhombic distortion of a~tetragonal lattice is a promising mechanism for generating two closely split vHS with strong density-of-states curvature between them. A phase diagram in terms of electron filling and Hubbard interaction parameter is presented, which shows the paramagnetic-metamagnetic-ferromagnetic phase transition and regions of saturated and non-saturated magnetism. The standard Landau theory expansion based on~the~electron density of states in the vicinity of the Fermi level is demonstrated to be insufficient to describe the whole magnetic phase diagram including the itinerant-electron metamagnetic transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.15748v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.104429</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, 104429 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>F. A. Vasilevskiy, P. A. Igoshev, V. Yu. Irkhin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Hall Antidot as a Fractional Coulombmeter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04209v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The detection of fractionally charged quasiparticles, which arise in the fractional quantum Hall regime, is of fundamental importance for probing their exotic quantum properties. While electronic interferometers have been central to probe their statistical properties, their interpretation is often complicated by bulk-edge interactions. Antidots, potential hills in the quantum Hall regime, are particularly valuable in this context, as they overcome the geometric limitations of conventional designs and act as controlled impurities within a quantum point contact. Furthermore, antidots allow for quasiparticle charge detection through straightforward conductance measurements, replacing the need for more demanding techniques. In this work, we employ a gate-defined bilayer graphene antidot operating in the Coulomb-dominated regime to study quasiparticle tunneling in both integer and fractional quantum Hall states. We show that the gate-voltage period and the oscillation slope directly reveal the charge of the tunneling quasiparticles, providing a practical method to measure fractional charge in graphene. We report direct measurements of fractional charge, finding $q = e/3$ at $\nu = 4/3$, 5/3 and 7/3, $q = 2e/3$ at $\nu = 2/3$ and $q = 3e/5$ at $\nu = 3/5$, while at $\nu = 8/3$ we observe signatures of both $e/3$ and $2e/3$ tunneling charge. The simplicity and tunability of this design open a pathway to extend antidot-based charge measurements to other van der Waals materials, establishing antidots as a powerful and broadly applicable platform to study the quantum Hall effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04209v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mario Di Luca, Emily Hajigeorgiou, Zekang Zhou, Tev\v{z} Lotri\v{c}, Tengyan Feng, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Steven H. Simon, Mitali Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Oxygen-driven altermagnetic symmetry inducing d-wave superconductivity in the cuprates and nickelates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06814</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.06814v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Since the discovery of cuprate high-Tc superconductivity, numerous theoretical frameworks have been proposed to explain its mechanism; Anderson's RVB picture [Science 235, 1196-1198, 1987] and U(1) gauge theory [Phys. Rev. Lett. 76, 503-506, 1996] motivate a minimal one-band view that largely integrates out oxygen. By contrast, altermagnetism [Phys. Rev. X 12, 040501, 2022] yields a d-wave-like k-space magnetic texture from alternatingly rotated nonmagnetic cages; La2CuO4 (the parent of a high-Tc cuprate) is a prototypical example. As a proof of principle, we show in La2CuO4 that an alternating local pairing potential on the two Cu sublattices (plus/minus s(r)) produces a nodal, d-wave-like Delta(k). As orthorhombic tilts are, however, not the driver (and even suppress superconductivity in nickelates; [Nature 621, 493, (2023)], we then show that the in-plane oxygen sublattice of CuO2/NiO2 layers, ubiquitous in cuprates and nickelates, intrinsically realizes the same symmetry. Imposing an oxygen-centered, staggered s pairing yields a d-wave gap with perfect C4 symmetry, demonstrated self-consistently in NdNiO2 from first principles. While the underlying mechanism that drives this order is unclear, we outline possible origins. Further, this description of superconductivity enables mapping a real-space superconducting order parameter onto a lattice picture, allowing superconductivity and Hubbard physics to be treated on the same footing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.06814v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tom G. Saunderson, James F. Annett, Samir Lounis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detective quantum efficiency based comparison of HRTEM and ptychography phase imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12037</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12037v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: High-resolution transmission electron microscopy (HRTEM) is an important method for imaging beam sensitive materials often under cryo conditions. Electron ptychography in the scanning transmission electron microscope (STEM) has been shown to reconstruct low-noise phase data at a reduced fluence for such materials. This raises the question of whether ptychography or HRTEM provides a more fluence-efficient imaging technique. Even though the transfer function is a common metric for evaluating the performance of an imaging method, it only describes the signal transfer with respect to spatial frequency, irrespective of the noise transfer. It can also not be well defined for methods, such as ptychography, that use an algorithm to form the final image. Here we apply the concept of detective quantum efficiency (DQE) to electron microscopy as a fluence independent and sample independent measure of technique performance. We find that, for a weak-phase object, ptychography can never reach the efficiency of a perfect Zernike phase imaging microscope but that ptychography is more robust to partial coherence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12037v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felix Bennemann, Angus I. Kirkland, David A. Muller, Peter Nellist</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing Variational Perturbation Theory for Effective Actions Using the Gaudin-Yang Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02919</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02919v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The background field formalism based on effective actions is a compelling framework for developing an effective field theory for nuclear density functional theory. Among the challenges in carrying out this development is handling both the particle-hole and pairing channels beyond the mean-field level, which includes how to incorporate collective degrees of freedom. Here we use the exactly solvable one-dimensional Gaudin-Yang model as a theoretical laboratory to explore candidate approaches. We compare Variational Perturbation Theory (VPT) to ordinary many-body perturbation theory and the inversion method, all to second order in their respective expansions, and verify issues with Hubbard-Stratonovich auxiliary fields. VPT outperforms the other approaches at this level over a wide range of densities. The next steps to extend this approach toward nuclei are outlined.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02919v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pranav Sharma, R. J. Furnstahl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
