<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 05:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Soluciones exactas para la interacci\'on de materiales de Dirac anis\'otropos con campos el\'ectricos y magn\'eticos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05579</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05579v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work analyzes anisotropic Dirac materials, such as graphene and borophene, under inhomogeneous electric and magnetic fields with position-dependent profiles. Exact solutions of the Dirac--Weyl equation are obtained for singular and exponentially decaying interactions, showing how anisotropy and field shape influence the energy spectrum, Landau levels, and state localization. The analysis is further extended using the Asymptotic Iteration Method (AIM) in its perturbative form, applied to systems with bounded domains $( -\infty, x_0 ]$ or $( 0, x_0 ]$. In particular, we consider the case $( -\infty, x_0 ]$, where the field vanishes asymptotically. The first-order corrections reveal how the finite range $x_0$ modifies localization and transport, and how a critical electric field emerges at which Landau levels collapse, providing insight into the design of field-defined regions in two-dimensional nanoelectronic and quantum devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05579v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julio Armando Mojica Z\'arate</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Josephson Diode Effect for a Kitaev Ladder System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05601v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the Josephson diode effect realized purely by geometry in a Kitaev-ladder Josephson junction composed of two parallel spinless $p$-wave chains coupled by an interleg hopping $t_\perp$. The junction is governed by two phases: the superconducting phase difference across the weak link, $\theta$, and the leg-to-leg phase difference, $\phi$. For $\phi\notin \{0, \pi\}$ (mod $2\pi$), time-reversal symmetry is broken, and the absence of leg-exchange symmetry leads to a breakdown of the antisymmetry of the current-phase relation, yielding nonreciprocal Josephson transport without magnetic fields or spin-orbit coupling. By resolving transport into bonding and antibonding channels defined by $t_\perp$, it is shown that the leg phase acts as an effective phase shift for interband ($p_\nu/p_{-\nu}$) tunneling, whereas the same-band ($p_\nu/p_\nu$) contribution remains unshifted. These channels arise at different perturbative orders and, together with the $4\pi$-periodic Majorana channel that emerges near the topological transition, interfere to produce a pronounced diode response. The class-D Pfaffian invariant identifies the parameter regime where the ladder hosts Majorana zero modes. Bogoliubov-de Gennes calculations reveal a dome-like dependence of the diode efficiency $\eta$ on $t_\perp$: $\eta\to 0$ for $t_\perp\to 0$ and for large $t_\perp$, with a maximum at intermediate coupling that is tunable by $\phi$. The present results establish a field-free, geometry-based route to superconducting rectification in one-dimensional topological systems and specify symmetry and topology conditions for optimizing the effect in ladder and network devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05601v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheng-Rong Xie, Hiroki Tsuchiura, Manfred Sigrist</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flat electronic bands from cooperative moir\'e and charge order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05648</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05648v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The formation of flat electronic bands from long-wavelength superperiodic moir\'e potentials in van der Waals heterostructures underpins the creation and control of a host of highly-tuneable correlated and topological phases. The underlying moir\'e periodicity is, however, typically considered a fixed property of the heterostructure. Here, we show how the development of a charge-density wave (CDW) in one of the constituent materials can create an emergent moir\'e periodicity, realising a superperiodic potential in TiSe$_2$/graphite epitaxial heterostructures with an order-of-magnitude longer wavelength than that expected from the normal-state lattice mismatch. We demonstrate how this drives the formation of a remarkably strong band flattening, which can be readily deactivated by carrier doping across the CDW phase transition, opening new prospects for engineering moir\'e matter by exploiting the rich many-body states of the parent compounds of 2D heterostructures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05648v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. K. Saika, S. Buchberger, S. Mo, A. Rajan, D. Halliday, Y. -C. Yao, L. C. Rhodes, B. Sarpi, T. Balasubramanian, C. Polley, P. Wahl, P. D. C. King</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single-Atom Photocatalysts on TiO2 : Insights from X-ray Absorption Spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05668</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05668v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Surface modification of TiO2 with single-atom catalysts (SACs) is an effective strategy for enhancing photocatalytic efficiency. However, thorough characterization of SACs at the atomic scale remains challenging. X-ray absorption spectroscopy (XAS) offers unique advantages for the in-depth analysis of TiO2-supported SACs. By employing XAS, the local atomic structure, oxidation state, and electronic properties of the SACs, as well as the underlying photocatalytic mechanism, can be revealed. Herein, we present a short review on the application of XAS in studying TiO2-supported SACs. We first elucidate the key role of XAS in simultaneously probing the structure and electronic properties of monometallic SACs across different periods. Next, we discuss XAS studies of bimetallic SACs from the perspective of each constituent element and highlight the element-specific capabilities of XAS for analyzing multi-element SACs. Finally, we demonstrate how in situ XAS can effectively monitor structural and electronic property changes in SACs under real photocatalytic reaction conditions. Additionally, we provide practical suggestions for utilizing XAS more efficiently in the analysis of various SAC systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05668v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yingying Li, David Morris, Peng Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exchange field induced symmetry breaking in quantum hexaborides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05738v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Symmetry breaking (SB) has proven to be a powerful approach for describing quantum materials: strong correlation, mass renormalization, and complex phase transitions are among the phenomena that SB can capture, even when coupled to a mean-field-like theory. Traditionally, corrective schemes were required to account for these effects; however, SB has emerged as an alternative that can also successfully describe the intricate physics of quantum materials. Here, we explore spin SB on EuB6 and SmB6 and how its relation to the exchange field can determine onsite properties, depending on the type of symmetry breaking. Using spin-polarized Density Functional Theory (DFT) calculations with the r2SCAN functional, we systematically compare four magnetic configurations, one totally symmetric - non-magnetic (NM) configuration - and three with different types of symmetry breaking: ferromagnetic (FM), antiferromagnetic (AFM) and a paramagnetic (PM) configuration - modeled through a Special Quasirandom Structure (SQS) method - to capture local symmetry-breaking effects. Our results show that the PM configuration produces distinct magnetic environments for the rare-earth atoms, leading to different exchange fields. These, in turn, induce symmetry breaking in the electronic and magnetic properties of Eu and Sm. Those results provide an alternative explanation for the experimental results on both materials, EuB6 and SmB6, where X-ray Absorption Spectroscopy (XAS) and X-ray Absorption Near Edge Structure (XANES) measurements suggest the presence of multiple atomic environments, previously attributed to a mixed-valence configuration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05738v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Rivera, Fernando P. Sabino, H. Raebiger, A. Ruzsinszky, J. P. Perdew, G. M. Dalpian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Excitation spectrum and low-temperature magnetism in disordered defect-fluorite Ho2Zr2O7</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05749v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we report on the thermomagnetic characterization and crystalline-electric field (CEF) energy scheme of the disordered defect-fluorite Ho2Zr2O7. This structural phase is distinguished by the coexistence of magnetic frustration and extensive disorder, with Ho3+ and Zr4+ sharing randomly the same 4a site with even 50% occupancy, and an average 1/8 oxygen vacancy per unit cell. AC magnetic susceptibility measurements performed on powder samples down to 0.5 K revealed signs of slowing spin dynamics without glassy behavior, including a frequency dependent peak at 1 K. Yet, no evidence for long-range magnetic order is found down to 150 mK in specific heat. Inelastic neutron scattering measurements show a weak, low-lying CEF excitation around 2 meV, accompanied by a broad level centered at 60 meV. To fit our observations, we propose an approach to account for structural disorder in the crystal-field splitting of the non-Kramers Ho3+. Our model provides an explanation to the broadening of the high-energy, single-ion excitations and suggests that the zirconate ground-state wave function has zero magnetic moment. However, structural disorder acts as guarantor of the magnetism in Ho2Zr2O7, allowing the mixing of low lying states at finite temperatures. Finally, we show that this scenario is in good agreement with the bulk properties reported in this work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05749v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. L. Oliveira Silva, J. G. A. Ramon, Viviane Pe\c{c}anha-Antonio, Tatiana Guidi, J. S. Gardner, Chun Sheng Fang, R. S. Freitas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral Cavity Control of the Interlayer Exciton Energy Spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05751</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05751v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Heterostructures of two-dimensional materials offer a versatile platform to study light-matter interactions of electron and hole gases. By separating electron and hole layers with an insulator long-lived electron-hole bound states known as interlayer excitons can form. We predict that by placing an interlayer exciton in a time-reversal-symmetry-breaking chiral cavity the energy spectrum of an interlayer exciton can be reordered. As a consequence of this reordering the ground state of the interlayer exciton can be driven from an s-orbital to a p-orbital, effectively changing the symmetry of the electron-hole pair. We present a phase diagram showing the couplings and separations required for a p-orbital excitonic ground state where we predict that larger interlayer separations require higher cavity couplings. We expect these results to be relevant for angular-momentum-tunable, single photon emission physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05751v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Sanchez-Lopez, Ze-Xun Lin, Di Luo, Prineha narang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Novel Pressure-Induced Transformations of PbTiO3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05756v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigated the behavior of lead titanate (PbTiO3) up to 100 GPa, both at room temperature and upon laser heating, using synchrotron X ray diffraction combined with density functional theory (DFT) computations. At the high pressure temperature (PT) conditions produced in laser heated diamond anvil cells, PbTiO3 dissociates into PbO and TiO2, consistent with our DFT computations showing that decomposition becomes enthalpically favored above 65 GPa. In contrast, on room temperature compression, PbTiO3 persists in the tetragonal I4mcm phase up to at least 100 GPa. Laser heating produces distinct PbO phases: a compressed form of alpha PbO and a previously unreported delta PbO polymorph, both of which transform to beta PbO on decompression. The calculations predict that alpha PbO undergoes pressure-induced band gap closure, metallizing above 70 GPa, whereas the delta and beta phases remain semiconducting with a band gap above 1 eV even at megabar pressures. The experimental and confirming theoretical results reveal an unanticipated dimension of the behavior of PbTiO3, showing that distinct equilibrium and metastable phases can be stabilized along different PT synthesis paths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05756v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Husam Farraj, Stefano Racioppi, Gaston Garbarino, Muhtar Ahart, Anshuman Mondal, Samuel G. Parra, Jesse S. Smith, R. E. Cohen, Eva Zurek, Jordi Cabana, Russell J. Hemley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controllable Superconductivity in Suspended van der Waals Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05763</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05763v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Tunable superconductors provide a versatile platform for advancing next-generation quantum technologies. Here, we demonstrate controllable superconductivity in suspended NbSe2 thin layers, achieved through local strain and thermal modulation of the superconducting state. Our results show that suspended NbSe2 structures enable strain modulation of the critical temperature by up to approximately 0.92 K (about 12.5% of the critical temperature) and allow the realization of gate-tunable superconducting critical currents. We further demonstrate configurable hysteretic transport characteristics exhibiting multistability and negative differential resistance, providing easily reconfigurable, spatially dependent superconducting states. These phenomena are well explained by calculations of electron-phonon coupling using density functional theory, together with time-dependent Ginzburg-Landau dynamics coupled to the thermal diffusion equation. Our work provides profound insight into strain and thermal modulation of van der Waals superconductors and opens new opportunities for tunable on-chip superconductor devices, integrated superconducting circuits, and quantum simulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05763v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruihuan Fang, Cuiju Yu, Youqiang Huang, Tosson Elalaily, Yuvraj Chaudhry, Yaoqiang Zhou, Andres Castellanos-Gomez, Sanshui Xiao, Jiwon Park, Hyunyong Choi, Fida Ali, Hanlin Fang, Jose Lado, Pertti Hakonen, Zhipei Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of electron-phonon interaction on the electronic structure of interfaces between organic molecules and a MoS$_2$ monolayer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05781v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: By means of first-principles calculations, we investigate the role of electron-phonon interaction in the electronic structure of hybrid interfaces, formed by MoS$_2$ and monolayers of the organic molecules pyrene and pyridine, respectively. Quasiparticle energies are initially obtained within the $G_0W_0$ approximation and subsequently used to evaluate the electron-phonon self-energy and momentum-resolved spectral functions to assess the temperature renormalization of the band structure. We find that the band-gap renormalization by zero-point vibrations of both hybrid systems is comparable to that of pristine MoS$_2$, with a value of approximately 80 meV. Pronounced features of molecular origin emerge in the spectral function of the valence region, which we attribute to satellites arising from out-of-plane vibrational modes of the organic monolayers. For pyrene, this satellite exhibits a predominantly molecular character, while for pyridine, it has a hybrid nature, originating from the coupling of molecular vibrations to the MoS$_2$ valence band.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05781v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ignacio Gonzalez Oliva, Sebastian Tillack, Fabio Caruso, Pasquale Pavone, Claudia Draxl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Unusual Dresselhaus Spin-Orbit Contribution of Even Order in Momentum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05787</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05787v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The spin-orbit (SO) coupling is conventionally known to manifest as \emph{odd} functions of momentum. Here, through both model calculations and symmetry analysis along with the method of invariants, we reveal that, in ordinary semiconductor heterostructures, a \emph{quadratic} Dresselhaus SO term -- inheriting from its bulk crystal form -- emerges via the interband effect, while complying with time-reversal and spatial symmetries. Furthermore, we observe that this unusual SO term gives rise to a range of striking quantum phenomena, including hybridized swirling texture, anisotropic energy dispersion, avoided band crossing, longitudinal \emph{Zitterbewegung}, and opposite spin evolution between different bands in quantum dynamics. These stand in stark contrast to those associated with the usual \emph{linear} SO terms. Our findings uncover a previously overlooked route for exploiting interband effects and open new avenues for spintronic functionalities that leverage unusual SO terms of \emph{even} orders in momentum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05787v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Yang, Wei Wang, Gerson J. Ferreira, Ning Hao, Ping Zhang, Jiyong Fu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crossover from quantum correlation to hot-carrier transport in scattering-tolerant 2D transistors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05846</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05846v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum correlation and hot-carrier transport represent two fundamentally distinct regimes of electronic conduction, rarely accessible within the same device. Here, we report a state-of-the-art monolayer transition metal dichalcogenides transistor architecture on a ferroelectric substrate that enables this crossover by leveraging the strong dielectric screening and in-plane gate control. At cryogenic temperatures, the devices exhibit reproducible quasi-periodic current fluctuations, consistent with an emergent potential landscape driven by electron-electron interactions at low carrier densities. As the temperature increases, this correlated potential profile thermally dissolves and transport is dominated by the lateral gate-field that drives the carriers with high kinetic energy. These hot-carriers can efficiently surmount the scattering events, exhibiting a record-high room-temperature electron mobility of ~4,800 cm^2/Vs and a maximum on-current ~0.5 mA/{\mu}m, surpassing traditional FETs in key performance metrics. These findings establish a unified approach for probing intermediate mesoscopic orders, while advancing the transistor performance limits in scalable 2D transistors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05846v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Debottam Daw, Houcine Bouzid, Sung-Gyu Lee, Wujoon Cha, Ki Kang Kim, Min-kyu Joo, Yan Wang, Manish Chhowalla, Young Hee Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of crystal field and momentum-based frustrated exchange interactions on multiorbital square skyrmion lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05896</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05896v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by recent theoretical predictions of a square-shaped skyrmion lattice (S-SkL) in centrosymmetric tetragonal Ce-based magnets [Yan Zha and Satoru Hayami, Phys. Rev. B 111, 165155 (2025)], we perform a comprehensive theoretical investigation on the role of multiorbital effects, magnetic anisotropy, and momentum-based frustrated exchange interactions in stabilizing such topologically nontrivial magnetic textures. By employing self-consistent mean-field calculations over a broad range of model parameters, we demonstrate that the cooperative interplay among multiorbital effects, frustrated exchange interactions at higher-harmonic wave vectors, and crystal-field anisotropy is crucial for the stabilization of the S-SkL. Furthermore, the competition between the easy-plane intraorbital coupling and the easy-axis interorbital coupling leads to a significant enhancement of the S-SkL stability region. We also identify a plethora of multi-$Q$ states, including magnetic bubble lattice and double-$Q$ phases with a local/global scalar chirality. Our findings elucidate the microscopic mechanism responsible for the emergence of S-SkLs in Ce-based magnets and provide a route toward realizing skyrmion lattices in a broader class of $f$-electron materials beyond conventional Gd- and Eu-based systems lacking orbital angular momentum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05896v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan S. Zha, Satoru Hayami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antiferromagnetic skyrmion as a magnonic lens</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05905</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05905v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A lens, a device transforming propagation directions in an organized fashion, is one of the fundamental tools for wave manipulation. Spin wave, the collective excitation of ordered magnetizations, stands out as a promising candidate for future energy-saving information technologies. Here we propose theoretically and verify by micromagnetic simulations, that an antiferromagnetic skyrmion naturally serves as a lens for spin wave, when the Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya strength exceeds a threshold. The underlying mechanism is the spin wave deflection caused by Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction, a mechanism that is ordinarily overshadowed by the magnetic topology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05905v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongbin Wu, Zi-Wu Wang, Jin Lan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploiting Negative Capacitance for Unconventional Coulomb Engineering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05943</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05943v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is known that the many-body ground state of a two-dimensional electron system can be tuned through Coulomb engineering by controlling the permittivity of the surrounding media. However, permittivities are traditionally restricted to positive values. In this paper we argue that the negative capacitance effect demonstrated in appropriately engineered structures can open new vistas in Coulomb engineering. Negative permittivities transform the natural repulsive interaction of electrons into an attractive one raising the intriguing possibility of a superconducting ground state. Using models of two-dimensional electron systems with linear and parabolic dispersion relations coupled to environments with negative capacitance, we estimate the strength and sign of the engineered Coulomb interaction and outline parameter regimes that could stabilize correlated electronic phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05943v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aravindh Shankar, Pramey Upadhyaya, Supriyo Datta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling the critical role of interfacial strain in adjusting electronic phase transitions in correlated vanadium dioxide</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05971</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05971v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Thermally activated abrupt switching between localized and itinerant electronic states during the insulator-metal transition (IMT) in correlated oxide systems serves as a powerful platform for exploring exotic physical phenomena and device functionality. One ongoing focal challenge lies in the realization of the broadly tunable IMT property in correlated system, to satisfy the demands of practical applications across diverse environments. Here, we unveil the overwhelming advantage associated with interfacial strain in bridging the bandwidth and band-filling control over the IMT property of VO2. Tailoring the orbital overlapping through strain-mediated bandwidth control enables a widely tunable thermally-driven IMT property in VO2. Benefiting from adjustable defect dynamics, filling-controlled Mott phase modulations from electron-localized t2g1eg0 state to electron-itinerant t2g1+{\Delta}eg0 state through oxygen vacancies can be facilitated by using in-plane tensile distortion, overcoming the high-speed bottlenecks in iontronic devices. Defect-engineered electronic phase transitions are primarily governed by the electron filling in t2g band of VO2, showcasing a definitive relationship with the incorporated defect concentration. Our findings provide fundamentally new insights into the on-demand design of emergent electronic states and transformative functionalities in correlated oxide system by unifying two fundamental control paradigms of bandwidth and band-filling control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05971v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuanchi Zhou, Xiaohui Yao, Xiaomei Qiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Properties of multiterminal superconducting nanostructure with double quantum dot</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05988</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05988v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the charge transport and thermoelectric properties of the junction, comprising double quantum dot embedded in T-shaped geometry on the interface between two normal/ferromagnetic electrodes and superconducting lead. We show that the interdot coupling plays major role in controlling the local and nonlocal transport properties of this setup. For the weak interdot coupling limit, we obtain the interferometric (Fano-type) lineshapes imprinted in the quasiparticle spectra, conductances and Seebeck coefficients. In contrast, for the strong interdot coupling, we predict that the local and nonlocal transport coefficients are primarily dependent on the molecular Andreev bound states induced by superconducting proximity effect, simultaneously in both quantum dots.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05988v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. G\'orski, K. Kucab, T. Doma\'nski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prevailing orbital excitations in paramagnetic kagome superconductor Cs(V$_{0.95}$Ti$_{0.05}$)$_3$Sb$_5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05999</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05999v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using the muon as a sensitive local magnetic probe, we investigated the layered kagome superconductor Cs(V$_{0.95}$Ti$_{0.05}$)$_3$Sb$_5$, a material notably devoid of both static magnetic moments and long-range charge order. Our transverse-field $\mu$SR measurements reveal that the local magnetic susceptibility, obtained via the muon Knight shift, is dominated by orbital excitations with a split energy levels around 20 meV. Meanwhile, the persistence of itinerant electron paramagnetism down to 5 K and 7 T confirms the absence of static magnetism within this regime. In addition, zero-field (ZF) $\mu$SR experiments detect a significant increase in the inhomogeneous nuclear dipolar field distribution below a featured temperature at 70 K. We attribute this ZF-$\mu$SR feature to the emergence of local lattice distortions at low temperatures, potentially arising from orbital ordering. Significantly, our study establishes that orbital excitations constitute an intrinsic property of the layered V-Sb kagome lattice. Despite its small magnitude, spin-orbit coupling plays a crucial role in governing the lattice dynamics, potentially driving the emergence of novel phenomena such as phonon carrying angular momentum in crystals with non-chiral point groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05999v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chennan Wang, Yuhang Zhang, Zhen Zhao, Zhouyouwei Lu, Hui Chen, Ziqiang Wang, Haitao Yang, Christian Bernhard, Xiaoli Dong, Hong-Jun Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large Spontaneous Nonreciprocal Charge Transport in a Zero-Magnetization Antiferromagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06009v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spontaneous breaking of time-reversal and spatial-inversion symmetries in solids triggers diverse intriguing phenomena. Although these phenomena have been extensively studied in insulators, similar investigations for metals remain limited. Herein, we report the observation and properties of spontaneous (i.e., zero-magnetic field) nonreciprocal charge transport in the zigzag intermetallic compound NdRu2Al10. This effect is attributed to the antiferromagnetic (AF) order, which can be interpreted as a magnetic toroidal dipole order. Our results reveal an excessively large nonreciprocal coefficient for this material, attributed to the strong effective magnetic field generated through c-f exchange interactions. The results also suggest that the nonreciprocal response of this material depends on the spin configurations of the AF domains. Overall, our findings are distinct from those previously reported for field-induced nonreciprocal charge transport and contribute to a comprehensive understanding of cross-correlations in symmetry-broken metals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06009v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/13pd-tlzp</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Kenta Sudo, Yuki Yanagi, Mitsuru Akaki, Hiroshi Tanida, Motoi Kimata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strain-Tunable Spin Filtering and Valley Splitting Coexisting with Anomalous Hall Effect in 2D Half-Metallic VSe2/VN Heterostructure: Toward a Unified Spintronic-Valleytronic Platform</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06069v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rapid progress in valleytronics and spintronics is limited by the scarcity of two-dimensional materials that simultaneously provide robust valley splitting and strong spin selectivity. Here we showed that a van der Waals heterostructure (VSe2/VN) built from hexagonal VSe2 and hexagonal VN addressed this gap. Using first-principles density functional theory, phonon, ab initio molecular dynamics stability tests, Bader charge analysis, and Wannier-based Berry-curvature calculations, we demonstrated an energetically and dynamically stable heterostructure that exhibited interlayer charge transfer and a work function intermediate between the constituent monolayers. The electronic structure showed small indirect PBE gap (108.9 meV), with HSE06 indicating a half-metallic tendency; a sizable conduction-band valley splitting (\Delta CKK' = 22.9 meV for spin-up and \Delta CKK' = 61.3 meV for spin-down); and pronounced spin asymmetry, where the spin-down channel showed a wide semiconducting gap (0.64 eV) while the spin-up channel was nearly gapless. These features yielded a high zero-strain spin-filter efficiency P = 75.4%, tunable to 82.5% under +4% biaxial tensile strain. The heterostructure also supported non-zero, valley-contrasting Berry curvature, and a large anomalous Hall conductivity (peak sigmaxy = 568.33 S/cm). Importantly, mean-field estimation placed the ferromagnetic Curie temperature near room temperature at zero strain (Tc = 284.04 K), while Tc decreased to 183.9 K at +4% strain, the magnetic order remained robust to cryogenic temperatures, providing a beneficial tuning knob to balance spin-filter performance with thermal stability in device-relevant regimes. These results identified VSe2/VN as a practical, strain-tunable platform for integrated valleytronic, spintronic devices, and for exploring anomalous Hall and valley-dependent transport phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06069v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vivek Chowdhury, Ahmed Zubair</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magneto-Optical Study of Chiral Magnetic Modes in NiI$_{2}$: Direct Evidence for Kitaev Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06093v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Bond-dependent magnetic interactions, particularly those described by the Kitaev model, have emerged as a key pathway toward realizing unconventional magnetic states such as quantum spin liquids and topologically nontrivial excitations, including skyrmions. These interactions frustrate conventional magnetic order and give rise to rich collective behavior that continues to challenge both theory and experiment. While Kitaev physics has been extensively explored in the context of honeycomb magnets, direct evidence for its role in real materials remains scarce. Magnetic van der Waals (vdW) materials have emerged as a versatile platform for exploring low-dimensional electrical, magnetic, and correlated electronic phenomena, and provide a fertile ground for potential applications ranging from spintronics to multiferroic devices and quantum information technologies. Here, we demonstrate, through magneto-transmission, Faraday angle rotation, and magnetic circular dichroism measurements, that the magnetic excitation spectrum of NiI$_2$, a van der Waals multiferroic material, is more accurately captured by a Kitaev-based spin model than by the previously invoked helical spin framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06093v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kartik Panda, Chaebin Kim, Daniel Bazyliansky, Javier Taboada-Guti\'errez, Florian Le Mardel\'e, Jan Dzian, Guy Levy, Jae Ha Kim, Youjin Lee, Bumchan Park, Martin Mourigal, Jae Hoon Kim, Alexey B. Kuzmenko, Milan Orlita, Je-Geun Park, Nimrod Bachar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phonon-Dominated Thermal Transport and Large Violation of the Wiedemann-Franz Law in Topological Semimetal CoSi</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06290v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Wiedemann-Franz (WF) law, relating the electronic thermal conductivity ($\kappa_{\rm e}$) to the electrical conductivity, is vital in numerous applications such as in the design of thermoelectric materials and in the experimental determination of the lattice thermal conductivity ($\kappa_{\rm L}$). While the WF law is generally robust, violations are frequently observed, typically manifesting in a reduced Lorenz number ($L$) relative to the Sommerfeld value ($L_0$) due to inelastic scattering. Here, we report a pronounced departure from the WF law in the topological semimetal CoSi, where the electronic Lorenz number ($L_{\rm e}$) instead rises up to $\sim40\%$ above $L_0$. We demonstrate that this anomaly arises from strong bipolar diffusive transport, enabled by topological band-induced electron-hole compensation, which allows electrons and holes to flow cooperatively and additively enhance the heat current. Concurrently, we unveil that the lattice contribution to thermal conductivity is anomalously large and becomes the dominant component below room temperature. As a result, if $\kappa_{\rm L}$ is assumed negligible -- as conventional in metals, the resulting $L$ from the total thermal conductivity ($\kappa_{\rm tot}=\kappa_{\rm L}+\kappa_{\rm e}$) deviates from $L_0$ by more than a factor of three. Our work provides deeper insight into the unconventional thermal transport physics in topological semimetals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06290v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luyao Zhong, Xin Jin, Mingquan He, Rui Wang, Xiaoyuan Zhou, Tianqi Deng, Xiaolong Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic and structural properties of epitaxial Er-substituted yttrium iron garnet films grown by pulsed laser deposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06324</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06324v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Er-substituted yttrium iron garnet (Er:YIG) holds the potential of combining the low magnetic damping of YIG with the telecom-band optical transitions of $\text{Er}^{3+}$ ions, making it a suitable material for hybrid optomagnonic devices and microwave-to-optical quantum transduction. We report the epitaxial growth of $\text{Er}_{x}\text{Y}_{3-x}\text{Fe}_{5}\text{O}_{12}$ films with $x=0.008-0.20$ on (111)-oriented gadolinium gallium garnet (GGG) substrates using pulsed laser deposition. X-ray diffraction, reciprocal space mapping, and scanning transmission electron microscopy confirm single-phase, fully coherent growth with atomically sharp interfaces across the entire substitution range. Magnetometry reveals a gradual decrease in saturation magnetization with increasing Er content, consistent with antiparallel coupling between Er$^{3+}$ spins and the net Fe$^{3+}$ moments, along with the emergence of an in-plane uniaxial magnetic anisotropy. The ferromagnetic resonance broadens with Er concentration due to increased Gilbert damping and inhomogeneous linewidth broadening. Films with low Er content ($x=0.008$), most relevant for optomagnonic applications, retain nearly isotropic magnetization and exhibit a damping parameter only slightly higher than that of undoped YIG. These results identify growth and substitution conditions that preserve YIG's low-loss magnetic properties while introducing optical functionality, establishing Er:YIG as a viable platform for hybrid quantum magnonics and microwave-to-optical transduction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06324v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Flajsman, Lars Peeters, Armi Kosunen, Lide Yao, Ionela Vrejoiu, Sebastiaan van Dijken</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear tetramer formation in nonmagnetic pyrochlore niobate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06366</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06366v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate displacive short-range order in pyrochlore Y2Nb2O7, which exhibits a nonmagnetic insulating state despite the presence of formally tetravalent Nb4+ (S = 1/2) ions on the pyrochlore network. Synchrotron x-ray diffraction on a single crystal reveals a characteristic x-ray diffuse scattering (XDS) pattern primarily around q = {0.5, 0.5, 2}. Reverse Monte Carlo (RMC) simulations uncover local Nb displacements along the &lt;111&gt; axes, leading to the formation of linear Nb4 tetramers. Our findings highlight a crucial role of molecular orbital degrees of freedom in stabilizing the nonmagnetic insulating state. This study demonstrates that RMC analysis of XDS provides a powerful approach for elucidating short-range correlations and the underlying mechanisms governing the physical properties of crystalline materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06366v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shota Nishida, Shunsuke Kitou, Shingo Toyoda, Yuiga Nakamura, Yusuke Tokunaga, Taka-hisa Arima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-valley 0.7 anomaly in bilayer graphene/WSe$_2$ quantum point contacts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06384</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06384v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report a well-resolved 0.7 conductance anomaly at $G = 0.7\times(2e^2/h)$ in bilayer graphene/WSe$_2$ quantum point contacts. Proximity-enhanced spin-orbit coupling splits the four-fold ground state of bilayer graphene into well-separated spin-valley locked Kramers doublets. The anomaly emerges between these opposite spin-valley states. Despite fundamentally different band structure and wavefunction characteristics, the temperature and bias phenomenology closely mirror GaAs systems. In contrast, the parallel magnetic field response differs significantly, confirming the central role of valley degrees of freedom. This opens new pathways to study valley-exchange correlation physics in regimes inaccessible to conventional semiconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06384v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonas D. Gerber, Efe Ersoy, Michele Masseroni, Markus Niese, Artem O. Denisov, Christoph Adam, Lara Ostertag, Jessica Richter, Takashi Taniguchi, Kenji Watanabe, Yigal Meir, Thomas Ihn, Klaus Ensslin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrafast symmetry modulation and induced magnetic excitation in the Kagome metal RbV3Sb5</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06389</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06389v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Light-matter interaction in frustrated Kagome metals enables access to hidden quantum states, yet the microscopic origin of symmetry breaking under ultrafast excitation remains elusive. Here, we uncover a microscopic mechanism for laser-induced symmetry breaking in RbV3Sb5 through first-principles real-time simulations. Selective excitation of a single-QM phonon mode dynamically breaks both rotational and time-reversal symmetries within the 2X2X1 charge density wave (CDW) superlattice. The resulting anisotropic lattice distortion lifts geometric frustration and stabilizes a nonequilibrium ferrimagnetic phase, accompanied by a sizable intrinsic anomalous Hall effect. Distinct from prior interpretations based on orbital antiferromagnetism or extrinsic perturbations, our findings reveal a spin-driven pathway for symmetry breaking under strong optical fields. These results provide a microscopic foundation for exploring how spin, lattice and charge degrees of freedom are intertwined in nonequilibrium correlated states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06389v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengxue Guan, Xiaodong Zhou, Jingyi Duan, Chaoxi Cui, Wei Jiang, Zeying Zhang, Binhua Zhang, Zhengwei Nie, Xun Shi, Zhiwei Wang, Yugui Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Facile Salt-Assisted Hydrothermal Synthesis of Nanodiamonds from CHO Precursors: Atomic-Scale Mechanistic Insights</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06467v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hydrothermal synthesis offers an economical and scalable way to produce nanodiamonds under relatively mild, low-pressure and low-temperature conditions. However,its sustainability and the detailed mechanisms behind diamond formation in such environments are still not fully understood. In this work, we designed ten hydrothermal synthesis protocols using different CHO-based molecular precursors containing COOH and OH groups, such as organic acids, polyols, sugars, and polysaccharides.The reactions were carried out at 190 degrees Centigrade in chlorinated, strongly alkaline aqueous solutions with alkali and alkaline-earth metal ions. Using high-resolution transmission electron microscopy and X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy, we confirmed the presence of diamond-specific lattice planes and sp3-hybridized carbon structures. Our results show that the type of precursor, its molecular size, and the ionic composition of the solution play key roles in determining the defect patterns and polymorph distribution in the resulting nanodiamonds. Atomic-scale imaging showed both coherent and incoherent transitions from graphite to diamond, along with gradual lattice compression and complex twinning patterns. These observations provide direct insight into how interfacial crystallography and defect dynamics drive diamond formation in aqueous systems. Overall, the study positions hydrothermal synthesis as a sustainable, chemistry-driven, and tunable approach for creating nanodiamonds tailored for applications in quantum technologies, biomedicine, catalysis, and advanced materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06467v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soumya Pratap Tripathy, Sayan Saha, Saurabh Kumar Gupta, Pallavee Das, Binay Priyadarsan Nayak, Anup Routray, Priya Choudhary, Srihari V, Bitop Maitra, Ashna Reyaz, Anushka Samant, Debopriya Sinha, Kritideepan Parida, Kuna Das, Abhijeet Sahoo, Kunal Pal, Sirsendu Sekhar Ray</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resonating valence bond pairing energy in graphene by quantum Monte Carlo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06506v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We determine the resonating-valence-bond (RVB) state in graphene using real-space quantum Monte Carlo with correlated variational wave functions. Variational and diffusion quantum Monte Carlo (DMC) calculations with Jastrow-Slater-determinant and Jastrow-antisymmetrized-geminal-power ansatze are employed to evaluate the RVB pairing energy. Using a rectangular graphene sample that lacks $\pi/3$ rotational symmetry, we found that the single-particle energy gap near the Fermi level depends on the system size along the $x$-direction. The gap vanishes when the length satisfies $L_x=3n\sqrt{3}d$, where $n$ is an integer and $d$ is the carbon-carbon bond length, otherwise, the system, exhibits a finite gap. Our DMC results show no stable RVB pairing in the zero-gap case, whereas the opening of a finite gap near the Fermi level stabilizes the electron pairing. The DMC predicted absolute value of pairing energy at the thermodynamic limit for a finite-gap system is $\sim 0.48(1)$ mHa/atom. Our results reveal a feometry-driven electron pairing mechanism in the confined graphene nanostructure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06506v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Azadi, A. Principi, T. D. K\"uhne, M. S. Bahramy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shape-controlled growth of two-dimensional kagome-lattice colloidal crystals through nanoparticle capping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06630</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06630v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Organic capping ligands can selectively bind to crystal facets to modulate growth kinetics and are important in chemical synthesis of inorganic nanocrystals. Using the capping ligands for shape-controlled growth of colloidal crystals is challenging due to the size mismatch of molecules and nanoparticle building blocks. In existing synthetic pathways, colloidal crystal shapes are determined by their thermodynamically favored phases yet controlling their shapes independent of lattice symmetry is vital to study many solid-state properties. Here, we develop a nanoparticle capping strategy to control colloidal crystal shapes and structural heterogeneity. Au bipyramids were used as building blocks and assembled into rhombohedral colloidal crystals driven by DNA hybridization. In (111) planes of the crystals, bipyramids assembled into kagome lattices, featuring structure cavities organized in a hexagonal lattice. The rhombohedral crystals have truncated tetrahedral crystal habits, and the degree of truncation defines the exposed facets and crystal shapes. Our surface capping strategy is to introduce DNA-modified nanospheres as effective capping agents, which selectively register on the surface vacancies of the kagome facets and resemble the role of organic ligands in classic nanocrystal growth. Such selective capping is driven by maximizing DNA hybridization and leads to slower growth of the (111) kagome facets, changing the crystal shape from three-dimensional truncated tetrahedra to two-dimensional layered microplates with structural heterogeneity and shape anisotropy. This study underpins the importance of capping agents in colloidal crystal growth and inspires effective ways to control the growth kinetics and heterostructures of colloidal crystals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06630v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rui Huang, Jordan Austin-Frank Wilson, Allen Sun, Artemis Harlow, Zhiwei Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Monte Carlo study of magnetism and chiral d+id-wave superconductivity in twisted bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06631v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We employ a large-scale, unbiased constrained-path quantum Monte Carlo method to systematically simulate the effective two-orbital Hubbard model for twisted bilayer graphene in order to gain deeper insight into the relationship between correlated states and the superconducting pairing mechanism in twisted bilayer graphene, as well as the influence of the twist angle on superconductivity. Initially, we investigate the modulation of superconductivity by nearest-neighbor attractive Coulomb interactions, demonstrating that electron-phonon coupling plays a significant role in the system. Our numerical results reveal that the superconducting state is dominated by chiral NN-d+id superconducting electron pairing symmetry, and that such nearest-neighbor attractive Coulomb interactions significantly enhance the effective long-range pairing correlation function of chiral NN-d+id wave. Then, we explore how the twist angle affects the superconducting state. Our results show that as the twist angle deviates downward from 1.08{\deg}, the effective pairing correlation function of the chiral NN-d+id wave increases substantially. Through these investigations, our numerical findings not only contribute to a more comprehensive understanding of strongly correlated systems such as twisted bilayer graphene, but also provide guidance for identifying twist-angle systems with potentially higher superconducting transition temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06631v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.7498/aps.74.20250305</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Shi-Chao Fang, Xin-Yi Liao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KTaO3-based editable superconducting diode</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06660v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Superconducting diodes, which enable dissipationless supercurrent flow in one direction while blocking it in the reverse direction, are emerging as pivotal components for superconducting electronics. The development of editable superconducting diodes could unlock transformative applications, including dynamically reconfigurable quantum circuits that adapt to operational requirements. Here, we report the first observation of the superconducting diode effect (SDE) in LaAlO3/KTaO3 heterostructures, a two-dimensional oxide interface superconductor with exceptional tunability. We observe a strong SDE in Hall-bar (or strip-shaped) devices under perpendicular magnetic fields (&lt; 15 Oe), with efficiencies above 40% and rectification signals exceeding 10 mV. Through conductive atomic force microscope lithography, we demonstrate reversible nanoscale editing of the SDE's polarity and efficiency by locally modifying the superconducting channel edges. This approach enables multiple nonvolatile configurations within a single device, realizing an editable superconducting diode. Our work establishes LAO/KTO as a platform for vortex-based nonreciprocal transport and provides a pathway toward designer quantum circuits with on-demand functionalities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06660v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yishuai Wang, Wenze Pan, Meng Zhang, Yanwu Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compression-induced magnetic obstructed atomic insulator and spin singlet state in antiferromagnetic KV2Se2O</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06712v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Among the complex many-body systems, the metal-insulator transition stands out as a cornerstone and a particularly fertile ground for scientific inquiry. The established models including Mott insulator, Anderson localization and Peierls transition, are still insufficient to capture the complex and intertwined phenomena observed in certain material systems. KV2Se2O, a newly discovered room-temperature altermagnetic candidate exhibiting a spin-density-wave transition below 100 K, provides a unique platform to investigate the interplay of many-body effects and unconventional magnetism, specifically the anticipated metal-insulator transition under extreme conditions. Here, we report a compression-induced insulator by suppressing the metallic behavior without structural phase transition. The newly opened gap is estimated to be 40 meV at around 43.5 GPa, given direct evidence for the insulating state. A concurrent switching of carrier type demonstrates the large Fermi surface reconstruction crossing the metal-insulator transition. The density functional theory calculations indicate that the discovered V+2.5-based insulator is a magnetic obstructed atomic insulator, being a spin-singlet state with bonding orbital order. This work not only presents an archetype of a pressure-driven metal-insulator transition decoupled from structural change but also delivers fundamental physical insights into the metal-insulator transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06712v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liucheng Chen, Jiayi Yue, Jingwen Cheng, Jianli Bai, Zexiao Zhang, Xiaoli Ma, Fang Hong, Genfu Chen, Jian-Tao Wang, Zhijun Wang, Xiaohui Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interface Roughness Scattering Processes in Quantum wells in a Tilted Quantizing Magnetic Field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06771</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06771v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Scattering processes by the interface roughness in a quantum well in a quantizing magnetic field are considered. An expression for the scattering rate is derived for a magnetic field tilted relative to the quantum well layers. By analyzing this expression, trends in the behavior of the scattering rate are established with variation in the magnetic field strength and orientation, the potential profile of the quantum well, and the interface roughness parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06771v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. P. Telenkov, Yu. A. Mityagin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal two-stage dynamics and phase control in skyrmion formation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06777</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06777v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We uncover a universal two-stage dynamics during skyrmion formation and establish its connection to equilibrium phases through the introduction of a chiral correlation $\chi$. Stage I involves stripe coarsening governed by the exchange-to-DMI ratio $J'$, while stage II entails stripe contraction driven by the synergy between $J'$ and the anisotropy-to-DMI ratio $K'$. The magnetic field-to-DMI ratio $B'$ influences both stages. By combining symbolic regression with neural networks, we model the competition and cooperation among these parameters and derive a skyrmion formation criterion, $0.58 K'J' + \mu B'J' &gt; 1$. Our model disentangles their distinct roles: $J'$ sets the stripe width, $K'$ primarily controls the skyrmion size, and $B'$ strongly affects the topological charge. This approach provides a general framework for predicting and controlling magnetic phases in chiral magnets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06777v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shiwei Zhu, Xinyuan Guan, Zhen Sun, Qiuyao Zhang, Changsheng Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heat Coulomb blockade in a double-island metal-semiconductor device</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06783v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the thermal transport properties of a mesoscopic device comprising two metallic islands embedded in a two-dimensional electron gas in the integer quantum Hall regime. It is shown that the $2M$ ballistic edge channels connecting the islands to the external reservoirs and the $N$ inter-island channels play a central role in the phenomenon of heat Coulomb blockade. Unlike the single-island case, where the heat flux is reduced by exactly one quantum of thermal conductance, we predict an additional suppression proportional to the factor $M^2/(2N+M)^2$. We further examine a configuration in which the islands are placed between electrodes at different temperatures and identify the conditions under which the Wiedemann-Franz law is violated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06783v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. V. Parafilo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polarization - Magnetization Coupling in Visible Light Ferroelectric Double Perovskites</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06800</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06800v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The bulk photovoltaic effect (BPVE), arising from broken inversion symmetry in ferroelectrics, offers a distinct pathway toward high-efficiency next-generation photovoltaics. We propose and investigate A/A$^\prime$-ordered double perovskites KLaFeMoO$_6$ and NaLaFeMoO$_6$ as promising single-phase ferroelectric photovoltaic (FE-PV) materials. First-principles calculations reveal robust P2$_1$ symmetry with A-site layer and B-site rock-salt ordering, accompanied by hybrid improper ferroelectricity driven by $a^{-}a^{-}c^{+}$ octahedral tilts. Both compounds exhibit significant spontaneous polarization and indirect band gaps of $\sim$ 1.8 eV, well suited for visible-light absorption ($&gt;$10$^5$ cm$^{-1}$). Low carrier effective masses along the polar axis indicate efficient charge transport. \textit{Ab initio} molecular dynamics simulations (AIMD) show that polarization-coupled magnetization switching is feasible above room temperature, making these materials suitable for room-temperature applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06800v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sathiyamoorthy Buvaneswaran, Trilochan Sahoo, Saurabh Ghosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physical properties and first-principles calculations of an altermagnet candidate Cs$_{1-\delta}$V$_2$Te$_2$O</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06865v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report the crystal growth, structure, physical properties, and first-principles calculations of a vanadium-based oxytelluride Cs$_{1-\delta}$V$_2$Te$_2$O. The material possesses two-dimensional V$_2$O square nets sandwiched by tellurium layers, with local crystallographic symmetry satisfying the spin symmetry for a $d$-wave altermagnet. An antiferromagnetic transition at 293 K is unambiguously evidenced from the measurements of magnetic susceptibility and specific heat. In addition, a secondary transition at $\sim$70 K is also observed, possibly associated with a Lifshitz transition. The first-principles calculations indicate robust N\'{e}el-type collinear antiferromagnetism in the V$_2$O plane. Consequently, spin splittings show up in momentum space, in relation with the real-space mirror/rotation symmetry. Interestingly, the V-$d_{yz}/d_{xz}$ electrons, which primarily contribute the quasi-one-dimensional Fermi surface, turns out to be fully orbital- and spin-polarized, akin to the case of a half metal. Our work lays a solid foundation on the potential applications utilizing altermagnetic properties in vanadium-based oxychalcogenides.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06865v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chang-Chao Liu, Jing Li, Ji-Yong Liu, Jia-Yi Lu, Hua-Xun Li, Yi Liu, Guang-Han Cao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultra-long-range spin coupling in graphene revealed by atomically resolved spin excitations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06887</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06887v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic interactions between localized spins-1/2 play a central role in quantum magnetism, spin-based quantum computing, and quantum simulation. The range and strength of these interactions are key figures of merit. Here, we probe exchange interactions in pairs and trimers of spins-1/2 introduced by chemisorption of individual hydrogen atoms on graphene. Using scanning tunneling microscopy and inelastic electron tunneling spectroscopy, supported by large-scale mean-field Hubbard calculations, we demonstrate 3 meV exchange couplings at separations beyond 10 nm, surpassing all prior systems. The couplings can be ferro- or antiferromagnetic depending on the relative sublattice arrangement. Real-space mapping of spin excitation amplitudes enables characterization with atomic-resolution. Through atomic manipulation we extend this control to spin trimers, revealing collective spin excitations when pairwise exchange couplings are comparable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06887v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Beatriz Vi\~na-Baus\'a, Antonio. T. Costa, Joao Henriques, Eva Cort\'es-del R\'io, Roberto Carrasco, Pierre Mallet, Jean-Yves Veuillen, Joaqu\'in Fern\'andez-Rossier, Iv\'an Brihuega</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Plasmon resonance in a sub-THz graphene-based detector: theory and experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06891</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06891v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a combined experimental and theoretical study of photovoltage generation in a bilayer graphene (BLG) transistor structure exposed to subterahertz radiation. The device features a global bottom and split top gate, enabling independent control of the band gap and Fermi level, thereby enabling the formation of a tunable p-n junction in graphene. Measurements show that the photovoltage arises primarily through a thermoelectric mechanism driven by heating of the p-n junction in the middle of the channel. We also provide a theoretical justification for the excitation of two-dimensional plasmons at a record-low frequency of 0.13 THz, which manifests itself as characteristic oscillations in the measured photovoltage. These plasmonic resonances, activated by a decrease in charge carrier concentration due to opening of the band gap, lead to a local enhancement of the electromagnetic field and an increase in the carrier temperature in the junction region. The record-low frequency of plasmon resonance is enabled by the low carrier density achievable in the bilayer graphene upon electrical induction of the band gap.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06891v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. M. Moiseenko, E. Titova, M. Kashchenko, D. Svintsov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-resolution magnetostriction measurements of the Pauli-limited superconductor Sr2RuO4</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06938</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06938v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We performed high-resolution magnetostriction measurements on the Pauli-limited superconductor Sr$_2$RuO$_4$ using high-quality single crystals. A first-order superconducting transition, accompanied by pronounced hysteresis, was observed under in-plane magnetic fields, where the relative length change of the sample, $\Delta L/L$, was on the order of $10^{-8}$. To ensure the reliability of the measurements, particular attention was paid to minimizing the influence of magnetic torque, which can significantly affect data under in-plane field configurations, via field-angle-resolved magnetostriction. Within the hysteresis regime, slightly below the Pauli-limited upper critical field, a hump-like anomaly in the magnetostriction coefficient was identified. Furthermore, a characteristic double-peak structure in the field-angle derivative of the magnetostriction provides additional support for this anomaly. Although these findings may reflect a lattice response associated with the emergence of the Fulde-Ferrell-Larkin-Ovchinnikov (FFLO) phase in Sr$_2$RuO$_4$, the possibility of a broadened first-order transition cannot be excluded. Notably, this magnetostriction anomaly qualitatively deviates from the FFLO phase boundary suggested by previous NMR measurements, highlighting the necessity for further experimental and theoretical investigations to elucidate the nature of the FFLO state in this material.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06938v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shunichiro Kittaka, Yohei Kono, Toshiro Sakakibara, Naoki Kikugawa, Shinya Uji, Dmitry A. Sokolov, Kazushige Machida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-local synchronization of continuous time crystals in a semiconductor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06964</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06964v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Synchronization resulting in unified collective behavior of the individual elements of a system that are weakly coupled to each other has long fascinated scientists. Examples range from the periodic oscillation of coupled pendulum clocks to the rhythmic behavior in biological systems. Here we demonstrate this effect in a solid-state platform: spatially remote, auto-oscillating electron-nuclear spin systems in a semiconductor. When two such oscillators separated by up to 40 ${\mu}$m are optically pumped, their individually different frequencies lock to a common value, revealing long-range coherent coupling. For larger separations, the synchronization breaks. The interaction distance matches the electron spin diffusion length, identifying spin transport as the coupling-mediating mechanism and establishing phase coherence over mesoscopic distances. As a consequence, a wide-area optical pump drives all oscillators within the illuminated spot into a single synchronized state, despite their inhomogeneity. This synchronization accounts for the exceptional stability of the resulting auto-oscillations, enabling collective motion in distributed spin systems and paving the way toward coherent spin networks in spintronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06964v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex Greilich, Nataliia E. Kopteva, Vladimir L. Korenev, Philipp A. Haude, Linus Kunze, Ben W. Grobecker, Sergiu Anghel, Markus Betz, Manfred Bayer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controlling viscosity to engineer focal conic domains in photonic cellulose nanocrystal films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06981</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06981v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cellulose nanocrystals (CNCs) form cholesteric architectures that can have color specific reflectivity and enable sustainable photonic films. However, achieving uniform color, suppressing iridescence, and accessing ordered defect structures such as focal conic domains remain challenging. Here, we control the photonic properties of CNC films by steering the self assembly process. Across 24 dish-cast films with varying salt concentrations and sonication doses, we combine viscosity measurements, timelapse polarized optical microscopy, and angle-resolved reflectance spectroscopy to correlate evaporation dynamics with photonic structure. We show that viscosity, jointly controlled by NaCl-mediated electrostatic screening and sonication-induced bundle fragmentation, dictates the extent of tactoid coalescence. Low-viscosity suspensions generate large, homogeneous cholesteric domains and narrow spectral responses, while high viscosity leads to arrested, heterogenous domains and increased diffuse light reflection. Critically, within a narrow parameter window of intermediate ionic strength and moderate sonication, we reproducibly engineer photonically active focal conic domains. These results identify viscosity-driven flow as a key, previously underappreciated factor in CNC self-assembly and establish design rules for producing structurally colored films with tunable photonic response, reduced iridescence, and controllable defect architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06981v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diogo V. Saraiva, Lotte Polling, Ivo R. Vermaire, Sander J. W. Vonk, Freddy T. Rabouw, Lisa Tran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microscopic origin of period-four stripe charge-density-wave in kagome metal CsV$_3$Sb$_5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06995</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06995v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The interplay between unconventional density waves and exotic superconductivity has attracted growing interest. Kagome superconductors $A\rm{V}_3\rm{Sb}_5$ ($A = \rm{K}, \rm{Rb}, \rm{Cs}$) offer a platform for studying quantum phase transitions and the resulting symmetry breaking. Among these quantum phases, the $4a_0$ stripe charge-density-wave (CDW) has been widely observed for $A=\rm{Rb}$ and $\rm{Cs}$ by scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) and nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) measurements. However, the microscopic origin of the $4a_0$ stripe CDW remains elusive, and no theoretical studies addressing this phenomenon have been reported so far. In this paper, we propose a microscopic mechanism for the emergence of the $4a_0$ stripe CDW. We analyze the CDW instability in the 12-site kagome lattice Hubbard model with the $2\times2$ bond order driven by the paramagnon-interference mechanism by focusing on the short-range magnetic fluctuations due to the geometrical frustration of kagome lattice. We reveal that the nesting vector of the reconstructed Fermi surface, formed by the $2\times 2$ bond order, gives rise to a $4a_0$-period CDW. Remarkably, the obtained stripe CDW is composed of both the off-site hopping integral modulations and on-site potentials. The real-space structure of the stripe CDW obtained here is in good qualitative agreement with the experimentally observed stripe pattern.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06995v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuma Murata, Rina Tazai, Youichi Yamakawa, Seiichiro Onari, Hiroshi Kontani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low Temperature Two Fluid State in SmB6</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07000v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Comprehensive study using DC transport, specific heat, magnetization, and two-coil mutual inductance measurements unveils an understanding of three temperature regimes in SmB$_6$: (i) $T \geq T^{*}$ ($\sim66$K), (ii) $T_g$ ($\sim40$ K) $\leq T &lt; T^{*}$, and (iii) $T &lt; T_g$. Onset of Kondo breakdown below $T^{*}$ releases disorder-driven magnetic fluctuations, which splits the bulk ($\sim116$K) and surface Kondo temperature ($T_k^{s} \approx 7$ K). Below $T_g$, as magnetic fluctuations subside, surface Kondo screening revives, stabilizing the topological surface state and generating an in-gap feature ($\sim2.2$ meV) across which Dirac-like carriers are excited. Nyquist impedance analysis reveals a crossover from purely capacitive to capacitive-inductive behavior, signalling a disorder-driven two-fluid phase of heavy quasiparticles and light, high-mobility carriers below $T_g$. We identify a characteristic length scale, $L_{\nu_0}(T)$, associated with the high-mobility phase, exhibiting an almost divergent trend below $T_k^{s}$. These findings underscore the complex nature of the surface conducting state in SmB$_6$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07000v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sayantan Ghosh, Sugata Paul, Tamoghna Chattoraj, Ritesh Kumar, Zachary Fisk, S. S. Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral phases and dynamics of dipoles in triangular optical ladders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07042</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07042v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dipoles in triangular optical ladders constitute a flexible platform for the study of the interplay between geometric frustration and long-range anisotropic interactions, and in particular for the observation of the spontaneous onset of chirality. Frustration magnifies the effect of the dipolar interactions in itinerant polarized dipolar bosons. As a result, the dipole-induced transition between a chiral superfluid and a non-chiral two-component superfluid may be observed for current state-of-the-art temperatures even for the weak inter-site interaction characterizing magnetic atoms in standard optical lattices. On the other hand, pinned spin-$1/2$ dipoles, which we discuss in the context of polar molecules in two rotational states, realize frustrated dipolar XXZ spin models. By controlling the external electric field strength and orientation, these systems can explore a rich ground-state landscape including chiral and nematic phases, as well as intriguing chiral dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07042v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arjo Dasgupta, Mateusz \L\k{a}cki, Henning Korbmacher, Gustavo A. Dom\'inguez-Castro, Jakub Zakrzewski, Luis Santos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic anisotropy and intermediate valence in CeCo$_5$ ferromagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07063v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The intermediate valence of Ce in CeCo$_5$ challenges standard density functional theory (DFT) and static DFT+$U$ approaches, which fail to capture its magnetic properties. By combining DFT+$U$ with exact diagonalization of the Anderson impurity model for the Ce 4$f$ shell, we find a substantial reduction of Ce spin and orbital moments, consistent with DFT+DMFT, arising from Ce$^{4+}$ - Ce$^{3+}$ valence fluctuations. The total magnetic moment of 6.70 $\mu_B$ agrees with experiment, and the calculated $4f$ density of states reproduces photoemission and Bremsstrahlung isochromat spectra. The uniaxial magnetic anisotropy energy reaches 4.8 meV/f.u. when Coulomb correlations on both Ce 4$f$ and Co 3$d$ shells are included, in very good agreement with experimental data. These results highlight the importance of dynamical correlations and provide guidance for exploring high-performance, low-rare-earth-content permanent magnets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07063v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander B. Shick (Institute of Physics, Czech Academy of Sciences, Na Slovance 2, 182 21 Prague, Czech Republic), Evgenia A. Tereshina-Chitrova (Institute of Physics, Czech Academy of Sciences, Na Slovance 2, 182 21 Prague, Czech Republic)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniaxial stress control of versatile helimagnetic phases in the square-lattice itinerant magnet EuAl$_{4}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07079</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07079v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate uniaxial-stress effects on the magnetic phase diagram of the square-lattice itinerant magnet EuAl$_{4}$, where strong coupling among spin, lattice, and charge produces a variety of helimagnetic phases, including rhombic and square skyrmion lattices. Combining resistivity and magnetization measurements with neutron scattering, we find that compressive stresses of only several tens of MPa along [010] enhance antiferromagnetic character and shorten the magnetic modulation period in the lowest-temperature single-Q spiral state, thereby driving the critical temperatures and fields of multiple phases to higher values. First-principles calculations show that increasing orthorhombic lattice distortion deforms the Fermi surface relevant to the magnetism, providing compelling evidence that Fermi-surface nesting plays a crucial role in stabilizing the helical magnetic modulations in EuAl$_{4}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07079v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masaki Gen, Takuya Nomoto, Hiraku Saito, Taro Nakajima, Yusuke Tokunaga, Rina Takagi, Shinichiro Seki, Taka-hisa Arima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defect-Mediated Phase Engineering of 2D Ag at the Graphene/SiC Interface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07151</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07151v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Atomically thin silver (Ag) films offer unique opportunities in plasmonic, quantum optics, and energy harvesting, yet conventional growth methods struggle to achieve structural control at the monolayer limit. Here, we demonstrate phase-selective synthesis of large-area, crystalline 2D Ag films via defect-engineered confinement heteroepitaxy (CHet) at the epitaxial graphene/silicon carbide (EG/SiC) interface. By tuning graphene growth and post-growth defect introduction, two distinct Ag phases are achieved with disparate properties: a nearly commensurate Ag(1) lattice stabilized by vacancy and line defects in epitaxial graphene, and a denser Ag(2) phase preferentially grown with sp3-rich zero-layer graphene. Structural and spectroscopic characterization confirm lattice registry with the SiC substrate, while theoretical calculations reveal a thermodynamic preference for Ag(2) but an easier nucleation for Ag(1). Both phases are found to be semiconducting, with the Ag(2) phase exhibiting slightly enhanced n-doping of graphene. Notably, nonlinear optical measurements reveal a three-order magnitude difference in second-order susceptibility between the two phases, demonstrating promise for phase-tunable 2D metals in reconfigurable optoelectronic and metamaterial platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07151v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arpit Jain, Boyang Zheng, Sawani Datta, Kanchan Ulman, Jakob Henz, Matthew Wei-Jun Liu, Van Dong Pham, Wen He, Chengye Dong, Li-Syuan Lu, Alexander Vera, Nader Sawtarie, Wesley Auker, Ke Wang, Bob Hengstebeck, Zachary W. Henshaw, Shreya Mathela, Maxwell Wetherington, William H. Blades, Kenneth Knappenberger, Ursula Wurstbauer, Su Ying Quek, Ulrich Starke, Shengxi Huang, Vincent H. Crespi, Joshua A. Robinson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct imaging of magnetotransport at graphene-metal interfaces with a single-spin quantum sensor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07181</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07181v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetotransport underlines many important phenomena in condensed matter physics, such as the Hall effect and magnetoresistance (MR) effect. Thus far, most magnetotransport studies are based on bulk resistance measurements without direct access to microscopic details of the spatial transport pattern. Here, we report nanoscale imaging of magnetotransport using a scanning single-spin quantum magnetometer, which is demonstrated in a graphene-metal hybrid device at room temperature. By visualizing the current flow at elevated magnetic fields (~0.5 T), we directly observe the Lorentz deflection of current near the graphene-metal interface, which is a hallmark of magnetotransport. Combining the local current distribution with global resistance measurements, we reveal that transport properties of the hybrid are governed by a complex interplay of intrinsic MR around the Dirac cone, carrier hydrodynamics, interface resistance, and the nanoscale device geometry. Furthermore, accessing the local transport pattern across the interface enables quantitative mapping of spatial variations in contact resistance, which is commonly present in electronic devices made from two-dimensional materials yet non-trivial to characterize. Our work demonstrates the potential of nanoscale current imaging techniques for studying complex electronic transport phenomena that are difficult to probe by resistance-based measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07181v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Ding, M. L. Palm, K. Kohli, T. Taniguchi, K. Watanabe, C. L. Degen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controlling Quantum Transport in a Superconducting Device via Dissipative Baths</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07196v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Within the quantum field-theoretical approach describing the evolution of a quadratic Liouvillian in the basis of Keldysh contour coherent states, we investigate the spectral and transport properties of a dissipative superconducting system coupled to normal Fermi reservoirs. We derive a generalization of the Meir-Wingreen formula and Onsager matrix for a superconducting system subject to an arbitrary number of fermionic baths. Following Kirchhoff's rule, we obtain an expression describing the dissipation induced loss current and formulate modified quantum kinetic equations. For wide-band contacts locally coupled to individual sites, we find that each contact reduces the degeneracy multiplicity of the non-equilibrium steady state by one. These results are numerically verified through several cases of the extended Kitaev model at symmetric points with a single contact. Furthermore, in the linear response regime at low temperatures, we demonstrate that (non-)degenerate non-equilibrium steady states correspond to (non-)quantized conductance peaks. Revisiting a paradigmatic problem of resonant transport in the Majorana mode of the Kitaev model we demonstrate that the dissipation accounts for the zero-bias peak suppression and its asymmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07196v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. V. Aksenov, M. S. Shustin, I. S. Burmistrov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kondo cloud conductance in cavity-coupled quantum dots with asymmetric barriers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07232</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07232v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Kondo effect emerges when a localized spin is screened by conduction electrons, giving rise to a strongly-correlated many-body ground state. In this work, we investigate this phenomenon in a GaAs/AlGaAs quantum dot, focusing on the spatial extension of the Kondo screening cloud in the electron reservoirs. To probe its properties, the dot is coupled to an electronic Fabry-P\'erot interferometer, enabling controlled modulation of the density of states at the Fermi level. The observation of Kondo temperature oscillations indicates a Kondo screening length comparable to the cavity size. Furthermore, we explore how the coupling asymmetry with the two reservoirs affects both the amplitude and the phase of the conductance oscillations, revealing a subtle interplay between coherent transport and Kondo effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07232v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Fossion, V. Champain, S. Mohapatra, A. Cavanna, U. Gennser, D. Mailly, B. Hackens, L. Jansen, X. Jehl, S. De Franceschi, B. Brun-Barri\`ere, H. Sellier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning Green's Functions of Strongly Correlated Hubbard Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07252</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07252v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate that a machine learning framework based on kernel ridge regression can encode and predict the self-energy of one-dimensional Hubbard models using only mean-field features such as static and dynamic Hartree-Fock quantities and first-order GW calculations. This approach is applicable across a wide range of on-site Coulomb interaction strengths $U/t$, ranging from weakly interacting systems ($U/t \ll 1$) to strong correlations ($U/t &gt; 8$). The predicted self-energy is transformed via Dyson's equation and analytic continuation to obtain the real-frequency Green's function, which allows access to the spectral function and density of states. This method can be used for nearest-neighbor interactions $t$ and long-range hopping terms $t'$, $t''$, and $t'''$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07252v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mateo C\'ardenes Wuttig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermal Tensor Network Simulations of Fermions with a Fixed Filling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07303</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07303v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Numerical simulations of strongly correlated fermions at finite temperature are essential for studying high-temperature superconductivity and other quantum many-body phenomena. The recently developed tangent-space tensor renormalization group (tanTRG) provides an efficient and accurate framework by representing thermal density operators as matrix product operators. However, the particle number generally varies during the cooling process. The conventional strategy of fine-tuning chemical potentials to reach a target filling is computationally demanding. Here we propose a fixed-$N$ tanTRG algorithm that stabilizes the average particle number by adaptively tuning the chemical potential within the imaginary-time evolution. We benchmark its accuracy on exactly solvable free fermions, and further apply it to the square-lattice Hubbard model. For hole-doped cases, we study the temperature evolution of charge and spin correlations, identifying several characteristic temperature scales for stripe formation. Our results establish fixed-$N$ tanTRG as an efficient and reliable tool for finite-temperature studies of correlated fermion systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07303v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiaoyi Li, Dai-Wei Qu, Bin-Bin Chen, Tao Shi, Wei Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Persistence of the Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless transition with long-range couplings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07305</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07305v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless (BKT) transition is an archetypal example of a topological phase transition, which is driven by the proliferation of vortices. In this Letter, we analyze the persistence of the BKT transition in the XY model under the influence of long-range algebraically decaying interactions of the form $\sim 1/{r^{2+\sigma}}$. The model hosts a magnetized low temperature phase for sufficiently small $\sigma$. Crucially, in the presence of long-range interactions, spin waves renormalize the interaction between vortices, which stabilizes the BKT transition. As a result, we find that there is no direct transition from the magnetized to the disordered phase and that the BKT transition persists for arbitrary long-range exponents, which is distinct from previous results. We use both Landau-Peierls-type arguments and renormalization group calculations - including a coupling between spin wave and topological excitations - and obtain similar results. We emphasize that Landau-Peierls-type arguments are a powerful tool for analyzing continuous spin models. We discuss the relevance of our findings for current Rydberg atom experiments, and highlight the importance of long-range couplings for other types of topological defects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07305v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luis Walther, Josef Willsher, Johannes Knolle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optically-Induced Faraday-Goldstone Waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07320</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07320v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Faraday waves, typically observed in driven fluids, result from the confluence of nonlinearity and parametric amplification. Here we show that optical pulses can generate analogous phenomena that persist much longer than the pump time-scales in ordered quantum solids. We present a theory of ultrafast light-matter interactions within a symmetry-broken state; dynamical nonlinear coupling between the Higgs (amplitude) and the Goldstone (phase) modes drives an emergent phason texture that oscillates in space and in time: Faraday-Goldstone waves. Calculated signatures of this spatiotemporal order compare well with measurements on K$_{0.3}$MnO$_{3}$; Higgs-Goldstone beating, associated with coherent energy exchange between these two modes, is also predicted. We show this light-generated crystalline state is robust to thermal noise, even when the original Goldstone mode is not. Our results offer a new pathway for the design of periodic structures in quantum materials with ultrafast light pulses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07320v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Kaplan, Pavel A. Volkov, Andrea Cavalleri, Premala Chandra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterizing Mott Insulators in the Interacting One-Body Picture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07331</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07331v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a framework to characterize Mott insulating phases within the interacting one-body picture, focusing on the Hubbard diamond chain featuring both Hubbard interactions and spin-orbit coupling simulated within cellular dynamical mean field theory. Using symmetry analysis of the single-particle Green's function, we classify spectral functions by irreducible representations at high-symmetry points of the Brillouin zone. Complementarily, we calculate the one-body reduced density matrix which allows us to reach both a qualitative description of charge distribution and an analysis of the state purity. Moreover, within the Tensor Network framework, we employ a Density Matrix Renormalization Group approach to confirm the presence of three distinct phases and their corresponding phase transitions. Our results highlight how symmetry-labelled spectral functions and effective orbital analysis provide accessible single-particle tools for probing correlation-driven insulating phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07331v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Theo N. Dionne, Santiago Villodre, Mikel Iraola, Maia G. Vergniory</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weak localization and universal conductance fluctuations in large area twisted bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07334</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07334v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study diffusive magnetotransport in highly p-doped large area twisted bilayer graphene samples as a function of twist angle, crossing from 1{\deg} (below), to 20{\deg} (above) the van Hove singularity with 7{\deg} and 9{\deg} samples near the van Hove singularity. We report weak localization in twisted bilayer graphene for the first time. All samples exhibit weak localization, from which we extract the phase coherence length and intervalley scattering lengths, and from that determine that dephasing is caused by electron-electron scattering and intervalley scattering is caused by point defects. We observe signatures of universal conductance fluctuations in the 9{\deg} sample, which has high mobility and is near the van Hove singularity. Further improvements in sample quality and applications to large area moire materials will open new avenues to observe quantum interference effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07334v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Spenser Talkington, Debarghya Mallick, An-Hsi Chen, Benjamin F. Mead, Seong-Jun Yang, Cheol-Joo Kim, Shaffique Adam, Liang Wu, Matthew Brahlek, Eugene J. Mele</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatio-temporal migration of antiferromagnetic domain walls in Sr2IrO4</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07359v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: By laser pump-probe time-resolved coherent magnetic X-ray diffraction imaging, we have measured the migration velocity of antiferromagnetic domain walls in the Mott insulator Sr2IrO4 at 100 K. During the laser-induced demagnetization, we observe domain walls moving at 3x10^6 m/s, significantly faster than acoustic velocities. This is understood to arise from a purely electronic spin contribution to the magnetic structure without any role for coupling to the crystal lattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07359v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ian Robinson, David Yang, Ross Harder, Dina Sheyfer, Longlong Wu, Jack Griffiths, Emil Bozin, Mark P. M. Dean, Jialun Liu, Hengdi Zhao, Gang Cao, Angel Rodriguez-Fernandez, Jan-Etienne Pudell, Roman Shayduk, James Wrigley, Alexey Zozulya, Rustam Rysov, Aliaksandr Leonau, Ulrike Boesenberg, Joerg Hallmann, Anders Madsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine-Learning Accelerated Calculations of Reduced Density Matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07367</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07367v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: $n$-particle reduced density matrices ($n$-RDMs) play a central role in understanding correlated phases of matter. Yet the calculation of $n$-RDMs is often computationally inefficient for strongly-correlated states, particularly when the system sizes are large. In this work, we propose to use neural network (NN) architectures to accelerate the calculation of, and even predict, the $n$-RDMs for large-size systems. The underlying intuition is that $n$-RDMs are often smooth functions over the Brillouin zone (BZ) (certainly true for gapped states) and are thus interpolable, allowing NNs trained on small-size $n$-RDMs to predict large-size ones. Building on this intuition, we devise two NNs: (i) a self-attention NN that maps random RDMs to physical ones, and (ii) a Sinusoidal Representation Network (SIREN) that directly maps momentum-space coordinates to RDM values. We test the NNs in three 2D models: the pair-pair correlation functions of the Richardson model of superconductivity, the translationally-invariant 1-RDM in a four-band model with short-range repulsion, and the translation-breaking 1-RDM in the half-filled Hubbard model. We find that a SIREN trained on a $6\times 6$ momentum mesh can predict the $18\times 18$ pair-pair correlation function with a relative accuracy of $0.839$. The NNs trained on $6\times 6 \sim 8\times 8$ meshes can provide high-quality initial guesses for $50\times 50$ translation-invariant Hartree-Fock (HF) and $30\times 30$ fully translation-breaking-allowed HF, reducing the number of iterations required for convergence by up to $91.63\%$ and $92.78\%$, respectively, compared to random initializations. Our results illustrate the potential of using NN-based methods for interpolable $n$-RDMs, which might open a new avenue for future research on strongly correlated phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07367v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Awwab A. Azam, Lexu Zhao, Jiabin Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coexistence of Ferroelectric and Relaxor-like Phases in a Multiferroic Solid Solution (1-x)Pb(Fe1/2Nb1/2)O3 - xPbMnO3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07371v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Experimental and theoretical studies of unusual polar, dielectric and magnetic properties of room temperature multiferroics, such as perovskites Pb(Fe1/2Nb1/2)O3 (PFN) and Pb(Fe1/2Ta1/2)O3 (PFT), are very important. We study the phase composition, dielectric, ferroic properties of the solid solutions PFN and PFT substituted with 5, 10, 15, 20 and 30 % of Mn ions prepared by the solid-state synthesis. The XRD analysis confirmed the perovskite structure of sintered ceramics. Electric measurements revealed the ferroelectric-type hysteresis of electric charge in pure PFN ceramics and in PFN ceramics substituted with (10 - 30)% of Mn. At the same time, the PFN-5% Mn ceramics did not show any ferroelectric properties due to very high conductivity.Temperature dependences of the dielectric permittivity of PFN-10% Mn and PFN-15% Mn ceramics have two pronounced maxima, one of which is relatively sharp and has a weak frequency dispersion; another is diffuse and has a strong frequency dispersion. A further increase in the Mn content up to 20% leads to the right shift in the paraelectric-ferroelectric phase transition temperature, as well as to the strong suppression of the second wide maximum, which transforms into a small diffuse shoulder. An increase in the Mn substitution up to 30% leads to a significant decrease in the dielectric permittivity, left shift of its maximum, and induces a pronounced frequency dispersion of the paraelectric-ferroelectric transition temperature, which is inherent to relaxor-like ferroelectrics.Comparison of the model with experiments reveal the coexistence of the ordered ferroelectric-like and disordered relaxor-like phases in the multiferroic solid solutions PFN-Mn and PFT-Mn.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07371v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna N. Morozovska, Victor N. Pavlikov, Yuriy O. Zagorodniy, Iryna V. Kondakova, Oleksandr S. Pylypchuk, Andrii V. Bodnaruk, Oksana V. Leshchenko, Myroslav V. Karpets, Roman O. Kuzian, Eugene A. Eliseev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The ideal limit of rhombohedral graphene: Interaction-induced layer-skyrmion lattices and their collective excitations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07402v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce an ideal limit of rhombohedral graphene multilayers. In this limit, we show analytically how short-range repulsion stabilizes a layer-pseudospin skyrmion lattice, which generates an effective magnetic field and gives rise to a Chern band. This establishes the real-space origin of interaction-driven topology in moir\'e rhombohedral graphene. The resulting interaction-induced skyrmion lattice is physically analogous to magnetic skyrmion crystals and hosts a hierarchy of collective excitations naturally described within the framework of skyrmion-lattice dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07402v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tixuan Tan, Patrick J. Ledwith, Trithep Devakul</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological and Trivial Valence-Bond Orders in Higher-Spin Kitaev Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07415v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the quantum phases of higher-spin Kitaev models using tensor network methods. Our results reveal distinct bond-ordered phases for spin-1, spin-$\tfrac{3}{2}$, and spin-2 models. In all cases, we find translational symmetry breaking with unit cells being tripled by forming valence-bond orders. However, these three phases are distinct, forming plaquette order, topological dimer order, and non-topological dimer order, respectively. Our findings are based on a cross-validation between variational two-dimensional tensor network calculations: an unrestricted exploration of symmetry-broken states versus the detection of symmetry breaking from cat-state behavior in symmetry-restricted states. The origin of different orders can also be understood from a theoretical analysis. Our work sheds light upon the interplay between topological and symmetry-breaking orders as well as their detection via tensor networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07415v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xing-Yu Zhang, Qi Yang, Philippe Corboz, Jutho Haegeman, Yuchi He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability theory of flat band solitons in nonlinear wave systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05671</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05671v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We establish a sharp criterion for the stability of a class of compactly supported, homogeneous density``minimal compact solitons'' or MCS states, of the time-dependent discrete nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation on a multi-lattice, $\mathbb L$ ($\mathbb L$-DNLS). MCS states arise for multi-lattices where a nearest neighbor Laplace-type operator on $\mathbb L$ has a flat band. Our stability criterion is in terms of the explicit form of the nonlinearity and the projection of distinguished vectors onto the flat band eigenspace. We apply our general results to MCS states of DNLS for the diamond, Kagom{\'e} and checkerboard lattices. In lattices where MCS states are unstable, we demonstrate how to engineer the nonlinearity to stabilize small amplitude MCS states. Finally, via systematic numerical computations, we put our analytical results in the context of global bifurcation diagrams.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05671v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheng Shi, Ross Parker, Panayotis G. Kevrekides, Michael I. Weinstein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The noiseless limit and improved-prior limit of the maximum entropy method and their implications for the analytic continuation problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06915v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum Monte Carlo (QMC) methods are uniquely capable of providing exact simulations of quantum many-body systems. Unfortunately, the applications of a QMC simulation are limited because extracting dynamic properties requires solving the analytic continuation (AC) problem. Across the many fields that use QMC methods, there is no universally accepted analytic continuation algorithm for extracting dynamic properties, but many publications compare to the maximum entropy method. We investigate when entropy maximization is an acceptable approach. We show that stochastic sampling algorithms reduce to entropy maximization when the Bayesian prior is near to the true solution. We investigate when is Bryan's controversial optimization algorithm [Bryan, Eur. Biophys. J. 18, 165-174 (1990)] for entropy maximization (sometimes known as the maximum entropy method) appropriate to use. We show that Bryan's algorithm is appropriate when the noise is near zero or when the Bayesian prior is near to the true solution. We also investigate the mean squared error, finding a better scaling when the Bayesian prior is near the true solution than when the noise is near zero. We point to examples of improved data-driven Bayesian priors that have already leveraged this advantage. We support these results by solving the double Gaussian problem using both Bryan's algorithm and the newly formulated dual approach to entropy maximization [Chuna et al., J. Phys. A: Math. Theor. 58, 335203 (2025)].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06915v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Chuna, Nicholas Barnfield, Paul Hamann, Sebastian Schwalbe, Michael P. Friedlander, Tobias Dornheim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Full Counting Statistics of Yu-Shiba-Rusinov Bound States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.04758</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.04758v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: With the help of scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) it has become possible to address single magnetic impurities on superconducting surfaces and to investigate the peculiar properties of the in-gap states known as Yu-Shiba-Rusinov (YSR) states. However, until very recently YSR states were only investigated with conventional tunneling spectroscopy, missing the crucial information contained in other transport properties such as shot noise. Here, we adapt the concept of full counting statistics (FCS) to provide a very deep insight into the spin-dependent transport in these hybrid systems. We illustrate the power of FCS by analyzing different situations in which YSR states show up including single-impurity junctions, as well as double-impurity systems where one can probe the tunneling between individual YSR states. The FCS concept allows us to unambiguously identify every tunneling process that plays a role in these situations. Moreover, FCS provides all the relevant transport properties, including current, shot noise and all the cumulants of the current distribution. Our approach can reproduce the experimental results recently reported on the shot noise of a single-impurity junction with a normal STM tip. We also predict the signatures of resonant (and non-resonant) multiple Andreev reflections in the shot noise of single-impurity junctions with two superconducting electrodes. In the case of double-impurity junctions we show that the direct tunneling between YSR states is characterized by a strong reduction of the Fano factor that reaches a minimum value of 7/32, a new fundamental result in quantum transport. The FCS approach presented here can be naturally extended to investigate the spin-dependent superconducting transport in a variety of situations, and it is also suitable to analyze multi-terminal superconducting junctions, irradiated contacts, and many other basic situations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.04758v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.5.033176</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 5, 033176 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>David Christian Ohnmacht, Wolfgang Belzig, Juan Carlos Cuevas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fermi Surface Bosonization for Non-Fermi Liquids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.14955</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.14955v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding non-Fermi liquids in dimensions higher than one remains one of the most formidable challenges in modern condensed matter physics. These systems, characterized by an abundance of gapless degrees of freedom and the absence of well-defined quasiparticles, defy conventional analytical frameworks. Inspired by recent work [Delacretaz, Du, Mehta, and Son, Physical Review Research, 4, 033131 (2022)], we present a procedure for bosonizing Fermi surfaces that does not rely on the existence of sharp excitation and is thus directly applicable to non-Fermi liquids. Our method involves parameterizing the generalized fermionic distribution function through a bosonic field that describes frequency-dependent local variations of the chemical potential in momentum space. We propose an effective action that produces the collisionless quantum Boltzmann equation as its equation of motion and can be used for any dimension and Fermi surface of interest. Even at the quadratic order, this action reproduces non-trivial results obtainable only through involved analysis with alternative means. By offering an alternative method directly applicable to studying the low-energy physics of Fermi and non-Fermi liquids, our work potentially stands as an important building block in advancing the comprehension of strange metals and associated phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.14955v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/yrkv-42wd</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 165116 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>SangEun Han, F\'elix Desrochers, Yong Baek Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A general formula of frequency and amplitude for shaking induced Mott insulator in atomtronic transistors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11355</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11355v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Mott insulator of atomic transport can be realized in driven optical lattices by choosing particular ratio of driving frequency and amplitude, which has been studied as Floquet engineering with time-independent effective Hamiltonian approach. Here, we give a general formula of frequency-amplitude radio for realization of the driving induced insulator-conductor transition in a double-well open system, using numerical computation with instantaneous eigenstates approach. The result is owing to the fact that the instantaneous eigenstates approach is applicable in more wide parameter range compared with the time-independent effective Hamiltonian approach. Analysis from the results of quantum master equation shows that the insulator effect is originated from coherent localization of atom wave packets in optical wells.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11355v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenxi Lai, Yu-Quan Ma, Yi-Wen Wei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lattice Models for Phases and Transitions with Non-Invertible Symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05964</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05964v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Non-invertible categorical symmetries have emerged as a powerful tool to uncover new beyond-Landau phases of matter, both gapped and gapless, along with second order phase transitions between them. The general theory of such phases in (1+1)d has been studied using the Symmetry Topological Field Theory (SymTFT), also known as topological holography. This has unearthed the infrared (IR) structure of these phases and transitions. In this paper, we describe how the SymTFT information can be converted into an ultraviolet (UV) anyonic chain lattice model realizing, in the IR limit, these phases and transitions. In many cases, the Hilbert space of the anyonic chain is tensor product decomposable and the model can be realized as a quantum spin-chain Hamiltonian. We also describe operators acting on the lattice models that are charged under non-invertible symmetries and act as order parameters for the phases and transitions. In order to fully describe the action of non-invertible symmetries, it is crucial to understand the symmetry twisted sectors of the lattice models, which we describe in detail. Throughout the paper, we illustrate the general concepts using the symmetry category $\mathsf{Rep}(S_3)$ formed by representations of the permutation group $S_3$, but our procedure can be applied to any fusion category symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05964v5</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lakshya Bhardwaj, Lea E. Bottini, Sakura Schafer-Nameki, Apoorv Tiwari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sublattice Dichotomy in Monolayer FeSe Superconductor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.15239v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The pairing mechanism behind the monolayer FeSe is one essential question for iron-based superconductors. In this work, we show the sublattice degree of freedoms of monolayer FeSe plays a special role in its pairing properties, namely the sublattice dichotomy. The high-quality monolayer FeSe samples with atomic flat $1\times1$ topography on the SrTiO$_3$(001) substrates are grown by molecular beam epitaxy. By comparing the tunneling spectra at $\alpha$ and $\beta$ Fe sublattices, we find the coherence peak of $\alpha$-Fe at the inner gap $+V_i$ is higher than $\beta$-Fe while the coherence peak of $\beta$-Fe at $-V_i$ is higher than $\alpha$-Fe with a similar amount. We also observed a reversed effect at the outer gap $\pm V_o$. We propose the $\eta$-pairing mechanism between $k$ and $-k+Q$ is the key mechanism for this unconventional sublattice dichotomy effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.15239v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cui Ding, Zhipeng Xu, Xiaotong Jiao, Yinqi Hu, Wenxuan Zhao, Lexian Yang, Kun Jiang, Lili Wang, Jin-Feng Jia, Jiangping Hu, Qi-Kun Xue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Free energy barrier and thermal-quantum behavior of sliding bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04532v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In multilayer graphene, the stacking order of the layers plays a crucial role in the electronic properties and the manifestation of superconductivity. By applying shear stress, it is possible to induce sliding between different layers, altering the stacking order. Here, focusing on bilayer graphene, we analyze how ionic fluctuations alter the free energy barrier between different stacking equilibria. We calculate the free energy barrier through the state-of-the-art self-consistent harmonic approximation, which can be evaluated at unstable configurations. We find that above 100 K there is a large reduction of the barrier of more than 30% due to thermal vibrations, which significantly improves the agreement between previous first-principles theoretical work and experiments in a single graphite crystal. As the temperature increases, the barrier remains nearly constant up to around 500 K, with a more pronounced decrease only at higher temperatures. Our approach is general and paves the way for systematically accounting for thermal effects in free energy barriers of other macroscopic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04532v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean Paul Nery, Lorenzo Monacelli, Francesco Mauri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Persistence of small polarons into the superconducting phase of Ba$_{1-x}$K$_x$BiO$_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00401v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Bipolaronic superconductivity is an exotic pairing mechanism proposed for materials like Ba$_{1-x}$K$_x$BiO$_3$ (BKBO); however, conclusive experimental evidence for a (bi)polaron metallic state in this material remains elusive. Here, we combine resonant inelastic x-ray and neutron total scattering techniques with advanced modelling to study the local lattice distortions, electronic structure, and electron-phonon coupling ($e$-ph) in BKBO as a function of doping. Data for the parent compound ($x = 0$) indicates that the electronic gap opens in predominantly oxygen-derived states strongly coupled to a long-range ordered breathing distortion of the oxygen sublattice. Upon doping, short-range breathing distortions and sizable ($e$-ph) coupling persist into the superconducting regime ($x = 0.4$). Comparisons with exact diagonalization and determinant quantum Monte Carlo calculations further support this conclusion. Our results provide compelling evidence that BKBO's metallic phase hosts a liquid of small (bi)polarons derived from local breathing distortions of the lattice, with implications for understanding the low-temperature superconducting instability</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00401v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/s3p1-cy1s</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review Research, 7(4), p.043082.(2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Muntaser Naamneh, Eugenio Paris, Daniel McNally, Yi Tseng, Wojciech R. Pudelko, Dariusz J. Gawryluk, J. Shamblin, Eric OQuinn, Benjamin Cohen-Stead, Ming Shi, Milan Radovic, M. Lang, Thorsten Schmitt, Steven Johnston, Nicholas C. Plumb</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric expansion of fluctuations and average shadows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08364</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08364v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Fluctuations of observables provide unique insights into the nature of physical systems, and their study stands as a cornerstone of both theoretical and experimental science. Generalized fluctuations, or cumulants, provide information beyond the mean and variance of an observable. In this paper, we develop a systematic method to determine the asymptotic behavior of cumulants of local observables as the region becomes large. Our analysis reveals that the expansion is closely tied to the geometric characteristics of the region and its boundary, with coefficients given by convex moments of the connected correlation function: the latter is integrated against intrinsic volumes of convex polytopes built from the coordinates, which can be interpreted as average shadows. A particular application of our method shows that, in two dimensions, the leading behavior of odd cumulants of conserved quantities is topological, specifically depending on the Euler characteristic of the region. We illustrate these results with the paradigmatic strongly-interacting system of two-dimensional quantum Hall state at filling fraction $1/2$, by performing Monte-Carlo calculations of the skewness (third cumulant) of particle number in the Laughlin state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08364v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cl\'ement Berthi\`ere, Benoit Estienne, Jean-Marie St\'ephan, William Witczak-Krempa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Antenna: A Non-Classical Beam-Steering Micro-Antenna Based on Spin Injection from a Topological Insulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16854</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16854v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Antennas are the quintessential means to communicate information wirelessly over long distances via electromagnetic waves. Traditional antennas have two shortcomings that have prevented miniaturization: (1) their radiation efficiencies plummet and (2) they radiate isotropically when miniaturized to small fractions of the radiated wavelength. Here, we report a new genre of non-classical antennas that overcome these limitations by employing non-traditional principles and harnessing topological insulators. An alternating charge current of frequency 1-10 GHz injected into a thin film of a three-dimensional topological insulator (3D-TI) injects a spin current of alternating spin polarization into a periodic array of cobalt nanomagnets deposited on the surface of the 3D-TI. This generates spin waves in the nanomagnets, which radiate electromagnetic waves in space, thereby implementing an antenna. The frequency of the electromagnetic wave is the same as that of the current. The antenna dimension is only 0.6-1.8% of the free space wavelength and yet it radiates with an efficiency several orders of magnitude larger than the theoretical limit for conventional antennas. Furthermore, it radiates anisotropically (despite being a "point source") and one can change the anisotropic radiation pattern by changing the direction of the injected alternating charge current, which changes the spin wave patterns within the nanomagnets because of spin-momentum locking in the 3D-TI. This enables beam steering without the use of a phased array. We have overcome several limitations of classical antennas by harnessing the quantum mechanical attributes of a quantum material, namely a 3D-TI.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16854v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raisa Fabiha, Patrick J. Taylor, Supriyo Bandyopadhyay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exceptional second-order topological insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06898</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06898v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Point-gap topological phases of non-Hermitian systems exhibit exotic boundary states that have no counterparts in Hermitian systems. Here, we develop classification of second-order point-gap topological phases protected by reflection symmetry. Based on this classification, we propose exceptional second-order topological insulators, exhibiting second-order boundary states stabilized by point-gap topology. As an illustrative example, we uncover a two-dimensional exceptional second-order topological insulator with point-gapless corner states. Furthermore, we identify a three-dimensional exceptional second-order topological insulator that features hinge states with isolated exceptional points, representing second-order topological phases intrinsic to non-Hermitian systems. Our work enlarges the family of point-gap topological phases in non-Hermitian systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06898v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yutaro Tanaka, Daichi Nakamura, Ryo Okugawa, Kohei Kawabata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electron-Ion Coupling Breaks Energy Symmetry in Bistable Organic Electrochemical Transistors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07921</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07921v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Organic electrochemical transistors are extensively studied for applications ranging from bioelectronics to analog and neuromorphic computing. Despite significant advances, the fundamental interactions between the polymer semiconductor channel and the electrolyte, which critically determine the device performance, remain underexplored. Here, we examine the coupling between the benchmark semiconductor PEDOT:PSS and an ionic liquid to explain the bistable and non-volatile behavior observed in OECTs. Using X-ray scattering and spectroscopy techniques, we demonstrate how the electrolyte modifies the channel composition, enhances molecular order, and reshapes the energetic landscape. Notably, the observed bistability arises from asymmetric and path-dependent energetics during doping and dedoping, resulting in two distinct paths, driven by a direct interaction between the electronic and ionic charge carriers. These findings highlight the electrolyte's role in tuning charge carrier dynamics, positioning it as a powerful yet underutilized lever for enabling novel device functionalities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07921v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s43246-025-00959-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Commun Mater 6, 241 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lukas M. Bongartz, Garrett LeCroy, Tyler J. Quill, Nicholas Siemons, Gerwin Dijk, Adam Marks, Christina Cheng, Hans Kleemann, Karl Leo, Alberto Salleo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-consistent tensor network method for correlated super-moir\'e matter beyond one billion sites</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.04373v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Moir\'e and super-moir\'e materials provide exceptional platforms to engineer exotic correlated quantum matter. The vast number of sites required to model moir\'e systems in real space remains a formidable challenge due to the immense computational resources required. Super-moir\'e materials push this requirement to the limit, where millions or even billions of sites need to be considered, a requirement beyond the capabilities of conventional methods for interacting systems. Here, we establish a methodology that allows solving correlated states in systems reaching a billion sites, that exploits tensor-network representations of real-space Hamiltonians and self-consistent real-space mean-field equations. Our method combines a tensor-network kernel polynomial method with quantics tensor cross interpolation algorithm, enabling us to solve exponentially large models, including those whose single particle Hamiltonian is too large to be stored explicitly. We demonstrate our methodology with super-moir\'e systems featuring spatially modulated hoppings, many-body interactions and domain walls, showing that it allows access to self-consistent symmetry broken states and spectral functions of real-space models reaching a billion sites. Our methodology provides a strategy to solve exceptionally large interacting problems, providing a widely applicable strategy to compute correlated super-moir\'e quantum matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.04373v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yitao Sun, Marcel Niedermeier, Tiago V. C. Ant\~ao, Adolfo O. Fumega, Jose L. Lado</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reflectionless modes as a source of Weyl nodes in multiterminal Josephson junctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10874</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10874v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Multiterminal Josephson junctions are a promising platform to study non-trivial topology in engineered quantum systems. Yet, experimentally meaningful insight into what exactly makes these systems topologically non-trivial remains elusive. In this work, we show that zero energy reflectionless scattering modes (RSMs) of the normal scattering matrix result in topological phase boundaries. By analyzing two different setups, we explain the origin of each topological phase boundary and furthermore provide generalizable insight into these systems. The considerations here can be of help for experimentalists as it connects the properties of the normal scattering region to the Andreev bound state spectrum of superconducting junctions in a multiterminal setup.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10874v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Christian Ohnmacht, Valentin Wilhelm, Wolfgang Belzig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In situ vs ex situ: Comparing the structure of PNIPAM microgels at the air/water and air/solid interfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14181</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14181v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For studying the structure of microgel particles at the air/water interface, specular and off-specular X-ray reflectivity (OSR/XRR) allows in situ measurements without any labelling techniques. Herein we investigate the vertical and lateral structure of poly(N-isopropylacrylamide) (PNIPAM) microgels (MGs) at the air/water interface and the effect of Langmuir-Blodgett (LB) transfer onto solid substrates. The initial ex situ atomic force microscopy (AFM) scans of LB-transferred MGs at the air/solid interface reveal strong lateral 2D hexagonal ordering across a broad range of lateral surface pressures at the air/water interface before LB-transfer. Notably, for the first time, these results were confirmed by OSR, demonstrating the existence of the long-range hexagonal ordering at low and intermediate surface pressures. For in situ conditions and upon uniaxial compression at the air/water interface, the MG lattice constant decreases non-monotonically. This indicates the formation of domains at low pressures that approach each other and only compress when the surface isotherm reaches a plateau. Comparing the results of in situ and ex situ measurements, our study demonstrates a clear transfer effect during the LB-deposition on the lateral ordering of the MGs: the distance between the particles decreased during LB-transfer, and at high pressures ($\Pi\,&gt;\,17\,\mathrm{mNm^{-1}}$) a second distance occurs indicating small domains with hexagonal internal ordering. The novel surface characterisation approaches debuted here highlight the use of both XRR and OSR to probe the vertical and lateral structure of adsorbed MGs, offering in situ, non-invasive insights without the need for doping or transfer-induced artefacts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14181v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hayden Robertson, Joanne Zimmer, Anuar Sifuentes Name, Cassia Lux, Sebastian Stock, Regine von Klitzing, Olaf Soltwedel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Floquet non-Abelian topological charges and edge states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14518</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14518v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Non-Abelian topological insulators are characterized by matrix-valued, non-commuting topological charges with regard to more than one energy gap. Their descriptions go beyond the conventional topological band theory, in which an additive integer is endowed separately with each (degenerate group of) energy band(s). In this work, we reveal that Floquet (time-periodic) driving could not only enrich the topology and phase transitions of non-Abelian topological matter, but also induce bulk-edge correspondence unique to nonequilibrium setups. Using a one-dimensional (1D), three-band model as an illustrative example, we demonstrate that Floquet driving could reshuffle the phase diagram of the non-driven system, yielding both gapped and gapless Floquet band structures with non-Abelian topological charges. Moreover, by dynamically tuning the anomalous Floquet $\pi$-quasienergy gap, non-Abelian topological transitions inaccessible to static systems could arise, leading to much more complicated relations between non-Abelian topological charges and Floquet edge states. These discoveries put forth the periodic driving as a powerful scheme of engineering non-Abelian topological phases (NATPs) and incubating unique non-Abelian band topology beyond equilibrium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14518v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/0256-307X/42/9/090706</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chinese Physics Letters 42, 090706 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jiaxin Pan, Longwen Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generic deformation channels for critical Fermi surfaces including the impact of collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.06945</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.06945v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper constitutes a sequel to our theoretical efforts to determine the nature of generic low-energy deformations of the Fermi surface of a quantum-critical metal, which arises at the stable non-Fermi liquid (NFL) fixed point of a quantum phase transition. The emergent critical Fermi surface, arising right at the Ising-nematic quantum critical point (QCP), is a paradigmatic example where an NFL behaviour is induced by the strong interactions of the fermionic degrees of freedom with those of the bosonic order parameter. It is an artifact of the bosonic modes becoming massless at the QCP, thus undergoing Landau-damping at the level of one-loop self-energy. We resort to the well-tested formalism of the quantum Boltzmann equations (QBEs) for identifying the excitations. While in our earlier works, we have focused on the collisionless regime by neglecting the collision integral and assuming the bosons to be in equilibrium, here we embark on a full analysis. In particular, we take into account the bosonic part of the QBEs as well, which, however, turn out to have no effect on the solutions. Decomposing the master equation into angular-momentum ($\ell$) channels, the emergent modes are of two types: Fermi-surface deformations with discrete spectra and particle-hole excitations forming a continuous band. The long-lived zero-sound mode, which corresponds to $\ell = 0$, is found to be robust against damping effects. Intriguingly, we have an infinite family of discrete modes corresponding to higher-order harmonics of the net deformation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.06945v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazi Ranjibul Islam, Aditya Savanur, Ipsita Mandal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Engineering the Kondo impurity problem with alkaline-earth atom arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14630</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14630v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose quantum simulation experiments of the Kondo impurity problem using cold alkaline-earth(-like) atoms (AEAs) in a combination of optical lattice and optical tweezer potentials. Within an ab initio model for atomic interactions in the optical potentials, we analyze hallmark signatures of the Kondo effect in a variety of observables accessible in cold-atom quantum simulators. We identify additional terms not part of the textbook Kondo problem, mostly ignored in previous works and giving rise to a direct competition between spin and charge correlations - strongly suppressing Kondo physics. We show that the Kondo effect can be restored by locally adjusting the chemical potential on the impurity site, and we identify realistic parameter regimes and preparation protocols suited to current experiments with AEA arrays. Our work paves the way for novel quantum simulations of the Kondo problem and offers new insights into Kondo physics in unconventional regimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14630v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/m7l3-y2f8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 112, 043301 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Adriano Amaricci, Andrea Richaud, Massimo Capone, Nelson Darkwah Oppong, Francesco Scazza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalable Machine Learning Models for Predicting Quantum Transport in Disordered 2D Hexagonal Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.07983</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.07983v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce scalable machine learning models to accurately predict two key quantum transport properties, the transmission coefficient T(E) and average local density of states (Average-LDOS) in two-dimensional (2D) hexagonal materials with magnetic disorder. Using a tight binding Hamiltonian combined with the Non-Equilibrium Green's Function (NEGF) formalism, we generate a large dataset of over 400,000 unique configurations across graphene, germanene, silicene, and stanene nanoribbons with varying geometries, impurity concentrations, and energy levels. A central contribution of this work is the development of a geometrydriven, physically interpretable feature space that enables the models to generalize across material types and device sizes. Random Forest regression and classification models are evaluated in terms of accuracy, stability, and extrapolation ability. Regression consistently outperforms classification in capturing continuous transport behavior on in-domain data. However, extrapolation performance degrades significantly, revealing the limitations of tree-based models in unseen regimes. This study highlights both the potential and constraints of scalable ML models for quantum transport prediction and motivates future research into physics-informed or graph-based learning architectures for improved generalization in spintronic and nanoelectronic device design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.07983v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seyed Mahdi Mastoor, Amirhossein Ahmadkhan Kordbacheh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantized and nonquantized Hall response in topological Hatsugai-Kohmoto systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20491</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20491v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explore the robustness of Hall conductivity quantization in several insulating systems, exhibiting one scenario where the quantization is not preserved. Specifically, we apply the Kubo formula to topological models with the Hatsugai-Kohmoto interaction. Starting from the many-body degeneracy induced by this interaction in the topological Kane-Mele model, we consider Zeeman fields to select specific states within the ground-state manifold that reveal a non-quantized Hall response, precisely for the case with a Zeeman field diagonal in the bands of the Kane-Mele model. From a physical point of view, this term may mimic a ferromagnetic order that arises naturally when couplings beyond the Hatsugai-Kohmoto interaction are taken into account.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20491v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thibaut Desort, Mark O. Goerbig, Corentin Morice</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-reciprocal spin-wave excitations in Rashba-Hubbard ferromagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03997</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03997v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explore the nonreciprocity of spin-wave excitations in the Rashba-Hubbard ferromagnet on a square lattice. Our study reveals that the propagation of spin-wave excitations exhibit non-reciprocal behavior, i.e., spin waves traveling in opposite directions display asymmetry in energy dispersion $\omega({\bf q}) \ne \omega(-{\bf q)}$, which also results in an asymmetric behavior of group velocity, spin stiffness, etc. We find that this asymmetric behavior arises only when the magnetic moments are aligned inside the atomic plane, while the excitations remain symmetric for out-of-plane magnetization. The first dominating term in the low-energy dispersion is linear. However, if the magnetic moments are out-of-plane, then the first dominant term is quadratic instead. The low-energy non-quadratic behavior is examined in the intermediate-to-strong coupling regime for various strengths of Rashba spin-orbit coupling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03997v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aastha Jain, Dheeraj Kumar Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of Metal Cation on Chiral Properties of 2D Halide Perovskites</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00158v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Chiral two-dimensional (2D) halide perovskites are formed by embedding chiral organic cations in a perovskite crystal structure. The chirality arises from distortions of the 2D metal halide layers induced by the packing of these organic cations. Sn-based octahedra spontaneously distort, but it remains unclear whether this intrinsic structural instability enhances the chirality. We investigate the effect of the metal cation on structural and phonon chirality in MBA$_{2}$Sn$_{\mathrm{x}}$Pb$_{1-\mathrm{x}}$I$_{4}$ (x = 0, 1/2, and 1). Incorporating Sn does distort the metal halide octehedra, yet it only has a minor impact on the structural chirality. In contrast, the phonons in MBA$_{2}$SnI$_{4}$ are substantially more chiral than in MBA$_{2}$PbI$_{4}$, especially the in-plane acoustic modes. However, this enhanced phonon chirality does not lead to a generation of a larger angular momentum under a temperature gradient, because the contributions of different chiral phonons tend to compensate one another.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00158v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mike Pols, Helena Boom, Geert Brocks, Sof\'ia Calero, Shuxia Tao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum action of the Josephson dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00902</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00902v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the beyond-mean-field Josephson dynamics of the relative phase between two coupled macroscopic quantum systems. Using a covariant background field method, we derive the one-loop only-phase quantum effective action and the corresponding equation of motion for the quantum average of the phase. These analytical results are benchmarked against the exact quantum dynamics of the two-site Bose-Hubbard model, demonstrating a relevant improvement over the standard mean-field predictions across a wide range of interaction strengths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00902v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s10773-025-06186-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Int. J. Theor. Phys. 64, 315 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Cesare Vianello, Sofia Salvatore, Luca Salasnich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological characterization of phase transitions and critical edge states in one-dimensional non-Hermitian systems with sublattice symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01174v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Critical edge states appear at the bulk gap closing points of topological transitions. Their emergence signify the existence of topologically nontrivial critical points, whose descriptions fall outside the scope of gapped topological matter. In this work, we reveal and characterize topological critical points and critical edge states in non-Hermitian systems. By applying the Cauchy's argument principle to two characteristic functions of a non-Hermitian Hamiltonian, we obtain a pair of winding numbers, whose combination yields a complete description of gapped and gapless topological phases in one-dimensional, two-band non-Hermitian systems with sublattice symmetry. Focusing on a broad class of non-Hermitian Su-Schrieffer-Heeger chains, we demonstrate the applicability of our theory for characterizing gapless symmetry-protected topological phases, topologically distinct critical points, phase transitions along non-Hermitian phase boundaries and their associated topological edge modes. Our findings not only generalize the concepts of topologically nontrivial critical points and critical edge modes to non-Hermitian setups, but also yield additional insights for analyzing topological transitions and bulk-edge correspondence in open systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01174v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Longwen Zhou, Rujia Jing, Shenlin Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radio-frequency charge detection on graphene electron-hole double quantum dots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12061v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: High-fidelity detection of charge transitions in quantum dots (QDs) is a key ingredient in solid state quantum computation. We demonstrate high-bandwidth radio-frequency charge detection in bilayer graphene quantum dots (QDs) using a capacitively coupled quantum point contact (QPC). The device design suppresses screening effects and enables sensitive QPC-based charge readout. The QPC is arranged to maximize the readout contrast between two neighboring, coupled electron and hole QDs. We apply the readout scheme to a single-particle electron-hole double QD and demonstrate time-resolved detection of charge states as well as magnetic field dependent tunneling rates. This promises a high-fidelity readout scheme for individual spin and valley states, which is important for the operation of spin, valley or spin-valley qubits in bilayer graphene.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12061v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katrin Hecker, Samuel M\"oller, Hubert Dulisch, \c{S}iyar Duman, Leon Stecher, Lucca Valerius, Tobias Deu{\ss}en, Saketh Ravuri, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Florian Libisch, Christian Volk, Christoph Stampfer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-Frequency Noise and Resistive Switching in $\beta$-Na$_{0.33}$V$_2$O$_5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00376</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00376v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The interplay between charge ordering and its manifestation in macroscopic electrical transport in low-dimensional materials is crucial for understanding resistive switching mechanisms. In this study, we investigate the electronic transport and switching behavior of single-crystalline $\beta$-Na$_{0.33}$V$_2$O$_5$, focusing on low-frequency resistance noise dynamics of charge-order-driven resistive switching. Using electrical transport, low frequency noise spectroscopy, and X-ray diffraction, we probe electron dynamics across the Na-ion-ordering (IO) and charge-ordering (CO) transitions. Near room temperature, the weak temperature dependence of the noise spectral density points to a dominance of nearest-neighbor polaron hopping. Below IO transition temperature (\( T_{IO} \sim 240 \, \text{K} \)), structural analysis reveals that Na-ions adopt a zig-zag occupancy pattern, breaking the two-fold rotational symmetry and influencing the electronic ground state. Subsequently, a sharp drop in resistance noise below the CO transition temperature (\( T_{CO} \sim 125 \, \text{K} \)) indicates the emergence of correlated electron behavior. Furthermore, application of sufficient electric field leads to the destabilization of the CO state, and a transition to a high-conducting state. The material exhibits distinct resistive switching between 35~K and 110~K, with a resistance change spanning two orders of magnitude, primarily driven by electronic mechanisms rather than Joule heating. These findings provide new insights into charge-order-induced switching and electronic correlations in quasi-one-dimensional systems, with potential applications in cryogenic memory and neuromorphic computing devices owing to the low noise levels in their stable resistive states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00376v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nitin Kumar, Nicholas Jerla, John Ponis, Sarbajit Banerjee, G. Sambandamurthy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse Purcell Suppression of Decoherence in Majorana Qubits via Environmental Engineering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00561</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00561v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a novel approach for optimizing topological quantum devices: instead of merely isolating qubits from environmental noise, we engineer the environment to actively suppress decoherence. For a Majorana qubit in a topological superconducting wire, the exponentially small energy splitting $\epsilon \sim e^{-L/\xi}$ provides protection against local perturbations but renders it highly susceptible to pure dephasing from low-frequency environmental noise. We show that coupling via a parity-conserving operator ($i\gamma_L\gamma_R$) to a bosonic environment yields a dephasing rate $\Gamma_\phi \propto S(\epsilon)$, where $S(\epsilon)$ is the environmental noise power at the qubit splitting frequency. In the experimentally relevant regime where $k_B T \gtrsim \hbar\epsilon$ (with $T \sim 10-100$ mK), the noise power scales as $S(\epsilon) \propto \rho(\epsilon) k_B T/\hbar\epsilon$, leading to a dephasing rate $\Gamma_\phi \propto \rho(\epsilon) T/\epsilon$. This exposes a fundamental challenge: the dephasing rate diverges as $1/\epsilon$ for a standard environment, e.g., a 1D system with linear dispersion where $\rho(\epsilon)$ is constant. We overcome this by designing environments with a suppressed density of states following $\rho_{\text{engineered}}(\epsilon) = \rho_{\text{free}}(\epsilon) (\epsilon/\omega_c)^\alpha$. This creates an ``inverse Purcell effect'' that yields a temperature-independent suppression factor $F_P = (\epsilon/\omega_c)^\alpha$. For $\alpha &gt; 1$, the engineered dephasing rate decreases exponentially with wire length, $\Gamma_{\phi,\text{engineered}} \propto e^{-(\alpha-1)L/\xi}$, meaning longer wires provide better coherence protection. This provides a quantitative design principle where environmental engineering transforms detrimental noise into a tool for coherence stabilization, while respecting fermion parity superselection rules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00561v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Toussaint</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Acoustics Demystifies the Strange Metals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01853</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01853v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Phonons have long been thought to be incapable of explaining key phenomena in strange metals, including linear-in-\textit{T} Planckian resistivity from high to very low temperatures. We argue that these conclusions were based on static, perturbative approaches that overlooked essential time-dependent and nonperturbative electron-lattice physics. In fact ``phonons'' are not the best target for discussion, just like ``photons'' are not the best way to think about Maxwell's equations. Quantum optics connects photons and electromagnetism, as developed 60 years ago by Glauber and others. We have been developing the parallel world of quantum acoustics. Far from being only of academic interest, the new tools are rapidly exposing the secrets of the strange metals, revealing strong vibronic (vibration-electronic) interactions playing a crucial role forming polarons and charge density waves, linear-in-$T$ resistivity at the Planckian rate over thousands of degrees, resolution of the Drude peak infrared anomaly, and the absence of a $T^4$ low-temperature resistivity rise in 2D systems, and of a Mott-Ioffe-Regel resistivity saturation. We derive Planckian transport, polarons, CDWs, and pseudogaps from the Fr\"ohlich model. The ``new physics'' has been hiding in this model all along, in the right parameter regime, if it is treated nonperturbatively. In the course of this work we have uncovered the generalization of Anderson localization to dynamic media: a universal Planckian diffusion emerges, a ``ghost'' of Anderson localization. Planckian diffusion is clearly defined and is more fundamental than the popular but elusive, model dependent concept of ``Planckian speed limit''.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01853v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric J. Heller, Alhun Aydin, Anton M. Graf, Joost de Nijs, Yoel Zimmermann, Xiaoyu Ouyang, Shaobing Yuan, Zixuan Chai, Siyuan Chen, Jasper Jain, Mingxuan Xiao, Chenzheng Yu, Zhongling Lu, Joonas Keski-Rahkonen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent Dynamical Translational Symmetry Breaking as an Order Principle for Localization and Topological Transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04360</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.04360v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Localization transitions represent a fundamental class of continuous phase transitions, yet they occur without any accompanying symmetry breaking. We resolve this by introducing the concept of dynamical translational symmetry (DTS), which is defined not by the Hamiltonian but by the long-time dynamics of local observables. Its order parameter, the time-averaged local translational contrast (TLTC), quantitatively diagnoses whether evolution restores or breaks translational equivalence. We demonstrate that the TLTC universally captures the Anderson localization transition, the many-body localization transition, and topological phase transitions, revealing that these disparate phenomena are unified by the emergent breaking of DTS. This work establishes a unified dynamical-symmetry framework for phases transitions beyond the equilibrium paradigm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.04360v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yucheng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>-Continuum limit of bipartite lattices - The SSH model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11900</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11900v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a continuous non-local model that faithfully replicates the rich topological and spectral features of the Su-Schrieffer-Heeger (SSH) model. Remarkably, our model shares the SSH models bulk energy spectrum, eigenstates, and Zak phase, hallmarks of its topological character, while introducing a tunable length-scale a quantifying non-locality. This parameter allows for a controlled interpolation between non-local and local regimes. Furthermore, for a specific value of a the exact spectral equivalence to the discrete SSH model is established. Distinct from previous continuous analogues based on Schr\"odinger or Dirac-type Hamiltonians, our approach maintains chiral symmetry, does not require an external potential and features periodic energy bands. On finite domains, the model supports a flat band with zero energy formed by a countable infinite set of exponentially localized zero-energy edge states of topological origin. Beyond SSH, our method lays the foundation for constructing non-local, continuous analogues of a wide class of bipartite and multipartite lattices, opening new paths for theoretical exploration and new challenges for experimental realization in topological quantum matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11900v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fotios K. Diakonos, P. Schmelcher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
