<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 05:00:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Fluctuation-induced giant magnetoresistance in charge-neutral graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09988</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.09988v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Johnson-Nyquist noise associated with the intrinsic conductivity of the electron liquid, induces fluctuations of the electron density in charge-neutral graphene devices. In the presence of external electric and magnetic fields, the fluctuations of charge density and electric current induce a fluctuating hydrodynamic flow. We show that the resulting advection of charge produces a fluctuation contribution to the macroscopic conductivity of the system, $\sigma_{\mathrm{fl}}$, and develop a quantitative theory of $\sigma_{\mathrm{fl}}$. At zero magnetic field, $\sigma_{\mathrm{fl}}$ diverges logarithmically with the system size and becomes rapidly suppressed at relatively small fields. This results in giant magnetoresistance of the system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.09988v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Levchenko, E. Kirkinis, A. V. Andreev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Switchable half-quantum flux states in a ring of the kagome superconductor CsV$_3$Sb$_5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10010v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic flux quantization in units of $\Phi_0 = h/2e$ is a defining feature of superconductivity, rooted in the charge-2e nature of Cooper pairs. In a ring geometry, the flux quantization leads to oscillations in the critical temperature with magnetic flux, known as the Little-Parks effect. While the maximal critical temperature is conventionally at zero flux, departures from this rule, for instance shifts by a half-quantum flux $\Phi_0/2$, clearly signal unconventional superconducting states and require sign-changing order parameters. Historically, such $\pi$-phase shifts in Little-Parks oscillations have been found in tricrystals or engineered ring structures that intentionally incorporate a $\pi$-phase shift. Here we report the discovery of switchable half-quantum flux states in rings made from single crystals of the kagome superconductor CsV$_3$Sb$_5$. We observe Little-Parks oscillations with a $\pi$-phase shift at zero bias current, which can be reversibly tuned to conventional Little-Parks oscillations upon applying a bias current. Between the $\pi$-phase and 0-phase regimes, $h/4e$ periodic oscillations appear. Our observations suggest unconventional pairing, potentially in the form of a multicomponent order parameter in the kagome superconductor CsV$_3$Sb$_5$, and reveal an electrically tunable landscape of competing superconducting condensates and fractional flux states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10010v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuo Wang, Ilaria Maccari, Xilin Feng, Ze-Nan Wu, Jia-Peng Peng, Kam Tuen Law, Y. X. Zhao, Andras Szabo, Andreas Schnyder, Ning Kang, Xiao-Song Wu, Jingchao Liu, Xuewen Fu, Mark H. Fischer, Manfred Sigrist, Dapeng Yu, Ben-Chuan Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gutzwiller approximation for paramagnetic ionic Hubbard model: Analytic expression for band - Mott insulator transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10096v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ionic Hubbard model is a paradigmatic setup for studying the competition between band and Mott insulating behavior. Within the variationally exact in infinite dimensions Gutzwiller approximation, we derive a compact analytic expression for the phase boundary between Mott and band insulator. While the method reproduces the expected band-Mott insulator phenomenology, it does not capture the correlated metallic state at finite staggered potential found for example in dynamical mean-field theory. This absence highlights that the metallic phase originates from incoherent Hubbard-band physics rather than Fermi-liquid behavior well captured by Gutzwiller approximation. Our formulation establishes a concise variational framework to ionic Hubbard model, with natural extensions to nonequilibrium setups and spin-exchange dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10096v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcin M. Wysoki\'nski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large Anomalous Hall Effect in Topologically Trivial Double-$Q$ Magnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10168</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10168v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multi-$Q$ magnets consist of superposed spin density waves with distinct magnetic modulation vectors, enabling a wide range of magnetic orders depending on their combination. Among them, topologically nontrivial spin textures, such as a magnetic skyrmion, has been extensively studied owing to the emergence of topological Hall effects induced by real-space scalar spin chirality. Contrary to this expectation, we theoretically investigate another route to enhancing the Hall response under a topologically \textit{trivial} double-$Q$ spin textures. Despite the cancellation of the scalar spin chirality, the double-$Q$ magnetism exhibits a pronounced Hall response with a nonmonotonic dependence on the uniform magnetization, which is in stark contrast to a ferromagnetic state and a single-$Q$ spiral state. Analyzing the multi-orbital Kondo lattice model, we show that orbital hybridization induced by the double-$Q$ superstructure enhances the Berry curvature in $\mathbf{k}$-space, leading to a large anomalous Hall effect. This mechanism accounts for the observed giant anomalous Hall effect in GdRu$_2$Si$_2$ and GdRu$_2$Ge$_2$, thereby highlighting topologically trivial double-$Q$ spin textures as promising spintronic materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10168v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Satoru Ohgata, Satoru Hayami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deterministic Electrical Control of Single Magnetic Bubbles in Nanostructured Cells</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10242</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10242v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Localized particle-like spin textures have been found to exhibit emergent electromagnetic properties, which hold promise for the development of intriguing spintronic devices. Among these textures, magnetic bubbles represent localized spin configurations that could serve as data bits. However, the precise methods for their electrical manipulation remain uncertain. Here, we demonstrate the deterministic electrical manipulations and detections of single magnetic bubbles in kagome-latticed Fe3Sn2 magnetic nanostructured cells. The current-induced dynamics of magnetic bubbles were explored using nanosecond pulsed currents. We show single pulsed currents with low and high densities can be applied for the creation and deletion of a single bubble, respectively. The mutual writing-deleting operations on single bubbles are attributed to the thermal heating and non-thermal spin-transfer torque effects in combination with micromagnetic simulations. We also realized the in-situ detection of a single bubble using the anisotropic magnetoresistance effect through a standard four-probe method. Our results could propel the development of bubble-based spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10242v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/adfm.202422342</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jialiang Jiang, Yaodong Wu, Lingyao Kong, Yongsen Zhang, Sheng Qiu, Huanhuan Zhang, Yihao Wang, Junbo Li, Yimin Xiong, Shouguo Wang, Mingliang Tian, Haifeng Du, Jin Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-orbit torques in bulk collinear antiferromagnets:complete classifications and the induced spin dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10356</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10356v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Electric field induced spin-orbit torques are the crucial mechanism for electric regulations of antiferromagnetic order. However, the spin-orbit torques in antiferromagnets and the induced spin dynamics remain largely unexplored. In this work, the full classifications of SOTs in bulk collinear AFMs have been achieved based on magnetic point group. Dependent on the symmetries connecting the opposite spin sublattices, the SOTs are classified into six distinct types. Among them, the SOTs and the induced Neel vector dynamics in three representative AFMs have been investigated, where the spin sublattices are connected by fractional translation, spatial inversion, and neither by translation nor inversion symmetry respectively. The SOTs on spin sublattices have been calculated by first-principles calculations based on Kubo linear response theory, and then the induced spin dynamics are simulated by LLG equations. In typical PT symmetric AFM and the inversion symmetry breaking altermagnet, the simulations indicate that the deterministic switching of Neel vectors can be driven by field like torques. What's more, the fully electric writing of multiple antiferromagnetic domains into single domain state with preset Neel vector direction and 180 deterministic switching may also be realized. Our work may shed light on the current control of antiferromagnetic orders in collinear AFMs. Especially, for inversion symmetry breaking altermagnet, the electric writing and reading of Neel vector are highly desirable for antiferromagnetic memory applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10356v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yizhuo Song, Jianting Dong, Jiahao Shentu, Jia Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surface acoustic wave-driven valley current generation in intervalley coherent states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10395</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10395v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent experiments have reported valley-gauge-symmetry-broken phases, identified as intervalley coherent (IVC) states. Exploration of anomalous responses, particularly those analogous to superconductivity, has become an urgent theoretical issue. In this study, we show that the IVC order gives rise to anomalous valley-current generation driven by surface acoustic waves (SAWs). The anomalous valley current exhibits a characteristic power-law dependence for low-frequency SAWs. Furthermore, we demonstrate by numerical analysis that the IVC order significantly enhances valley-current generation in rhombohedral graphene. These results open a pathway toward exploring exotic phenomena emerging from valley-gauge-symmetry breaking, in close analogy with gauge-symmetry breaking in superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10395v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroto Tanaka, Youichi Yanase</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic structure, orbital-dependent renormalizations, and magnetic correlations in double-layer La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ under doping tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10527v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using the DFT+dynamical mean-field theory approach we study the effects of electronic correlations and doping on the normal state electronic structure of the double-layer nickelate superconductor La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ under pressure. In agreement with experiments, we obtain significant orbital-dependent quasiparticle renormalizations of the Ni $x^2-y^2$ and $3z^2-r^2$ bands, accompanied by incoherence (bad metal behavior) of the $3z^2-r^2$ states, caused by the proximity of the Ni $3d$ states to orbital-dependent localization. Our results demonstrate a sensitive, non-monotonic dependence of $m^*/m$ on doping, with a remarkable, by about 20\%, increase for the Ni $x^2-y^2$ orbitals upon electron doping $x \sim 0.2$ (per Ni ion), implying a significant enhancement of orbital-dependent correlations with oxygen deficiency in LNO. We observe a reconstruction of the low-energy electronic structure of LNO upon doping above $x\sim -0.3$ and 0.2. It is associated with the Lifshitz transition, with a crossover to a self-doping regime characterized by partial occupation of the La $5d$ bands (upon an electron doping $x&gt;0.2$). Our analysis of the static magnetic susceptibility $\chi({\bf q})$ obtained within DFT+DMFT suggests the possible formation of the spin and charge (or bond) density wave stripes, implying strong spin and charge correlations in LNO. We show that this behavor is associated with suppression of the N\'eel $G$-type antiferromagnetic ordering of the Ni$^{2+}$ ions upon hole doping. Interestingly, upon a moderate electron doping of the Ni$^{2.5+}$ ions (e.g., with oxygen deficiency), we find a significant enhancement of the strength of in-plane spin and charge fluctuations. We note a close resembles of our results to those for the bilayer Hubbard model, which shows the boosting of superconductivity as one of the two electron bands approaches the Lifshitz transition (e.g., upon doping).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10527v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. V. Leonov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Binding of holes and competing spin-charge order in simple and extended Hubbard model on cylindrical lattice: An exact diagonalization study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10577v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the binding of holes and the emergence of competing spin-charge order in the simple and extended Hubbard model using exact diagonalization on the 3x4 cylindrical lattice. For the simple Hubbard model (V=0), we find weakly bound hole pairing mediated by magnetic correlations at intermediate repulsive U, without any evidence of phase separation. Introducing nearest-neighbor interaction V reveals a rich phase diagram: attractive V drives multi-hole clustering and phase separation with localized magnetic quenching, while repulsive V stabilizes charge-density-wave (CDW) order that coexists with bound hole pairs within a modulated magnetic background. At strong coupling (U=10), the competition sharpens, with attractive V overcoming on-site repulsion to form magnetically quenched clusters and repulsive V producing robust CDW order that constrains pairing. Real-space analysis of spin and charge correlations provides microscopic evidence of distinct binding mechanisms -- phase separation versus correlation-mediated pairing -- depending on the sign and strength of intersite interaction V . Our results establish a comprehensive picture of how nonlocal Coulomb interactions reshape the landscape of hole-binding and collective order in correlated electron systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10577v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Md Fahad Equbal, M. A. H. Ahsan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase structure of the one-dimensional $\mathbb{Z}_2$ lattice gauge theory with second nearest-neighbor interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10755v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the ground-state phase diagram of a one-dimensional $\mathbb{Z}_2$ lattice gauge theory (LGT) model with hard-core bosons at half-filling, extending previous studies by including second nearest-neighbor (2NN) interactions. Using matrix product state techniques within the density matrix renormalization group, we compute charge gap, static structure factor, and pair-pair correlation functions for various interaction strengths and field parameters. We analyze two representative neatest-neighbor interaction strengths ($V_1$) that correspond to the Luttinger liquid (LL) and Mott insulator (MI) phases in the absence of the 2NN interactions. We introduce the 2NN coupling $V_2$ and investigate its impact on the system. Our results reveal very rich behavior. As the 2NN repulsion increases, in the case of small $V_1$, we observe a direct transition from the LL phase to a charge-ordered insulator (COI) phase, whereas for large $V_1$, we observe a transition from the MI phase (previously found with only $V_1$ included), going through an intermediate LL region, and finally reaching the COI regime. Additionally, the inclusion of 2NN interactions enhances charge order and suppresses pair coherence, evidenced by sharp peaks in the structure factor and rapid decay in pair-pair correlators. Our work extends the well-studied phase structure of 1D $\mathbb{Z}_2$ LGT models and demonstrates the interplay between gauge fields, confinement, and extended interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10755v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yeimer Zambrano, Aleksey Alekseev, Konrad J. Kapcia, Krzysztof Cichy, Agnieszka Cichy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Engineering of a Frustrated Antiferromagnetic Triradical in Aza-Triangulene Architectures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10869v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Open-shell nanographenes provide a versatile platform to host unconventional magnetic states within their {\pi}-conjugated networks. Particularly appealing are graphene architectures that incorporate spatially separated radicals and tunable interactions, offering a scalable route toward spin-based quantum architectures. Triangulenes are ideal for this purpose, as their radical count scales with size, although strong hybridization prevents individual spin control. Here, we realize a radical reconfiguration strategy that transforms a single-radical aza-triangulene into a frustrated antiferromagnetic triradical by covalently extending it with armchair anthene moieties of increasing length. Scanning tunnelling spectroscopy reveals edge-localized Kondo resonances and a doublet-to-quartet spin excitation, evidencing the emergence of correlated spins. Multi-reference electronic-structure calculations trace the progressive increase in polyradical character with anthene length, driven by the clustering of frontier states within a narrow energy window. Consequently, the initial single-radical doublet reorganizes into a frustrated triradical with weakly coupled edge spins, a molecular analog of a three-qubit quantum register.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10869v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francisco Romero-Lara, Manuel Vilas-Varela, Ricardo Ortiz, Manish Kumar, Alessio Vegliante, Luc\'ia G\'omez-Rodrigo, Jan Patrick Calupitan, Diego Soler, Nikas Friedrich, Dongfei Wang, Jon Ortuzar, Stefano Trivini, Fabian Schulz, Thomas Frederiksen, Pavel Jel\'inek, Diego Pe\~na, Jose Ignacio Pascual</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disorder mediated fully compensated ferrimagnetic spin-gapless semiconducting behaviour in Cr3Al Heusler alloy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10885</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10885v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spin-gapless semiconductors (SGSs) that simultaneously host fully compensated ferrimagnetism are highly sought for energy-efficient and stray-field-free spintronic technologies, yet their realization in chemically disordered systems has remained elusive. Here, we demonstrate that the binary Heusler alloy Cr3Al despite adopting a fully A2-disordered structure exhibits a rare coexistence of SGS transport and a fully compensated ferrimagnetic (FCF) ground state. Single-crystalline and polycrystalline Cr3Al samples were synthesized, and comprehensive structural analyses using single crystal XRD, synchrotron powder XRD, and neutron powder diffraction reveal complete Cr/Al site mixing. Remarkably, this chemical disorder does not disrupt magnetic order; instead, magnetization, X-ray magnetic circular dichroism (XMCD), and temperature-dependent neutron diffraction establish a robust compensated ferrimagnetic state with a vanishingly small ordered moment of 0.1(1) muB/f.u and a high Curie temperature of 773(2) K. Electrical and thermal transport measurements uncover clear SGS characteristics, including weak temperature-dependent conductivity, very low Seebeck coefficients, and electron-hole compensated transport. Hall measurements show unusual temperature-dependent carrier concentrations consistent with disorder-modified electronic states. First-principles calculations on an A2-disordered SQS structure reproduce the experimentally observed negligibly small magnetization (0.0072 muB/f.u) and reveal a vanishing spin-up band gap unambiguously supporting SGS behavior driven by chemical disorder. Our results identify Cr3Al as the first experimentally verified A2-disordered Heusler alloy exhibiting both fully compensated ferrimagnetism and spin-gapless semiconducting transport, positioning it as a robust and disorder-tolerant platform for next-generation, high-temperature spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10885v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Reshna Elsa Philip, Pooja Vyas, Nikhil Joseph Joy, Sandip Kumar Kuila, Sonia Beniwal, Akshata Magar, Dinesh Kumar Shukla, Partha Pratim Jana, Amit Kumar, Aftab Alam, Jayakumar Balakrishnan, Soham Manni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shaping chaos in bilayer graphene cavities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10914</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10914v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Bilayer graphene (BLG) cavities, where electrons are confined in finite graphene flakes, provide a suitable platform to study quantum chaotic phenomena in condensed matter systems due to the trigonal warping of the Fermi surface. Here, we investigate the effect of the misalignment between the BLG lattice and the cavity geometry, introduced by rotating the boundary relative to the lattice, which can drive the system towards chaos. Based on a tight-binding model, eigenenergy level statistics reveals that rotation leads to level repulsion following Wigner-Dyson statistics, while corresponding eigenstate analysis indicates a transition from near-integrability to spatially uncorrelated random waves. Analysis of the semiclassical ray-dynamics with the trigonal-warped dispersion unveils an ergodic phase space structure, providing a quantum-classical correspondence of the onset of chaos. These findings establish an avenue to quantum chaotic phenomena in BLG cavities with potential applications in quantum device engineering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10914v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jucheng Lin, Yicheng Zhuang, Anton M. Graf, Joonas Keski-Rahkonen, Eric J. Heller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pair-density-wave in quarter-metals from a repulsive fermionic interaction in graphene heterostructures: A renormalization group study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10944v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Electronic bands in chirally stacked $n$ layer carbon-based honeycomb heterostructures, encompassing rhombohedral ($n \geq 3$), Bernal bilayer ($n=2$), and monolayer ($n=1$) graphene, possess four-fold valley and spin degeneracy. Such systems with $n \geq 2$, when subject to external perpendicular electric displacement fields, feature a fully degenerate metal at high doping, a spin non-degenerate but valley degenerate half-metal at moderate doping, and a non-degenerate quarter-metal at low doping. Due to the fully polarized nature of the quasiparticles in the quarter-metal, realized around one particular valley otherwise chosen spontaneously, it can sustain a single local superconducting ground state, representing a pair-density-wave that is chiral and odd parity in nature. From a leading order renormalization group analysis, here we show that repulsive density-density interaction among such polarized fermionic excitations can foster the pair-density-wave phase at low temperatures. Possible connections with experimentally observed superconducting states in the close vicinity of the quarter-metal in some members of such graphene heterostructures family are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10944v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sk Asrap Murshed, Bitan Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reaching Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev physics by shaking the Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02755v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev (SYK) model has attracted widespread attention due to its relevance to diverse areas of physics, such as high temperature superconductivity, black holes, and quantum chaos. The model is, however, extremely challenging to realize experimentally. In this work, we show how a particular form of Floquet engineering, termed ``kinetic driving'', effectively eliminates single-particle processes and creates quasi-random all-to-all interactions when applied to models of Hubbard type. For the specific case of the Bose-Hubbard model, we explicitly verify that the driven system indeed reproduces SYK physics by direct comparison of the spectral form factor and out-of-time ordered correlation functions (OTOCs). Our findings indicate that a cold-atom realization of kinetic driving -- achieved through modulation of hopping amplitudes in an optical lattice -- offers a practical and accurate platform for quantum simulation of the SYK model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02755v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charles Creffield, Fernando Sols, Marco Schir\`o, Nathan Goldman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generation of Perfectly Achromatic Optical Vortices Using a Compensated Tandem Twisted Nematic Cell</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10090</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10090v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The generation of white optical vortices is currently constrained by intrinsic trade-offs between spectral bandwidth, conversion efficiency, and temporal pulse integrity in conventional diffractive and geometric-phase approaches. In this work, we theoretically investigate a compensated tandem crossed twisted nematic (TN) liquid crystal architecture that overcomes these fundamental limitations. By developing a rigorous Jones matrix model and defining specific figures of merit for chromatic fidelity, we analyze the impact of manufacturing imperfections and non-adiabatic waveguiding (deviations from the Mauguin regime) on the device performance. We propose and evaluate three distinct compensation strategies, ranging from optimized passive designs for specific manufacturing tolerances to a robust active compensation scheme utilizing a tunable retarder. Our analysis demonstrates that the active approach effectively nullifies parasitic amplitude modulation, enabling the generation of perfectly achromatic vortices with high phase purity across an arbitrary bandwidth. This establishes the compensated tandem TN cell as a superior and versatile platform for high-fidelity white-light singular optics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10090v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dmytro O. Plutenko, Mikhail V. Vasnetsov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Second Harmonic Hall Response in Insulators: Inter-band Quantum Geometry and Breakdown of Kleinman's Conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07456</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07456v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The nonlinear Hall effect has recently garnered significant attention as a powerful probe of Fermi surface quantum geometry in metals. While current studies mainly focus on the nonlinear Hall response driven by quasi-static electric fields of low frequencies, the extension of the response to higher frequencies is another promising frontier, which introduces quantum geometry into inter-band transitions. Here, we demonstrate that a specific nonlinear Hall response, namely the second harmonic Hall (SHH) response, can arise from inter-band transitions. We establish the quantum geometric origin of the SHH response and show that inter-band quantum geometry dominates the SHH response when driven near inter-band resonance. Crucially, we find that the inter-band SHH response in insulators exhibits strong frequecy dispersion, manifesting the breakdown of Kleinman's conjecture in nonlinear optics. This connects the SHH response to the breakdown of Kleinman's conjecture and reveals that frequency dispersive insulators generally allow the SHH response. Furthermore, we predict a giant SHH susceptibility in gated strained bilayer graphene and propose that one can apply the polarization resolved second harmonic microscopy to detect the SHH response there.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07456v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Yu He, K. T. Law</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay of orbital-selective Mott criticality and flat-band physics in La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_6$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19617</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19617v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Superconductivity in nickelates apparently takes place in two different Ni oxidation regimes, namely either for infinite-layer-type compounds close to Ni$^{+}$, or for Ruddlesden-Popper materials close to Ni$^{2+}$. The reduced La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_6$ bilayer with a nominal Ni$^{1.5+}$ oxidation state may therefore serve as a normal-state mediator between the two known families of $3d^8$-like and $3d^9$-like superconducting nickelates. Using first-principles many-body theory, we explain its experimental 50\,meV charge gap as originating from a new type of correlated (quasi-)insulator. Flat-band electrons of Ni-$d_{z^2}$ character become localized from scattering with orbital-selective Mott-localized Ni-$d_{x^2-y^2}$ electrons, by trading in residual hopping energy for a gain in local exchange energy in a ferromagnetic Kondo-lattice scenario. Most importantly, the flat-band electrons offer another route to unconventional superconductivity in nickelates at ambient pressure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19617v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/3r7g-89r8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 245125 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Frank Lechermann, Steffen B\"otzel, Ilya M. Eremin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral Heisenberg Gross-Neveu-Yukawa criticality: Honeycomb vs. SLAC fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15000v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We perform large scale quantum Monte Carlo simulations of the Hubbard model at half filling with a single Dirac cone close to the critical point, which separates a Dirac semi-metal from an antiferromagnetically ordered phase where SU(2) spin rotational symmetry is spontaneously broken. We discuss the implementation of a single Dirac cone in the SLAC formulation for eight Dirac components and the influence of dynamically induced long-range super-exchange interactions. The finite size behavior of dimensionless ratios and the finite size scaling properties of the Hubbard model with a single Dirac cone are shown to be superior compared to the honeycomb lattice. We extract the critical exponent believed to belong to the chiral Heisenberg Gross-Neveu-Yukawa universality class: The critical exponent ${\nu = 1.02(3)}$ coincides for the two lattice types once honeycomb lattices of linear dimension ${L\ge 15}$ are considered. In contrast to the SLAC formulation, where the anomalous dimensions are estimated to be ${\eta_{\phi}=0.73(1)}$ and ${\eta_{\psi}=0.09(1)}$, they remain less stable on honeycomb lattices, but tend towards the estimates from the SLAC formulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15000v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/vlgd-7ln8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 245121 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Thomas C. Lang, Andreas M. L\"auchli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Altermagnetism and Weak Magnetism in the Insulating Distorted Perovskite Antiferromagnet NaOsO$_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17159</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17159v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The GdFeO$_3$-type perovskite antiferromagnet NaOsO$_3$, calculated here to be altermagnetic for all three typical collinear antiferromagnetic orders, was suggested early on to be a Slater-type insulator, due in large part to its continuous metal-insulator transition and its small energy gap. Below the N\'eel temperature, the gap opens along with ``weak magnetism'', accompanied by a sharp change in the magnetic susceptibility and resistivity. Without explicit correlation in the band structure calculation, and neglecting spin-orbit coupling (SOC), already a gap opens. Inclusion of a modest on-site Coulomb repulsion ($U\sim$1 eV) is sufficient to eliminate a SOC-induced small band overlap, opening a gap similar to the experimentally observed gap of around 100 meV. Combined evidence supports the viewpoint that NaOsO$_3$ lies in an unusual crossover region between Slater and Mott insulator. The unreported altermagnetism in NaOsO$_3$ is demonstrated and its consequences are considered. The origin of the very weak magnetism has been investigated using a combination of {\it ab initio} calculations and symmetry analysis of the magnetic space group, confirming the origin lying in the Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya SOC buttressed by altermagnetic order. After determining the easy axis, our calculation leads to an Os spin canting angle of about 3$^{\circ}$, accounting for the observed weak magnetism and sharp change in the susceptibility. The altermagnetism spin-split bands (up to $\sim$100 meV) are accompanied by a chiral-split magnon spectrum in both acoustic and optical modes in the THz range, and lead to significant anomalous Hall conductivity upon hole doping.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17159v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/ljrc-jcb4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Materials 9, 124405 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hong-Suk Choi, M. -C. Jung, K. -H. Ahn, W. E. Pickett, K. -W. Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconductivity in imbalanced bilayer Hubbard model: enhanced $d$-wave and weakened $s^\pm$-wave pairing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10503</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10503v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the bilayer model with two layers of imbalanced densities coupled by the interlayer hybridization. Using the large-scale dynamical cluster quantum Monte Carlo simulation, we discovered that increased hybridization induces a transition in the superconducting pairing from $d$-wave to $s^{\pm}$-wave and the superconducting $T_c$ of $d$-wave pairing exhibits a non-monotonic dependence on the density imbalance. Remarkably, the optimal superconductivity(SC) occurs at a moderate imbalance. Our results support the possibility of $T_c$ enhancement in composite picture where the underdoped layer provides the pairing strength while the overdoped layer promotes the phase coherence. In addition, the SC can be possibly hosted by a single layer, which is reminiscent of our recent exploration on the trilayer Hubbard model. Our present study thus provides new insight that the SC can be enhanced via the layer differentiation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10503v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziying Jia, Xun Liu, Mi Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From hidden order to skyrmions: Quantum Hall states in an extended Hofstadter-Fermi-Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12184</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12184v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The interplay between topology and strong interactions gives rise to a variety of exotic quantum phases, including fractional quantum Hall (FQH) states and their lattice analogs - fractional Chern insulators (FCIs). Such topologically ordered states host fractionalized excitations and, for spinful systems, are often accompanied by ferromagnetism and skyrmions. Here, we study a Hofstadter-Hubbard model of spinful fermions on a square lattice, extended by nearest-neighbor interactions. Using large-scale density matrix renormalization group (DMRG) simulations, we demonstrate the emergence of a spin-polarized $\frac{1}{3}$-Laughlin-like FCI phase, characterized by a quantized many-body Chern number, a finite charge gap, and hidden off-diagonal long-range order. We further investigate the quantum Hall ferromagnet at $\nu=1$ and its skyrmionic excitations upon doping. In particular, we find that nearest-neighbor repulsion is sufficient to stabilize both particle- and hole-skyrmions in the ground state around $\nu=1$, whereas we do not find such textures around $\nu=\frac{1}{3}$. The diagnostic toolbox presented in this work, based on local densities, correlation functions, and spin-resolved observables, is directly applicable in quantum gas microscopy experiments. Our results open new pathways for experimental exploration of FCIs with spin textures in both ultracold atom and electronic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12184v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabian J. Pauw, Ulrich Schollw\"ock, Nathan Goldman, Sebastian Paeckel, Felix A. Palm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconductivity suppression and bilayer decoupling in Pr substituted YBa$_2$Cu$_3$O$_{7-\delta}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15078v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The mechanism behind superconductivity suppression induced by Pr substitutions in YBa$_2$Cu$_3$O$_{7-\delta}$ (YBCO) has been a mystery since its discovery: in spite of being isovalent to Y$^{3+}$ with a small magnetic moment, it is the only rare-earth element that has a dramatic impact on YBCO's superconducting properties. Using angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) and DFT+$U$ calculations, we uncover how Pr substitution modifies the low-energy electronic structure of YBCO. Contrary to the prevailing Fehrenbacher-Rice (FR) and Liechtenstein-Mazin (LM) models, the low energy electronic structure contains no signature of any $f$-electron hybridization or new states. Yet, strong electron doping is observed primarily on the antibonding Fermi surface. Meanwhile, we reveal major electronic structure modifications to Cu-derived states with increasing Pr substitution: a pronounced CuO$_2$ bilayer decoupling and an enhanced CuO chain hopping, implying indirect electron-release pathways beyond simple 4$f$ state ionization. Our results challenge the long-standing FR/LM mechanism and establish Pr substituted YBCO as a potential platform for exploring correlation-driven phenomena in coupled 1D-2D systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15078v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinming Yang, Zheting Jin, Siqi Wang, Camilla Moir, Mingyu Xu, Brandon Gunn, Xian Du, Zhibo Kang, Keke Feng, Makoto Hashimoto, Donghui Lu, Jessica McChesney, Martin Sundermann, Hlynur Gretarsson, Shize Yang, Wei-Wei Xie, Alex Frano, M. Brian Maple, Sohrab Ismail-Beigi, Yu He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interaction-Induced Breakdown of Anderson Localization: Thermodynamic Segregation disguised as the Skin Effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05393</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05393v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the interplay between strong disorder and repulsive interactions in the one-dimensional Fermi-Hubbard model under open boundary conditions. While uncorrelated disorder is widely accepted to localize all single-particle eigenstates, a phenomenon typically reinforced by interactions in the Many-Body Localization (MBL) regime, we report a counter-intuitive breakdown of this paradigm. We demonstrate that strong repulsive interactions can overcome disorder-induced localization, driving the system into a macroscopically segregated phase where spin species accumulate at opposite boundaries. Although this boundary accumulation phenomenologically mimics the Non-Hermitian Skin Effect (NHSE) observed in non-reciprocal systems, our comprehensive analysis reveals a fundamentally different origin. By performing a rigorous control experiment in the Hermitian limit, we prove that the segregation persists without non-reciprocity, identifying many-body energy minimization as the primary driver. This "interaction-induced segregation" manifests as a sharp thermodynamic crossover, characterized by a divergent energy susceptibility, challenging the conventional understanding of disorder-interaction competition in open quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05393v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Tozar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
