<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 04:00:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>peaks: a Python package for analysis of angle-resolved photoemission and related spectroscopies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.04803v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The electronic band structure, describing the motion and interactions of electrons in materials, dictates the electrical, optical, and thermodynamic properties of solids. Angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) provides a direct experimental probe of such electronic band structures, and so is widely employed in the study of functional, quantum, and 2D materials. \texttt{peaks} (\textbf{P}ython \textbf{E}lectron spectroscopy \textbf{A}nalysis by \textbf{K}ing group @ \textbf{S}t Andrews) provides a Python package for advanced data analysis of ARPES and related spectroscopic data. It facilitates the fast visualisation and analysis of multi-dimensional datasets, allows for the complex data hierarchy typical to ARPES experiments, and supports lazy data loading and parallel processing, reflecting the ever-increasing data volumes used in ARPES. It is designed to be run in an interactive notebook environment, with extensive inline and pop-out GUI support for data visualisation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.04803v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Phil D. C. King, Brendan Edwards, Shu Mo, Tommaso Antonelli, Edgar Abarca Morales, Lewis Hart, Liam Trzaska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse Lieb Materials: Altermagnetism and More</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.04839v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Lieb lattice, originally proposed for cuprate superconductors, has gained new attention in the emerging field of altermagnetism as a minimal analytical model for the latter. While initially the so-called inverse Lieb lattice (ILL) was deemed only a theoretical model, recently several real materials with this crystallographic motif have been found. The unique geometry of ILL can accommodate complex magnetic orderings arising from competing exchange interactions and geometric frustration, offering great tunability for magnetic properties. In this work, we provide comprehensive insights into magnetic phases in ILL materials and establish guidelines for efficient identification of altermagnetic materials within this family. We begin by constructing phase diagrams using a simple Heisenberg model to elucidate the fundamental mechanisms underlying altermagnetism and other complex magnetic phases observed experimentally. To bridge theory with experiment, we systematically investigate a series of existing ILL compounds using density functional theory (DFT) calculations to determine their magnetic ground states. Our computational results are in good agreement with experimental observations. Importantly, we identify a trend linking magnetic ordering to the $d$-shell filling of transition metal ions, with $d^{2-3}$ and $d^{5}$ configurations showing propensity for altermagnetic behavior. Additionally, we identify a promising metallic compound Sr$_{2}$CrO$_{2}$Cr$_{2}$OAs$_{2}$ as an altermagnet that is highly anisotropic in its $J_2$ exchange couplings with large N\'eel temperature ($\sim 600$ K). Using exchange coupling parameters extracted from DFT calculations, we compute the magnon spectra for altermagnetic systems. As expected, chiral splittings in the magnon dispersion are directly correlated with anisotropy between crystallographically inequivalent $J_{2}$ exchange interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.04839v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Po-Hao Chang, Igor I. Mazin, Kirill D. Belashchenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Engineering Topological Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.04927v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The tenfold classification provides a powerful framework for organizing topological phases of matter based on symmetry and spatial dimension. However, it does not offer a systematic method for transitioning between classes or engineering materials to realize desired topological properties. In this work, we introduce a general method for designing topological materials by embedding defects or spatial textures, which alter symmetry or dimension. This enables controlled navigation across the tenfold table, allowing one to induce topological phase transitions on demand. We illustrate this approach through several nontrivial examples, demonstrating how local defects can generate phases with different symmetries and topological invariants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.04927v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amit Goft, Eric Akkermans</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chern junctions in Moir\'e-Patterned Graphene/PbI2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04935</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.04935v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Expanding the moir\'e material library continues to unlock novel quantum phases and emergent electronic behaviors. In this work, we introduce PbI2 into the moir\'e family and investigate the magnetotransport properties of moir\'e superlattice in a hexagonal boron nitride/graphene/PbI2 heterostructures. In high-field quantum Hall regime, we observe a robust dissipationless transport at charge neutrality point, indicative of incompressible states stabilized at the filling factor vh = 0. Additionally, a fractional conductance plateau at 2/3 e2/h emerges, which we attribute to a Chern junction between domains with distinct Chern numbers originating from moir\'e-modulated and conventional integer quantum Hall states. The moir\'e Hofstadter spectrum displays an unconventional flavor sequence, likely influenced by proximity-induced spin-orbit coupling from the PbI2 layer. We also see coherent electronic interference along lines with Chern number vm = -2. These findings position PbI2-based heterostructures as a versatile platform for realizing spin-orbit-enhanced moir\'e phenomena and engineering coherent edge transport in two-dimensional quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.04935v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sun Yan, M. Monteverde, V. Derkach, K. Watanabe, T. Taniguchi, F. Chiodi, H. Bouchiat, A. D. Chepelianskii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Anisotropy in Two-dimensional van der Waals Magnetic Materials and Their Heterostructures: Importance, Mechanisms, and Opportunities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04952</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.04952v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2D) magnetism in atomically thin van der Waals (vdW) monolayers and heterostructures has attracted significant attention due to its promising potential for next-generation spintronic and quantum technologies. A key factor in stabilizing long-range magnetic order in these systems is magnetic anisotropy, which plays a crucial role in overcoming the limitations imposed by the Mermin-Wagner theorem. This review provides a comprehensive theoretical and experimental overview of the importance of magnetic anisotropy in enabling intrinsic 2D magnetism and shaping the electronic, magnetic, and topological properties of 2D vdW materials. We begin by summarizing the fundamental mechanisms that determine magnetic anisotropy, emphasizing the contributions from strong ligand spin-orbit coupling of ligand atoms and unquenched orbital magnetic moments. We then examine a range of material engineering approaches, including alloying, doping, electrostatic gating, strain, and pressure, that have been employed to effectively tune magnetic anisotropy in these materials. Finally, we discuss open challenges and promising future directions in this rapidly advancing field. By presenting a broad perspective on the role of magnetic anisotropy in 2D magnetism, this review aims to stimulate ongoing efforts and new ideas toward the realization of robust, room-temperature applications based on 2D vdW magnetic materials and their heterostructures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.04952v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/adfm.202509453</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Advanced Functional Materials (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yusheng Hou, Ruqian Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alpha-, Beta-, and Gamma-TODD-G: Novel 2D Planar Carbon Allotropes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.05013v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive first-principles investigation of three novel two-dimensional carbon allotropes: alpha-, beta-, and gamma-TODD-Graphene (TODD-G), composed of 3-8-12-16, 3-8-12-16, and 3-4-8-12 interconnected carbon rings with sp/sp2 hybridization, respectively. Structural optimization, phonon spectra, and ab initio molecular dynamics simulations confirm their thermal and dynamical stability. All phases exhibit metallic electronic behavior, with distinct Dirac-like features and tilted Dirac cones that suggest anisotropic charge transport. Mechanical analysis reveals tunable anisotropy: alpha-TODD-G is strongly anisotropic, beta-TODD-G shows moderate anisotropy, and gamma-TODD-G displays an almost isotropic mechanical response. Optical spectra further differentiate the phases, with gamma-TODD-G showing strong absorption in the infrared region, while alpha- and beta-TODD-G mainly absorb in the visible and ultraviolet ranges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.05013v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kleuton A. L. Lima, Jose A. S. Laranjeira, Alysson M. A. Silva, Bill. D. Aparicio-Huacarpuma, Fabr\'icio M. Vasconcelos, Julio R. Sambrano, Douglas S. Galv\~ao, Luiz A. Ribeiro Junior</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aharonov-Bohm interference from coherent spin-polarized edge transport in Fe(Te,Se) superconducting rings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05030</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.05030v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report the coexistence of Aharonov-Bohm and Little-Parks oscillations in mesoscopic Fe(Te,Se) rings. The magnetoresistance shows two distinct periodicities: an $h/e$ component from ballistic edge interference and an $h/2e$ component from fluxoid quantization of Cooper pairs. Aharonov-Bohm oscillations persist deep into the superconducting phase, exhibit current-field symmetry, and follow a temperature dependence captured by a helical Luttinger liquid model, consistent with edge states in a topological superconductor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.05030v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Javadi Balakan, Shiva Heidari, Genda Gu, Qiang Li, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Ji Ung Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple quantum spin Hall states and topological current divider in Twisted Bilayer WSe$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05092</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.05092v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It has been demonstrated that topological quantum spin Hall (QSH) state exist in twisted bilayers of transition metal dichalcogenides. However, a comprehensive theoretical characterization of the topological edge states remains a topic of interest and an unresolved issue. Here, the topological transport properties of the twisted WSe$_2$ bilayers are investigated. Beyond the conventional single QSH, we identify emergent double and quartuple quantum spin Hall states, hosting two and four pairs of counter-propagating helical edge channels respectively. Furthermore, the charge carriers in these edge states are not localized at edge but rather the high potential point of the moire superlattice boundary, undergoing interlayer transitions and propagating forward continuously. We term these edge states as moire edge states. These edge states can survive in non-magnetic disorder, with the robustness of double QSH states surpassing that of single QSH states. At a twisting angle of 2.45$^\circ$, the transition between the single and double QSH states can be achieved by adjusting the gate on the surface. Based on this, we propose a five-terminal device to as a topological current devider. Our findings provide support for the development of dissipationless spintronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.05092v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao He, Zhao Gong, Shuai Li, Jian-Jun Liu, Hui-Ying Mu, Xing-Tao An</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A case for resonant x-ray Bragg diffraction by a collinear antiferromagnet Li2Ni3P4O14</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.05174v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic axial and polar (Dirac) nickel multipoles contribute to resonant x-ray Bragg amplitudes in a symmetry informed analysis of monoclinic Li2Ni3P4O14 presented for future diffraction experiments. Magnetic long-range order below a temperature 14.5 K can be viewed as a two-dimensional trimerized antiferromagnet with Ni ions in two Wyckoff positions in the centrosymmetric magnetic space group P21/c. It permits the coupling to circular polarization in the primary x-ray beam, unlike the corresponding diffraction by an antiferromagnet characterized by anti-inversion and a linear magnetoelectric effect, e.g., historically significant chromium sesquioxide (Cr2O3) and Cu2(MoO4)(SeO3) (Lovesey &amp; van der Laan, 2024). The space group is inferred from neutron Bragg diffraction patterns, without an allowance for permitted Dirac dipoles (anapoles) and quadrupoles (Chikara et al., 2025).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.05174v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephen W. Lovesey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced spin-to-charge conversion in La$_{0.67}$Sr$_{0.33}$MnO$_3$/NdNiO$_3$ bilayers at the nickelate metal-insulator phase transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.05300v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Phase transition materials such as NdNiO3 (NNO) when coupled with low damping ferromagnets such as La$_{0.67}$Sr$_{0.33}$MnO$_3$ (LSMO) can lead to new multi-functional material systems harnessing the interplay of charge, spin and orbital degrees of freedom. In this study, we probe the evolution of the spin-to-charge conversion in epitaxial all-oxide LSMO (12 nm)/NNO (4, 8, and 16 nm) bilayers. Using spin pumping ferromagnetic resonance we track the spin-charge conversion in the NNO layer through the paramagnetic metal to antiferromagnetic insulator transition and observe a pronounced enhancement of the inverse spin Hall effect signal at the onset of this transition. We attribute this enhancement to the electronic and magnetic disorder in NNO at the first-order phase transition, thereby providing insights into the mechanism of spin transport through the phase transition. The tunability of spin charge conversion in this low damping bilayer system offers a pathway for developing multifunctional, energy-efficient spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.05300v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Biswajit Sahoo, Sarmistha Das, Akilan K, Alexandre Pofelski, Sebastien Petit-Watelot, Juan-Carlos Rojas-S\'anchez, Yimei Zhu, Alex Frano, Eric E Fullerton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal relations between thermoelectrics and noise in mesoscopic transport across a tunnel junction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.05413v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a unified theory of weakly probed differential observables for currents and noise in transport experiments. Our findings uncover a set of universal transport relations between thermoelectric and noise properties of a system probed through a tunnel contact, with the Wiedemann-Franz law being just one example of such universality between charge and heat currents. We apply this theory to various quantum dot systems, including multichannel Kondo, quantum Hall and Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev quantum dots, and demonstrate that each of the microscopic theories is characterized by a set of universal relations connecting conductance and thermoelectrics with noise. Violations of these relations indicate additional energy scales emerging in a system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.05413v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei I. Pavlov, Mikhail N. Kiselev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonreciprocal inertial spin-wave dynamics in twisted magnetic nanostrips</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05576</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.05576v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a theoretical framework for inertial spin-wave dynamics in three-dimensional twisted soft-magnetic nanostrips, where curvature and torsion couple with magnetic inertia to generate terahertz (THz) magnetic oscillations. The resulting spin-wave spectra exhibit pronounced nonreciprocity due to effective symmetry breaking arising from geometric chirality and inertial effects. We show that this behavior is governed by a curvature-induced geometric (Berry) phase, which we analytically capture through compact expressions for dispersion relations and spectral linewidths in both nutational (THz) and precessional (GHz) regimes. Topological variations, including M\"obius and helical geometries, impose distinct wavenumber quantization rules, elucidating the role of topology in spin-wave transport. These results position twisted magnetic strips as a viable platform for curvilinear THz magnonics and nonreciprocal spintronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.05576v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Massimiliano d'Aquino, Riccardo Hertel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Band Structure and Pairing Nature of La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ Thin Film at Ambient Pressure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10409v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently, evidences of superconductivity (SC) with onset $T_c$ above the McMillan limit have been detected in the La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ ultrathin film grown on the LaSrAlO$_4$ substrate at ambient pressure. This progress opens a new era in the field of the nickelate superconductors. Here we perform a density-functional-theory (DFT) based calculation for the band structure of this material. The obtained DFT+$U$ band structure has the feature that the bonding $d_{z^2}$ band crosses the Fermi level, forming the hole pocket $\gamma$, consistent with the angle-resolved photoemission spectrum (ARPES). Taking the low-energy Ni-$(3d_{z^2},3d_{x^2-y^2})$ orbitals placed on the tetragonal lattice structure, we construct a 2D bilayer four-band tight-binding model which well captures the main features of the DFT+$U$ band structure. Then considering the multi-orbital Hubbard interaction, we adopt the random-phase approximation (RPA) approach to investigate the pairing nature. The obtained pairing symmetry is $s^{\pm}$ or $d_{xy}$ for the hole-doping level $\delta$ below or above 0.12, induced by the different Fermi surface nesting situations. For the realistic $\delta=0.21$ measured by the ARPES, our RPA calculations obtain the next-nearest-neighbor pairing $d_{xy}$-wave SC dominated by the $d_{z^2}$ orbital, consistent with the experimental observation that the $T_c$ enhances with the shrinking of the in-plane lattice constants. This pairing state is induced by the nesting between the different patches within the $\gamma$ pocket. Our results appeal for experimental verifications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10409v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/9t6n-jqr5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 024506 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zhi-Yan Shao, Yu-Bo Liu, Min Liu, Fan Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bipartite Fluctuations and Charge Fractionalization in Quantum Wires</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14410v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a quantum information method for measuring fractional charges in ballistic quantum wires generalizing bipartite fluctuations to the chiral quasiparticles in Luttinger liquids, i.e. adding charge and current fluctuations in a region of the wire. Bipartite fluctuations at equilibrium are characterized through a logarithmic scaling with distance encoding the entangled nature of these fractional charges in one-dimensional (1D) fluids. This approach clarifies the physical meaning of the dephasing factor of electronic interferences in a ballistic ring geometry at zero temperature, as a result of charge fractionalization. We formulate an analogy towards ground-state energetics. We show how bipartite current fluctuations represent a useful tool to locate quantum phase transitions associated to Mott physics. We address a spin chain equivalence and verify the fractional charges through an algorithm such as Density Matrix Renormalization Group (DMRG). Adding a potential difference between the two sides (parties) of the wire, bipartite fluctuations can detect a bound state localized at the interface through the Jackiw-Rebbi model coexisting with fractional charges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14410v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Magali Korolev, Karyn Le Hur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Epitaxial growth and transport properties of a metallic altermagnet CrSb on a GaAs (001) substrate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08117v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A newly identified class of magnetic materials called altermagnets has attracted much attention due to the practical properties of spin-splitting bands akin to ferromagnets and small compensated magnetization akin to antiferromagnets. These features make them promising candidates for applications in spintronics devices. Among candidate materials, CrSb is promising because of its high ordering temperature (~705 K) and large spin-splitting energy; however, it is predicted that tuning the N\'eel vector requires additional symmetry breaking or a change in the easy magnetization axis. While applying epitaxial strain can modulate the symmetry, the selection of substrates with closely matched lattice constants for heteroepitaxial growth is limited for altermagnets, which generally have low crystal symmetry. Therefore, exploring the heteroepitaxial growth of altermagnet thin films on well-established, dissimilar crystal systems is valuable. (001)-oriented III-V semiconductors, which share group-V elements with the overgrown CrSb, offer an ideal platform because they are expected to have material compatibility with stable interfaces, as well as tunability of the buffer layer's bandgap and lattice constant by varying the atomic composition of their group-III and group-V atoms. In this study, we have achieved the molecular beam epitaxial growth of a CrSb ($\bar{1}10$) thin film on a GaAs (001) substrate by inserting thin FeSb ($\bar{1}10$) / AlAs (001) buffer layers. The in-plane epitaxial relationship is found to be CrSb [110] $\|$ GaAs [110] and CrSb [001] $\|$ GaAs [$\bar{1}10$], and epitaxial strain is also confirmed. We also characterized the magneto-transport properties of the grown CrSb thin film. Although the obtained conductivity tensors are mainly explained by a two-carrier model, not by an anomalous Hall effect, this model reveals the presence of high-mobility electron and hole carriers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08117v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/xjrx-wbv6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review Materials 9, 074410 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Seiji Aota, Masaaki Tanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BaCo$_2$(AsO$_4$)$_2$: Strong Kitaev, After All</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20859</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20859v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The inelastic neutron scattering results and their analysis unequivocally point to a dominant Kitaev interaction in the honeycomb-lattice cobaltate BaCo$_2$(AsO$_4$)$_2$. Our anisotropic-exchange model closely describes $all$ available neutron scattering data in the material's field-polarized phase. The density-matrix renormalization group results for our model are in close accord with the unusual double-zigzag magnetic order and the low in-plane saturation field of BaCo$_2$(AsO$_4$)$_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20859v5</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/k1gq-k8m7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 066703 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pavel A. Maksimov, Shengtao Jiang, L. P. Regnault, A. L. Chernyshev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single-Particle Dispersion and Density of States of the Half-Filled 2D Hubbard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02614v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Implementing an improved method for analytic continuation and working with imaginary-time correlation functions computed using quantum Monte Carlo simulations, we resolve the single-particle dispersion relation and the density of states (DOS) of the two-dimensional Hubbard model at half-filling. At intermediate interactions of $U/t = 4,6$, we find quadratic dispersion around the gap minimum at wave-vectors $\mathbf{k} = (\pm \pi/2, \pm \pi/2)$ (the $\Sigma$ points). We find saddle points at $\mathbf{k} = (\pm \pi,0),(0,\pm \pi)$ (the X points) where the dispersion is approximately quartic, leading to a sharp DOS maximum above the almost flat ledge arising from the states close to $\Sigma$. The fraction of quasiparticle states within the ledge is $n_{\rm ledge} \approx 0.15$. Upon doping away from half-filling, within the rigid-band approximation, these results support Fermi pockets around the $\Sigma$ points, with states around the X points becoming filled only at doping fractions $x \ge n_{\rm ledge}$. The high density of states away from the $\Sigma$ gap edge may be an important clue for a finite minimum doping level for superconductivity and other instabilities of doped Mott insulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02614v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/8dnp-w7c6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 085109 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Gabe Schumm, Shiwei Zhang, Anders W. Sandvik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Absence of nontrivial local conserved quantities in the Hubbard model on the two or higher dimensional hypercubic lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.20106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.20106v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: By extending the strategy developed by Shiraishi in 2019, we prove that the standard Hubbard model on the $d$-dimensional hypercubic lattice with $d\ge2$ does not admit any nontrivial local conserved quantities. The theorem strongly suggests that the model is non-integrable. To our knowledge, this is the first extension of Shiraishi's proof of the absence of conserved quantities to a fermionic model. Although our proof follows the original strategy of Shiraishi, it is essentially more subtle compared with the proof by Shiraishi and Tasaki of the corresponding theorem for $S=\tfrac12$ quantum spin systems in two or higher dimensions; our proof requires three steps, while that of Shiraishi and Tasaki requires only two steps. It is also necessary to partially determine the conserved quantities of the one-dimensional Hubbard model to accomplish our proof.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.20106v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahiro Futami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A superinductor in a deep sub-micron integrated circuit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13202v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Superinductors are circuit elements characterised by an intrinsic impedance in excess of the superconducting resistance quantum ($R_\text{Q}\approx6.45~$k$\Omega$), with applications from metrology and sensing to quantum computing. However, they are typically obtained using exotic materials with high density inductance such as Josephson junctions, superconducting nanowires or twisted two-dimensional materials. Here, we present a superinductor realised within a silicon integrated circuit (IC), exploiting the high kinetic inductance ($\sim 1$~nH/$\square$) of TiN thin films native to the manufacturing process (22-nm FDSOI). By interfacing the superinductor to a silicon quantum dot formed within the same IC, we demonstrate a radio-frequency single-electron transistor (rfSET), the most widely used sensor in semiconductor-based quantum computers. The integrated nature of the rfSET reduces its parasitics which, together with the high impedance, yields a sensitivity improvement of more than two orders of magnitude over the state-of-the-art, combined with a 10,000-fold area reduction. Beyond providing the basis for dense arrays of integrated and high-performance qubit sensors, the realization of high-kinetic-inductance superconducting devices integrated within modern silicon ICs opens many opportunities, including kinetic-inductance detector arrays for astronomy and the study of metamaterials and quantum simulators based on 1D and 2D resonator arrays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13202v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. H. Swift, F. Olivieri, G. Aizpurua-Iraola, J. Kirkman, G. M. Noah, M. de Kruijf, F. E. von Horstig, A. Gomez-Saiz, J. J. L. Morton, M. F. Gonzalez-Zalba</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
