<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 05:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Paramagnetic Phases of Strongly Correlated Ultracold Fermions Coupled to an Optical Cavity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10802</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10802v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We numerically study a gas of two-component fermions coupled to a transversely pumped optical cavity and confined to a two-dimensional static square optical lattice. In the dispersive regime, the steady state of the system is described by an extended Hubbard Hamiltonian with cavity-mediated long-range interactions. Using real-space dynamical mean-field theory (RDMFT), we investigate the formation of the (superradiant) checkerboard density-wave phase both at quarter and half filling. We focus on the paramagnetic phase assuming sufficiently high temperatures such that no magnetic long-range order develops. At quarter filling, we find a reentrant homogeneous Fermi liquid to density wave phase transition with increasing temperature, which is due to the higher entropy of the ordered phase. At half filling, in addition to the Fermi liquid to Mott insulator phase transition, marked by a vanishing quasiparticle residue at the Fermi level, we identify the transition into a density-wave phase. Due to perfect Fermi surface nesting at half filling, we find that arbitrarily small long-range interactions destabilize the system towards the density-wave phase in the absence of short-range interactions. By varying short- and long-range interactions at a fixed low temperature, we obtain the full phase diagram and identify a region of coexistence between the homogeneous Fermi liquid and Mott insulating phase with the density-wave phase. In this region, we determine the thermodynamic phase transition by comparing the energies of the different RDMFT solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10802v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Renan da Silva Souza, Youjiang Xu, Walter Hofstetter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anyonic Chern insulator in graphene induced by surface electromagnon vacuum fluctuations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10836</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10836v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Sub-wavelength cavities have emerged as a promising platform to realize strong light-matter coupling in condensed matter systems. Previous studies are limited to dielectric sub-wavelength cavities, which preserve time-reversal symmetry. Here, we lift this constraint by proposing a cavity system based on magneto-electric materials, which host surface electromagnons with non-orthogonal electric field and magnetic field components. The quantum fluctuations of the surface electromagnons drive a nearby graphene monolayer into an anyonic Chern insulator, characterized by anyonic quasi-particles and a topological gap that decays polynomially with the graphene-substrate distance. Our work opens a path to controllably break time-reversal symmetry and induce exotic quantum states through cavity vacuum fluctuations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10836v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinle Cheng, Emil Vi\~nas Bostr\"om, Frank Y. Gao, Edoardo Baldini, Dante M. Kennes, Angel Rubio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of Nitrogen Atom Clusters and Vacancy Defects on Graphene: A Molecular Dynamics Investigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10908v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Graphene's exceptional mechanical properties are crucial for its integration into advanced technological applications. However, real-world synthesis and functionalization processes introduce structural modifications that can compromise its mechanical integrity. Nitrogen doping, while beneficial for electronic property tuning, often results in atomic clustering rather than uniform distribution, while concurrent vacancy defect formation represents another common structural alteration during processing. This study systematically investigates the comparative effects of nitrogen atom clusters and equivalent sized vacancy defects on the mechanical behavior of graphene sheets through molecular dynamics simulations. The Nitrogen clustering significantly degraded mechanical performance almost similarly to random doping. In comparison, systems with equivalent-sized vacancy defects showed higher stiffness and lower ductility than those with clusters. The study revealed distinct failure mechanisms between doped and defective configurations, with nitrogen clusters showing modified crack propagation patterns while vacancies acted as pronounced stress concentrators, leading to premature failure. However, this study also showed that defect morphology critically influences mechanical properties. These findings provide important insights for optimizing graphene synthesis and processing protocols, highlighting the differential mechanical risks associated with dopant clustering versus vacancy formation. The results inform defect-tolerant design strategies for graphene-based nanoelectronics, composites, and sensors, where mechanical reliability is paramount for device performance and longevity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10908v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Indranil Rudra, Md. Moktadir Billah Tahmid, Jahid Emon, Mohammad Jane Alam Khan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ripple-assisted adsorption of noble gases on graphene at room temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10951v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Controllable gas adsorption is critical for both scientific and industrial fields, and high-capacity adsorption of gases on solid surfaces provides a significant promise due to its high-safety and low-energy consumption. However, the adsorption of nonpolar gases, particularly noble gases, poses a considerable challenge under atmospheric pressure and room temperature (RT). Here, we theoretically simulate and experimentally realize the stable adsorption of noble gases like xenon (Xe), krypton (Kr), argon (Ar), and helium (He) on highly rippled graphene at RT. The elemental characteristics of adsorbed Xe are confirmed by electron energy loss spectroscopy and X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy. The adsorbed gas atoms are crystalized with periodic arrangements. These adsorbed noble gases on graphene exhibit high stability at RT and can be completely desorbed at approximately 350 {\deg}C without damaging the intrinsic lattice of graphene. The structural and physical properties of graphene are significantly influenced by the adsorbed gas, and they fully recover after desorption. Additionally, this controllable adsorption could be generalized to other layered adsorbents such as NbSe2, MoS2 and carbon nanotubes. We anticipate that this ripple-assisted adsorption will not only re-define the theoretical framework of gas adsorption, but also accelerate advancements in gas storage and separation technologies, as well as enhance the applications in catalysis, surface modification, and other related fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10951v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weilin Liu, Xianlei Huang, Li-Guo Dou, Qianglong Fang, Ang Li, Guowen Yuan, Yongjie Xu, Zhenjia Zhou, Jun Li, Yu Jiang, Zichong Huang, Zihao Fu, Peng-Xiang Hou, Chang Liu, Jinlan Wang, Wu Zhou, Ming-Gang Ju, Shao-Chun Li, Hui-Ming Cheng, Libo Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of doping on hot-carrier thermal breakdown in perforated graphene metasurfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10960</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10960v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We examine the robustness of the S-shaped current-voltage characteristics associated with hot-carrier-induced electrical breakdown in perforated graphene metasurfaces (PGMs) as a function of doping. The perforation of the graphene layer forms interdigital arrays of graphene microribbons (GMRs) interconnected by graphene nanoribbon (GNR) bridges. These GNR constrictions act as energy barriers for electrons and holes emitted from the GMRs and govern the inter-GMR thermionic current under an applied bias voltage. The doping and the voltage bias establish distinct electron and hole populations in adjacent GMRs. Peltier heating of these carriers within the GMRs increases their effective temperatures, thereby enhancing the inter-GMR current. The resulting positive feedback between carrier heating and current amplification can trigger an electrothermal breakdown, transforming a superlinear current-voltage dependence into an S-shaped characteristic exhibiting negative differential resistance. The degree of electron-hole asymmetry significantly influences this positive feedback and strongly modifies the overall current-voltage response. These results provide a framework for optimizing PGM-based devices employing GMR/GNR architectures, including voltage-controlled fast switches, incandescent emitters, and terahertz bolometric detectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10960v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Ryzhii, V. Ryzhii, C. Tang, T. Otsuji, M. S. Shur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical conductivity of layered topological semimetal TaNiTe$_5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11105</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11105v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an infrared spectroscopy study of the layered topological semimetal TaNiTe$_5$, a material with a quasi-one-dimensional structure and strong in-plane anisotropy. Despite its structural features, infrared reflectivity and electronic transport measurements along the $a$ and $c$ crystallographic axes show metallic behavior without evidence of reduced dimensionality. Optical conductivity reveals an anisotropic but conventional metallic response with low scattering rates and a single sharp infrared-active phonon mode at $396$ cm$^{-1}$ ($49$ meV). Ab initio calculations closely match the experimental optical data and confirm a three-dimensional electronic structure. Our results demonstrate that TaNiTe$_5$ behaves as a three-dimensional anisotropic semimetal in its electronic and optical properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11105v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jakov Budi\'c, Serena Nasrallah, D. Santos-Cottin, A. Pulkkinen, J. Min\'ar, P. Sa\v{c}er, B. Gudac, V. Despoja, N. Bari\v{s}i\'c, C. C. Homes, Ana Akrap, Mario Novak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable electronic band structure in WSSe van der Waals Alloys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11146v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The electronic structure of semiconducting 2D materials such as transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) is known to be tunable by its environment, from simple external fields applied with electrical contacts up to complex van der Waals heterostructure assemblies. However, conventional alloying from reference binary TMD compounds to composition-controlled ternary alloys also offers unexplored opportunities. In this work, we use nano-angle resolved photoemission spectroscopy (nano-ARPES) and density functional theory (DFT) calculations to study the structural and electronic properties of different alloy compositions of bulk WS2(1-x)Se2x. Our results demonstrate the continuous variation of the band structure and the progressive evolution of the valence band splitting at the K points from 420 to 520 meV in bulk WS2(1-x)Se2x. We also carried out scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) measurements and DFT to understand the possible S or Se substitutions variants in WS2(1-x)Se2x alloys, with different local atomic configurations. Our work opens up perspectives for the fine control of the band dispersion in van der Waals materials and demonstrate how the band structure can be tuned in bulk TMDs. The collected information can serve as a reference for future applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11146v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PRB 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Meryem Bouaziz, Leonard Schue, Noeliarinala Felana Andriambelaza, Natalia Alyabyeva, Jean-Christophe Girard, Pavel Dudin, Fabian Cadiz, Jose Avila, Yannick Dappe, Cesar Gonzalez, Julien Chaste, Fabrice Oehler, Christine Giorgetti, Fausto Sirotti, Abdelkarim Ouerghi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic and magnetic properties of light rare-earth cubic Laves compounds derived from XMCD experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11260</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11260v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work presents electronic and magnetic properties of selected members in the cubic Laves phase series Nd1-xPrxCoNi and Ce0.25Pr0.75CoNi, together with the corresponding binary compositions (NdCo2, NdNi2, PrCo2, PrNi2, CeCo2, CeNi2), using soft x-ray absorption spectroscopy, x-ray magnetic circular dichroism (XMCD), density-functional theory, and crystal field multiplet calculations. All transition-metal moments saturate below 1 T, while the rare-earth moments do not saturate even at 5 T, consistent with van Vleck paramagnetic contributions and crystal field suppression. While the sum rules are widely used to extract element-specific magnetic moments from XMCD, we show that for 3d transition metals, their application requires accurate estimates of the number of unoccupied 3d states. We observe a finite magnetic moment on Ni, challenging the common assumption of its nonmagnetic character in Laves phases. The orbital magnetic moments were determined using the spin rules, while the spin moments were estimated from single-ion values from multiplet calculations, due to the invalidity of the spin sum rule for light rare-earth elements. The magnetic moments of Nd and Pr are found to be suppressed relative to their free-ion values, with multiplet theory indicating that this is due to crystal field effects. Our results confirm that Nd and Pr maintain localized 4f3 and 4f2 configurations, respectively, and that their element-specific magnetic moments are robust to rare-earth substitution. Ce, on the other hand, exhibits a tunable mixed-valent ground state with both magnetic 4f1 and nonmagnetic 4f0 components. The relative fraction of these states varies with the electronegativity of the surrounding 3d transition metals, revealing a pathway to tune Ce magnetism via composition. This work establishes a framework for accurately interpreting XMCD in light rare-earth-based intermetallics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11260v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vilde G. S. Lunde, Benedicte S. Ofstad, {\O}ystein S. Fjellv{\aa}g, Philippe Ohresser, Anja O. Sj{\aa}stad, Bj{\o}rn C. Hauback, Christoph Frommen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological states and flat bands in exactly solvable decorated Cayley trees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11261v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We derive the full spectrum of decorated Cayley trees that constitute tree analogs of selected two-dimensional Euclidean lattices; namely of the Lieb, the double Lieb, the kagome, and the star lattice. The common feature of these Euclidean lattices is that their nearest-neighbor models give rise to flat energy bands interpretable through compact localized states. We find that the tree analogs exhibit similar flat or nearly flat energy bands at the corresponding energies. Interestingly, such flat bands in the decorated Cayley trees acquire an interpretation that is absent in their Euclidean counterparts: as edge states localized to the inner or the outer boundary of the tree branches. In particular, we establish an exact correspondence between the Lieb-Cayley tree and an ensemble of one-dimensional Su-Schrieffer-Heeger chains, which maps topological edge states on one side of the chains to flat-band states localized in the bulk of the tree, furnishing the flat energy band with a topological stability. Similar mapping to topological edge states or to states bound to edge defects in one-dimensional chains is shown for flat-band states in all the considered tree decorations. We finally show that the persistence of exact flat bands on infinite decorated trees (i.e., Bethe lattices) arises naturally from a covering interpretation of tree graphs. Our findings reveal a rich landscape of flat-band and topological phenomena in non-Euclidean systems, where geometry alone can generate and stabilize unconventional quantum states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11261v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wanda P. Duss, Askar Iliasov, Tom\'a\v{s} Bzdu\v{s}ek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relaxation to an Ideal Chern Band through Coupling to a Markovian Bath</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11394</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11394v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a microscopic, weak-coupling mechanism by which generic Chern bands relax toward ideal bands. We consider coupling interacting electrons to a Caldeira-Leggett like Ohmic bosonic bath. Using the Born-Markov approximation, Slater determinant states of a Chern band under Hartree-Fock approximation evolve toward Slater determinant states corresponding to an ideal Chern band. We validate our proposal by performing numerical simulation of a massive Dirac model, showing that the Berry curvature and quantum metric indeed co-evolve to saturate the trace condition. Our proposal provides a concrete dissipative route to realize ideal Chern bands, a fundamental building block for the stabilization of fractional Chern insulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11394v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bruno Mera, Tomoki Ozawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ARPES signatures of trions in van der Waals materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11448v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) has recently emerged as a direct probe of excitonic correlations in two-dimensional semiconductors, resolving their dispersion and dynamics in energy-momentum space, including dark exciton states inaccessible to optical techniques. However, the ARPES fingerprint of charged excitons (trions), which plays a key role in all doped and gated 2D material systems, has remained unknown so far. We present a first theoretical analysis of trion signatures in monolayer transition-metal dichalcogenides, highlighting how the additional charge carrier modifies the spectral position and shape relative to neutral excitons in ARPES spectra. Interestingly, we further predict that mass-imbalanced trions yield a characteristic double-peak structure, clearly separated in energy and line shape from neutral excitons. The predicted temperature dependence of these features offers guidance for experimental investigations aimed at identifying trionic states, thereby establishing a framework for ARPES studies of many-body Coulomb complexes in doped two-dimensional semiconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11448v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giuseppe Meneghini, Maja L\"owe, Raul Perea-Causin, Jan Philipp Bange, Wiebke Bennecke, Marcel Reutzel, Stefan Mathias, Ermin Malic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visible and Terahertz Nonlinear Responses in the Topological Noble Metal Dichalcogenide PdTe2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11493</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11493v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nonlinear processes can offer pathways to next-generation sensors and frequency mixing devices to overcome modern imaging, detection, and communication challenges. In this article, we report on strong second and third-order nonlinear optical responses in visible and terahertz (THz) light in single crystals of the noble metal dichalcogenide PdTe2. We find that buried conduction and valence topological surface states of PdTe2 lead to resonant enhancement of optical second-harmonic generation. On the other hand, although the nonlinear responses obtained with THz excitation are not close to this resonance, they can be clearly observed in reflection geometry, even in the presence of broadband excitation, where optical filters are not necessary to observe the odd-order higher harmonic gain. By carefully considering the radiative photocurrent framework of stimulated THz emission, we are able to extract fingerprints of both second- and third-order processes in the THz regime, and show that PdTe2 is a promising material candidate for radio frequency rectification, frequency mixing, and beam focusing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11493v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>George J. de Coster, Lucas Lafeta, Stefan Heiserer, Cormac \'O Coile\'ain, Zdenek Sofer, Achim Hartschuh, Georg S. Duesberg, Paul Seifert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coherent-state path integrals in quantum thermodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11547v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In these notes, we elucidate some subtle aspects of coherent-state path integrals, focusing on their application to the equilibrium thermodynamics of quantum many-particle systems. These subtleties emerge when evaluating path integrals in the continuum, either in imaginary time or in Matsubara-frequency space. Our central message is that, when handled with due care, the path integral yields results identical to those obtained from the canonical Hamiltonian approach. We illustrate this through a pedagogical treatment of several paradigmatic systems: the bosonic and fermionic harmonic oscillators, the single-site Bose-Hubbard and Hubbard models, the weakly-interacting Bose gas with contact and finite-range interactions, and the BCS superconductor with contact and finite-range interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11547v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Salasnich, Cesare Vianello</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Human-AI collaborative autonomous synthesis with pulsed laser deposition for remote epitaxy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11558v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Autonomous laboratories typically rely on data-driven decision-making, occasionally with human-in-the-loop oversight to inject domain expertise. Fully leveraging AI agents, however, requires tightly coupled, collaborative workflows spanning hypothesis generation, experimental planning, execution, and interpretation. To address this, we develop and deploy a human-AI collaborative (HAIC) workflow that integrates large language models for hypothesis generation and analysis, with collaborative policy updates driving autonomous pulsed laser deposition (PLD) experiments for remote epitaxy of BaTiO$_3$/graphene. HAIC accelerated the hypothesis formation and experimental design and efficiently mapped the growth space to graphene-damage. In situ Raman spectroscopy reveals that chemistry drives degradation while the highest energy plume components seed defects, identifying a low-O$_2$ pressure low-temperature synthesis window that preserves graphene but is incompatible with optimal BaTiO$_3$ growth. Thus, we show a two-step Ar/O$_2$ deposition is required to exfoliate ferroelectric BaTiO$_3$ while maintaining a monolayer graphene interlayer. HAIC stages human insight with AI reasoning between autonomous batches to drive rapid scientific progress, providing an evolution to many existing human-in-the-loop autonomous workflows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11558v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Asraful Haque, Daniel T. Yimam, Jawad Chowdhury, Ralph Bulanadi, Ivan Vlassiouk, John Lasseter, Sujoy Ghosh, Christopher M. Rouleau, Kai Xiao, Yongtao Liu, Eva Zarkadoula, Rama K. Vasudevan, Sumner B. Harris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-wavelength transparent microfluidics for UV-visible spectroscopy and X-ray scattering studies of photoactive systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11441</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11441v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Microfluidic devices are increasingly used in synchrotron-based experiments to deliver and probe liquid samples, offering advantages such as minimal sample consumption and reduced radiation damage. Despite their growing use, few devices have been specifically designed for monitoring liquids under photoexcitation, a promising approach for fast structural transitions. Here, a microfluidic device that is transparent to X-rays in one direction, and simulaneously transmits UV and visible light in the perpendicular direction is presented. The device is fabricated using lamination and UV lithography on a dry-film resist, eliminating the need for cleanroom facilities and simplifying production. Its multi-wavelength transparency was validated through UV-visible spectroscopy, where photoexcitation at different wavelengths induced reversible trans-to-cis isomerization of azobenzene and fluoro-azobenzene. X-ray transparency was validated through Small Angle X-ray Scattering (SAXS) measurements on hemoglobin and CO-ligated hemoglobin sensitive to quaternary structural changes. These resusts confirm the suitability of the device for resolving protein structures and photoinduced conformational dynamics. The design further supports, as some proof of concept results show, temperature-jump and time resolved pump-probe experiments, providing a versatile platform for studying structural evolution in liquid samples using synchrotron SAXS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11441v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benedetta Marmiroli, Sumea Klokic, Barbara Sartori, Marie Reissenbuechel, Alessio Turchet, Heinz Amenitsch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrability for the spectrum of Jordanian AdS/CFT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11521</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11521v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Jordanian deformations offer rare integrable realisations of non-AdS holography, whose solvability methods differ from conventional AdS/CFT examples. Here we study the $\mathfrak{sl}(2,R)$ sector of the Jordanian deformed $AdS_5\times S^5$ string and its weak-coupling spin chain counterpart: the $\mathrm{XXX}_{-1/2}$ model with a non abelian Jordanian Drinfel'd twist. While the twist breaks the usual highest-weight structure that underlies conventional Bethe ans\"atze, we show that the complete spectrum remains solvable within the Baxter framework. We argue that the functional form of the $TQ$-relation is unchanged, yet the structure of the $Q$-functions is nontrivially modified. This allows us to obtain analytic expressions at arbitrary spin chain length $J$, which match the deformed string spectrum at the one-loop level and to subleading order in the large-$J$ expansion, despite the severely reduced symmetry. Our results provide nontrivial tests of the Jordanian AdS/CFT correspondence and lay the groundwork for implementing the Separation of Variables program in non-abelian Drinfel'd-twisted models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11521v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sibylle Driezen, Fedor Levkovich-Maslyuk, Adrien Molines</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete time crystals detected by time-translation twist</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21461</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21461v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a boundary condition twisted by time translation as a novel probe to characterize dynamical phases in periodically driven (Floquet) quantum systems. Inspired by twisted boundary conditions in equilibrium systems, this approach modifies the temporal evolution of the system upon completing a spatial loop, enabling the identification of distinct Floquet phases, including discrete time crystals (DTCs). By studying the spectral form factor (SFF) and its response to the twist, we uncover signatures of time-crystalline order, which exhibits periodic dependence on the twist parameter analogous to the Little-Parks effect in superconductors. We apply this framework to the kicked Ising model, demonstrating that our twist can distinguish time-crystalline phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21461v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/1dc6-y1x8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 165138 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ryota Nakai, Taozhi Guo, Shinsei Ryu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ten-valley excitonic complexes in charge-tunable monolayer WSe$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08923v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Excitons dominate the optical response of two-dimensional (2D) semiconductors. Strong interactions produce peculiar excitonic complexes, which provide a testing ground for exciton and quantum many-body theories. Here, we report a hitherto unobserved many-body exciton that emerges upon filling both the K and Q valleys of WSe$_2$. We optically probe the exciton landscape using charge-tunable devices with unusually thin dielectrics that facilitate doping up to several $10^{13}$ cm$^{-2}$. We observe the emergence of the thermodynamically stable complex when 10 valleys are electrostatically filled. We gain insight into its physics using magneto-optical measurements. Our results are well-described by a model where the number of distinguishable Fermi seas interacting with the photoexcited electron-hole pair defines the complex's behavior. In addition to expanding the repertoire of excitons in 2D semiconductors, this complex could probe the limit of exciton models and answer open questions about screened Coulomb interactions in 2D semiconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08923v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41467-025-65731-x</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Alain Dijkstra, Amine Ben Mhenni, Dinh Van Tuan, Elif \c{C}etiner, Muriel Schur-Wilkens, Junghwan Kim, Laurin Steiner, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Matteo Barbone, Nathan P. Wilson, Hanan Dery, Jonathan J. Finley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital-Selective Band Structure Evolution in BaFe$_{2-x}$M$_x$As$_2$ (M = Cr, Co, Cu, Ru and Mn) Probed by Polarization-Dependent ARPES</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19190v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a systematic study of the evolution of the band structure in the Fe-based superconductor family BaFe$_{2-x}$M$_x$As$_2$ (M = Cr, Co, Cu, Ru and Mn) using polarization-dependent angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES). Low-substituted samples, with comparable spin-density wave transition temperatures ($T_\text{SDW}$), were chosen to facilitate controlled comparisons. The sizes of the central hole pockets ($\alpha$, $\beta$, and $\gamma$) remain largely unchanged across different substitutions, showing no clear correlation with either $T_\text{SDW}$ or the As height relative to the Fe planes. However, subtle trends are observed: a modest increase in the size of the $\eta_\text{X}$ electron pocket correlates with the suppression of $T_\text{SDW}$. Furthermore, the contraction of the $\eta_\text{X}$ pocket appears to be linked to an increase in the As height relative to the Fe planes. Our results suggest that the suppression of $T_\text{SDW}$ is primarily driven by changes in the Fe-As bond length, with the effect being more pronounced in electronic states with planar character. These findings provide insight into the electronic structure of BaFe$_{2-x}$M$_x$As$_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19190v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. R. Pakuszewski, M. R. Cantarino, I. Romanenko, A. P. Machado, M. M. Piva, G. S. Freitas, H. B. Pizzi, F. A. Garcia, P. G. Pagliuso, C. Adriano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing interaction-driven restructuring of quantum Hall edge states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00156</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00156v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Many topological phases host gapless boundary modes that can be dramatically modified by electronic interactions. Even for the long-studied edge modes of quantum Hall phases, forming at the boundaries of two-dimensional (2D) electron systems, the nature of such interaction-induced changes has been elusive. Despite advances made using local probes, key experimental challenges persist: the lack of direct information about the internal structure of edge states on microscopic scales, and complications from edge disorder. Here, we use scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) to image pristine electrostatically defined quantum Hall edge states in graphene with high spatial resolution and demonstrate how correlations dictate the structures of edge channels on both magnetic and atomic length scales. For integer quantum Hall states in the zeroth Landau level, we show that interactions renormalize the edge velocity, dictate the spatial profile for copropagating modes, and induce unexpected edge valley polarization that differ from those of the bulk. While some of our findings can be understood by mean-field theory, others show breakdown of this picture, highlighting the roles of edge fluctuations and inter-channel couplings. We also extend our measurements to spatially resolve the edge state of fractional quantum Hall phases and detect spectroscopic signatures of interactions in this chiral Luttinger liquid. Our study establishes STM as a promising tool for exploring edge physics of the rapidly expanding 2D topological phases, including newly realized fractional Chern insulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00156v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiachen Yu, Haotan Han, Kristina G. Wolinski, Ruihua Fan, Amir S. Mohammadi, Tianle Wang, Taige Wang, Liam Cohen, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Andrea F. Young, Michael P. Zaletel, Ali Yazdani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-resolution magnetostriction measurements of the Pauli-limited superconductor Sr2RuO4</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06938</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06938v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We performed high-resolution magnetostriction measurements on the Pauli-limited superconductor Sr$_2$RuO$_4$ using high-quality single crystals. A first-order superconducting transition, accompanied by pronounced hysteresis, was observed under in-plane magnetic fields, where the relative length change of the sample, $\Delta L/L$, was on the order of $10^{-8}$. To ensure the reliability of the measurements, particular attention was paid to minimizing the influence of magnetic torque, which can significantly affect data under in-plane field configurations, via field-angle-resolved magnetostriction. Within the hysteresis regime, slightly below the Pauli-limited upper critical field, a hump-like anomaly in the magnetostriction coefficient was identified. Furthermore, a characteristic double-peak structure in the field-angle derivative of the magnetostriction provides additional support for this anomaly. Although these findings may reflect a lattice response associated with the emergence of the Fulde-Ferrell-Larkin-Ovchinnikov (FFLO) phase in Sr$_2$RuO$_4$, the possibility of a broadened first-order transition cannot be excluded. Notably, this magnetostriction anomaly qualitatively deviates from the FFLO phase boundary suggested by previous NMR measurements, highlighting the necessity for further experimental and theoretical investigations to elucidate the nature of the FFLO state in this material.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06938v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shunichiro Kittaka, Yohei Kono, Toshiro Sakakibara, Naoki Kikugawa, Shinya Uji, Dmitry A. Sokolov, Kazushige Machida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electrically-gated laser-induced spin dynamics in magneto-electric iron garnet at room temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20366</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20366v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Ultrafast pump-probe imaging reveals that the efficiency of optical excitation of coherent spins waves in epitaxial iron garnet films can be effectively controlled by an external electric field at room temperature. Although a femtosecond laser pulse alone does not excite any pronounced coherent spin oscillations, an electrical gating with the field of 0.5 MV/m dramatically changes the outcome in a laser-induced launching of spin waves. The effect, demonstrated under room-temperature conditions, is estimated to be orders of magnitude larger than in magnetic van der Waals semiconductors observed at 10 K. This electrical gating of laser-induced spin dynamics enriches opto-magnonics with a new tool and thus opens up a new avenue in fundamental and applied magnonics research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20366v3</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. T. Gareev, N. E. Khokhlov, L. K\"orber, A. P. Pyatakov, A. V. Kimel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A superinductor in a deep sub-micron integrated circuit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13202v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Superinductors are circuit elements characterised by an intrinsic impedance in excess of the superconducting resistance quantum ($R_\text{Q}\approx6.45~$k$\Omega$), with applications from metrology and sensing to quantum computing. However, they are typically obtained using exotic materials with high density inductance such as Josephson junctions, superconducting nanowires or twisted two-dimensional materials. Here, we present a superinductor realised within a silicon integrated circuit (IC), exploiting the high kinetic inductance ($\sim 1$~nH/$\square$) of TiN thin films native to the manufacturing process (22-nm FDSOI). By interfacing the superinductor to a silicon quantum dot formed within the same IC, we demonstrate a radio-frequency single-electron transistor (rfSET), the most widely used sensor in semiconductor-based quantum computers. The integrated nature of the rfSET reduces its parasitics which, together with the high impedance, yields a sensitivity improvement of more than two orders of magnitude over the state-of-the-art, combined with a 10,000-fold area reduction. Beyond providing the basis for dense arrays of integrated and high-performance qubit sensors, the realization of high-kinetic-inductance superconducting devices integrated within modern silicon ICs opens many opportunities, including kinetic-inductance detector arrays for astronomy and the study of metamaterials and quantum simulators based on 1D and 2D resonator arrays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13202v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. H. Swift, F. Olivieri, G. Aizpurua-Iraola, J. Kirkman, G. M. Noah, M. de Kruijf, F. E. von Horstig, A. Gomez-Saiz, J. J. L. Morton, M. F. Gonzalez-Zalba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
