<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 01:18:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On the magnetization of electronic ground states in frustrated superstable graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07079</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07079v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Geometric frustration lies at the heart of many unconventional quantum phases in strongly interacting electron systems. Here, we analytically determine the ground state magnetization of the half-filled Hubbard model on frustrated geometries where superstable states -- eigenstates which are robust against frustration -- are manifest. Our results apply to a broad class of lattices, including those where altermagnetic and superconducting states are known to emerge. Furthermore, they provide evidence for phase transitions involving a geometric rearrangement of magnetic correlations in the thermodynamic limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07079v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. P. M. M\'endez-C\'ordoba, J. Tindall, D. Jaksch, F. Schlawin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Altermagnetism revealed by polarized neutrons in MnF$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07087</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07087v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by possible spintronics applications in antiferromagnets, it was recently observed that symmetry admits magnets that combine attractive features of both ferromagnets and antiferromagnets. These systems, dubbed altermagnets, have been the subject of intense study with direct spectroscopic evidence, from ARPES and RIXS, techniques reported in a handful of materials in the last year. Inelastic neutron scattering (INS) is one of the most powerful direct probes of magnetism and has recently been used to witness a splitting of magnon bands in MnTe that is compatible with altermagnetism although the nature and origin of the splitting remain to be fully characterized. However, the full power of neutron scattering for such systems comes from using polarized neutrons to measure the chirality of the magnon bands. Such a measurement provides a direct characterization of altermagnetism directly from the spin wave excitations. In this article, we present results on MnF$_2$ once thought to be an archetypal antiferromagnet. We present a polarized INS data that demonstrate the material is, in fact, altermagnetic. It had long been realized that the magnon bands in this material should have a weak splitting coming from the long-range dipolar coupling. Our data is the first to visualize this splitting directly. While the dipolar splitting on its own is not altermagnetic, using a domain biased sample, the data reveals a nonzero chirality in the neutron scattering cross section that reverses sign between the two magnon modes. It is this feature that clearly demonstrates altermagnetism in MnF$_2$. This finding highlights the potential for polarized INS to characterize altermagnets not least through its exquisite sensitivity to fine-structure in the magnon spectrum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07087v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Quentin Faure, Dalila Bounoua, Victor Bal\'edent, Arsen Gukasov, V. Ovidiu Garlea, Afonso Ribeiro, Jeffrey G. Rau, Sylvain Petit, Paul McClarty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kondo echo dynamics of terahertz-pumped heavy fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07117v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We provide a theoretical framework to describe the nonequilibrium temporal dynamics of correlated electron systems for realistic system parameters and the consequent, often exponentially long time scales. It is based on an entirely integro-differential formulation of time-dependent dynamical mean-field theory, the noncrossing approximation, and the quantum representation of a driving electromagnetic field. For heavy-fermion systems, we identify two key nonequilibrium mechanisms governing their time evolution after a single-cycle terahertz excitation: transient, instantaneous shift from the Kondo toward the mixed-valence regime by an enhanced, photoassisted hybridization, and slow recovery of the heavy-fermion state due to the long Kondo coherence time. This explains recent time-resolved terahertz spectroscopy experiments microscopically and establishes the latter as a technique for direct experimental access to the Kondo coherence time and to the heavy-fermion quasiparticle weight, central for the classification of heavy-fermion quantum phase transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07117v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francisco Meirinhos, Michael Turaev, Michael Kajan, Tim Bode, Johann Kroha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scanned SQUID Microscope with High-speed Electrical Connectivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07137</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07137v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report on a scanned superconducting quantum interference device (SQUID) microscope operating in a cryogen-free cryostat, with the capability of up to forty RF connections with 20 GHz bandwidth to a device under test. The system utilizes planar gradiometric DC SQUIDs, which are fully shielded except for a pair of pickup coils with radii as small as 250 nm and have on chip field coils allowing for susceptometry. The system noise is 1.3 $\mu\Phi_{0}/\sqrt{Hz}$ at the base temperature of 3.3 K. The sample temperature is variable and both magnetometry and susceptibility measurements are simultaneously possible with the sample temperature above 40 K. Through the use of a cryogenic chip socket and silicon interposer round trip RF losses to a sample are approximately 15 dB at 20 GHz. A combination of both active and passive magnetic shielding result in a residual magnetic field less than 100 nT at the sample location.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07137v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ian W. Haygood, Bochao Xu, John Biesecker, Michael L. Schneider</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D Mapping of Defects and Moir\'e Corrugations via Electron Ptychography Atomic Coordinate Retrieval</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07140</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07140v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Defects and reconstructions in 2D moir\'e materials cause out-of-plane deformations which strongly modify their electronic properties but are difficult to experimentally access. Here, we solve the 3D atomic coordinates of twisted bilayer WSe$_2$ with picometer-scale accuracy using multislice electron ptychography (MEP) acquired from a single orientation. The resulting atomic models individually visualize each of the six atomic planes, revealing the curvature of each WSe$_2$ layer, variations in the interlayer spacing, and the 3D locations of individual vacancies -- which lie exclusively in the outer Se planes. We also observe a new, unexpected type of structural disorder consisting of mixed bending -- and breathing-type moir\'e-induced corrugations that should strongly impact the emergent electronic properties. Broadly, our methods generate 3D atom-by-atom models of a 2D heterointerface from data acquired in about 30 seconds, methods that should unlock routine access to 3D atomic information in 2D systems and catalyze design methods to control out-of-plane deformations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07140v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeffrey Huang, Yichao Zhang, Sang hyun Bae, Ballal Ahammed, Elif Ertekin, Pinshane Y. Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Theory of Exciton Magnetic Moment: Interaction and Topological Effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07284v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Combining magnetometry with optical spectroscopy has uncovered novel quantum phenomena and is emerging as a platform for quantum information science. Yet, the theory of magnetic response of excitons, correlated electron-hole pairs in semiconductors, remains incomplete due to insufficient treatment of electron-hole interaction and topological effects. In biased bilayer graphene, for instance, theoretical predictions of valley g-factor for p-excitons deviate from experiment by nearly an order of magnitude. Here, we develop a quantum theory of exciton orbital magnetic moment that reveals several conceptually new terms absent in prior theories, including an unforeseen contribution from exciton band quantum geometry. Our ab initio calculations yield results in excellent agreement with measurements, establishing the importance of a full theory including interaction and topological effects for the magnetic response of excitons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07284v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gurjyot Sethi, Jiawei Ruan, Fang Zhang, Weichen Tang, Chen Hu, Mit Naik, Steven G. Louie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Phases in Twisted Homobilayer Transition Metal Dichalcogenides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07360</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07360v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Twisted homobilayer transition metal dichalcogenides - specifically twisted bilayer MoTe$_2$ and twisted bilayer WSe$_2$ - have recently emerged as a versatile platform for strongly correlated and topological phases of matter. These two-dimensional systems host tunable flat Chern bands in which Coulomb interactions can dominate over kinetic energy, giving rise to a variety of interaction-driven phenomena. A series of groundbreaking experiments have revealed a rich landscape of quantum phases, including integer and fractional quantum anomalous Hall states, quantum spin Hall states, anomalous Hall metals, zero-field composite Fermi liquids, and unconventional superconductors, along with more conventional topologically trivial correlated states including antiferromagnets. This review surveys recent experimental discoveries and theoretical progress in understanding these phases, with a focus on the key underlying mechanisms - band topology, electron interactions, symmetry breaking, and charge fractionalization. We emphasize the unique physics of twisted TMD homobilayers in comparison to other related systems, discuss open questions, and outline promising directions for future research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07360v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bohao Li, Wen-Xuan Qiu, Fengcheng Wu, A. H. MacDonald</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alter-magnetic properties in the perovskite compounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07366</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07366v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Our high-throughput computational screening of the Materials Project database has identified 140 candidate materials exhibiting antiferromagnetic behavior in the $Pnma$ space group. Through systematic density functional theory calculations comparing various magnetic configurations, we demonstrate that 91 of these compounds preferentially stabilize in altermagnetic ground states, with 20 adopting the perovskite structure. Using NaCoF$_3$ as a prototypical example, we perform a comprehensive investigation of its electronic structure, magnetic ordering, and orbital configurations. Our analysis reveals that the magnetic Co$^{2+}$ ions occupy the 4c Wyckoff position and support three distinct antiferromagnetic (AFM) phases, among which the $G$-AFM configuration emerges as the ground state. Detailed symmetry analysis uncovers that the inter-sublattice coupling in the $G$-AFM phase is mediated by the combined time-reversal and rotation operation $\hat{T}\{R_{2x}|\frac{1}{2}\frac{1}{2}0\}$. This unique symmetry protection gives rise to several remarkable physical phenomena: (i) anisotropic optical conductivity, (ii) prominent anomalous transport effects including the anomalous Hall effect (AHE), Nernst effect (ANE), and thermal Hall effect (ATHE), and (iii) strong magneto-optical responses manifested through both Kerr and Faraday effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07366v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sining Zhang, Zhengxuan Wang, Minping Zhang, Xilin Zhang, Guangtao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magneto-optical Kerr-effect measurements under pulsed magnetic fields over 40 T using a compact sample fixture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07383</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07383v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic field is one of the most fundamental control parameters in materials science. Pulsed magnetic-field apparatus can generate high magnetic fields that are inaccessible by conventional DC-field magnets. One important issue is that measurement techniques compatible with pulsed fields are rather limited due to short pulse duration and large electromagnetic or mechanical noises originating from field pulses. Magneto-optical Kerr effect (MOKE), change in states of light polarization upon reflection from magnetic materials, has potential to become a powerful tool for investigation of magnetic properties of a wide range of materials including non-transparent materials or thin films in pulsed fields. Nevertheless, since MOKE response is typically very small, MOKE measurements under pulsed fields are quite challenging. Here, we present a new method to measure polar MOKE under high pulsed magnetic fields of 2-ms pulse width. The keys of this new technique are a ferrule-based compact sample-fiber fixture and a phase-resolved numerical lock-in analysis, combined with the high-resolution optical apparatus based on an all-fiber loop-less Sagnac interferometer. We succeeded in measuring MOKE of various ferromagnetic or ferrimagnetic samples above 40 T and down to 77 K, largely extending limits of previously reported pulse-field MOKE measurements. Our apparatus is simple enough to be compatible with larger-scale experiments in pulse-field facilities, thus becoming a new promising tool to optically investigate materials properties in pulsed fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07383v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Atsutoshi Ikeda, Sota Nakamura, Soichiro Yamane, Kosuke Noda, Akihiko Ikeda, Shingo Yonezawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic modes induced by spin and charge perturbations in Mott and Kondo insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07428v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Electronic band structures usually remain unaffected by doping via a chemical-potential shift or by increasing the temperature in conventional band insulators. In contrast, it has been shown that those of Mott and Kondo insulators can change by doping or by increasing the temperature: electronic modes are induced within the band gap, exhibiting momentum-shifted magnetic dispersion relations from the band edges. Here, by generalizing the underlying mechanism of the remarkable strong-correlation effects, this study shows that various spin and charge perturbations, including magnetization of spin-gapped Mott and Kondo insulators, can induce electronic modes. The emergent modes can change the band structure, provided that a macroscopic number of spins or charges are excited by the perturbations at a moment. The origins and dispersion relations of the emergent modes are elucidated by investigating the selection rules and using the Bethe ansatz and effective theory for weak inter-unit-cell hopping. The theoretical results are validated by numerical calculations for the one- and two-dimensional Hubbard models, periodic Anderson models, Kondo lattice models, and ladder and bilayer Hubbard models. This study significantly advances the fundamental understanding of the changes in the band structure driven by spin and charge perturbations and paves the way for band-structure engineering in strong-correlation electronics, utilizing the unconventional characteristics of strongly correlated insulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07428v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masanori Kohno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First-principles study of formic acid decomposition on single Pt atoms supported on heteroatom-doped graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07494</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07494v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Formic acid is a promising liquid hydrogen carrier, but its catalytic decomposition requires both high activity and selectivity toward dehydrogenation. Here, we investigated the catalytic activity and selectivity of formic acid decomposition on single Pt atoms supported on pristine and heteroatom-doped graphene using first-principles calculations based on the density functional theory. Reaction energy profiles reveal that single Pt atoms on P- and O-doped graphene show catalytic activity comparable to Pt(111), while all systems maintain strong dehydrogenation selectivity. These findings highlight doped graphene as a promising support for reducing precious metal usage in dehydrogenation catalysts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07494v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazuma Sato, Norihito Sakaguchi, Yuji Kunisada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin susceptibility in a pseudogap state with fluctuating spiral magnetic order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07826</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07826v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We compute the electron spin susceptibility in the pseudogap regime of the two-dimensional Hubbard model in the framework of a SU(2) gauge theory of fluctuating magnetic order. The electrons are fractionalized in fermionic chargons with a pseudospin degree of freedom and bosonic spinons. The chargons are treated in a renormalized mean-field theory and order in a N\'eel or spiral magnetic state in a broad range around half-filling below a transition temperature $T^*$. Fluctuations of the spin orientation are captured by the spinons. Their dynamics is governed by a non-linear sigma model, with spin stiffnesses computed microscopically from the pseudospin susceptibility of the chargons. The SU(2) gauge group is higgsed in the chargon sector, and the spinon fluctuations prevent breaking of the physical spin symmetry at any finite temperature. The electron spin susceptibility obtained from the gauge theory shares many features with experimental observations in the pseudogap regime of cuprate superconductors: the dynamical spin susceptibility $S(\mathbf{q},\omega)$ has a spin gap, the static uniform spin susceptibility $\kappa_s$ decreases strongly with temperature below $T^*$, and the NMR relaxation rate $T_1^{-1}$ vanishes exponentially in the low temperature limit if the ground state is quantum disordered. At low hole doping, $S(\mathbf{q},\omega)$ exhibits nematicity below a transition temperature $T_{\rm nem} &lt; T^*$, and at larger hole doping in the entire pseudogap regime below $T^*$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07826v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paulo Forni, Pietro M. Bonetti, Henrik M\"uller-Groeling, Demetrio Vilardi, Walter Metzner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hong-Ou-Mandel interferometry for fractional excitations: Unified framework and dip width scaling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07875</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07875v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Extending Hong--Ou--Mandel (HOM) interferometry to the fractional quantum Hall effect (FQHE) promises direct access to anyonic statistics, yet remains challenging: on-demand anyon injection is hindered by integer-charged minimal excitations, and recent HOM experiments in the FQHE lack a fully consistent theoretical framework. Here we provide a general theory of time-resolved HOM interferometry in quantum Hall systems. Combining the nonequilibrium bosonized edge theory (NEBET) with the unifying non-equilibrium perturbative theory (UNEPT), we derive exact and perturbative relations obeyed by the relevant cross-correlations of chiral currents valid for spatially extended tunneling operators and generic quadratic edge dynamics. Then, within the Tomonaga--Luttinger liquid (TLL) framework, we analyze the width of the HOM dip for injected pulses carrying integer and fractional charges. We show that it is governed by the width of the pulses and, for the fractional charge, by a non-trivial power-law behavior of the scaling dimension. Our results establish a robust theoretical foundation for interpreting recent experiments on anyonic statistics and electronic interferometry in the quantum Hall regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07875v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleksander Latyshev, Imen Taktak, Ipsita Mandal, Ines Safi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase engineering of 1T$'$ and 1T CrS2 and Cr2S3 by MOCVD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07899v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Layered Cr-chalcogenides compounds offer a rich range of phases with different magnetic properties some of which have been predicted only. Here we demonstrate a not yet reported crystal phase of CrS2 which is the distorted octahedral one (1T$'$) synthesized via metal-organic chemical vapour deposition (MOCVD). We achieved the tuneable synthesis of either 1T$'$ CrS2, or 1T CrS2. The phases were identified using polarized Raman spectroscopy, density functional perturbation theory (DFPT) and 4D-scanning transmission electron microscopy (STEM)-scanning electron diffraction. The phases of CrS2 were uniquely identified also in contrast with Cr2S3 which was synthesized and characterized by a Neel temperature of ~46 K. Using magneto-optic Kerr imaging, the 1T$'$ CrS2 crystals have soft ferromagnetic nature at low temperature, shedding light on the magnetic properties of this just predicated material. The 4DSTEM characterization reveals that the synthesis of the thermodynamically stable 1T$'$ phase occurs via a complex transformation process from the 1T to 1T$'$ resulting in a spatially correlated domain structure of differently oriented 1T$'$ crystals. Our MOCVD growth of complex and distorted phases of 2D CrS2 with long-range magnetic order paves the way for the scalable synthesis of 2D magnets for ultrathin magnetic memories for logic-in-memory applications and spintronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07899v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoyu Bai, Gareth R. M Tainton, Mauro Och, Max Rimmer, Indrajit Maity, Filippo Mione, Khagesh Tanwar, Rongsheng Cai, Joseph Parker, Kho Zhiquan, Ercin C Duran, Evan Tillotson, Sam Sullivan-Allsop, David Hopkinson, Siyuan Deng, Dan Bromley, Jack N. Carter-Gartside, Alex Vanstone, Sandrine Heutz, Will R. Branford, Efr\'en Navarro-Moratalla, Johannes C. Lischner, Sarah Haigh, Cecilia Mattevi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UTe$_2$: a narrow band superconductor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07915v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the nature of the 5$f$ electrons in the unconventional odd-parity superconductor UTe$_2$, focusing on the degree of covalency, localization versus itinerancy, and dominant electronic configuration. This is achieved using density functional theory (DFT) in combination with dynamical mean-field theory (DMFT) calculations. A key aspect of our approach is the material-specific tuning of the double-counting correction parameter, $\mu_{\rm dc}$, within the DFT+DMFT part. This tuning is guided by the energy dependence of photo-ionization cross-sections in valence band photoelectron spectroscopy. The reliability of the parameters is confirmed by the accurate reproduction of the angle-resolved valence-band photoemission spectra and the U 4$f$ core-level data. The DFT+DMFT model reveals that in UTe$_2$ U 5$f^n$ configurations with n=1 to 4 contribute to the ground state, with the 5$f^2$ configuration being most prevalent and an average 5$f$ shell fillings close to 2.5. The model further suggests that the 5$f$ electrons form narrow bands and that charge fluctuations due to degeneracy play a role in addition to coherent valence dynamics arising from hybridization with the conduction bath. Additionally, the significance of the U 6$d$ states in UTe$_2$ is discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07915v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Sundermann, Takaki Okauchi, Naoki Ito, Denise S. Christovam, Andrea Marino, Daiskue Takegami, Andrei Golskovskii, Priscila F. S. Rosa, Jan Kune\v{s}, Shin ichi Fujimori, Liu Hao Tjeng, Andrea Severing, Atsushi Hariki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Subbaths Cluster Dynamical Mean-Field Theory (SB-CDMFT)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07931</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07931v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cluster Dynamical Mean Field Theory (CDMFT) with an exact diagonalization (ED) impurity solver faces exponential scaling limitations from the Hilbert space dimension. We introduce subbath CDMFT (SB-CDMFT), an alternative to the conventional CDMFT-ED method in which the discrete bath is subdivided into separate subbaths, each coupled to the cluster with distinct hybridization functions. In this approach, only one subbath at a time is actively involved in ED, dramatically reducing the computational cost by replacing a single large impurity problem with multiple smaller separate ones. Our method successfully reproduces key physical properties including particle-hole symmetry and Mott physics, while allowing for an extended bath representation at a fraction of the typical computational cost.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07931v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. de Lagrave, D. S\'en\'echal, M. Charlebois</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-legged approximation for building non-empirical hybrids and analyzing correlation at finite temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07970</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07970v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Warm dense matter is a highly energetic phase characterized by strong correlations, thermal effects, and quantum effects of electrons. Thermal density functional theory is commonly used in simulations of this challenging phase, driving the development of temperature-dependent approximations to the exchange-correlation free energy. In this work, a finite-temperature extension of the two-legged adiabatic connection construction is demonstrated for the uniform electron gas and asymmetric Hubbard dimer at warm dense matter conditions. This provides the structure of a temperature- and density-dependent weighting scheme for a hybrid exchange-correlation approximation. The construction also provides evidence that nonlinear thermal effects on the balance between exchange and correlation, as well as that between kinetic, entropic, and potential components of the correlation, persist and can even be emphasized by strong electron-electron interaction. These findings point additionally to a complicated interplay between temperature, density, and interaction strength in the strong correlation character of these model systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07970v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brittany P. Harding, Francisca Sagredo, Vincent Martinetto, Aurora Pribram-Jones</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linking thermodynamic correlation signatures and superconductivity in twisted trilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07977</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07977v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Twisted graphene multilayers exhibit strong electronic correlations, which manifest in a range of experimental signatures. Yet how these signatures relate to each other and the microscopic ground states-and how twist angle and band structure reshape them-remains poorly understood. Here we study this interplay by correlating local thermodynamic and transport measurements in a twisted trilayer graphene (TTG) sample with unequal angles and flat electronic bands. We use a scanning single-electron transistor to map the impact of electron-electron interactions in a region of the sample where the local twist angle evolves smoothly. We observe gapped correlated insulators and a sawtooth in electronic compressibility, both exhibiting pronounced electron-hole (e-h) asymmetry with distinct magic angles for conduction and valence bands. Subsequent transport measurements in the same region reveal robust superconductivity with a similar e-h asymmetry. Our measurements indicate that superconductivity is not directly tied to the correlated insulators. Instead, its critical temperature correlates closely with the strength of the sawtooth in compressibility, suggesting a common origin or link between the two. By combining a local probe with transport measurements, we uncover connections between superconductivity and thermodynamic correlation signatures that are not apparent from either technique in isolation, highlighting the power of our dual approach and establishing their dependence on interlayer twist angles in TTG.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07977v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jesse C. Hoke, Yifan Li, Yuwen Hu, Julian May-Mann, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Trithep Devakul, Aaron Sharpe, Benjamin E. Feldman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Tensor Network Framework for Lindbladian Spectra and Steady States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07709</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07709v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum systems coupled to (non-)Markovian environments attract increasing attention due to their peculiar physical properties. Exciting prospects such as unconventional non-equilibrium phases beyond the Mermin-Wagner limit, or the environment-assisted, robust preparation of highly entangled states, demand a systematic analysis of quantum many-body phases out of equilibrium. Akin to the equilibrium case, this requires the computation of the low-lying eigenstates of Lindbladians, a problem challenging conventional approaches for simulating quantum many-body systems. Here, we undertake a first step to overcome this limitation and introduce a tensor-network-based framework to compute systematically not only steady states, but also low-lying excited states with unprecedented precision for large, driven quantum many-body systems. Our framework is based on recent advances utilizing complex-time Krylov spaces, and we leverage these ideas to create a toolbox tailored to solve the challenging non-Hermitian eigenvalue problem ubiquitous in open quantum systems. At the example of the interacting Bose-Hubbard model driven by dissipation-assisted hopping, we demonstrate the high efficiency and accuracy, enabling us to perform a reliable finite-size scaling analysis of the spectral gap and demonstrating the existence of anomalous relaxation. This method unlocks the capability of spectral analysis of generic open quantum many-body systems, suitable also for non-Markovian environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07709v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philipp Westhoff, Mattia Moroder, Ulrich Schollw\"ock, Sebastian Paeckel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuous cloud position spectroscopy using a magneto-optical trap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07736v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate a continuous spectroscopy technique with frequency sensitivity well below the natural transition linewidth, while maintaining a locking range hundreds of times larger. The method exploits the position dependence of a continuous, broadband magneto-optical trap operating on the 7.5 kHz-wide intercombination line of strontium. We show that the frequency sensitivity is fundamentally insensitive to the effective MOT laser linewidth. By applying active feedback on the MOT position to a dispersion-optimized frequency comb, which serves as the reference for stabilizing the MOT laser, we achieve a frequency instability below $4.4\times10^{-13}$ after 400 s of averaging in both the optical and radio-frequency domains, surpassing the performance of conventional hot-vapor modulation transfer spectroscopy. Our method is a broadly applicable alternative route to long-term frequency references in the high $10^{-14}$ range around 100 s.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07736v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benedikt Heizenreder, Ananya Sitaram, Sana Boughdachi, Andrew von H\"orsten, Yan Xie, Andreas Brodschelm, Florian Schreck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grain boundary-limited thermal transport in suspended thin graphite across an unexplored thickness regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.10704</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.10704v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present systematic thermal conductivity measurements of suspended thin graphite ribbons, 234-527 nm thick, using a four-probe 3-omega method. Unlike recent reports of phonon hydrodynamics and exceptionally high thermal conductivity in micrometer-thick graphite (Science, 2020),we observe significantly lower thermal conductivity and no signatures of collective phonon flow in this intermediate thickness regime. Instead, our measured thermal conductivity lies between few-layer graphene and bulk graphite.These results agree with a first-principles-informed Peierls-Boltzmann transport model with spatially resolved Monte Carlo sampling. Additionally, the temperature for the peak thermal conductivity shifts lower with increasing thickness, due to the interplay of phonon-boundary and phonon-isotope scattering. Incorporating grain boundary scattering into simulations is necessary to replicate the experimental trends. These findings delineate the boundary between ballistic, hydrodynamic, and diffusive transport regimes in graphite, and underscore the dominant role of disorder and geometry in phonon transport in quasi-two-dimensional materials, offering insights for nanoscale thermal management.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.10704v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wonjae Jeon, Yu Pei, Xun Li, Lucas Lindsay, Sangyeop Lee, Renkun Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magneto-optical transport in tilted type-I multi-Weyl semimetals in the presence of orbital magnetic moment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09888v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The magneto-optical transport of gapless type-I tilted single Weyl semimetals exhibits suppression of total magnetoconductivities in the presence of orbital magnetic moment(OMM) in linear and nonlinear responses (Yang Gao et al., Phys. Rev. B {\bf 105}, 165307 (2022)). In this work, we extend our study to investigate magnetoconductivities in gapless type-I tilted multi-Weyl semimetals(mWSMs) within the semiclassical Boltzmann approach and show the differences that arise compared to single-Weyl semimetals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09888v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amit Gupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deconfined quantum critical points in fermionic systems with spin-charge separation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04073</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04073v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Deconfined quantum critical points are intriguing transition points not predicted by the Landau-Ginzburg-Wilson symmetry-breaking paradigm which are usually identified by the appearance of a continuous phase transition between locally ordered phases. Here, we reveal the presence of deconfined quantum critical points with unexplored properties. Contrary to previously known examples, we show that the phenomenon of spin-charge separation peculiar to interacting low dimensional fermions can allow for the appearance of partially gapped deconfined quantum critical points. We first infer this point by performing a field theory analysis of generic one-dimensional fermionic systems in the low energy limit. Subsequently, we derive a microscopic model where phase transitions between different locally ordered phases can take place. Here, by performing a numerical analysis we explicitly derive, among others, the gaps, local order parameters and correlation functions behavior, supporting the presence of partially gapped deconfined quantum critical points. Our results thus provide new interesting insights on the widely investigated topic of quantum phase transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04073v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niccol\`o Baldelli, Arianna Montorsi, Sergi Juli\`a-Farr\'e, Maciej Lewenstein, Matteo Rizzi, Luca Barbiero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulating the two-dimensional $t-J$ model at finite doping with neural quantum states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.10430</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.10430v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Simulating large, strongly interacting fermionic systems remains a major challenge for existing numerical methods. In this work, we introduce Gutzwiller projected hidden fermion determinant states (G-HFDS) to simulate the strongly interacting limit of the Fermi-Hubbard model, namely the $t$-$J$ model, across the entire doping regime. We demonstrate that the G-HFDS achieve energies competitive with matrix product states (MPS) on lattices as large as $10 \times 10$ sites while using several orders of magnitude fewer parameters, suggesting the potential for efficient application to even larger system sizes. This remarkable efficiency enables us to probe low-energy physics across the full doping range, providing new insights into the competition between kinetic and magnetic interactions and the nature of emergent quasiparticles. Starting from the low-doping regime, where magnetic polarons dominate the low energy physics, we track their evolution with increasing doping and different next-nearest neighbor hopping amplitudes through analyses of spin and polaron correlation functions as well as the Fermi surface. Our findings demonstrate the potential of determinant-based neural quantum states with inherent fermionic sign structure, opening the way for simulating large-scale fermionic systems at any particle filling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.10430v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hannah Lange, Annika B\"ohler, Christopher Roth, Annabelle Bohrdt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-dimensional moir\'{e} phonon polaritons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00313v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Phonon polaritons (PhPs) are hybrid light-matter modes. We investigate them in two-dimensional (2D) materials with twisted moir\'{e} structures, revealing that the moir\'{e} potential creates a new class of `moir\'{e} PhPs'. These exhibit a fundamental spectral reconstruction into multiple branches and, crucially, electromagnetic wavefunctions that are nano-patterned by the superlattice. Through numerical simulations based on realistic lattice models, we confirm the existence of these intriguing modes. The inherent nanoscale structuring produces a robust, spatially varying near-field response, establishing moir\'{e} superlattices as a platform for engineering light-matter interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00313v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Shi, Chu Li, Ding Pan, Xi Dai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlated helimagnetic configuration in a nonsymmorphic magnetic nodal semimetal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03832</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.03832v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Nonsymmorphic magnetic Weyl semimetal materials such as ReAlX (Re=rare earth, X=Si/Ge) provide a unique opportunity to explore the correlated phenomena between Weyl fermions and nontrivial magnetic configurations. To be specific, we study a lattice model in which the magnetic configuration is determined by the competition among ferromagnetic (FM) interaction, the Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction, and the Kondo coupling $K_0$ to the Weyl fermion. Both quantum and finite-temperature phase transitions between FM and correlated nesting helical configurations are found. Different from the uncorrelated helimagnet that decouples from the Weyl fermions, this correlated helimagnet induces a magnetic Brillouin zone with a $K_0$-dependent nesting in the band structure of the conduction electrons instead of the monopole-like Weyl cone. By measuring the current induced by the chiral magnetic effect on the conduction electron with nesting Weyl nodes, one can distinguish the correlated nesting helical order from the ferromagnetism because the chiral magnetic effect is considerably suppressed in the former case. These properties we find here may explain the experimental observations in ReAlX.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.03832v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/89jl-7bj3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 115116 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xi Luo, Yu-Ge Chen, Ye-Min Zhan, Yue Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Systematic Mapping of Altermagnetic Magnons by Resonant Inelastic X-Ray Circular Dichroism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02533</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02533v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Altermagnets, a unique class of magnetic materials that combines features of both ferromagnets and antiferromagnets, have garnered attention for their potential in spintronics and magnonics. While the electronic properties of altermagnets have been well studied, characterizing their magnon excitations is essential for fully understanding their behavior and enabling practical device applications. In this work, we introduce a measurement protocol combining resonant inelastic X-ray scattering with circular polarization and azimuthal scanning to probe the chiral nature of the altermagnetic split magnon modes in CrSb. This approach circumvents the challenges posed by domain averaging in macroscopic samples, allowing for precise measurements of the polarization and energy of the magnons in individual antiferromagnetic domains. Our findings demonstrate a pronounced circular dichroism in the magnon peaks, with an azimuthal dependence that is consistent with the theoretical predictions and the $g$-wave symmetry. By establishing a reliable and accessible method for probing altermagnetic magnons, this work opens new avenues for fundamental studies of these collective excitations and for developing next-generation magnonic device applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02533v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikolaos Biniskos, Manuel dos Santos Dias, Stefano Agrestini, David Svit\'ak, Ke-Jin Zhou, Ji\v{r}\'i Posp\'i\v{s}il, Petr \v{C}erm\'ak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dead, Slow and Overworked Graphite: Operando X-ray Microdiffraction Mapping of Aged Electrodes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.06113</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.06113v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Aging limits lithium-ion battery lifetime and must be understood to improve durability and performance, requiring a detailed understanding of how aging alters the availability of cyclable lithium and the integrity of active particles. In this work, (de)lithiation mechanisms are examined and spatially-resolved at the microscale in aged graphite electrodes dismounted from a large format graphite/LiFePO4-Li(NiCoAl)O2 cell at 70% remaining capacity. A multi-technique workflow is employed, combining electrochemical methods with post-mortem structural and morphological analyses, and introducing synchrotron microX-ray 2D diffraction imaging as a technique to probe aged graphite, applied at C-rates from C/5 to C. In-plane and through-plane heterogeneities in graphite dynamics are evidenced, showing the presence of inactive regions localized in two dimensions. In these areas, particles are either disconnected (irreversibly lost) or kinetically limited (reactivated at a slow C-rate), with dead or slow particles exhibiting a wide range of compositions, from x = 0 to x = 1 in LixC6. These inactivated graphite particles are found to be heterogeneously distributed throughout the depth of the aged negative electrode. In particular, the most inactivated region localizes at the negative electrode-separator interface, correlating to overworking graphite near the separator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.06113v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/aenm.202502032</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Adv. Energy Mater. 2025, e02032</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Gozde Oney (Univ. Grenoble, Alpes, CEA, CNRS, Grenoble INP, IRIG, SyMMES, F-38000 Grenoble), Federico Monaco (Univ. Grenoble, Alpes, CEA, CNRS, Grenoble INP, IRIG, SyMMES, F-38000 Grenoble), Saptarshee Mitra (Univ. Grenoble, Alpes, CEA, CNRS, Grenoble INP, IRIG, SyMMES, F-38000 Grenoble), Asma Medjahed (European Synchrotron Radiation Facility, F-38043 Grenoble Cedex, France), Manfred Burghammer (European Synchrotron Radiation Facility, F-38043 Grenoble Cedex, France), Dmitry Karpov (European Synchrotron Radiation Facility, F-38043 Grenoble Cedex, France, Univ. Grenoble Alpes, CEA, IRIG, MEM, 38000 Grenoble, France), Marta Mirolo (European Synchrotron Radiation Facility, F-38043 Grenoble Cedex, France), Jakub Drnec (European Synchrotron Radiation Facility, F-38043 Grenoble Cedex, France), Isabelle C. Jolivet (TotalEnergies OneTech, CSTJF, avenue Larribau, 64018 Pau Cedex, France), Quentin Arnoux (TotalEnergies OneTech, Centre de recherche de Solaize, 69360 Solaize, France), Samuel Tardif (Univ. Grenoble Alpes, CEA, IRIG, MEM, 38000 Grenoble, France), Quentin Jacquet (Univ. Grenoble, Alpes, CEA, CNRS, Grenoble INP, IRIG, SyMMES, F-38000 Grenoble), Sandrine Lyonnard (Univ. Grenoble, Alpes, CEA, CNRS, Grenoble INP, IRIG, SyMMES, F-38000 Grenoble)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin and Charge Transport Mediated by Fractionalized Excitations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13590</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13590v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study charge and spin transport in systems composed of itinerant electrons and localized magnetic moments of a Kitaev quantum spin liquid (QSL) phase. For example, $\alpha-{\rm RuCl}_3$ either intrinsically doped or in proximity to graphene. Our analysis reveals distinct temperature-dependent transport behaviors due to the QSL gap and the Majorana excitation spectrum, which are greatly enhanced when the velocities of itinerant-electrons and QSL excitations become comparable. These transport characteristics could potentially be employed to reveal the fractionalized excitations of the spin liquid.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13590v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexey Ermakov, Alessandro Principi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-energy structure and topology of the two-band Hubbard-Kanamori model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.01269v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the Mott transition in a two-band Hubbard-Kanamori model using Dynamical Mean-Field Theory (DMFT) with the Density Matrix Renormalization Group (DMRG) and the Numerical Renormalization Group (NRG) as impurity solvers. Our study focuses on the case where the intraorbital and interorbital Coulomb interactions are equal (U = U2) and the Hund's coupling is absent (J = 0). Spectral analysis confirms the absence of an orbital-selective Mott transition (OSMT), even in systems with significantly different bandwidths (t1 and t2 for the wide and narrow bands, respectively), indicating a simultaneous Mott transition in both bands. Notably, the NRG results reveal the emergence of a pseudo-gap-like feature and a central peak in the narrow band, whose characteristics depend on the hopping parameter t2. These spectral features may serve as precursors to OSMT in more realistic systems with finite Hund's coupling (J &gt; 0). Furthermore, in the Mott insulating phase, the self-energies of both bands diverge, suggesting that the Mott transition represents a topological phase transition. Our results highlight the crucial role of accurate impurity solvers in capturing the density of states and detailed spectral structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.01269v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nayara G. Gusm\~ao, Germ\'an Blesio, Armando Aligia, Walber H. Brito, Maria C. O. Aguiar, Karen Hallberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic Energy Scales of Cr$X_3$ ($X$ = Cl, Br, and I) using High-resolution X-ray Scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.04053</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.04053v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Chromium tri-halides Cr$X_3$ ($X$ = Cl, Br, and I) have recently become a focal point of research due to their intriguing low-temperature,layer-dependent magnetism that can be manipulated by an electric field. This makes them essential candidates for spintronics applications. These magnetic orders are often related to the electronic structure parameters, such as spin-orbit coupling (SOC), Hund's coupling ($J_H$), $p-d$ covalency, and inter-orbital Coulomb interactions. Accurately determining such parameters is paramount for understanding Cr$X_3$ physics. We have used ultra high-resolution resonant inelastic x-ray scattering (RIXS) spectroscopy to study Cr$X_3$ across phase transition temperatures. Ligand field multiplet calculations were used to determine the electronic structure parameters by incorporating the crystal field interactions in a distorted octahedral with $C_3$ symmetry. These methods provide the most detailed description of Cr$X_3$ magneto-optical and electronic energetic (terms) to date. For the first time, the crystal field distortion parameters $D\sigma$ and $D\tau$ were calculated, and the energies of $d$ orbitals have been reported. Our RIXS spectroscopic measurements reveal a clear energy separation between spin-allowed quartet states and spin-forbidden doublet states in Cr$X_3$. The role of SOC in Cr $2p$ orbitals for the spin-flip excitations has been demonstrated. The determined 10$Dq$ values are in good agreement with the spectrochemical series, and Racah B follows the Nephelauxetic effect. Such precise measurements offer insights into the energy design of spintronic devices that utilize quantum state tuning within 2D magnetic materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.04053v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chamini Pathiraja, Jayajeewana N. Ranhili, Deniz Wong, Christian Schulz, Yi-De Chuang, Yu-Cheng Shao, Di-Jing Huang, Hsiao-Yu Huang, Amol Singh, Byron Freelon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable spin-orbit splitting in bilayer graphene/WSe$_2$ quantum devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.05864v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Bilayer graphene (BLG)-based quantum devices represent a promising platform for emerging technologies, such as quantum computing and spintronics. However, their intrinsically weak spin-orbit coupling (SOC) complicates spin and valley manipulation. Integrating BLG with transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) enhances the SOC via proximity effects. While this enhancement has been demonstrated in 2D-layered structures, 1D and 0D nanostructures in BLG/TMD remain unrealized, with open questions regarding SOC strength and tunability. Here, we investigate quantum point contacts and quantum dots in two BLG/WSe$_2$ heterostructures with different stacking orders. Across multiple devices, we reproducibly demonstrate spin-orbit splitting up to 1.5 meV - more than 1 order of magnitude higher than in pristine BLG. Furthermore, we show that the induced SOC can be tuned in situ from its maximum value to near-complete suppression via the perpendicular electric field. This enhancement and in situ tunability establish the SOC as a control mechanism for dynamic spin and valley manipulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.05864v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.nanolett.5c02309</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nano Lett. 2025, 25, 12480-12486</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jonas D. Gerber, Efe Ersoy, Michele Masseroni, Markus Niese, Michael Laumer, Artem O. Denisov, Hadrien Duprez, Wei Wister Huang, Christoph Adam, Lara Ostertag, Chuyao Tong, Takashi Taniguchi, Kenji Watanabe, Vladimir I. Fal'ko, Thomas Ihn, Klaus Ensslin, Angelika Knothe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultraviolet/infrared mixing-driven suppression of Kondo screening in the antiferromagnetic quantum critical metal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01561</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01561v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study a magnetic impurity immersed in the two-dimensional antiferromagnetic quantum critical metal (AFQCM), using the field-theoretic functional renormalization group. Critical spin fluctuations represented by a bosonic field compete with itinerant electrons to couple with the impurity through the spin-spin interaction. At long distances, the antiferromagnetic electron-impurity (Kondo) coupling dominates over the boson-impurity coupling. However, the Kondo screening is weakened by the boson with an increasing severity as the hot spots connected by the magnetic ordering wave-vector are better nested. For $v_{0,i} \ll 1$, where $v_{0,i}$ is the bare nesting angle at the hot spots, the temperature $T_K^{\mathrm{AFQCM}}$ below which Kondo coupling becomes $O(1)$ is suppressed as $\frac{\log \Lambda/T_K^{\mathrm{AFQCM}}}{\log \Lambda/T_K^{\mathrm{FL}}} \sim \frac{g_{f,i}}{v_{0,i} \log 1/v_{0,i} }$, where $T_K^{\mathrm{FL}}$ is the Kondo temperature of the Fermi liquid with the same electronic density of states, and $g_{f,i}$ is the boson-impurity coupling defined at UV cutoff energy $\Lambda$. The remarkable efficiency of the single collective field in hampering the screening of the impurity spin by the Fermi surface originates from a ultraviolet/infrared (UV/IR) mixing: bosons with momenta up to a UV cutoff actively suppress Kondo screening at low energies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01561v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francisco Borges, Peter Lunts, Sung-Sik Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signatures of the Fermi surface reconstruction of a doped Mott insulator in a slab geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04155</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04155v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate a hole-doped Mott insulator in a slab geometry using the dynamical cluster approximation. We show that the enhancement of the correlation strength at the surface results in the remarkable evolution of the layer-projected Fermi surface, which exhibits hole-like pockets in the superficial layers, but gradually evolves into a single electron-like surface in the innermost layers. We further analyze the behavior of the Friedel oscillations induced by the surface and identify distinct signatures of the Fermi surface reconstruction as function of hole-doping. In addition, we introduce a computationally tractable quantity that diagnoses the same Fermi surface variation by the concurrent breakdown of Luttinger's theorem. Both the latter quantity and the Friedel oscillations serve as reliable indicators of the change in Fermi surface topology, without the need for any periodization in momentum space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04155v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gregorio Staffieri, Michele Fabrizio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computation and Sensitivity Analysis of the Deformation-Gradient Tensor Reconstruction in Dark-Field X-ray Microscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17929v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Spatially resolved strain measurements are crucial to understanding the properties of engineering materials. Although strain measurements utilizing techniques such as transmission electron microscopy and electron backscatter diffraction offer high spatial resolution, they are limited to surface or thin samples. X-ray diffraction methods, including Bragg Coherent Diffraction Imaging and X-ray topography, enable strain measurements deep inside bulk materials but face challenges in simultaneously achieving both high spatial resolution and large field-of-view. Dark-field X-ray Microscopy (DFXM) offers a promising solution with its ability to image bulk crystals at the nanoscale while offering a field-of-view approaching a few hundred $\mu$m. However, an inverse modeling framework to explicitly relate the angular shifts in DFXM to the strain and lattice rotation tensors is lacking. In this paper, we develop such an inverse modeling formalism. Using the oblique diffraction geometry, enabling access to noncoplanar symmetry-equivalent reflections, we demonstrate that the reconstruction of the full deformation gradient tensor ($\mathbf{F^{(g)}}$) is possible. We also develop the computational framework to both forward calculate the anticipated angular shifts and reconstruct the average $\mathbf{F^{(g)}}$ for an individual pixel from DFXM experiments. Finally, utilizing the established formalism and computational framework, we present methods for sensitivity analysis to relate individual components of the rotation or strain tensor to specific angles of DFXM. The developed sensitivity analysis also enables explicit computation of the errors associated with the reconstruction of each component. The formalism, the computational framework, and the sensitivity analysis established in this paper should assist both the interpretation of past DFXM experiments and the design of future DFXM experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17929v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brinthan Kanesalingam, Darshan Chalise, Carsten Detlefs, Leora Dresselhaus-Marais</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Edge modes of topological Mott insulators and deconfined quantum critical points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04455</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.04455v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Topology and anomalies lead to edge modes that can interact with critical bulk fluctuations. To study this setup, pertaining to boundary criticality, we consider a model exhibiting a deconfined quantum critical point (DQCP) between a dynamically generated quantum spin Hall state (i.e.a topological Mott insulator) and an s-wave superconductor. For the topological Mott insulator, the bulk Goldstone modes are shown to be irrelevant at the helical Luttinger liquid fixed points. The deconfined quantum critical point is an instance of an emergent anomaly, and we observe a sharp localized edge state at this point. The sharpness of the edge mode is consistent with an ordinary phase in which electronic edge modes decouple from critical edge bosonic fluctuations. At the DQCP, the scaling dimension of the edge electron shows a jump, a feature argued to be a signature of the emergent anomaly. Our results are based on large-scale auxiliary-field quantum Monte Carlo simulations.We also carry out calculations for the Kane-Mele-Hubbard model to confirm spectral features of the ordinary and extraordinary-log phases in the vicinity of the bulk critical point.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.04455v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuhai Liu, Toshihiro Sato, Disha Hou, Zhenjiu Wang, Wenan Guo, Fakher F. Assaad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elastic Metastability: Thermally Activated Snap-through Transitions in Nanostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14658</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14658v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The morphological snap-through transition of a bistable elastic structure typically requires external loading, unless it is miniaturized to the nanoscale, where thermal fluctuations play a significant role. We propose that metastability can emerge in microscopic elastic systems when coupled to a thermal environment, giving rise to thermally activated transitions between metastable configurations. Using atomistic simulations combined with rare event methods, we demonstrate that snap-through events can occur as well-defined thermally activated transitions in a geometrically constrained graphene nanoribbon. Well-tempered metadynamics is employed to determine the transition energetics and pathways. Notably, the temperature dependence of the transition rate constant is accurately described by generalized transition state theory in terms of the Landau free energy. This study introduces a theoretical framework for understanding elastic metastability, extends reaction rate theory to nanomechanical systems, and suggests strategies for designing temperature-responsive nanodevices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14658v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Renjie Zhao, Yiquan Zhang, Chenglin Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissipative Quantum Chaos unveiled by Stochastic Quantum Trajectories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.15479</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.15479v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We define quantum chaos and integrability in open quantum many-body systems as a dynamical property of single stochastic realizations, referred to as quantum trajectories. This definition relies on the predictions of random matrix theory applied to the subset of the Liouvillian spectrum involved in each quantum trajectory. Our approach, which we name spectral statistics of quantum trajectories (SSQT), enables a natural distinction between transient and steady-state quantum chaos as general phenomena in open setups. We test the generality and reliability of the SSQT criterion on several dissipative systems, further showing that an open system with a chaotic structure can evolve towards either a chaotic or integrable steady state. We apply our theoretical framework to two driven-dissipative bosonic systems. First, we study the driven-dissipative Bose-Hubbard model, an example of quantum simulator, clarifying the interplay of integrability, transient, and steady-state chaos across its phase diagram. Our analysis shows the existence of an emergent dissipative quantum chaotic phase, whereas the classical and semi-classical limits display integrable behavior. In this regime, chaos arises from the quantum and classical fluctuations associated with the dissipation mechanisms. Second, we investigate dissipative quantum chaos in the dispersive readout of a transmon qubit: a measurement technique ubiquitous in superconducting-based quantum hardware. Through the SSQT, we distinguish regimes where the performance of the measurement instrument can be connected to the integrable or chaotic nature of the underlying driven-dissipative bosonic system. Our work offers a general understanding of the integrable and chaotic dynamics of open quantum systems and paves the way for the investigation of dissipative quantum chaos and its consequences on state-of-the-art noisy intermediate-scale quantum devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.15479v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.7.013276</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 7, 013276 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Filippo Ferrari, Luca Gravina, Debbie Eeltink, Pasquale Scarlino, Vincenzo Savona, Fabrizio Minganti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
