<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 04:00:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Order Without Band Topology in Moir\'e Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15027v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The discovery of zero-field fractional Chern insulators (FCIs) in moir\'e materials has attracted intense interest in the interplay between topology and correlations. Here, we demonstrate that fractionalized topological order can emerge under realistic conditions even within a topologically trivial moir\'e band. By projecting long-range Coulomb interactions into a trivial band of twisted multilayer graphene, we identify a set of incompressible FCI ground states exhibiting fractional quantized Hall conductance. Their Laughlin-like behavior is further confirmed through the particle-cut entanglement spectrum. We trace the origin of this phase to the strongly inhomogeneous distribution of quantum geometry within the moir\'e Brillouin zone, which reshapes interaction effects independently of the band topology. Extending this heuristic quantum geometric mechanism, we demonstrate that similarly unexpected Laughlin-like FCIs can also be stabilized in higher-Chern-number moir\'e bands under experimentally accessible conditions. Our results establish realistic scenarios under which many-body topological order can emerge independently of single-particle band topology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15027v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hui Liu, Raul Perea-Causin, Zhao Liu, Emil J. Bergholtz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconductivity suppression and bilayer decoupling in Pr substituted YBa$_2$Cu$_3$O$_{7-\delta}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15078v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The mechanism behind superconductivity suppression induced by Pr substitutions in YBa$_2$Cu$_3$O$_{7-\delta}$ (YBCO) has been a mystery since its discovery: in spite of being isovalent to Y$^{3+}$ with a small magnetic moment, it is the only rare-earth element that has a dramatic impact on YBCO's superconducting properties. Using angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) and DFT+$U$ calculations, we uncover how Pr substitution modifies the low-energy electronic structure of YBCO. Contrary to the prevailing Fehrenbacher-Rice (FR) and Liechtenstein-Mazin (LM) models, the low energy electronic structure contains no signature of any $f$-electron hybridization or new states. Yet, strong electron doping is observed primarily on the antibonding Fermi surface. Meanwhile, we reveal major electronic structure modifications to Cu-derived states with increasing Pr substitution: a pronounced CuO$_2$ bilayer decoupling and an enhanced CuO chain hopping, implying indirect electron-release pathways beyond simple 4$f$ state ionization. Our results challenge the long-standing FR/LM mechanism and establish Pr substituted YBCO as a potential platform for exploring correlation-driven phenomena in coupled 1D-2D systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15078v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinming Yang, Zheting Jin, Siqi Wang, Camilla Moir, Mingyu Xu, Brandon Gunn, Xian Du, Zhibo Kang, Keke Feng, Makoto Hashimoto, Donghui Lu, Jessica McChesney, Shize Yang, Wei-Wei Xie, Alex Frano, M. Brian Maple, Sohrab Ismail-Beigi, Yu He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Orbital-Selective Flat Bands in Transition-Metal Oxychlorides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15080</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15080v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Flat electronic bands, which amplify electron correlations by quenching kinetic energy, provide an ideal foundation for exotic quantum phases. However, prevailing strategies -- including geometrically frustrated lattices, moire superlattices and heavy-fermion physics -- suffer from inherent trade-offs among robustness, tunability and orbital selectivity, limiting their broad applicability. Here, we unveil an intrinsic orbital-selective flat-band mechanism in the van der Waals materials NbOCl2 and TaOCl2, directly observed by angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) and understood through density functional theory (DFT) and Wannier analysis. Crucially, we experimentally demonstrate that this momentum-independent flat band exhibits remarkable robustness, surviving from the bulk crystal down to the few-layer limit at room temperature. Our theoretical analysis traces its origin to the hybridization between Nb-dz2 orbital chains and the Lieb-like dx2-y2 sublattice, which is further reinforced by Peierls dimerization. Our findings not only establish transition-metal oxychlorides as a robust and tunable platform for flat-band-driven correlated phases under ambient conditions, but also uncover a new orbital-selective design principle for realizing flat bands in quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15080v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiangyu Luo, Ludovica Zullo, Sahaj Patel, Dongjin Oh, Qian Song, Asish K. Kundu, Anil Rajapitamahuni, Elio Vescovo, Natalia Olszowska, Rafal Kurleto, Dawid Wutke, Giorgio Sangiovanni, Riccardo Comin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advancing AI-Driven Analysis in X-ray Absorption Spectroscopy: Spectral Domain Mapping and Universal Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15167</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15167v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In recent years, rapid progress has been made in developing artificial intelligence (AI) and machine learning (ML) methods for x-ray absorption spectroscopy (XAS) analysis. Compared to traditional XAS analysis methods, AI/ML approaches offer dramatic improvements in efficiency and help eliminate human bias. To advance this field, we advocate an AI-driven XAS analysis pipeline that features several inter-connected key building blocks: benchmarks, workflows, databases, and AI/ML models. Specifically, we present two case studies for XAS ML. In the first study, we demonstrate the importance of reconciling the discrepancies between simulation and experiment using spectral domain mapping (SDM). Our ML model, which is trained solely on simulated spectra, predicts an incorrect oxidation state trend for Ti atoms in a combinatorial zinc titanate film. After transforming the experimental spectra into a simulation-like representation using SDM, the same model successfully recovers the correct oxidation state trend. In the second study, we explore the development of universal XAS ML models that are trained on the entire periodic table, which enables them to leverage common trends across elements. Looking ahead, we envision that an AI-driven pipeline can unlock the potential of real-time XAS analysis to accelerate scientific discovery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15167v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nina Cao, Pavan Ravindra, Shubha R. Kharel, Chuntian Cao, Boyang Li, Xuance Jiang, Matthew R. Carbone, Xiaohui Qu, Deyu Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does Moire Matter? Critical Moire Dependence with Quantum Fluctuations in Graphene Based Integer and Fractional Chern Insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15309</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15309v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rhombohedral multilayer graphene has emerged as a powerful platform for investigating flat-band-driven correlated phenomena, yet most aspects remain not understood. In this work, we systematically study the moire-dependent band topology in rhombohedral hexalayer graphene. For the first time we demonstrate that the moire twist angle plays a crucial role in the formation of the moire Chern insulators in rhombohedral hexalayer graphene/hexagonal boron nitride (RHG/hBN) moire superlattices. In the moire-distant regime at filling factor v = 1, only systems with a twist angle {\theta} &lt; 1.1{\deg} exhibit an integer moire Chern insulator, while the fractional Chern insulator at v = 2/3 requires smaller twist angle to be stabilized. Our theoretical modelling, which includes quantum fluctuations and exact diagonalization results, suggests that mean-field theory, which has been widely adopted, does not explain the twist-angle dependence of the v = 1 phase diagram, and that correlation effects are crucial. Moreover, we realize two distinct stacking configurations ( /Xi=0 and /Xi=1) between graphene and hBN, and find that both cases can yield a Chern insulator at v = 1. Our experimental work upends the current mean-field paradigm, illuminates how quantum fluctuations and moir\'e effects shape the RHG/hBN phase diagram, and paves the way for future understanding and engineering of topological correlated states in rhombohedral graphene moire systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15309v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zihao Huo, Wenxuan Wang, Jian Xie, Yves H. Kwan, Jonah Herzog-Arbeitman, Zaizhe Zhang, Qiu Yang, Min Wu, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Kaihui Liu, Nicolas Regnault, B. Andrei Bernevig, Xiaobo Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Altermagnetism induced surface Chern insulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15357</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15357v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a new pathway to the quantized anomalous Hall effect (QAHE) by coupling an altermagnet to a topological crystalline insulator (TCI). The former gaps the topological surface states of the TCI, thereby realizing the QAHE in a robust and switchable platform with near- vanishing magnetization. We demonstrate the feasibility of this approach by studying a slab of the TCI SnTe coupled to an altermagnetic RuO2 layer. Our first-principles calculations reveal that the d-wave altermagnetism in RuO2 induces a 7 meV gap to the Dirac surface states on the (110) surface of SnTe, producing a finite anomalous Hall effect. Our approach generalizes to broader classes of altermagnetic materials and TCIs, thereby providing a family of topological altermagnetic heterostructures with small or vanishing magnetization that support nontrivial Chern numbers. Our results highlight a promising new topological platform with great tunability and applications to spintronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15357v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuance Jiang, Sayed Ali Akbar Ghorashi, Deyu Lu, Jennifer Cano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unravelling the Catalytic Activity of Dual-Metal Doped N6-Graphene for Sulfur Reduction via Machine Learning-Accelerated First-Principles Calculations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15397</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15397v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding and optimizing polysulfide adsorption and conversion processes are critical to mitigating shuttle effects and sluggish redox kinetics in lithium-sulfur batteries (LSBs). Here, we introduce a machine-learning-accelerated framework, Precise and Accurate Configuration Evaluation (PACE), that integrates Machine Learning Interatomic Potentials (MLIPs) with Density Functional Theory (DFT) to systematically explore adsorption configurations and energetics of a series of N6-coordinated dual-atom catalysts (DACs). Our results demonstrate that, compared with single-atom catalysts, DACs exhibit improved LiPS adsorption and redox conversion through cooperative metal-sulfur interactions and electronic coupling between adjacent metal centers. Among all DACs, Fe-Ni and Fe-Pt show optimal catalytic performance, due to their optimal adsorption energies (-1.0 to -2.3 eV), low free-energy barriers (&lt;=0.4 eV) for the Li2S2 to Li2S conversion, and facile Li2S decomposition barriers (&lt;=1.0 eV). To accelerate catalyst screening, we further developed a machine learning (ML) regression model trained on DFT-calculated data to predict the Gibbs free energy (\Delta G) of Li2Sn adsorption using physically interpretable descriptors. The Gradient Boosting Regression (GBR) model yields an R^2 of 0.85 and an MAE of 0.26 eV, enabling the rapid prediction of \Delta G for unexplored DACs. Electronic-structure analyses reveal that the superior performance originates from the optimal d-band alignment and S-S bond polarization induced by the cooperative effect of dual metal centres. This dual ML-DFT framework demonstrates a generalizable, data-driven design strategy for the rational discovery of efficient catalysts for next-generation LSBs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15397v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sahil Kumar, Adithya Maurya K R, Mudit Dixit</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractional Quantum Hall Wedding Cakes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15472v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work investigates the coexistence of distinct topologically ordered phases within a single setup. We demonstrate this concept through tensor network simulations of the Hofstadter-Bose-Hubbard model under a spatially modulated chemical potential. Focusing on cylindrical geometries, we realize regions exhibiting the Laughlin-1/2 phase and its particle-hole conjugate, and confirm their topological character via the local St\v{r}eda's response and Laughlin's flux insertion protocol. Our approach offers a new pathway for experimentally and numerically charting entire phase diagrams within a single system, possibly eliminating the need for independent parameter scans.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15472v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chlo\'e Van Bastelaere, Felix A. Palm, Botao Wang, Nathan Goldman, Laurens Vanderstraeten</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gate-tunable Josephson diodes in magic-angle twisted bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15503</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15503v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report low-temperature measurements of two adjacent, gate-defined Josephson junctions (JJs) in magic-angle twisted bilayer graphene (MATBG) at a moir\'e filling factor near $\nu = -2$. We show that both junctions exhibit a prominent, gate-tunable Josephson diode effect, which we explain by a combination of large kinetic inductance and non-uniform supercurrent distribution. Despite their proximity, the JJs display differences in their interference patterns and different diode behavior, underscoring that microscopic inhomogeneities such as twist angle variations shape the non-uniform supercurrent and drive the diode behavior. As a result, the nonreciprocal supercurrent can be tuned by gate voltage, enabling tuning of the diode efficiency and even reversing the polarity at fixed magnetic fields. Our findings offer potential routes for tailoring Josephson diode performance in superconducting quantum circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15503v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Rothstein, R. J. Dolleman, L. Klebl, A. Achtermann, F. Volmer, K. Watanabe, T. Taniguchi, F. Hassler, L. Banszerus, B. Beschoten, C. Stampfer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synergistic modulation of band structure and phonon transport for higher thermoelectric performance of WSe2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15523</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15523v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Tungsten diselenide (WSe2) emerges as a promising thermoelectric (TE) candidate due to its high thermopower (S), cost-effectiveness, and environmentally friendly characteristics. However, pristine WSe2 exhibits limited electrical conductivity (sigma), a low power factor (PF), and high lattice thermal conductivity (k_L), which restrict its overall TE performance. Here, we show that through co-doping of Nb for W and Te for Se in WSe2, its power factor increases 17-fold, reaching 8.91 microW cm^-1 K^-2 at 850 K. Simultaneously, its lattice thermal conductivity (k_L) decreases from 1.70 W m^-1 K^-1 to 0.48 W m^-1 K^-1. Experiments and density functional theory (DFT) analysis demonstrate that the enhancement of PF is linked to an increased density of states, higher effective mass (md*), improved mobility (mu), and elevated electrical conductivity (sigma) owing to the replacement of Se2- with Te2-; while the observed 72% reduction in k_L results primarily from phonon scattering at Te-Se and Nb-W defects. As a result, a remarkable ZT_max ~ 1 is obtained at 850 K for the sample W0.95Nb0.05Se2-yTey with y = 0.3, which is about a 30-fold increase compared to WSe2, proving that Nb and Te co-doping in WSe2 can significantly boost its TE performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15523v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.cej.2025.164510</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Mazhar Hussain Danish, Amil Aligayev, Zahir Muhammad, Tao Chen, Adil Mansoor, Zia Ur Rahman, F. J. Dominguez-Gutierrez, Di Li, Jian Zhang, Zhuang Hao Zheng, Xiaoying Qin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent Topology in Kagome Ferromagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15536v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the emergence of a topological magnon phase in a two-dimensional kagome ferromagnet with Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction (DMI) and scalar spin chirality. By incorporating a chiral interaction term proportional to the scalar triple product chi_ijk = S_i (S_j x S_k), we examine how the interplay between DMI and the topological orbital coupling kappa_TO gives rise to geometric phase, nontrivial Berry curvature, and quantized Chern numbers in the magnon bands. Using a momentum-space representation and linear spin-wave theory, we compute the orbital texture, its vorticity, and the Berry curvature across the Brillouin zone. We show that noncoplanar spin textures, driven by finite DMI, form momentum-space skyrmions that act as sources of geometric curvature. Importantly, we demonstrate that DMI alone is insufficient to break time-reversal symmetry; only the presence of finite scalar chirality terms allows the system to develop a nonzero Berry phase and topological transport signatures. We further explore the effect of a global plaquette rotation, showing that while the band structure remains invariant under this unitary transformation, the Berry curvature and Chern number are modulated, highlighting the geometric sensitivity of the topological response. Our results establish a direct correspondence between the lattice geometry, chirality, and magnon topology, providing a route toward tunable topological phases in frustrated magnetic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15536v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seif Alwan, Jonas Fransson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atomically-resolved exciton emission from single defects in MoS$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15676</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15676v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding how atomic defects shape the nanoscale optical properties of two-dimensional (2D) semiconductors is essential for advancing quantum technologies and optoelectronics. Using scanning tunneling spectroscopy (STS) and luminescence (STML), we correlate the atomic structure and optical fingerprints of individual defects in monolayer MoS$_2$. A bilayer of hexagonal boron nitride (hBN) effectively decouples MoS$_2$ from the graphene substrate, increasing its band gap and extending the defect charge state lifetime. This enables the observation of sharp STML emission lines from MoS$_2$ excitons and trions exhibiting nanoscale sensitivity to local potential fluctuations. We identify the optical signatures of common point defects in MoS$_2$: sulfur vacancies (Vac$_\text{S}^-$), oxygen substitutions (O$_\text{S}$), and negatively charged carbon-hydrogen complexes (CH$_\text{S}^-$). While Vac$_\text{S}^-$ and O$_\text{S}$ only suppress pristine excitonic emission, CH$_\text{S}^-$ generate defect-bound exciton complexes ($A^-X$) about 200\,meV below the MoS$_2$ exciton. Sub-nanometer-resolved STML maps reveal large spectral shifts near charged defects, concurrent with the local band bending expected for band-to-defect optical transitions. These results establish an atomically precise correlation between structure, electronic states, and optical response, enabling deterministic engineering of quantum emitters in 2D materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15676v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lysander Huberich, Eve Ammerman, Gu Yu, Yining Ren, Sotirios Papadopoulos, Chengye Dong, Joshua A. Robinson, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Oliver Gr\"oning, Lukas Novotny, Tingxin Li, Shiyong Wang, Bruno Schuler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-Time Modeling of Skyrmion Dynamics in Arbitrary 2D Spatially Dependent Pinning Potential Landscapes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15713</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15713v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Non-flat energy landscapes leading to localized pinning of skyrmions pose an inherent and unavoidable challenge for studies of fundamental 2D spin structure dynamics as well as applications. Accounting for pinning is a key requirement for predictive modeling of skyrmion systems, as it impacts the systems' dynamics and introduces randomizing effects. In this article, we use magneto-optical Kerr microscopy to image skyrmions in a magnetic thin film system in real time and analyze their hopping dynamics within the non-flat energy landscape. To achieve a fully quantitative model, we utilize skyrmion diffusion and dwell times at pinning sites to extrapolate the pinning energy landscape into regions that cannot be sampled on reasonable experimental time scales. For evaluation with a coarse-grained Thiele model, we perform long-time measurements of skyrmion diffusion and then develop a two-step procedure to determine simulation parameters by comparing them to experimentally accessible behavior. This provides a direct conversion between simulation and experimental units, which is the missing key step that has previously prevented quantitative quasiparticle modeling. We demonstrate the predictive power of our approach by measuring the experimentally unexplored density dependence of skyrmion diffusion and show that it is in excellent agreement with simulation predictions. Our technique thus enables quantitative skyrmion simulations on experimental time and length scales, allowing for predictive in-silico prototyping of skyrmion devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15713v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon M. Fr\"ohlich (Institute of Physics, Johannes Gutenberg University Mainz, 55099 Mainz, Germany), Tobias Sparmann (Institute of Physics, Johannes Gutenberg University Mainz, 55099 Mainz, Germany), Maarten A. Brems (Institute of Physics, Johannes Gutenberg University Mainz, 55099 Mainz, Germany), Jan Roth\"orl (Institute of Physics, Johannes Gutenberg University Mainz, 55099 Mainz, Germany), Fabian Kammerbauer (Institute of Physics, Johannes Gutenberg University Mainz, 55099 Mainz, Germany), Klaus Raab (Institute of Physics, Johannes Gutenberg University Mainz, 55099 Mainz, Germany), Sachin Krishnia (Institute of Physics, Johannes Gutenberg University Mainz, 55099 Mainz, Germany), Mathias Kl\"aui (Institute of Physics, Johannes Gutenberg University Mainz, 55099 Mainz, Germany), Peter Virnau (Institute of Physics, Johannes Gutenberg University Mainz, 55099 Mainz, Germany)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring the magnetic anisotropy of the spin Hall effect and spin relaxation length in nickel and permalloy via electrical spin injection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15809v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The spin Hall effect in ferromagnets is of great interest in the field of spintronics, and while the effect has been quantified in many materials, the dependence of the spin Hall angle on the relative orientation of spin polarization and the magnetization is less well studied. Of equal importance for the purpose of spin-charge interconversion in ferromagnets is the spin relaxation length, which is predicted to be highly anisotropic with respect to magnetization. Using a modified lateral spin valve geometry with a copper channel and permalloy spin injector, we measure the dependence of the spin Hall angle and spin relaxation length on magnetization orientation in permalloy and nickel, using two distinct device geometries. This allows us to disentangle the contributions of the spin relaxation length and spin Hall angle to the measured spin-charge interconversion voltage output. Our results indicate a large anisotropy in both the spin relaxation length and spin Hall angle in both permalloy and nickel, in agreement with theoretical calculations. The quantities change in opposite directions, with the spin relaxation length rising as the magnetization is moved parallel to the spin polarization and the spin Hall angle falling, leading to a near total cancellation of the spin-charge interconversion output.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15809v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/dx73-2lp6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 134404 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Eoin Dolan, Jone Mencos, Williams Savero Torres, Maxen Cosset-Ch\'eneau, Jean-Philippe Attan\'e, Laurent Vila, Luis E. Hueso, F\`elix Casanova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum geometry of common semiconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15853</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15853v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The quantum geometric properties of typical diamond-type (C, Si, Ge) and zincblende-type (GaAs, InP, etc) semiconductors are investigated by means of the $sp^{3}s^{\ast}$ tight-binding model, which allows to calculate the quantum metric of the valence band states throughout the entire Brillouin zone. The global maximum of the metric is at the $\Gamma$ point, but other differential geometric properties like Ricci scalar, Ricci tensor, and Einstein tensor are found to vary significantly in the momentum space, indicating a highly distorted momentum space manifold. The momentum integration of the quantum metric further yields the gauge-invariant part of the spread of valence band Wannier function, whose value agrees well with that experimentally extracted from an optical sum rule of the dielectric function. Furthermore, the dependence of these geometric properties on the energy gap offers a way to quantify the quantum criticality of these common semiconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15853v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Porlles, Wei Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distinct amplitude mode dynamics upon resonant and off-resonant excitation across the charge density wave energy gap in LaTe3 investigated by time- and angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13604</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13604v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Non-equilibrium states generated by ultrafast laser pulses are characterized by specific phenomena that are not accessible in static measurements. Previous time- and angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (TARPES) studies on rare-earth tritelluride materials have revealed the laser-driven melting of the charge density wave order as well as its collective amplitude mode excitation. Variation of the excess energy deposited by optical pumping in the material promises pathways to control the dynamic material response. To this end, we use an optical parametric amplifier to generate a tunable pump photon energy. Studying LaTe3 we compare the dynamics driven by pumping resonantly across the charge density wave energy gap with the effect of pumping at a twice higher photon energy in a TARPES pump-probe experiment. We clearly identify a pump photon energy dependent behavior. At the larger pump photon energy, the excess electronic energy generates lattice heating mediated by e-ph coupling and softening of the amplitude mode frequency from 3 to 2 THz. Remarkably, the resonant pumping across the CDW gap results in a time-independent amplitude mode frequency. We conclude that the resonant excitation across the energy gap excites the amplitude mode selectively while additional electronic excess energy deposited at higher pump photon energy modifies the crystal properties transiently by incoherent dissipative processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13604v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.7566/JPSJ.94.104706</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. 94, 104706 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kecheng Liu, Takeshi Suzuki, Yigui Zhong, Teruto Kanai, Jiro Itatani, Linda Ye, Maya Martinez, Anisha Singh, Ian R. Fisher, Uwe Bovensiepen, Kozo Okazaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Projected and Solvable Topological Heavy Fermion Model of Twisted Bilayer Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14039</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.14039v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the topological heavy-fermion (THF) model of magic-angle twisted bilayer graphene (MATBG) in the projected limit, where only the flat bands are present in the low-energy spectrum. Such limit has been previously analyzed in momentum-space Bistritzer-MacDonald-type continuum models, but not in a real-space formalism. In this regime, the Hubbard interaction ($U_1$) of the $f$-electrons is larger than the bandwidth ($2M$) of the flat bands but smaller than the gap ($\gamma$) between the flat and remote bands. In the THF model, concentrated charge (in real space) and concentrated Berry curvature (in momentum space) are respectively realized by exponentially localized $f$-orbitals and itinerant Dirac $c$-electrons. Local moments naturally arise from $f$-orbitals. Hybridizing the $f$-electrons with $c$-electrons produces power-law tails of the flat-band Wannier functions, raising the question of relevance of the local moment picture in the projected $U_1\ll \gamma$ limit. Nonetheless, we find that the local moments remain stable as long as $U_1 \gg \Delta(\omega)$ for $|\omega|\lesssim U_1$, where $\Delta(\omega)\sim \gamma^2 N(\omega)$ is the hybridization function seen by each $f$-site, and $N(\omega)$ is the density of states of the Dirac $c$-bands. Notably, the comparison between $U_1$ and $\gamma$ is irrelevant to the local moment formation if $N(\omega)$ is unknown. Within the framework of THF, we also derive the correlated self-energy of the flat bands using the Hubbard-I approximation and estimate the coupling strength between the local moments. Finally, we comment that, in the regime of extremely concentrated Berry curvature, the single-particle gap between flat bands and remote bands vanishes and the interaction is always larger than the gap.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.14039v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoyu Hu, Zhi-Da Song, B. Andrei Bernevig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Room-Temperature Pauli Spin Blockade and Current Rectification in 15-13-15 Armchair Graphene Nanoribbon Heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01662</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01662v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this study, we investigate the electronic structures of 13-11-13 and 15-13-15 armchair graphene nanoribbon (AGNR) superlattices (SLs) using a tight-binding model. We demonstrate that the conduction and valence subbands of 15-13-15 AGNR SLs can be accurately described by the Su-Schrieffer-Heeger model, with topologically protected interface states emerging at the junctions between 15-AGNR and 13-AGNR segments. These interface states enable the formation of quantum dot arrays with energy levels well separated from bulk states, making them promising candidates for high-temperature solid-state quantum processors. For 15-13-15 AGNRH segments, we observe both localized zigzag edge states and topologically protected interface states under longitudinal electric fields, with the latter providing efficient tunneling channels in contrast to the less conductive edge states. We further explore nonlinear charge transport through these interface states under Pauli spin blockade, showing that tunneling current spectra reveal charge stability diagrams and Coulomb blockade oscillations, consistent with experimental findings in other serial double quantum dot systems. Additionally, we examine the impact of orbital offsets on tunneling current rectification and demonstrate that significant current rectification is achieved over a wide temperature range when level broadening is optimized. These results highlight the potential of 15-13-15 AGNRHs for robust spin-current conversion and applications in quantum devices, offering advantages over other proposed structures due to precise tunability of key parameters via bottom-up synthesis techniques and the ease of two-gate electrode integration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01662v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1039/d5nr02677f</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>David M T Kuo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mott metal-insulator transition in a modified periodic Anderson model: Insights from entanglement entropy and role of short-range spatial correlations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16533</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16533v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Mott transition is a paradigmatic phenomenon where Coulomb interactions between electrons drive a metal-insulator phase transition. It is extensively studied within the Hubbard model, where a quantum critical transition occurs at a finite temperature second-order critical point. This work investigates the Mott transition in a modified periodic Anderson model that may be viewed as a three-orbital lattice model including an interacting, localized orbital coupled to a delocalized conduction orbital via a second conduction orbital. Within the dynamical mean field theory, this model possesses a strictly zero temperature quantum critical point separating a Fermi liquid and a Mott insulating phase. By employing a simplified version of the dynamical mean field theory, namely, the two-site or linearized dynamical mean field theory, an analytical estimate is provided for the critical parameter strengths at which the transition occurs at zero temperature. An analytical estimate of the single-site von Neumann entanglement entropy is also provided. This measure can be used as a robust identifier for the phase transition. These calculations are extended to their cluster version to incorporate short-range, spatial correlations and discuss their effects on the transition observed in this model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16533v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/adts.202501224</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Adv. Theory Simul. 2025, e01224</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ankur Majumder, Sudeshna Sen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Transformer Backflow for Solving Momentum-Resolved Ground States of Strongly Correlated Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09275</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09275v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Strongly correlated materials host a rich variety of exotic quantum phases but remain challenging to solve due to strong interactions. We introduce the Neural Transformer Backflow (NTB) framework, a powerful neural-network ansatz formulated within a multi-band projection formalism. NTB is mean-field transcendental, parameter-efficient and fermionic intrinsic, exhibiting superior performance compared with existing neural ansatzes. By naturally enforcing momentum conservation, NTB enables direct computation of momentum-resolved many-body ground states, providing detailed access to degeneracies and energy gaps. It achieves high accuracy on small systems and scales efficiently to larger sizes and higher-band truncations far beyond the reach of exact diagonalization. We demonstrate the power of NTB in capturing diverse correlated phases in twisted MoTe$_2$, including charge density waves, fractional Chern insulators, and anomalous Hall Fermi liquids, within a unified framework. This approach offers a generic, scalable route towards understanding and discovering quantum phases in strongly correlated materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09275v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lixing Zhang, Di Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudogap-induced change in the nature of the Lifshitz transition in the two-dimensional Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09783v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the behavior of the density of states and the $B_{1g}$ nematic susceptibility extracted from Raman response data across the doping-driven Lifshitz transition comparing the weak and strong interaction cases. Our results were obtained using cluster dynamical mean field theory for the two-dimensional Hubbard model. In the weakly correlated Fermi liquid regime, both quantities are approximately symmetric around the Lifshitz transition doping $p_{LT}$. In the strongly correlated regime, the low-doping pseudogap leads to an asymmetric, discontinuous evolution when the Fermi surface changes from hole-like to electron-like at $p_{LT}$. The Lifshitz transition thus changes character because it is tied to the pseudogap-Fermi-liquid transition. These results are consistent with available observations and should foster further experimental investigations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09783v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maria C. O. Aguiar, Helena Bragan\c{c}a, Indranil Paul, Marcello Civelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable quantum metric and band topology in bilayer Dirac models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23622v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum metric, a fundamental component of quantum geometry, has attracted broad interest in recent years due to its critical role in various quantum phenomena. Meanwhile, band topology, which serves as an important framework in condensed matter physics, has led to the discovery of various topological phases. In this work, we introduce a bilayer Dirac model that allows precise tuning of both properties. Our approach combines two Dirac Hamiltonians with distinct energy scales; one producing relatively dispersive bands and the other yielding relatively flat bands. The dispersive and flat bands are weakly coupled via hybridization $\lambda$. By inducing a band inversion in the layer subspace, we achieve flexible tuning of band topology across all Altland-Zirnbauer symmetry classes and quantum metric scaling as $g \propto 1/\lambda^2$ near band inversion point. Using the bilayer Su-Schrieffer-Heeger model, we investigate the localization properties of gapless boundary states, which are affected by quantum metric. Our work lays a foundation for exploring the interplay between band topology and quantum metric.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23622v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xun-Jiang Luo, Xing-Lei Ma, K. T. Law</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defect mediated quantum melting of charge ordered insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00099v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2d) electronic systems on a lattice at fractional filling $\nu = p/q$ exhibit a competition between charge ordered insulators, called Wigner-Mott insulators (WMIs), at large Coulomb repulsion and Fermi-liquid metals at large electronic kinetic energy. When those two energy scales are roughly equal, insulating states that restore the lattice translation symmetry, which we call quantum charge liquids (QCLs), may emerge. When gapped, these QCLs must exhibit topological order. In this work, we show that the allowed topological ordered phases that are proximate to the WMI strongly depend on the charge ordering in the WMI. In particular, we show that when $q$ is even, no direct transition exists between a WMI with the smallest allowed unit cell size from filling constraints, i.e., the "minimal" WMI, and the topological order with the smallest ground state degeneracy on a torus allowed by filling constraints, i.e., the "minimal" TO. Furthermore, we describe the quantum melting transition of the WMIs to the proximate QCLs in terms of the proliferation of the topological defects of the WMIs. The field theory of this transition in terms of the topological defects reveals their role as precursors to the anyon excitations in the QCLs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00099v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abijith Krishnan, Ajesh Kumar, T. Senthil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A recipe for local simulation of strongly-correlated fermionic matter on quantum computers: the 2D Fermi-Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14543v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The simulation of quantum many-body systems, relevant for quantum chemistry and condensed matter physics, is one of the most promising applications of near-term quantum computers before fault-tolerance. However, since the vast majority of quantum computing technologies are built around qubits and discrete gate-based operations, the translation of the physical problem into this framework is a crucial step. This translation will often be device specific, and a suboptimal implementation will be punished by the exponential compounding of errors on real devices. The importance of an efficient mapping is already revealed for models of spinful fermions in two or three dimensions, which naturally arise when the relevant physics relates to electrons. Using the most direct and well-known mapping, the Jordan-Wigner transformation, leads to a non-local representation of local degrees of freedom, and necessities efficient decompositions of non-local unitary gates into a sequence of hardware accessible local gates. In this paper, we provide a step-by-step recipe for simulating the paradigmatic two-dimensional Fermi-Hubbard model on a quantum computer using only local operations. To provide the ingredients for such a recipe, we briefly review the plethora of different approaches that have emerged recently but focus on the Derby-Klassen compact fermion mapping in order to make our discussion concrete. We provide a detailed recipe for an end-to-end simulation including embedding on a physical device, preparing initial states such as ground states, simulation of unitary time evolution, and measurement of observables and spectral functions. We explicitly compute the resource requirements for simulating a global quantum quench and conclude by discussing the challenges and future directions for simulating strongly-correlated fermionic matter on quantum computers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14543v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.7.043018</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 7, 043018 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Arash Jafarizadeh, Frank Pollmann, Adam Gammon-Smith</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Macroscopic suppression of supersonic quantum transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19788</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19788v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider a broad class of strongly interacting quantum lattice gases, including the Fermi-Hubbard and Bose-Hubbard models. We focus on macroscopic particle clusters of size $\theta N$, with $\theta\in(0,1)$ and $N$ the total particle number, and we study the quantum probability that such a cluster is transported across a distance $r$ within time $t$. Conventional effective light cone arguments yield a bound of the form $\exp(v t-r)$. We report a substantially stronger bound $\exp(\theta N(vt-r))$, which provides exponential suppression that scales with system size. Our result establishes a universal dynamical large deviation principle: macroscopic suppression of supersonic macroscopic transport (MASSMAT).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19788v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J\'er\'emy Faupin, Marius Lemm, Israel Michael Sigal, Jingxuan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-space Hubbard-corrected density functional theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.23612v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present an accurate and efficient framework for real-space Hubbard-corrected density functional theory. In particular, we obtain expressions for the energy, atomic forces, and stress tensor suitable for real-space finite-difference discretization, and develop a large-scale parallel implementation. We verify the accuracy of the formalism through comparisons with established planewave results. We demonstrate that the implementation is highly efficient and scalable, outperforming established planewave codes by more than an order of magnitude in minimum time to solution, with increasing advantages as the system size and/or number of processors is increased. We apply this framework to examine the impact of exchange-correlation inconsistency in local atomic orbital generation and introduce a scheme for optimizing the Hubbard parameter based on hybrid functionals, both while studying TiO$_2$ polymorphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.23612v2</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sayan Bhowmik, Andrew J. Medford, Phanish Suryanarayana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
