<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 04:00:22 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>$\mathbb{Z}_2$ Universality of the Mott Transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25845</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25845v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate that the Mott transition exhibits universal scaling as a consequence of the breaking of a $\mathbb{Z}_2$ symmetry in momentum space. A direct consequence of this discrete symmetry breaking is the charge or Mott gap itself. From extensive numerics, we proffer that it is the charge compressibility that acts as the underlying order parameter as it is zero in the insulator and non-zero in the metallic state. Additionally, the Widom line (temperature of the extremum of the compressibility) obeys a universal scaling of $T_m=0.39U$ deep into the insulating state directly from $Z_2$ universality. Furthermore, the temperature at which the second derivative of the compressibility has a minimum is independent of lattice geometry, exhibiting a universal scaling of $|U-U_c|^\alpha$ where $\alpha\approx 1$. Finally, our computational approach reproduces the key features of the doping dependence of the compressibility demonstrated in recent cold-atom quantum simulators of the Hubbard model, thereby corroborating our conclusions on $\mathbb{Z}_2$ universality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25845v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinchao Zhao, Peizhi Mai, Gaurav Tenkila, Philip W. Phillips</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sweet-spot protection of hole spins in sparse arrays via spin-dependent magneto-tunneling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25857</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25857v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent advances in the scaling of spin qubits have led to the development of sparse architectures where spin qubits are distributed across multiple quantum dots. This distributed approach enables qubit manipulation through hopping and flopping modes, as well as protocols for spin shuttling to entangle spins beyond nearest neighbors. Therefore, understanding spin tunneling across quantum dots is fundamental for the improvement of sparse array encodings. Here, we develop a microscopic theory of a minimal sparse array formed by a hole in a double quantum dot. We show the existence of spin-dependent magnetic corrections to the tunnel couplings that help preserve existing sweet spots, even for quantum dots with different $g$-factors, and introduce new ones that are not accounted for in the simplest models. Our analytical and numerical results explain observed sweet spots in state-of-the-art shuttling and cQED experiments, are relevant to hopping and flopping modes, and apply broadly to sparse array encodings of any size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25857v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Esteban A. Rodr\'iguez-Mena, Biel Mart\'inez, Ahmad Fouad Kalo, Yann-Michel Niquet, Jos\'e C. Abadillo-Uriel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theories of Superconducting Diode Effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25864v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Superconducting diode effects (SDE), both in bulk superconductors and in Josephson junctions, have garnered a lot of attention due to potential applications in classical and quantum computing, as well as superconducting sensors. Here we review various mechanisms that have been theoretically proposed for their realization. We first provide a brief historical overview and discuss the basic but subtle phenomenological Ginzburg-Landau theory of SDE, emphasizing the need to the simultaneous breaking of time-reversal and inversion symmetries. We then proceed to more microscopic treatments, focusing especially on implementations in noncentrosymmetric materials described by the Rashba-Zeeman model. Finally, we review proposals based on other condensed matter systems such as altermagnets, valley polarized and topological materials, and systems out of equilibrium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25864v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Shaffer, Alex Levchenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mutual enhancement of altermagnetism and ferroelectricity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25899v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider theoretically the possibility of coexisting ferroelectric and metallic altermagnetic order, which has recently been predicted in insulating and semiconducting systems via ab initio calculations. Solving self-consistently a mean-field Hubbard model, accounting also for the energy cost of distorting the lattice to produce an electric polarization, our results show that metallic altermagnetism and ferroelectricity suppress or enhance each other depending on the doping level of the system. Close to half-filling, the system can lower its energy by becoming altermagnetic, but at the expense of losing the electric polarization. Away from half-filling, the coexistence of ferroelectricity and altermagnetism is much more robust toward an increase in the energy cost associated with the deformation of the lattice. Therefore, our results suggest that filling fractions corresponding to doping relatively far away from half-filling constitute the most promising regime to look for coexistent ferroelectricity and metallic altermagnetism with mutual enhancement. Moreover, we propose a way to electrically tune altermagnetism between nodal and nodeless phases as well as achieving coexistence of a nodal and nodeless phase for the two spin species.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25899v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chi Sun, Jacob Linder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric and Orbital Control of Correlated States in Small Hubbard Clusters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25919</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25919v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Arrays of semiconductor quantum dots provide a powerful platform to design correlated quantum matter from the bottom up. We establish a predictive framework for engineering local electron pairing in these artificial molecules by systematically deploying three control levers: lattice geometry, orbital hybridization, and external electric fields. Using Hartree-Fock simulations on canonical 3D clusters from the tetrahedron (Z = 3) to the FCC lattice (Z = 12), at and near half-filling, we uncover three fundamental design principles. (i) Geometric Hierarchy: The resilience to Coulomb repulsion U is dictated by the coordination number Z, which controls kinetic delocalization. (ii) Orbital Hybridization: Counter-intuitively, inter-orbital hopping t_orb acts not as a simple suppressor of pairing, but as a sophisticated control knob that enhances double occupancy at moderate U by engineering the on-site energy landscape. (iii) Field Squeezing: An electric field robustly induces pairing by forcing charge localization, an effect most potent in low-connectivity clusters. These principles form a blueprint for deterministically targeting charge and spin correlations in quantum-dot-based quantum hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25919v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shivanshu Dwivedi, Kalum Palandage</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperbolic Fracton Model, Subsystem Symmetry and Holography III: Extension to Generic Tessellations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25994</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25994v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We generalize the Hyperbolic Fracton Model from the $\{5,4\}$ tessellation to generic tessellations, and investigate its core properties: subsystem symmetries, fracton mobility, and holographic correspondence. While the model on the original tessellation has features reminiscent of the flat-space lattice cases, the generalized tessellations exhibit a far richer and more intricate structure. The ground-state degeneracy and subsystem symmetries are generated recursively layer-by-layer, through the inflation rule, but without a simple, uniform pattern. The fracton excitations follow exponential-in-distance and algebraic-in-lattice-size growing patterns when moving outward, and depend sensitively to the tessellation geometry, differing qualitatively from both type-I or type-II fracton model on flat lattices. Despite this increased complexity, the hallmark holographic features -- subregion duality via Rindler reconstruction, the Ryu-Takayanagi formula for mutual information, and effective black hole entropy scaling with horizon area -- remain valid. These results demonstrate that the holographic correspondence in fracton models persists in generic tessellations, and provide a natural platform to explore more intricate subsystem symmetries and fracton physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25994v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yosef Shokeeb, Ludovic D. C. Jaubert, Han Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High Resolution Polar Kerr Effect Studies of Cs3Sb5 and ScV6Sn6 Below the Charge Order Transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26010v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report high resolution polar Kerr effect measurements on CsV3Sb5 and ScV6Sn6 single crystals in search for signatures of spontaneous polar Kerr effect (PKE) below the charge order transitions of these materials. Utilizing two separate zero-area loop Sagnac interferometers operating at 1550 nm and 830 nm wavelengths, we studied the temperature dependence of possible PKE after training with magnetic field. While a finite field Kerr measurement yielded optical rotation expected from the Pauli susceptibility of the itinerant carriers, no signal was detected at zero-field to within the noise floor limit of the apparatus of below $\sim$100 nanoradians. Simultaneous coherent reflection measurements confirm the sharpness of the charge order transition in the same optical volume as the Kerr measurements. Application of strain to reveal a hidden flux-ordered magnetic state did not result in a finite Kerr effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26010v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David R. Saykin, Qianni Jiang, Zhaoyu Liu, Chandra Shekhar, Claudia Felser, Jiun-Haw Chu, Aharon Kapitulnik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photoinduced Electronic Band Dynamics and Defect-mediated Surface Potential Evolution in PdSe$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26011</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26011v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We use time- and angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (TR-ARPES) combined with density functional theory to investigate ultrafast carrier dynamics in low-symmetry layered semiconducting PdSe$_2$. The indirect bandgap is determined to be 0.55~eV. Following photoexcitation above this gap, we resolve a valence band shift and broadening, both lasting less than a picosecond, consistent with bandgap renormalization and carrier scattering, indicative of strong many-body interactions. Subsequently, hot carriers populate the conduction band minimum and are captured by defect states. A surface photovoltage (SPV) of $\sim$ 67~meV emerges, persisting for over 50~ps, driven by defect-assisted charge separation. The formation of native vacancies, promoted by the low-symmetry lattice, likely gives rise to the mid-gap states responsible for this long-lived SPV response. Detailed analysis of TR-ARPES spectra disentangles the contributions of bandgap renormalization, carrier scattering, defect states, and SPV. These findings establish PdSe$_2$ as a prototypical layered quantum material exhibiting exotic photoresponses on ultrafast timescales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26011v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Omar Abdul-Aziz, Manuel Tuniz, Wibke Bronsch, Fulvio Parmigiani, Federico Cilento, Daniel Wolverson, Charles J. Sayers, Giulio Cerullo, Claudia Dallera, Ettore Carpene, Paul H. M. van Loosdrecht, Hamoon Hedayat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective-Hamiltonian reconstruction through Bloch-wave interferometry in bulk GaAs driven by strong THz fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26028</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26028v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Effective Hamiltonians are powerful tools for understanding the emergent phenomena in condensed matter systems. Reconstructing an effective Hamiltonian directly from experimental data is challenging due to the complex relationship between Hamiltonian parameters and observables. Complimentary to ARPES, which probes surface electronic properties, bulk-sensitive techniques based on HHG and HSG have shown strong potential for Hamiltonian reconstruction. Here, we reconstruct an effective three-band electron-hole Hamiltonian in bulk GaAs based on HSG. Based on previous understanding of HSG in bulk GaAs in terms of Bloch-wave interferometry, an analytic model is derived to quantitatively connect the Hamiltonian parameters with the measured sideband electric fields under strong, low-frequency THz fields. Assuming that the exciton reduced mass and the parameter that defines the hole Bloch wavefunctions in bulk GaAs are known from existing absorbance and HSG experiments, we show that the bandgap of GaAs, two dephasing constants associated with two electron-hole species, and an additional Hamiltonian parameter that determines the electron-hole reduced masses, can be simultaneously and unambiguously determined through Bloch-wave interferometry. We thus demonstrate the full capability of Hamiltonian reconstruction by combining absorbance spectroscopy and HSG experiments. We find that the extracted bandgap of GaAs is approximately 13\,meV higher than the expected value based on previous absorbance measurements. Quantum kinetic analysis suggests that, in the HSG experiments, the electron-hole energy could have been renormalized through Fr\"ohlich interaction that is modified by the strong THz fields. We also show that the energy threshold in emission of optical phonons can be suppressed by applying a strong THz field, leading to nearly constant dephasing rates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26028v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qile Wu, Seamus D. O Hara, Joseph B. Costello, Loren N. Pfeiffer, Ken W. West, Mark S. Sherwin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theoretical design of the large topological magnetoelectric effect in the Co-intercalated NbS$_2$ structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26054</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26054v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A triangular Co-ion lattice intercalated between 1-H NbS$_2$ layers can exhibit a large anomalous Hall effect (AHE) due to the finite scalar spin chirality originating from the non-coplanar $3q$ ordering of Co spins. This large AHE occurs when the scalar spin chirality is uniform in all Co layers, as indeed found in the Co$_{1/3}$NbS$_2$ case [Phys. Rev. Mater. 6, 024201 (2022)]. However, if the spin chirality were staggered with the opposite signs in the adjacent Co layers, the net AHE would disappear, yielding instead the topological magneto-electric effect. Here, we theoretically verify that a transverse electric field generates a finite orbital magnetization under such conditions, consistent with the axion-like coupling. Using first-principles calculations, we show that the resulting magneto-electric coupling, $\alpha^{zz}$ can be as large as 0.9 $e^2/2h$. We also demonstrate that the inter-layer magnetic coupling in these materials can be tuned by strain, enabling the switching between the AHE and the axionic states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26054v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hyowon Park, Ivar Martin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct observation of the surface superconducting gap in the topological superconductor candidate \beta-PdBi2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26070v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: \beta-PdBi2 is one of the candidates for topological superconductors with a superconducting (SC) transition temperature (Tc) of 5.3 K, in which parity mixing of spin singlet and spin triplet has been anticipated, being crucial for the further understanding of relationship with inversion symmetry and parity mixing in the superconductivity. In this work, we measured the SC gap in high-quality single crystal of \beta-PdBi2 by using high-resolution laser angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy below Tc. We found the isotropic SC gaps in momentum space for multiple bands, and observed that the difference between the SC gap of the topological surface bands and the bulk bands is about 0.1 meV, consistent with other experimental results. These direct and quantitative experimental results support the possibility of \beta-PdBi2 as a topological superconductor, characterized by unique crystal and electronic band structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26070v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akifumi Mine, Takeshi Suzuki, Yigui Zhong, Sahand Najafzadeh, Kenjiro Okawa, Masato Sakano, Kyoko Ishizaka, Shik Shin, Takao Sasagawa, Kozo Okazaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Invariants for (2+1)D bosonic crystalline topological insulators for all 17 wallpaper groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26074</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26074v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study bosonic symmetry-protected topological (SPT) phases in (2+1) dimensions with symmetry $G = G_{\text{space}}\times K$, where $G_{\text{space}}$ is a general wallpaper group and $K=\text{U}(1),\mathbb{Z}_N, \text{SO}(3)$ is an internal symmetry. In each case we propose a set of many-body invariants that can detect all the different phases predicted from real space constructions and group cohomology classifications. They are obtained by applying partial rotations and reflections to a given ground state, combined with suitable operations in $K$. The reflection symmetry invariants that we introduce include `double partial reflections', `weak partial reflections' and their `relative' or `twisted' versions which also depend on $K$. We verify our proposal through exact calculations on ground states constructed using real space constructions. We demonstrate our method in detail for the groups p4m and p4g, and in the case of p4m also derive a topological effective action involving gauge fields for orientation-reversing symmetries. Our results provide a concrete method to fully characterize (2+1)D crystalline topological invariants in bosonic SPT ground states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26074v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Calvera, Naren Manjunath, Maissam Barkeshli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Josephson effect with periodic order parameter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26128</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26128v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the Josephson effect in a two-dimensional superconducting system with a smoothly and periodically varying order parameter. The order parameter is modulated along one direction while remaining uniform in the perpendicular direction, leading to a spatially periodic superconducting phase. We show that the periodicity of the order parameter determines the winding number of the eigenfunctions, which serves as a topological characterization of the system. The winding number is calculated analytically and visualized through the trajectory of the corresponding three-dimensional Bloch vector. By solving the Bogoliubov-de Gennes equation, we obtain both plane-wave solutions describing bulk states and exponentially localized solutions that correspond to edge modes. The analytic bulk-edge connection is employed to identify the conditions under which the edge states emerge from the bulk spectrum. We find that the winding numbers depend on the boundary conditions, which differ between the plane-wave and exponential solutions. These results establish a direct connection between the spatial modulation of the order parameter, the topological structure of the eigenstates, and the emergence of edge modes in periodically modulated Josephson systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26128v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Klaus Ziegler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Laser-Induced Commensurate-Incommensurate Transition of Charge Order in a Hubbard Superlattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26288v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the nonequilibrium dynamics of charge density waves in a pumped one-dimensional Hubbard superlattice with staggered onsite Coulomb interactions at half-filling, using time-dependent exact diagonalization. In equilibrium, the system exhibits commensurate charge correlations consistent with the superlattice periodicity. Under laser excitation, the charge correlation function exhibits distinct behaviors across four representative frequencies, spanning both linear and nonlinear optical regimes. Notably, we observe a laser-induced commensurate-to-incommensurate transition in the charge order, manifested by a shift in the peak wavevector of the charge structure factor. This transition is driven by sublattice-selective doublon-holon dynamics, where the laser frequency and intensity determine whether excitations predominantly destabilize the charge order on the weakly or strongly interacting sublattice. Our analysis of the excitation spectrum and site-resolved correlation dynamics reveals the underlying mechanisms of this transition. These results suggest a promising optical strategy for controlling charge order in superlattice-based quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26288v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hua Chai, Zhenyu Cheng, Qinxin Hu, Zhongbing Huang, Xiang Hu, Xuedong Tian, Liang Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigation of the intrinsic hidden spin texture and spin-state segregation in centrosymmetric monolayer dichalcogenide: effectiveness of the electric-field approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26394</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26394v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The emergence of hidden spin polarization in centrosymmetric nonmagnetic crystals due to local symmetry breaking has created new opportunities for potential spintronic applications and for enhancing our understanding of mechanisms to electrically manipulate spin-related phenomena. In this work, we investigate within density functional theory the properties of the hidden spin texture and spin-layer segregation in a prototype centrosymmetric dichalcogenide-monolayer material using an electric-field-based method. This method is shown to yield a precise and robust alternative to traditional layer-projected spin-polarization techniques for obtaining the intrinsic hidden spin textures in such materials. Moreover, it gives access at the same time to the spatial distribution within the monolayer of the individual spin-segregated states responsible for the hidden spin textures, not provided by other techniques. With this approach we determine and study the hidden spin textures of the upper valence bands of the PtTe2 monolayer together with the spatial behavior of the probability densities and spin polarization densities of the corresponding maximally segregated spin states. This combined study enabled by the electric-field method yields new insights into the mechanisms controlling the spin-layer segregation and resulting hidden spin texture in such systems. We also discuss the symmetry rules governing the shape in the Brillouin zone of the hidden spin texture, which can be straightforwardly predicted within the present framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26394v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.commatsci.2025.114189</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Comput. Mater. Sci. 260, 114189 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ameneh Deljouifar, Anita Yadav, Nata\v{s}a Stoji\'c, H. Rahimpour Soleimani, Nadia Binggeli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-orbit coupled spin-boson model : A variational analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26468v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The spin-boson (SB) model is a standard prototype for quantum dissipation, which we generalize in this work, to explore the dissipative effects on a one-dimensional spin-orbit (SO) coupled particle in the presence of a sub-ohmic bath. We analyze this model by extending the well-known variational polaron approach, revealing a localization transition accompanied by an intriguing change in the spectrum, for which the doubly degenerate minima evolves to a single minimum at zero momentum as the system-bath coupling increases. For translational invariant system with conserved momentum, a continuous magnetization transition occurs, whereas the ground state changes discontinuously. We further investigate the transition of the ground state in the presence of harmonic confinement, which effectively models a quantum dot-like nanostructure under the influence of the environment. In both the scenarios, the entanglement entropy of the spin-sector can serve as a marker for these transitions. Interestingly, for the trapped system, a cat-like superposition state corresponds to maximum entanglement entropy below the transition, highlighting the relevance of the present model for studying the effect of decoherence on intra-particle entanglement in the context of quantum information processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26468v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sudip Sinha, S. Sinha, S. Dattagupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bi-isotropic effects on hybrid surface polaritons in bilayer configurations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26500</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26500v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we investigate the bi-isotropic effects in the formation and tunability of hybrid surface polaritons in bilayer configurations. We consider a heterostructure composed of a medium with bi-isotropic constitutive relations and an AFM layer. Using the transfer matrix formalism, we derive general expressions for the dispersion relations of surface polaritonic modes, including the dependence on the bi-isotropic parameter, and analyze their coupling to bulk magnon-polaritons. As an illustration of application, we consider a heterostructure formed with Bi$_{2}$Se$_{3}$ interfaced with antiferromagnetic (AFM) materials that support terahertz-frequency magnons, specifically Cr$_{2}$O$_{3}$ and FeF$_{2}$. In the strong bi-isotropic coupling regime, the surface Dirac plasmon--phonon--magnon polariton (DPPMP) dispersion undergoes a pronounced redshift, accompanied by suppression of the characteristic anticrossing between the Dirac plasmon and the phonon. This effect, observed in all AFM materials considered, suggests a weakening of the hybrid interaction, possibly due to saturation or detuning mechanisms induced by increased $\alpha$. Furthermore, increasing the Fermi energy of the topological insulator enhances the surface plasmon and phonon contributions, inducing a blueshift of the DPPP branches and bringing them closer to resonance with the magnon mode, thereby increasing the hybridization strength. Intriguingly, this redshift partially compensates the blueshift induced by a higher Fermi level, restoring the system to a weak-coupling regime analogous to that observed at lower Fermi energies. Our findings reveal that both the Fermi level and the bi-isotropic response offer independent and complementary control parameters for tuning the strength of light--magnon coupling in TI/AFM heterostructures, with potential implications for reconfigurable THz spintronic and photonic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26500v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Nonato, Pedro D. S. Silva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable Colloidal Synthesis Enabling {\mu}-ARPES on Individual Two-dimensional Bismuth Nanocrystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26558v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two-dimensional bismuth (Bi) is a promising platform for quantum and energy technologies due to strong spin-orbit coupling, high thermoelectric efficiency, and magnetoresistance. However, scalable and flexible synthesis of high-quality Bi with fast research turnaround remains challenging. We report a controlled colloidal synthesis of Bi nanosheets with tunable lateral sizes (0.6 - 4.1 um), hexagonal shape, and a layered single-crystalline structure along the {00l} planes. The nanosheets exhibit excellent oxidation resistance and ambient stability. ARPES measurements on individual nanosheets reveal a band structure in excellent agreement with DFT calculations, confirming high crystal quality and uniformity. Our findings enable fast production and characterization of two-dimensional Bi, paving the way for fundamental studies and integration into next-generation quantum and energy devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26558v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fagui He, Yan Yan Grisan Qiu, Simone Mearini, Vitaliy Feyer, Kevin Oldenburg, Rostyslav Lesyuk, Christian Klinke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strain Engineering of Altermagnetic Symmetry in Epitaxial RuO$_2$ Films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26581v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The magnetic ground state of RuO$_2$ has been under intense debate. Using first-principles calculations, we show that compressive strain along [001] direction stabilizes an altermagnetic phase in RuO$_2$ thin films grown on (100) and (110) TiO$_2$ substrates. We further identify that compressive strain enhances the density of states near the Fermi level, resulting in a Fermi surface instability and the emergence of altermagnetism. The magnitude of strain and the associated increase in the density of states can be tuned by varying the film thickness, as systematically confirmed by x-ray diffraction and photoemission spectroscopy measurements. Symmetry analysis further reveals that (100) RuO$_2$ hosts an ideal altermagnetic order, whereas broken symmetry in (110) films leads to an uncompensated ferrimagnetic state. Finally, we discuss the effects of Hubbard $U$ parameters and evaluate the realistic tunneling magnetoresistance of (100) RuO$_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26581v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johnathas D. S. Forte, Seung Gyo Jeong, Anand Santhosh, Seungjun Lee, Bharat Jalan, Tony Low</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical control of Coulomb interactions and Hubbard bands in monolayer 1T-TaS$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26584v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Monolayer 1T-TaS$_2$ hosts a star-of-David charge-density wave (CDW) that stabilizes a low-temperature Mott-insulating state. Recent time-resolved spectroscopies indicate a coupling between the CDW amplitude mode and the electronic correlation strength, yet the role of the screened Coulomb interaction remains unclear. Using the constrained random-phase approximation, we show that the CDW amplitude modifies the bare and screened on-site interactions, leading to sizable variations in the effective Hubbard U. Our combined density functional and dynamical mean-field theory calculations reveal that the Hubbard bands shift in concert with the CDW amplitude, and that a reduced distortion drives a transition from a Mott insulator to a correlated metal. These results demonstrate a direct link between lattice distortions and Coulomb interactions in transition-metal dichalcogenides, providing a microscopic mechanism for light-induced control of correlated phases in two-dimensional quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26584v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niklas Notter, Markus Aichhorn, Anna Galler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local-moment magnetism in Mn-based pnictides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26595</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26595v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report a comprehensive study of electronic-correlation effects in Manganese-based antiferromagnetic pnictides BaMn$_2$Pn$_2$ (Pn=P,As,Sb,Bi). Our density functional theory plus slave-spin mean-field simulations indicate that all the compounds lie on the strong-coupling side of an itinerant-to-localized moment crossover, corresponding to the critical interaction strength for the Mott transition in the high-temperature paramagnetic phase. We also show that the experimental N\'eel temperature of each compound scales with the distance from this crossover.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26595v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Crispino, Niklas Witt, Tommaso Gorni, Giorgio Sangiovanni, Luca de' Medici</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental Milestones Towards Majorana Braiding with Acoustic Metamaterials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26598v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Here we show the first experimental implementation of the fully general Kitaev chain with complex-valued order parameter $\Delta$ and site-varying synthetic chemical potential $\mu$, using a passive multilayer acoustic resonator design and fabrication. Our laboratory model faithfully reproduces the key symmetries and the topological phase diagram of the model, and displays robust Majorana-like edge modes spatially localized at smoothly engineered domain walls and energetically localized in the middle of the bulk spectral gap. We demonstrate precise control over mode positioning through smooth spatial variations of $\mu$, and validate the stability of the modes and of the spectral gap under continuous and complex variations of $\Delta$ -- both critical requirements for topological braiding operations. These results establish and validate the fundamental building blocks for experimental implementation of complete braiding protocols, opening concrete pathways toward accessible non-abelian physics and topologically protected information processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26598v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jackson Saunders, Emil Prodan, Camelia Prodan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Giant orbital Zeeman effects in a magnetic topological van der Waals interphase</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26662</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26662v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Van der Waals (vdW) heterostructures allow the engineering of electronic and magnetic properties by the stacking different two-dimensional vdW materials. For example, orbital hybridisation and charge transfer at a vdW interface may result in electric fields across the interface that give rise to Rashba spin-orbit coupling. In magnetic vdW heterostructures, this in turn can drive the Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction which leads to a canting of local magnetic moments at the vdW interface and may thus stabilise novel 2D magnetic phases. While such emergent magnetic "interphases" offer a promising platform for spin-based electronics, direct spectroscopic evidence for them is still lacking. Here, we report Zeeman effects with Land\'e $g$-factors up to $\approx230$ at the interface of graphene and the vdW ferromagnet Fe$_3$GeTe$_2$. They arise from a magnetic interphase in which local-moment canting and itinerant orbital moments generated by the non-trivial band topology of Fe$_3$GeTe$_2$ conspire to cause a giant asymmetric level splitting when a magnetic field is applied. Exploiting the inelastic phonon gap of graphene, we can directly access the buried vdW interface to the Fe$_3$GeTe$_2$ by scanning tunnelling spectroscopy. Systematically analyzing the Faraday-like screening of the tip electric field by the graphene, we demonstrate the tunability of the constitutional interface dipole, as well as the Zeeman effect, by tip gating. Our findings are supported by density functional theory and electrostatic modelling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26662v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Wichmann, Mirco Sastges, Keda Jin, Jose Martinez-Castro, Tom G. Saunderson, Dongwook Go, Honey Boban, Samir Lounis, Lukasz Plucinski, Markus Ternes, Yuriy Mokrousov, F. Stefan Tautz, Felix L\"upke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractional Chern insulators on cylinders: Tao-Thouless states and beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26671</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26671v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Topological phases in two-dimensional quantum lattice models are often studied on cylinders for revealing different topological properties and making the problem numerically tractable. This makes a proper understanding of finite-circumference effects crucial for reliably extrapolating the results to the thermodynamic limit. Using matrix product states, we investigate these effects for the Laughlin-1/2 phase in the Hofstadter-Bose-Hubbard model, which can be viewed as the lattice discretization of the bosonic quantum Hall problem in the continuum. We propose a scaling of the model's parameters with the cylinder circumference that simultaneously approaches the continuum and thermodynamic limits. We find that different scaling schemes yield distinct topological signatures: we either retrieve a spontaneous formation of charge density wave ordering reminiscent of the Tao-Thouless states, known from the continuum problem on thin cylinders, or we find uniform states with a topological degeneracy that can be identified as minimally entangled states known from studies of chiral spin liquids on cylinders. Finally, we carry out a similar analysis of the non-Abelian Moore-Read phase in the same model. Our results clarify the role of symmetries in numerical studies of topologically ordered states on cylinders and highlight the role of lattice effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26671v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felix A. Palm, Chlo\'e Van Bastelaere, Laurens Vanderstraeten</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phases of Quasi-One-Dimensional Fractional Quantum (Anomalous) Hall - Superconductor Heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26686</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26686v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by recent observations of fractional Chern insulators (FCIs) in the vicinity of superconducting (SC) phases, we study fractional quantum (anomalous) Hall-superconductor heterostructures in the presence of $U(1)$ order-parameter fluctuations and particularly focus on the case of $\nu = 2/3$ quantum Hall states leading to $\mathbb Z_3$ parafermions. We first employ a phenomenological field theory to qualitatively determine the phase diagram. Furthermore, we generalize a previously established alternating pattern of superconductor and tunneling regions, coupled to fractional quantum Hall edge states, to map the problem onto a topological Josephson junction chain involving lattice parafermions. Using density matrix renormalization group simulations, we establish a phase diagram composed of Mott insulating phases and two different Luttinger liquids whose fundamental excitations carry charges 2e and $2e/3$, respectively. In agreement with analytical considerations using conformal field theory, we numerically find transitions of Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless (BKT) type as well as a continuous $\mathbb Z_3 \times U(1)$ second-order phase transition characterized by central charge c = 9/5. We finally extract information about a possible ground state degeneracy and comment on the stability of parafermionic edge states in the presence of fluctuations. These theoretical foundations can be expected to be of practical importance for gate-defined FCI-SC heterostructures in moir\'e materials, in which broad superconducting transitions indicative of strong order parameter fluctuations were observed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26686v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Steffen Bollmann, Andreas Haller, Jukka I. V\"ayrynen, Thomas L. Schmidt, Elio J. K\"onig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature dependent ferroelectricity in strained KTaO3 with machine learned force field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26693</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26693v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ferroelectric materials are a class of dielectrics that exhibit spontaneous polarization which can be reversed under an external electric field. The emergence of ferroelectric order in incipient ferroelectrics is a topic of considerable interest from both fundamental and applied perspectives. Among the various strategies explored, strain engineering has been proven to be a powerful method for tuning ferroelectric polarization in materials. In the case of KTaO3, first principles calculations have suggested that strain can drive a ferroelectric phase transition. In this study, we investigate the impact of in-plane uniaxial and biaxial strain, ranging from 0% to 1%, on pristine KTaO3 to explore its potential for ferroelectricity induction via inversion symmetry breaking. By integrating density functional theory calculations with the stochastic self-consistent harmonic approximation assisted by on the fly machine learned force field, we obtain accurate structural information and dynamical properties under varying strain conditions while incorporating higher-order anharmonic effects. Employing the Berry phase method, we obtained the ferroelectric polarization of the strained structures over the entire temperature range up to 300 K. Our findings provide valuable insights into the role of strain in stabilizing ferroelectricity in KTaO3, offering guidance for future experimental and theoretical studies on strain-engineered ferroelectric materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26693v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Zhu, Luigi Ranalli, Taikang Chen, Wei Ren, Cesare Franchini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Topological Phases in a Strongly Correlated Ladder Model via Entanglement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26713</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26713v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The interplay between non-trivial band topology and strong electronic correlations is a central challenge in modern condensed matter physics. We investigate this competition on a two-leg ladder model with a p-wave-like hybridisation between the legs. This model hosts a symmetry-protected topological phase in its non-interacting limit. Using the density-matrix renormalisation group algorithm, we compute the comprehensive quantum phase diagram in the presence of a repulsive inter-leg density-density interaction. Our analysis, based on entanglement entropy and the entanglement spectrum, reveals a fascinating dichotomy in the stability of the topological phase. We find a non-trivial change in the value of the edge entanglement entropy as we include interaction. Furthermore, we find that the phase boundary separating a trivial insulator phase and a topological one with winding number two remains robustly pinned at its non-interacting location, irrespective of the interaction strength. Variation of the effective conformal field theory's central charge near the critical line explains the robustness of the gap. In contrast, the transition to an insulating phase with winding number one is heavily renormalised, with the critical line shifting significantly as the interaction increases. By successfully mapping the phase diagram and identifying the distinct behaviours of the phase boundaries, our work clarifies how interactions can selectively preserve or destroy different aspects of a topological phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26713v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aminul Hussain, Nisa Ara, Rudranil Basu, Sudeshna Sen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Role of Phase Fluctuation in Dynamic Competition Between Charge Order and Superconductivity in Cuprates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26763</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26763v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Phase fluctuations are a key factor distinguishing nonthermal (ultrafast) and thermal phase transitions. Charge order in cuprates is characterized by short-range coherence while competing with superconductivity, and as such, it provides a representative case to study the role of phase fluctuation in coupled order parameter dynamics. In this work, we investigated the intertwined evolution of charge order and superconductivity in cuprate/manganite heterostructures using time-resolved resonant X-ray scattering. The resulting dynamics are analyzed within a space- and time-dependent nonperturbative model capturing both amplitude and phase dynamics. At low fluence, photo-induced suppression of superconductivity results in a nonthermal enhancement of charge order, underscoring the dynamic competition between charge order and superconductivity. With increasing fluence, the slowing down of melting and recovery dynamics is observed, indicating a critical role of phase fluctuations. At high fluence, both charge order and superconductivity remain suppressed for an extended time window due to decoupling between amplitude and phase dynamics and the delayed recovery of phase coherence. Our work underscores the importance of phase fluctuation for understanding the dynamic competition between order parameters in cuprates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26763v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingu Kang, Pavel E. Dolgirev, Chao C. Zhang, Hoyoung Jang, Byungjune Lee, Minseok Kim, Sang-Youn Park, Ronny Sutarto, Eugene Demler, Jae-Hoon Park, John Y. T. Wei, Riccardo Comin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin Polarons in Flat Band Ferromagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26798v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spin polarons are bound states of electrons and spin-flips that form above spin polarized electronic insulators.These bound states conventionally form in one of two settings: in frustrated lattices with dispersive bands -- where the motion of an electron preferences binding a nearby spin-flip -- or in topological flat bands -- where the Chern number enforces an effective dipolar interaction between electrons and spin flips. In this work, we report the formation of a spin polaron in a context that doesn't fall cleanly into either of these paradigms. In particular, we study the one-dimensional Mielke-Tasaki chain, a paradigmatic model of flat band ferromagnetism, which has an exact ferromagnetic ground state, trivial band topology, and quenched kinetic energy in its lowest band. Despite these features, our density matrix renormalization group simulations reveal the presence of spin polarons upon electron doping this model. More surprisingly, combining these numerics with analytic calculations, we show that polaron binding occurs when the interaction-induced kinetic energy of the model is zero -- contrary to intuition from kinetic magnetism -- and the glue binding the electrons and spin-flips arises from weak mixing with the model's dispersive band -- contrary to what occurs in topological flat bands. Our results open the doors to exploring how the quantum geometry of flat bands drives the formation of exotic charge carriers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26798v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saranesh Prembabu, Rahul Sahay, Stefan Divic, Ashvin Vishwanath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resonating-valence-bond superconductor from small Fermi surface in twisted bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26801</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26801v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mechanism of superconductivity in twisted bilayer graphene (TBG) remains one of the central problems in strongly correlated topological systems. The most intriguing question is about the nature of the normal state: is the Cooper pair formed from small Fermi surface or large Fermi surface? In this work we point out the possibility of a symmetric pseudogap metal with small hole pockets, dubbed as second Fermi liquid (sFL). In the sFL phase at $\nu=-2-x$, there is a two-component picture: two electrons mainly localize on the AA sites and form a paired singlet due to anti-Hund's coupling mediated by the optical phonon, while additional holes form small Fermi surfaces. The sFL phase corresponds to an intrinsically strongly interacting fixed point and violates the perturbative Luttinger theorem. We develop a unified framework to describe both a renormalized Fermi liquid (FL) and an sFL phase. We propose that the normal state of the TBG superconductor is the sFL phase, but it evolves toward the FL phase under increasing hole doping. The superconducting phase emerges from the sFL phase by transferring pairing of local moments to the mobile carriers. Interestingly, the superconducting gap can exhibit a nematic nodal $p_x$-pairing symmetry. This work provides, to our knowledge, the first unified theory that explains both the pseudogap metal above $T_c$ and the two-gap nematic superconductivity below it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26801v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jing-Yu Zhao, Ya-Hui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Divergent Series to Geometry: Resurgence of the Quantum Metric</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25907v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we analyze perturbative expansions of the quantum metric tensor (QMT) in anharmonic oscillators, focusing on quartic, sextic, and $d$-dimensional models. Using high-order perturbation theory, we show that the divergent QMT series exhibit factorial growth. Our analysis identifies universal non-perturbative scales, with coefficients displaying large-order behavior consistent with resurgence theory. Then, we apply resurgence and Borel--Pad\'e resummation to the QMT. Comparisons with exact diagonalization confirm that Borel--Pad\'e resummations yield accurate results, especially for the ground state. For completeness, we also present the analysis of the energy eigenvalues in the examples. Our findings extend resurgent techniques from energies to the QMT, highlighting the interplay between quantum geometry and non-perturbative physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25907v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcos J. Hern\'andez, Bogar D\'iaz, J. David Vergara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generative Image Restoration and Super-Resolution using Physics-Informed Synthetic Data for Scanning Tunneling Microscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25921</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25921v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Scanning tunnelling microscopy (STM) enables atomic-resolution imaging and atom manipulation, but its utility is often limited by tip degradation and slow serial data acquisition. Fabrication adds another layer of complexity since the tip is often subjected to large voltages, which may alter the shape of its apex, requiring it to be conditioned. Here, we propose a machine learning (ML) approach for image repair and super-resolution to alleviate both challenges. Using a dataset of only 36 pristine experimental images of Si(001):H, we demonstrate that a physics-informed synthetic data generation pipeline can be used to train several state-of-the-art flow-matching and diffusion models. Quantitative evaluation with metrics such as the CLIP Maximum Mean Discrepancy (CMMD) score and structural similarity demonstrates that our models are able to effectively restore images and offer a two- to fourfold reduction in image acquisition time by accurately reconstructing images from sparsely sampled data. Our framework has the potential to significantly increase STM experimental throughput by offering a route to reducing the frequency of tip-conditioning procedures and to enhancing frame rates in existing high-speed STM systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25921v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikola L. Kolev (London Centre for Nanotechnology, University College London, London, United Kingdom, Department of Electronic and Electrical Engineering, University College London, London, United Kingdom), Tommaso Rodani (University of Trieste, Trieste, Italy, AREA Science Park, Trieste, Italy), Neil J. Curson (London Centre for Nanotechnology, University College London, London, United Kingdom, Department of Electronic and Electrical Engineering, University College London, London, United Kingdom), Taylor J. Z. Stock (London Centre for Nanotechnology, University College London, London, United Kingdom, Department of Electronic and Electrical Engineering, University College London, London, United Kingdom), Alberto Cazzaniga (AREA Science Park, Trieste, Italy)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equivalent class of Emergent Single Weyl Fermion in 3d Topological States: gapless superconductors and superfluids Vs chiral fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25959v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this article, we put forward a practical but generic approach towards constructing a large family of $(3+1)$ dimension lattice models which can naturally lead to a single Weyl cone in the infrared (IR) limit. Our proposal relies on spontaneous charge $U(1)$ symmetry breaking to evade the usual no-go theorem of a single Weyl cone in a 3d lattice. We have explored three concrete paths in this approach, all involving fermionic topological symmetry protected states (SPTs). Path a) is to push a gapped SPT in a 3d lattice with time-reversal symmetry (or $T$-symmetry) to a gapless topological quantum critical point (tQCP) which involves a minimum change of topologies,i.e. $\delta N_w=2$ where $\delta N_w$ is the change of winding numbers across the tQCP. Path b) is to peal off excessive degrees of freedom in the gapped SPT via applying $T$-symmetry breaking fields which naturally result in a pair of gapless nodal points of real fermions. Path c) is a hybrid of a) and b) where tQCPs, with $\delta N_w \geq 2$, are further subject to time-reversal-symmetry breaking actions. In the infrared limit, all the lattice models with single Weyl fermions studied here are isomorphic to either a tQCP in a DIII class topological superconductor with a protecting $T$-symmetry, or its dual, a $T$-symmetry breaking superconducting nodal point phase, and therefore form an equivalent class. For a generic $T$-symmetric tQCP along Path a), the conserved-charge operators span a six-dimensional linear space while for a $T$-symmetry breaking gapless state along Path b), c), charge operators typically span a two-dimensional linear space instead. Finally, we pinpoint connections between three spatial dimensional lattice chiral fermion models and gapless real fermions that can naturally appear in superfluids or superconductors studied previously.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25959v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel Meyniel, Fei Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fermionic dynamics on a trapped-ion quantum computer beyond exact classical simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26300v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Simulation of the time-dynamics of fermionic many-body systems has long been predicted to be one of the key applications of quantum computers. Such simulations -- for which classical methods are often inaccurate -- are critical to advancing our knowledge and understanding of quantum chemistry and materials, underpinning a wide range of fields, from biochemistry to clean-energy technologies and chemical synthesis. However, the performance of all previous digital quantum simulations has been matched by classical methods, and it has thus far remained unclear whether near-term, intermediate-scale quantum hardware could offer any computational advantage in this area. Here, we implement an efficient quantum simulation algorithm on Quantinuum's System Model H2 trapped-ion quantum computer for the time dynamics of a 56-qubit system that is too complex for exact classical simulation. We focus on the periodic spinful 2D Fermi-Hubbard model and present evidence of spin-charge separation, where the elementary electron's charge and spin decouple. In the limited cases where ground truth is available through exact classical simulation, we find that it agrees with the results we obtain from the quantum device. Employing long-range Wilson operators to study deconfinement of the effective gauge field between spinons and the effective potential between charge carriers, we find behaviour that differs from predictions made by classical tensor network methods. Our results herald the use of quantum computing for simulating strongly correlated electronic systems beyond the capacity of classical computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26300v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Faisal Alam, Jan Lukas Bosse, Ieva \v{C}epait\.e, Adrian Chapman, Laura Clinton, Marcos Crichigno, Elizabeth Crosson, Toby Cubitt, Charles Derby, Oliver Dowinton, Paul K. Faehrmann, Steve Flammia, Brian Flynn, Filippo Maria Gambetta, Ra\'ul Garc\'ia-Patr\'on, Max Hunter-Gordon, Glenn Jones, Abhishek Khedkar, Joel Klassen, Michael Kreshchuk, Edward Harry McMullan, Lana Mineh, Ashley Montanaro, Caterina Mora, John J. L. Morton, Dhrumil Patel, Pete Rolph, Raul A. Santos, James R. Seddon, Evan Sheridan, Wilfrid Somogyi, Marika Svensson, Niam Vaishnav, Sabrina Yue Wang, Gethin Wright</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wrinkle-Induced Hexagonal Boron Nitride Nanochannels for Biomolecule Localization and Imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26370v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fluorescence-based single-molecule localization, transport, and sensing require spatial confinement to extend the molecule's residence time during imaging, sufficient temporal resolution to capture fast dynamics, and efficient fluorescence background suppression. Two-dimensional (2D) materials offer large-area, atomically flat surfaces suitable for massively parallel in-plane biomolecule imaging, yet achieving guided motion in one-dimensional confinements using top-down nanofabrication remains challenging. Here, we demonstrate that thermally induced wrinkles in exfoliated hexagonal boron nitride (hBN) act as self-assembled nanochannels that enable biomolecule confinement and imaging under wide-field fluorescence microscopy. By controlling annealing parameters and substrate properties, we obtain scalable and reproducible wrinkle networks whose densities and morphologies can be tuned. Structural characterization using atomic force and scanning electron microscopy is complemented by fluorescence imaging and Kelvin probe force microscopy, confirming that aqueous solutions fill and remain stably retained within the nanochannels for periods exceeding 10 hours. We further achieve selective ATTO647N-DNA localization and imaging in the one-dimensional channels through the formation of a graphene/hBN vertical heterostructure. The graphene overlayer serves as a quenching mask that suppresses background fluorescence both from high-strain hBN regions and from DNA adsorbed on top of the 2D layer. Overall, these results provide a scalable, lithography-free route for creating planar nanofluidic confinements fully compatible with single-molecule imaging. This platform enables fundamental nanobiology studies as well as on-chip biomolecule transport and sensing applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26370v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiliang Yang, Tetsuo Martynowicz, Allard Katan, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Sabina Caneva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perfect Particle Transmission through Duality Defects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26780</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26780v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study wavepackets that propagate across (a) topological interfaces in quantum spin systems exhibiting non-invertible symmetries and (b) duality defects coupling dual theories. We demonstrate that the transmission is always perfect, and that a particle traversing the interface is converted into a nonlocal string-like excitation. We give a systematic way of constructing such a defect by identifying its Hilbert space with the virtual bond dimension of the matrix product operator representing defect lines. Our work both gives an operational meaning to topological interfaces, and provides a lattice analogue of recent results solving the monopole paradox in quantum field theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26780v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Atsushi Ueda, Vic Vander Linden, Laurens Lootens, Jutho Haegeman, Paul Fendley, Frank Verstraete</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controlling the Exchange Field of Surface Spin Impurities via DC Voltages</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03866v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent advances in scanning tunneling microscopy have enabled quantum-coherent control of single surface spins via all-electric electron spin resonance (ESR). Such control requires magnetoelectric coupling, since spin resonance is a magnetic effect. We show that a magnetic tip induces a bias-dependent exchange field on a localized Anderson impurity via virtual particle exchange with the magnetic lead. This field differs from Heisenberg exchange and can be tuned, reversed, or suppressed by the bias voltage. Our model reproduces bias-controlled resonance shifts for S = 1/2 titanium atoms and Fe(II) phthalocyanine, enabling spin control via the exchange field and revealing the magnetoelectric mechanism behind all-electric ESR for spin-based quantum technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03866v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xue Zhang, Jose Reina-G\'alvez, Di'an Wu, Jan Martinek, Andreas J. Heinrich, Taeyoung Choi, Christoph Wolf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flux attachment theory of fractional excitonic insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05427</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.05427v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The search for fractional quantized Hall phases in the absence of a magnetic field has primarily targeted flat-band systems that mimic the features of a Landau level. In an alternative approach, the fractional excitonic insulator (FEI) has been proposed as a correlated electron-hole fluid that arises near a band inversion between bands of different angular momentum with strong interactions. It remains an interesting challenge to find Hamiltonians with realistic interactions that stabilize this state. Here, we describe composite boson and composite fermion theories that highlight the importance of $(p_x+ip_y)^m$ excitonic pairing in stabilizing FEIs in a class of band inversion models. We predict a sequence of Jain-like and Laughlin-like FEI states, the simplest of which has the topological order of the bosonic $\nu=1/2$ fractional quantized Hall state. We discuss implications for recent numerical studies on a chiral spin liquid phase in interacting Chern insulator models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.05427v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/x789-kxy3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 186602 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Steven Gassner, Ady Stern, C. L. Kane</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Persistent Homology-Based Indicator of Orientational Ordering in Two-Dimensional Quasi-Particle Systems Applied to Skyrmion Lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14688</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14688v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2D) particle systems, such as magnetic skyrmions, exhibit topological phase transitions between unique 2D phases. However, a simple and computationally efficient methodology to capture lattice configurational properties and construct an appropriate, easily calculable descriptor for phase identification remains elusive. Here, we propose an indicator for topological phase transitions using persistent homology (PH). PH offers novel insights beyond conventional indicators by capturing topological features derived from the configurational properties of the lattice. The proposed persistent-homology-based indicator, which selectively counts stable features in a persistence diagram, effectively traces the lattice's ordering changes, as confirmed by comparisons with the conventionally used measure of the ordering (the magnitude of the orientational order parameter $\langle|\Psi_6|\rangle$), typically used to identify lattice phases. We demonstrate the applicability of our indicator to experimental data, showing that it yields results consistent with those of simulations. This experimental validation highlights the robustness of the proposed method for real physical systems beyond idealized simulated systems. While our method is demonstrated in the context of skyrmion lattice systems, the approach is general and can be extended to other two-dimensional systems composed of interacting particles. As a key advantage, our indicator offers lower computational complexity than the conventionally used measures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14688v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michiki Taniwaki, Thomas Brian Winkler, Jan Roth\"orl, Raphael Gruber, Chiharu Mitsumata, Masato Kotsugi, Mathias Kl\"aui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shubnikov-de Haas Oscillations in 2D $\text{PtSe}_2$: A fermiological Charge Carrier Investigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15666</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.15666v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: High magnetic field and low temperature transport is carried out in order to characterize the charge carriers of $\text{PtSe}_2$. In particular, the Shubnikov-de Haas oscillations arising at applied magnetic field strengths $\gtrsim 4.5\,\text{T}$ are found to occur exclusively in plane and emerge at a layer thickness of $\approx 18\,\text{nm}$, increasing in amplitude and decreasing in frequency for thinner $\text{PtSe}_2$ flakes. Moreover, the quantum transport time, Berry phase, Dingle temperature and cyclotron mass of the charge carriers are ascertained. The emergence of weak antilocalization (WAL) lies in contrast to the presence of magnetic moments from Pt vacancies. An explanation is provided on how WAL and the Kondo effect can be observed within the same material. Detailed information about the charge carriers and transport phenomena in $\text{PtSe}_2$ is obtained, which is relevant for the design of prospective spintronic and orbitronic devices and for the realization of orbital Hall effect-based architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.15666v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julian Max Salchegger, Rajdeep Adhikari, Bogdan Faina, Alberta Bonanni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hierarchical Topological States without Dimension Reduction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.07048</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.07048v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Topological insulators exhibit boundary states protected by bulk band topology, a principle first established in quantum systems and later extended to classical waves, including phononics. Conventionally, an $n$-dimensional bulk with nontrivial topology hosts $(n-1)$-dimensional topologically protected boundary states, which may be further gapped out by breaking the symmetry that protects them, potentially leading to the emergence of $(n-2)$-dimensional, or even lower-dimensional topological states, as in higher-order topological insulators. In this work, we introduce an alternative mechanism for gapping out topological states and forming new topological modes within the resulting gap without further unit-cell symmetry breaking or dimension reduction. Using one- and two-dimensional Su-Schrieffer-Heeger (SSH) models, we show that controlled repositioning of topological domain walls enables the construction of hierarchical unit cells that gap out the original domain-wall states while preserving the underlying symmetry. This process produces higher-hierarchical-level topological states, characterized by a generalized winding number, and can be iterated to realize multiple - potentially infinite - hierarchical levels of topological states. Our approach expands the conventional topological classification and offers a versatile route for engineering complex networks of protected modes in higher dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.07048v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joel R. Pyfrom, Kai Sun, Jihong A. Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling up the transcorrelated density matrix renormalization group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.07441</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.07441v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Explicitly correlated methods, such as the transcorrelated method which shifts a Jastrow or Gutzwiller correlator from the wave function to the Hamiltonian, are designed for high-accuracy calculations of electronic structures, but their application to larger systems has been hampered by the computational cost. We develop improved techniques for the transcorrelated density matrix renormalization group (DMRG), in which the ground state of the transcorrelated Hamiltonian is represented as a matrix product state (MPS), and demonstrate large-scale calculations of the ground-state energy of the two-dimensional Fermi-Hubbard model. Our developments stem from three technical inventions: (i) constructing matrix product operators (MPO) of transcorrelated Hamiltonians with low bond dimension and high sparsity, (ii) exploiting the entanglement structure of the ground states to increase the accuracy of the MPS representation, and (iii) optimizing the non-linear parameter of the Gutzwiller correlator to mitigate the non-variational nature of the transcorrelated method. We examine systems of size up to $12 \times 12$ lattice sites, four times larger than previous transcorrelated DMRG studies, and demonstrate that transcorrelated DMRG yields significant improvements over standard non-transcorrelated DMRG for equivalent computational effort. Transcorrelated DMRG reduces the error of the ground state energy by $3\times$-$17 \times$, with the smallest improvement seen for a small system at half-filling and the largest improvement in a dilute closed-shell system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.07441v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/nzrt-l2j1</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Corbett, Akimasa Miyake</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ginzburg-Landau theory for unconventional surface superconductivity in PtBi$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.02415v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent experimental evidence suggests the presence of an unconventional, nodal surface-su\-per\-con\-duc\-ting state in trigonal PtBi\textsubscript{2}. We construct a Ginzburg--Landau theory for the three superconducting order parameters, which correspond to the three irreducible representations of the point group $C_{3v}$. The irreducible representations $A_1$ and $A_2$ are the most likely. We develop a systematic method to determine the symmetry-allowed terms and apply it to derive all terms up to fourth order in the three order parameters. The Ginzburg--Landau functional also includes coupling to the magnetic field. The functional is employed to determine the effect of an applied uniform magnetic field on the nodal structure for $A_1$ and $A_2$ pairing. The results facilitate clear-cut experimental differentiation between these symmetries. We also predict field-induced helical superconductivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.02415v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/kkqg-ntcz</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 144519 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Harald Waje, Fabian Jakubczyk, Jeroen van den Brink, Carsten Timm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collective Fluorescence of Graphene Quantum Dots on a surface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22458</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.22458v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This study explores the organization of graphene quantum dots on the surface of monocrystalline halide perovskite. We show that graphene quantum dots tends to aggregate on the surface of perovskite unlike in solution or on other substrates, even at very low concentration of the initial solution that should yield single-molecule samples. Spectral analysis on small clusters shows a back-and-forth dynamical transition between an uncoupled, monomer-like state, and an excimer state. Following this "dance" between states, a drastic one-way increase in fluorescence intensity combined with a shortening of the excited state lifetime has been observed on some clusters. This behavior is related to the emission of a collective state that may be a consequence of the dynamical organization of graphene quantum dots under illumination on the surface of the perovksite.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.22458v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hugo Levy-Falk, Suman Sarkar, Thanh Trung Huynh, Daniel Medina-Lopez, Lauren Hurley, Oc\'eane Capelle, Muriel Bouttemy, Ga\"elle Tripp\'e-Allard, St\'ephane Campidelli, Lo\"ic Rondin, Elsa Cassette, Emmanuelle Deleporte, Jean-S\'ebastien Lauret</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of spin-conserving two-spinon continuum in the $S$=1/2 antiferromagnetic chain system Sr$_2$CuO$_3$ using Cu $K$-edge resonant inelastic x-ray scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.22492v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report a Cu $K$-edge resonant inelastic x-ray scattering (RIXS) study of spin excitations in the $S$=1/2 antiferromagnetic chain system Sr$_2$CuO$_3$. The spectral weight observed below the charge-transfer gap appears in two-spinon continuum, indicating the fractionalization of a spin-conserving ($\Delta S = 0$) magnetic excitation into two-spinon states. The intensity of these excitations reaches a maximum near the midpoint between the center and the boundary of the Brillouin zone, and decreases toward the zone boundary; this behavior contrasts with that of the spin-flip ($\Delta S = 1$) excitations typically observed via inelastic neutron scattering or Cu $L_3$-edge RIXS. The momentum dependence of the intensity is described by the spin-exchange dynamical structure factor. A phenomenological analysis of the symmetry between the polarization and the $d$ orbital explains the resonance condition for the two-spinon excitations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.22492v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/53wr-vpcp</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Kenji Ishii, Kenji Tsutsui, Takayuki Kawamata, Yoji Koike</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature Dependence of the Momentum-Resolved Static Spin Susceptibility in a Mott-Proximate Cuprate Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16884v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents the temperature dependence of the static spin susceptibility at $\mathbf{q} = (\pi, \pi)$ and $\mathbf{q} = (\pi, 0)$ in a Mott-proximate cuprate model with an antinodal pseudogap -- a model system for high-temperature superconducting (HTSC) cuprates.
  The results show the susceptibility onset temperature tracks the critical temperature ($T_c$) of HTSCs with a comparable scale across the electron filling factor. Also, as the electron filling decreases and the chemical potential approaches the antinodal van Hove region, the susceptibility at $\mathbf{q}=(\pi,0)$ -- the axial particle-hole response -- grows markedly.
  It suggests that the emergence of cuprate superconductivity correlates with a suppression of low-energy antinodal spin response and associated particle-hole excitations, which would otherwise dephase $d$-wave pairing, commonly attributed to spin fluctuations. In this context, the pseudogap partially suppresses antinodal spectral weight near $\omega = 0$, thereby reducing the low-$\omega$ particle-hole phase space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16884v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keishichiro Tanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New Framework for Quantum Phases in Open Systems: Steady State of Imaginary-Time Lindbladian Evolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03239v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This study delves into the concept of quantum phases in open quantum systems, examining the shortcomings of existing approaches that focus on steady states of Lindbladians and highlighting their limitations in capturing key phase transitions. In contrast to these methods, we introduce the concept of imaginary-time Lindbladian evolution as an alternative framework. This new approach defines gapped quantum phases in open systems through the spectrum properties of the imaginary-Liouville superoperator. We find that, in addition to all pure gapped ground states, the Gibbs state of a stabilizer Hamiltonian at any finite temperature can also be characterized by our scheme, demonstrated through explicit construction. Moreover, the closing of the imaginary Liouville gap is associated with the divergence of the Markov length, which has recently been proposed as an indicator of phase transitions in open quantum systems. To illustrate the effectiveness of this framework, we apply it to investigate the phase diagram for open systems with $\mathbb{Z}_2^{\sigma}\times \mathbb{Z}_2^{\tau}$ symmetry, including cases with nontrivial average symmetry protected topological order or spontaneous symmetry breaking order. Our findings demonstrate universal properties at quantum criticality, such as nonanalytic behaviors of steady-state observables, divergence of correlation lengths, and closing of the imaginary-Liouville gap. These results advance our understanding of quantum phase transitions in open quantum systems. In contrast, we find that the steady states of real-time Lindbladians do not provide an effective framework for characterizing phase transitions in open systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03239v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuchen Guo, Ke Ding, Shuo Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complex wave functions, CPT and quantum field theory for classical generalized Ising models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24392v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The quantum or quantum field theory concept of a complex wave function is useful for understanding the information transport in classical statistical generalized Ising models.
  We relate complex conjugation to the discrete transformations charge conjugation ($C$), parity ($P$) and time reversal ($T$).
  A subclass of generalized Ising models are probabilistic cellular automata (PCA) with deterministic updating and probabilistic initial conditions.
  Simple two-dimensional PCA correspond to discretized quantum field theories for Majorana--Weyl, Weyl or Dirac fermions.
  Momentum and energy are conserved statistical observables.
  For PCA describing free massless fermions we investigate the vacuum and field operators for particle excitations.
  For the correlation function one finds the Lorentz-invariant Feynman propagator of quantum field theory.
  Furthermore, these automata admit probabilistic boundary conditions that correspond to thermal equilibrium with the quantum Fermi--Dirac distribution.
  PCA with updating sequences of propagation and interaction steps can realize a rich variety of discrete quantum field theories for fermions with interactions.
  For information theory the quantum formalism for PCA sheds new light on deterministic computing or signal processing with probabilistic input.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24392v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christof Wetterich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological crystals and soliton lattices in a Gross-Neveu model with Hilbert-space fragmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18675</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18675v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We explore the finite-density phase diagram of the single-flavour Gross-Neveu-Wilson (GNW) model using matrix product state (MPS) simulations. At zero temperature and along the symmetry line of the phase diagram, we find a sequence of inhomogeneous ground states that arise through a real-space version of the mechanism of Hilbert-space fragmentation. For weak interactions, doping the symmetry-protected topological (SPT) phase of the GNW model leads to localized charges or holes at periodic arrangements of immobile topological defects separating the fragmented subchains: a topological crystal. Increasing the interactions, we observe a transition into a parity-broken phase with a pseudoscalar condensate displaying a modulated periodic pattern. This soliton lattice is a sequence of topological charges corresponding to anti-kinks, which also bind the doped fermions at their respective centers. Out of this symmetry line, we show that quasi-spiral profiles appear with a characteristic wavevector set by the density $k = 2{\pi}{\rho}$, providing non-perturbative evidence for chiral spirals beyond the large-N limit. These results demonstrate that various exotic inhomogeneous phases can arise in lattice field theories, and motivate the use of quantum simulators to confirm such QCD-inspired phenomena in future experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18675v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergio Cerezo-Roquebr\'un, Simon Hands, Alejandro Bermudez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
