<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 04:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Time-dependent correlations of the Edwards-Anderson order parameter above the spin-glass transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08955</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08955v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In 1975 Edwards and Anderson introduced a new paradigm that interacting quenched systems, such as a spin-glass, have a phase transition in which long time memory of spatial patterns is realized without spatial correlations. We show here that the information about the time-dependent correlations above the spin-glass transition are embedded in the four spin correlations of the intensity of speckle pattern. This encodes the spin-orientation memory and can be measured by the technique of resonant magnetic x-ray photon correlation spectroscopy (RM- XPCS). We have implemented this method to observe and accurately characterize the critical slowing down of the spin orientation fluctuations in the classic metallic spin glass alloy $Cu_{1-x}{Mn}_x$ over time scales of ${2}$ sec. to $2 \times 10^{\mathbf{4}}$ secs. Remarkably the divergence of the correlation time as a function of temperature is consistent with the Vogel-Vulcher law, universally used to characterize the viscous relaxation time in structural glasses. Our method also opens the way for studying phase transitions in systems such as spin ices, quantum spin liquids, the structural glass transition, as well as possibly provide new perspectives on the multifarious problems in which spin-glass concepts have found applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08955v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingjin Song, Sheena K. K. Patel, Rupak Bhattacharya, Yi Yang, Sudip Pandey, Xiao M. Chen, Eric Lee-Wong, Kalyan Sasmal, M. Brian Maple, Eric E. Fullerton, Sujoy Roy, Claudio Mazzoli, Chandra M. Varma, Sunil K. Sinha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dichotomy in Low- and High-energy Band Renormalizations in Trilayer Nickelate $La_{4}Ni_{3}O_{10}$: a Comparison with Cuprates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08974</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08974v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Band renormalizations comprise crucial insights for understanding the intricate roles of electron-boson coupling and electron correlation in emergent phenomena such as superconductivity. In this study, by combining high-resolution angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy and theoretical calculations, we systematically investigate the electronic structure of the trilayer nickelate superconductor $La_{4}Ni_{3}O_{10}$ at ambient pressure. We reveal a dichotomy in the electronic band renormalizations of $La_{4}Ni_{3}O_{10}$ in comparison to cuprate superconductors. At a high energy scale of hundreds of meV, its band structure is strongly renormalized by electron correlation effect enhanced by Hund coupling. The resultant waterfall-like dispersions resemble the high-energy kinks in cuprate superconductors. However, at low energy scales of tens of meV, the dispersive bands are nearly featureless and devoid of any resolvable electron-boson interactions, in drastic contrast to the low-energy kinks observed in cuprates and other correlated 3d transition-metal compounds. The dichotomic band renormalizations highlight the disparity between nickelate and cuprate superconductors and emphasize the importance of strong electron-correlation in the superconductivity of Ruddlesden-Popper phase nickelates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08974v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>X. Du, Y. L. Wang, Y. D. Li, Y. T. Cao, M. X. Zhang, C. Y. Pei, J. M. Yang, W. X. Zhao, K. Y. Zhai, Z. K. Liu, Z. W. Li, J. K. Zhao, Z. T. Liu, D. W. Shen, Z. Li, Y. He, Y. L. Chen, Y. P. Qi, H. J. Guo, L. X. Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-monotonic band flattening near the magic angle of twisted bilayer MoTe$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08993</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08993v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Twisted bilayer MoTe$_2$ (tMoTe$_2$) is an emergent platform for exploring exotic quantum phases driven by the interplay between nontrivial band topology and strong electron correlations. Direct experimental access to its momentum-resolved electronic structure is essential for uncovering the microscopic origins of the correlated topological phases therein. Here, we report angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) measurements of tMoTe$_2$, revealing pronounced twist-angle-dependent band reconstruction shaped by orbital character, interlayer coupling, and moir\'e potential modulation. Density functional theory (DFT) captures the qualitative evolution, yet underestimates key energy scales across twist angles, highlighting the importance of electronic correlations. Notably, the hole effective mass at the K point exhibits a non-monotonic dependence on twist angle, peaking near 2{\deg}, consistent with band flattening at the magic angle predicted by continuum models. Via electrostatic gating and surface dosing, we further visualize the evolution of electronic structure versus doping, enabling direct observation of the conduction band minimum and confirm tMoTe$_2$ as a direct band gap semiconductor. These results establish a spectroscopic foundation for modeling and engineering emergent quantum phases in this moir\'e platform.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08993v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yujun Deng, William Holtzmann, Ziyan Zhu, Timothy Zaklama, Paulina Majchrzak, Takashi Taniguchi, Kenji Watanabe, Makoto Hashimoto, Donghui Lu, Chris Jozwiak, Aaron Bostwick, Eli Rotenberg, Liang Fu, Thomas P. Devereaux, Xiaodong Xu, Zhi-Xun Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sliding-tuned Quantum Geometry in Moir\'e Systems: Nonlinear Hall Effect and Quantum Metric Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09077</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09077v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Sliding is a ubiquitous phenomenon in moir\'e systems, but its direct influence on moir\'e bands, especially in multi-twist moir\'e systems, has been largely overlooked to date. Here, we theoretically show that sliding provides a unique pathway to engineer the quantum geometry (Berry curvature and quantum metric) of moir\'e bands, exhibiting distinct advantages over conventional strategies. Specifically, we first suggest alternating twisted trilayer $\mathrm{MoTe_2}$ (AT3L-$\mathrm{MoTe_2}$) and chirally twisted triple bilayer graphene (CT3BLG) as two ideal paradigmatic systems for probing sliding-engineered quantum geometric phenomena. Then, two sliding-induced exotic quantum geometry phenomena are predicted: (1) an intrinsic nonlinear Hall effect via sliding-produced non-zero Berry curvature dipole, with CT3BLG as an ideal platform; (2) significant quantum metric modulation in AT3L-$\mathrm{MoTe_2}$, enabling tests of quantum geometric criteria for fractional Chern insulating state (FCIS). Our work establishes sliding as a new degree of freedom for manipulating quantum geometry of moir\'e bands, which emerges as a signature phenomenon of multi-twist moir\'e systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09077v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shi-Ping Ding, Miao Liang, Tian-Le Wu, Meng-Hao Wu, Jing-Tao L\"u, Jin-Hua Gao, X. C. Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing Electronic Structure of Twisted Bilayer MoTe2 in Devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09080</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09080v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The pursuit of emergent quantum phenomena lies at the forefront of modern condensed matter physics. A recent breakthrough in this arena is the discovery of the fractional quantum anomalous Hall effect (FQAHE) in twisted bilayer MoTe2 (tbMoTe2), marking a paradigm shift and establishing a versatile platform for exploring the intricate interplay among topology, magnetism, and electron correlations. While significant progress has been made through both optical and electrical transport measurements, direct experimental insights into the electronic structure - crucial for understanding and modeling this system - have remained elusive. Here, using spatially and angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy ({\mu}-ARPES), we directly map the electronic band structure of tbMoTe2. We identify the valence band maximum, whose partial filling underlies the FQAHE, at the K points, situated approximately 150 meV above the {\Gamma} valley. By fine-tuning the doping level via in-situ alkali metal deposition, we also resolve the conduction band minimum at the K point, providing direct evidence that tbMoTe2 exhibits a direct band gap - distinct from all previously known moire bilayer transition metal dichalcogenide systems. These results offer critical insights for theoretical modeling and advance our understanding of fractionalized excitations and correlated topological phases in this emergent quantum material.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09080v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheng Chen, William Holtzmann, Xiao-Wei Zhang, Eric Anderson, Shanmei He, Yuzhou Zhao, Chris Jozwiak, Aaron Bostwick, Eli Rotenberg, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Ting Cao, Di Xiao, Xiaodong Xu, Yulin Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three-dimensional flat bands and possible interlayer triplet pairing superconductivity in the alternating twisted NbSe$_2$ moir\'e bulk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09109</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09109v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Moir\'e superlattices hosting flat bands and correlated states have emerged as a focal topic in condensed matter research. Through first-principles calculations, we investigate three-dimensional flat bands in alternating twisted NbSe$_2$ moir\'e bulk structures. These structures exhibit enhanced interlayer interactions compared to twisted bilayer configurations. Our results demonstrate that moir\'e bulks undergo spontaneous large-scale structural relaxation, resulting in the formation of remarkably flat energy bands at twist angles $\leq$ 7.31{\deg}. The $k_z$-dependent dispersion of flat bands across different moir\'e bulks reveals their intrinsic three-dimensional character. The presence of out-of-plane mirror symmetry in these moir\'e bulk structures suggests possible interlayer triplet superconducting pairing mechanisms that differ from those in twisted bilayer systems. Our work paves the way for exploring potential three-dimensional flat bands in other moir\'e bulk systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09109v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuang Liu, Peng Chen, Shihao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bilateral Hydrogenation Realizes High-Temperature Quantum Anomalous Hall Insulator in 2D Cr$_{\text{2}}$Ge$_{\text{2}}$Te$_{\text{6}}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09164v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The pursuit of high-temperature quantum anomalous Hall (QAH) insulators faces fundamental challenges, including narrow topological gaps and low Curie temperatures ($T_{\text{C}}$) in existing materials. Here, we propose a transformative strategy using bilateral hydrogenation to engineer a robust QAH state in the topologically trivial ferromagnetic semiconductor Cr$_{\text{2}}$Ge$_{\text{2}}$Te$_{\text{6}}$. First-principles calculations reveal that hydrogenation induces a topological phase transition in Cr$_{\text{2}}$Ge$_{\text{2}}$Te$_{\text{6}}$ by shifting its Dirac points-originally embedded in the conduction bands-to the vicinity of the Fermi level in Cr$_{\text{2}}$Ge$_{\text{2}}$Te$_{\text{6}}$H$_{\text{6}}$. This electronic restructuring, coupled with spin-orbit coupling, opens a global topological gap of 118.1 meV, establishing a robust QAH state with Chern number $C=$ 3. Concurrently, hydrogenation enhances ferromagnetic superexchange via the $d_{z^{2}}$-$p_{z}$-$d_{xz}$ channel, significantly strengthening the nearest-neighbor coupling $J_{\text{1}}$ by 3.06 times and switching $J_{\text{2}}$ from antiferromagnetic to ferromagnetic. Monte Carlo simulations predict a high $T_{\text{C}}$ = 198 K, sustained well above liquid nitrogen temperature and far exceeding pristine Cr$_{\text{2}}$Ge$_{\text{2}}$Te$_{\text{6}}$ (28 K). This work establishes surface hydrogenation as a powerful route to simultaneously control topology and magnetism in 2D materials, unlocking high-temperature QAH platforms for dissipationless spintronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09164v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiang Li, Xin-Wei Yi, Jing-Yang You, Jia-Wen Li, Qing-Han Yang, Gang Su, Bo Gu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surfaces and interfaces of infinite-layer nickelates studied by dynamical mean-field theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09184</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09184v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Infinite-layer nickelate superconductors are typically synthesized as thin films and thus include, besides the more bulk-like inner layers, distinct surface and interface layers in contact with the vacuum and substrate, respectively. Here, we employ density-functional theory and dynamical mean-field theory to investigate how electronic correlations influence these surface and interface regions. Our results show that electronic correlations can significantly modify the electronic structure, even driving surface layers into a Mott-insulating state with a 3$d^8$ electronic configuration. Moreover, surface termination effects induce a polar field that can shift the $\Gamma$ and $A$ pocket above the Fermi level, even for the undoped parent compound NdNiO$_2$. Finally, for an $n$-type interface, often synthesized experimentally, we find the Ti 3$d$ orbitals to become electron doped.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09184v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonard M. Verhoff, Liang Si, Karsten Held</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fragmented Spin Liquid and Shadow Pinch Points in Dipole-Octupole Pyrochlore Spin Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09205</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09205v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the classical dipole-octupole pyrochlore spin systems in an external magnetic field along the $[111]$ direction. We identify an intermediate fragmented spin liquid phase that precedes full spin saturation, characterized by the coexistence of three phenomena: U(1) spin liquid on the Kagome planes, spontaneous $\mathbb{Z}_2$ symmetry breaking, and partial spin polarization from explicit symmetry breaking. We show that even without dipolar interactions, the dipolar components can form a spin liquid driven by the octupolar spin liquid. The physics manifests itself experimentally as shadow pinch points: low-intensity pinch points underlying the strong Bragg peaks. We discuss how these discoveries are directly relevant to various experiments on dipole-octupole pyrochlore materials, including neutron scattering, magnetization, and magnetostriction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09205v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Lozano-G\'omez, Han Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unusual ferromagnetic band evolution and high Curie temperature in monolayer 1T-CrTe2 on bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09249</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09249v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: 2D van der Waals ferromagnets hold immense promise for spintronic applications due to their controllability and versatility. Despite their significance, the realization and in-depth characterization of ferromagnetic materials in atomically thin single layers, close to the true 2D limit, has been scarce. Here, a successful synthesis of monolayer (ML) 1T-CrTe2 is reported on a bilayer graphene (BLG) substrate via molecular beam epitaxy. Using angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy and magneto-optical Kerr effect measurements, that the ferromagnetic transition is observed at the Curie temperature (TC) of 150 K in ML 1T-CrTe2 on BLG, accompanied by unconventional temperature-dependent band evolutions. The spectroscopic analysis and first-principle calculations reveal that the ferromagnetism may arise from Goodenough-Kanamori super-exchange and double-exchange interactions, enhanced by the lattice distortion and the electron doping from the BLG substrate. These findings provide pivotal insight into the fundamental understanding of mechanisms governing 2D ferromagnetism and offer a pathway for engineering higher TC in 2D materials for future spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09249v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/smll.202506671</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Small 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kyoungree Park, Ji-Eun Lee, Dongwook Kim, Yong Zhong, Camron Farhang, Hyobeom Lee, Hayoon Im, Woojin Choi, Seha Lee, Seungrok Mun, Kyoo Kim, Jun Woo Choi, Hyejin Ryu, Jing Xia, Heung-Sik Kim, Choongyu Hwang, Ji Hoon Shim, Zhi-Xun Shen, Sung-Kwan Mo, Jinwoong Hwang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic order induced symmetry breaking in lattice dynamics of Co$_3$Sn$_2$S$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09253v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Based on the molecular Berry curvature (MBC) framework, we develop an \textit{ab initio} algorithm to capture the quantitative effects of magnetic order on lattice dynamics. Using the ferromagnetic Weyl semimetal Co$_3$Sn$_2$S$_2$ as a prototype, we show that electronic-order-driven phonon symmetry breaking requires spin-orbit coupling (SOC) and leads to an MBC term that breaks both time-reversal ($\mathcal{T}$) and mirror symmetries. We demonstrate that mirror-symmetry breaking is essential to account for the experimentally observed phonon splitting, $\mathcal{T}$-breaking alone is insufficient. The MBC is widely distributed across the Brillouin zone, giving rise to significant off-$\Gamma$ effects. Our results agree well with experiments and establish a framework for predicting large phonon magnetism in magnetic materials with strong spin-orbit coupling and electron-phonon coupling. This work also suggests new avenues for controlling non-reciprocal phonon transport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09253v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuai Zhang, Mengqi Wang, Tiantian Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Transformer Backflow for Solving Momentum-Resolved Ground States of Strongly Correlated Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09275</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09275v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Strongly correlated materials, such as twisted transition-metal dichalcogenide homobilayers, host a variety of exotic quantum phases but remain notoriously difficult to solve due to strong interactions. We introduce a powerful neural network ansatz, Neural Transformer Backflow (NTB), formulated within a multi-band projection framework. It naturally enforces momentum conservation and enables efficient calculations of momentum-resolved ground states. NTB attains high accuracy on small systems and scales to higher bands and larger system sizes far beyond the reach of exact diagonalization. By evaluating observables such as the structure factor and momentum distribution, we show that NTB captures diverse correlated states in tMoTe$_2$, including charge density waves, fractional Chern insulators, and anomalous Hall Fermi liquids, within a unified framework. Our approach paves the way for understanding and discovering novel phases of matter in strongly correlated materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09275v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lixing Zhang, Di luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scanning photocurrent microscopy and its application to one- and two-dimensional materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09390</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09390v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The electrical response of a material when illuminated with light is a key to many optoelectronic device applications. This so-called photoresponse typically has a non-uniform spatial distribution through the active device area, and the ability to spatially resolve the photoresponse enables an in-depth understanding of the underlying physical mechanisms. Scanning photocurrent microscopy (SPCM) is a method that allows the spatial mapping of the photoresponse by raster scanning a focused laser beam over the sample. SPCM is becoming more popular due to its simplicity and power in unraveling fundamental optoelectronic processes. In this review, first, we provide the fundamentals of SPCM to lay the basics for the subsequent discussions. Then, we focus on the literature that employs SPCM to identify the photoresponse of one- and two-dimensional materials. We discuss SPCM measurement results of common materials in detail and introduce a systematic approach to interpreting the SPCM measurements. We have given particular emphasis on the photothermal mechanisms that are excited by the focused laser beam and critically reviewed studies in the literature from the perspective of laser-induced heating of the electronic and the lattice degrees of freedom. Finally, we discuss the shortcomings of SPCM in determining the mechanisms leading to the photoresponse.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09390v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>TAlip Serkan Kas{\i}rga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relativistic Mott transition, high-order van Hove singularity, and mean-field phase diagram of twisted double bilayer WSe${}_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09398</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09398v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent experiments on twisted double bilayer tungsten diselenide have demonstrated that moir\'e semiconductors can be used to realize a relativistic Mott transition, i.e., a quantum phase transition from a Dirac semimetal to a correlated insulating state, by twist-angle tuning. In addition, signatures of van Hove singularities were observed in the material's moir\'e valence bands, suggesting further potential for the emergence of strongly-correlated states in this moir\'e semiconductor. Based on a Bistritzer-MacDonald-type continuum model, we provide a detailed analysis of the twist-angle dependence of the system's moir\'e valence band structure, focusing on both, the evolution of the Dirac excitations and the Fermi-surface structure with its Lifshitz transitions across the van Hove fillings. We exhibit that the twist angle can be used to band engineer a high-order van Hove singularity with power-law exponent~$-1/4$ in the density of states, which can be accessed by gate tuning of the hole filling. We then study the magnetic phase diagram of an effective Hubbard model for twisted double bilayer tungsten diselenide on the effective moir\'e honeycomb superlattice with tight-binding parameters fitted to the two topmost bands of the continuum model. To that end, we employ a self-consistent Hartree-Fock mean-field approach in real space. Fixing the angle-dependent Hubbard interaction based on the experimental findings, we explore a broad parameter range of twist angle, filling, and temperature. We find a rich variety of magnetic states that we expect to be accessible in future experiments by twist or gate tuning, including, e.g., a non-coplanar spin-density wave with non-zero spin chirality and a half-metallic uniaxial spin-density wave.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09398v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bilal Hawashin, Julian Kleeschulte, David Kurz, Michael M. Scherer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quenched disorder and the BCS-BEC crossover in the Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09399</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09399v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the impact of weak quenched disorder on the BCS-BEC crossover in the Hubbard model within a functional-integral framework. By deriving the thermodynamic potential up to second order in both the disorder potential and pairing fluctuations, we obtain self-consistent expressions for the number equation, condensate fraction, superfluid fraction and sound speed at zero temperature. In the dilute BEC limit, our results analytically reproduce the known continuum limits of weakly interacting bosons, where weak disorder depletes the superfluid more strongly than the condensate due to broken translational symmetry, and enhances the sound speed through the overcompensation of the static compressibility. These findings establish a unified and controlled framework for describing the BCS-BEC crossover in disordered lattice models, and they provide a foundation for future extensions to finite temperatures and multiband Hubbard models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09399v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Iskin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the magnetic landscape of easily-exfoliable two-dimensional materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09531</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09531v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic materials often exhibit complex energy landscapes with multiple local minima, each corresponding to a self-consistent electronic structure solution. Finding the global minimum is challenging, and heuristic methods are not always guaranteed to succeed. Here, we apply a recently developed automated workflow to systematically explore the energy landscape of 194 magnetic monolayers obtained from the Materials Cloud 2D crystals database and determine their ground-state magnetic order. Our approach enables effective control and sampling of orbital occupation matrices, allowing rapid identification of local minima. We find a diverse set of self-consistent collinear metastable states, further enriched by Hubbard-corrected energy functionals, when the $U$ parameters have been computed from first principles using linear-response theory. We categorise the monolayers by their magnetic ordering and highlight promising candidates. Our results include 109 ferromagnetic, 83 antiferromagnetic, and 2 altermagnetic monolayers, along with 12 novel ferromagnetic half-metals with potential for spintronics technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09531v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fatemeh Haddadi, Davide Campi, Flaviano dos Santos, Nicolas Mounet, Louis Ponet, Nicola Marzari, Marco Gibertini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flux-driven charge and spin transport in a dimerized Hubbard ring with Fibonacci modulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09542</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09542v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study quantum transport in a one-dimensional Hubbard ring with dimerized nearest-neighbor hoppings and a Fibonacci-modulated onsite potential. For non-interacting case our analysis reveals that at half-filling, the charge current along with the Drude weight decreases with increasing onsite potential when inter-cell hopping dominates over the intra-cell hopping, while for dominating intra-cell hopping it shows non-monotonic behavior with sharp peak at certain critical modulation strength, indicating enhanced transport. Moving away from half-filling gives rise to re-entrant features in both quantities at fillings associated with Fibonacci numbers. On the other hand, in spin-imbalanced systems, both spin and charge current shows multiple peaks and re-entrant behavior, tunable via hopping dimerization and filling. Including the on-site Hubbard interaction preserves the re-entrant behavior in current and moreover favors finite transport which is absent in the non-interacting ring. These results reveal rich interplay among Fibonacci modulated potential, electron fillings, hopping dimerization and interaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09542v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Souvik Roy, Soumya Ranjan Padhi, Tapan Mishra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong long-wavelength electron-phonon coupling in Ta$_2$Ni(Se,S)$_5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09620</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09620v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The search for intrinsic excitonic insulators (EI) has long been confounded by coexisting electron-phonon coupling in bulk materials. Although the ground state of an EI may be difficult to differentiate from density-wave orders or other structural instabilities, excited states offer distinctive signatures. One way to provide clarity is to directly inspect the phonon spectral function for long wavelength broadening due to phonon interaction with the high velocity EI phason. Here, we report that the quasi-one-dimensional (quasi-1D) EI candidate Ta$_2$NiSe$_5$ shows extremely anisotropic phonon broadening and softening in the semimetallic normal state. In contrast, such a behavior is completely absent in the broken symmetry state of Ta$_2$NiSe$_5$ and in the isostructural Ta$_2$NiS$_5$, where the latter has a fully gapped normal state. By contrasting the expected phonon lifetimes in the BCS and BEC limits of a putative EI, our results suggest that the phase transition in Ta$_2$Ni(Se,S)$_5$ family is closely related to strong interband electron-phonon coupling. We experimentally determine the dimensionless coupling $\frac{g}{\omega_0}\sim10$, showing Ta$_2$Ni(Se,S)$_5$ as a rare "ultra-strong coupling" material.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09620v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhibo Kang, Burak Gurlek, Weichen Tang, Xiang Chen, Jacob P. C. Ruff, Ahmet Alatas, Ayman Said, Robert J. Birgeneau, Steven G. Louie, Angel Rubio, Simone Latini, Yu He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kondo destruction quantum critical point: fixed point annihilation and thermodynamic stability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09627</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09627v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A wide range of strongly correlated electron systems exhibit strange metallicity, and they are increasingly recognized as in proximity to correlation-driven localization-delocalization transitions. A prototype setting arises in heavy fermion metals, where the proximity to the electron localization is manifested as Kondo destruction. Here we show that the Kondo destruction quantum critical point is linked to the phenomenon of fixed point annihilation. This connection reveals the absence of residual entropy density at the quantum critical point and, thus, its thermodynamic stability. Broader implications of our results are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09627v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiming Wang, Lei Chen, Haoyu Hu, Ang Cai, Jianhui Dai, C. J. Bolech, Qimiao Si</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prediction of several Co-based La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$-like superconducting materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09664</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09664v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High temperature superconductivity has been found in Fe, Ni, and Cu compounds, but not Co, where the Ni compounds include the recently found bilayer nickelate La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ under high pressure. Here we theoretically predict several Co-based La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$-like high-temperature superconducting materials. With electron doping to high-pressure bilayer cobaltate La$_3$Co$_2$O$_7$, we find that LaTh$_2$Co$_2$O$_7$, La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_5$Cl$_2$, and La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_5$Br$_2$ may show similar crystal structures and strongly correlated electronic structures to bilayer nickelate La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ under high pressure. Within the random-phase approximation (RPA), the leading pairing symmetry in these materials is $s$-wave.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09664v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jing-Xuan Wang, Yi-Heng Tian, Jian-Hong She, Rong-Qiang He, Zhong-Yi Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Projector Method for Nonlinear Light-Matter Interactions and Quantum Geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09216</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09216v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a systematic projector-based Feynman diagram framework that intrinsically encodes quantum geometry for nonlinear optical responses. By explicitly incorporating geometric quantities such as the quantum geometric tensor, quantum hermitian connection, and triple phase product, the method ensures component-wise gauge invariance and seamlessly extends to multiband systems, enabling accurate calculations of quantum geometry and nonlinear optical responses. We derive the projector formalism in Wannier function basis and implement the \textit{ab initio} calculations of shift current in GeS, demonstrating excellent agreement with the sum rule and Wilson loop approaches. This work extends projector-based representations within the Wannier functions basis, offering an efficient and reliable tool for investigating nonlinear light-matter interactions and quantum geometry in realistic materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09216v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhichao Guo, Zhuocheng Lu, Hua Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interaction-Induced Topological Phase Transition in Magnetic Weyl Semimetals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17044</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17044v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Despite the tremendous interest raised by the recent realization of magnetic Weyl semimetals and the observation of giant anomalous Hall signals, most of the theories used to interpret experimental data overlook the influence of magnetic fluctuations, which are ubiquitous in such materials and can massively impact topological and transport properties. In this work, we predict that in such magnetic topological systems, the interaction between electrons and magnons substantially destabilizes the Weyl nodes, leading to a topological phase transition below the Curie temperature. Remarkably, the sensitivity of the Weyl nodes to electron-magnon interaction depends on their spin chirality. We find that Weyl nodes with a trivial chirality are more sensitive to electron-magnon interactions than Weyl nodes presenting an inverted chirality, demonstrating the resilience of the latter compared to the former. Our results open perspectives for the interpretation of the transport signatures of Weyl semimetals, especially close to the Curie temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17044v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Konstantinos Sourounis, Aur\'elien Manchon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrability of the Kondo model with time dependent interaction strength</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20125</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20125v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this letter we consider the time dependent Kondo model where a magnetic impurity interacts with the electrons through a time dependent interaction strength $J(t)$. We develop a new framework based on Bethe ansatz and construct an exact solution to the time-dependent Schrodinger equation. We show that when periodic boundary conditions are applied, the consistency of the solution results in a constraint equation which relates the amplitudes corresponding to a certain ordering of the particles in the configuration space. This constraint equation takes the form of a matrix difference equation, and the associated consistency conditions restrict the interaction strength $J(t)$ for the system to be integrable. For a given $J(t)$ satisfying these constraints, the solution to the matrix difference equations provides the exact many-body wavefunction that satisfies the time-dependent Schrodinger equation. We provide a concrete example of $J(t)$ which satisfies these constraint equations. We show that in this case, the matrix difference equations turn into quantum Knizhnik-Zamolodchikov (qKZ) equations, which are well studied in the literature. The framework developed in this work allows one to probe the non-equilibrium physics of the Kondo model, and being general, it also allows one to solve new class of Hamiltonians with time-dependent interaction strength which are based on quantum Yang-Baxter algebra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20125v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Parameshwar R. Pasnoori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phonon-mediated intrinsic topological superconductivity in Fermi arcs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03250</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.03250v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose that phonons can intrinsically mediate topological superconductivity on the surface of Weyl semimetals. Weyl semimetals are gapless topological materials with nondegenerate zero energy surface states known as Fermi arcs. We derive the phonon spectrum and electron-phonon coupling in an effective model of a Weyl semimetal and apply weak-coupling Bardeen-Cooper-Schrieffer theory of superconductivity. In a slab geometry, we find that surface superconductivity dominates over bulk superconductivity in a range of chemical potentials around the Weyl nodes. The superconducting gap function realizes spinless chiral $p$-wave Cooper pairing in the Fermi arcs, leading to Majorana bound states in the core of vortices. Furthermore, we find a suppression of the absolute value of the gap in the center of the Fermi arcs, which is not captured by a local Hubbard attraction. The suppression is due to the nonlocal origin of electron-phonon coupling, leading to a layer dependence which has important consequences for topological surface states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.03250v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/47vs-qgzk</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Kristian M{\ae}land, Masoud Bahari, Bj\"orn Trauzettel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Designing Antiferromagnetic Spin-1/2 Chains in Janus Fullerene Nanoribbons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18849</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.18849v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We design antiferromagnetic spin-1/2 chains in fullerene nanoribbons by introducing extra C$_{60}$ cages at one of their edges. The resulting odd number of intermolecular bonds induces an unpaired $\pi$-electron and hence a quantised magnetic moment in otherwise non-magnetic nanoribbons. We further reveal the formation of an antiferromagnetic ground state upon the linear arrangement of spin-1/2 C$_{60}$ cages that is insensitive to the specific structural motifs. Compared with graphene nanoribbons, Janus fullerene nanoribbons may offer an experimentally more accessible route to magnetic edge states with atomic precision in low-dimensional carbon nanostructures, possibly serving as a versatile nanoarchitecture for scalable spin-based devices and the exploration of many-body quantum phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.18849v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bo Peng, Michele Pizzochero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ambient-pressure superconductivity and electronic structures of engineered hybrid nickelate films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03502</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03502v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Ruddlesden-Popper (RP) nickelates have emerged as a crucial platform for exploring the mechanisms of high-temperature superconductivity. However, the Fermi surface topology required for superconductivity remains elusive. Here, we report the thin film growth and ambient-pressure superconductivity of both hybrid monolayer-bilayer (1212) and pure bilayer (2222) structures, together with the absence of superconductivity in hybrid monolayer-trilayer (1313) structure, under identical compressive epitaxial strain. The onset superconducting transition temperature is up to 50 K, exceeding the McMillan limit, in the 1212 structure. Angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy reveals key Fermi surface differences in these atomically-engineered structures. In superconducting 1212 and 2222 films, a dispersive hole-like band (i.e. the {\gamma} band) crosses the Fermi level, surrounding the Brillouin zone corner. In contrast, the top of the {\gamma} flat band is observed ~70 meV below the Fermi level in the non-superconducting 1313 films. Our findings expand the family of ambient-pressure nickelate superconductors and establish a connection between structural configuration, electronic structure, and the emergence of superconductivity in nickelates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03502v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zihao Nie, Yueying Li, Wei Lv, Lizhi Xu, Zhicheng Jiang, Peng Fu, Guangdi Zhou, Wenhua Song, Yaqi Chen, Heng Wang, Haoliang Huang, Junhao Lin, Dawei Shen, Peng Li, Qi-Kun Xue, Zhuoyu Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalizing the composite fermion theory for fractional Chern insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06265</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.06265v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a generalized composite fermion (CF) theory for fractional Chern insulators (FCIs) by adapting the quantum mechanics approach of CFs. The theoretical framework naturally produces an effective CF Hamiltonian and a wavefunction ansatz, and the Bloch band characteristics of FCIs determine effective scalar and vector potentials experienced by CFs. Our analysis clarifies the construction of CF wavefunctions and state counting in CF phase space, which is subject to a density-of-states correction for filling factors $|\nu| \neq 1/2$. We apply the theory to study the $\nu=-2/3$ FCI state of the twisted bilayer MoTe$_2$ system, modeling it as either a $1/3$-filled electron band or a $2/3$-filled hole band. While both CF models exhibit trends and features consistent with exact diagonalization results, the electron-based model shows better agreement. Furthermore, we find that the FCI phase transition coincides with a topological phase transition in unoccupied CF $\Lambda$-bands.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.06265v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Jin, Junren Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Examining density wave correlations in high pressure $\rm{La_3Ni_2O_7}$ through variational Monte Carlo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07219</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07219v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: $\rm La_3Ni_2O_7$, a nickelate compound with a reported superconducting transition temperature of $\rm 80~K$, has attracted significant attention in recent years. Density-wave phenomena arising from strong electron correlations are widely regarded as key to unraveling the superconductivity mechanism, but the ordering and stability of these density waves remain a subject of contention in existing theoretical studies. In this work, we employ the variational Monte Carlo (VMC) method to thoroughly examine the nature of density waves as functions of Coulomb repulsion and exchange interactions in bilayer two-orbital model proposed for the high pressure phase of $\rm La_3Ni_2O_7$. We analyse the spin and charge correlation functions in a wide range of parameter space, and delineate a schematic phase diagram that separates different density-wave ground states. Our results provide useful insights into the understanding of electron correlations in $\rm La_3Ni_2O_7$, and highlight the potential of VMC to elucidate its superconducting mechanism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07219v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanxin Chen, Haoxiang Chen, Tonghuan Jiang, Ji Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
