<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 04:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Doping a spin-one Mott insulator: possible application to bilayer nickelate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02673</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02673v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article, we review some recent theoretical developments on potential high-temperature superconductors and unconventional metallic states that can arise from doping a spin-one Mott insulator in the $d^{8}$ valence. These studies are particularly relevant-though not limited-to the recently discovered bilayer nickelate superconductor La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$. We focus on a ferromagnetic (FM) Kondo lattice model with mobile electrons in the $d_{x^2-y^2}$ orbital coupled to the localized spin moments in $d_{z^2}$ orbital through a large Hund's coupling $J_H$. In the large $J_H$ limit, the model reduces to the type II t-J model with a mixture of spin-half singlon states and spin-one doublon states. We summarize DMRG results on the Luther-Emery liquid in one dimensional chain and two-leg ladder. Then we mainly focus on bilayer square lattice and show that a large inter-layer coupling $J_\perp$ of $d_{z^2}$ orbital can induce strong inter-layer pairing of $d_{x^2-y^2}$ orbital. In the strong $J_\perp$ limit, a kinetic-energy driven high $T_c$ superconductivity is demonstrated in an ideal model with only a single hopping term. Furthermore, the model predicts a symmetric pseudogap metal-dubbed `second Fermi liquid"-in the underdoped regime, yielding a phase diagram analogous to that of hole-doped cuprates. The bilayer Kondo model therefore, presents a promising platform for both realizing higher-Tc superconductors and exploring non-Fermi liquid physics. We also comment on the possible limitations of the current models for the bilayer nickelate material and point out some future directions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02673v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanbit Oh, Hui Yang, Ya-Hui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust superconductivity upon doping chiral spin liquid and Chern insulators in a Hubbard-Hofstadter model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02675</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02675v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Demonstrating superconductivity in purely repulsive Hubbard models is a compelling goal which underscores the counter-intuitive ability of Coulomb interactions to mediate superconductivity. Here, we present numerical evidence for robust superconductivity in a triangular Hubbard-Hofstadter model at $\pi/2$ flux per plaquette. Employing infinite density matrix renormalization group calculations on infinite cylinders of finite circumference, we observe superconducting ground states for a wide range of dopings, whose pair-correlations strengthen as the 2D limit is approached. At a density of one electron per site, Hubbard interactions have been reported to drive the insulating parent state of the superconductor from an integer quantum Hall (IQH) state to a chiral spin liquid (CSL). Our findings give credence to a recent proposal that proximity to the IQH-CSL transition serves to make chiral superconductivity energetically favorable on doping, and also correctly predicts the nature of the edge modes in the superconductor. On the CSL side, this suggests the superconductor can be thought of as arising from Laughlin's `anyon superconductivity' mechanism. Thus the Hubbard-Hofstadter model studied here offers a clean and experimentally accessible setup, potentially realizable in moir\'e heterostructures, for exploring the properties of anyonic matter at finite density and the interplay of topological order, quantum criticality and superconductivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02675v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Clemens Kuhlenkamp, Stefan Divic, Michael P. Zaletel, Tomohiro Soejima, Ashvin Vishwanath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In search of exotic pairing in the Hubbard model: many-body computation and quantum gas microscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02688</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02688v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Pair density waves and exotic superconductivity have long been of strong interest, and have attracted much recent attention. We present a joint theoretical and experimental exploration of possible signatures of fermion pairing with finite center-of-mass momentum, or the Fulde-Ferrell-Larkin-Ovchinnikov (FFLO) order. Experimentally a doped and spin-imbalanced attractive two-dimensional Hubbard model is realized with a cold atomic gas in an optical lattice, and quantum gas microscopy is used to probe its properties. Computationally we study the same model with state-of-the-art constrained-path (CP) auxiliary field quantum Monte Carlo (AFQMC). Direct comparisons between experiment and computation on various short-range magnetic and charge correlations show excellent agreement. We then investigate these correlations, as well as pairing correlation functions, systematically to low temperatures with CP-AFQMC, and determine parameter regimes in density and magnetization where signatures of FFLO order may be observed. We show that the temperature at which precursors of such orders appear is already within reach of the current experiment. We discuss routes for direct experimental detection and measurements of such states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02688v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chunhan Feng, Thomas Hartke, Yuan-Yao He, Botond Oreg, Carter Turnbaugh, Ningyuan Jia, Martin Zwierlein, Shiwei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Chiral Superconductivity in the Triangular-Lattice Hofstadter-Hubbard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02757</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02757v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Moir\'e materials provide exciting platforms for studying the interplay of strong electronic correlation and large magnetic flux effects. We study the lightly doped Hofstadter-Hubbard model on a triangular lattice through large-scale density matrix renormalization group and determinantal quantum Monte Carlo simulations. We find strong evidence for a robust chiral superconducting (SC) phase with dominant power-law pairing correlations and a quantized spin Chern number. The SC phase emerges at very weak interaction and grows stronger at intermediate interaction strengths (U ) for a wide range of hole doping. We also discuss the possible distinct nature of the normal state in different U regimes. Our work provides theoretical insights into the emergence of topological superconductivity from doping topological Chern bands or magnetic flux induced chiral spin liquid states of Moir\'e materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02757v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Feng Chen, Wen O. Wang, Jia-Xin Zhang, Leon Balents, D. N. Sheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Current-induced molecular dissociation: Topological insulators as robust reaction platforms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02831v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The growing interest in topological materials with symmetry-protected surface states as catalytic platforms has sparked the emerging field of \textit{topocatalysis}. As robust transport is one of the key features of topological insulators, here we explore current-induced molecular dissociation in a transport setup. Using the non-equilibrium Green's function formalism, we compare how the occupancies of bonding and antibonding levels, as well as the associated electronic forces in a diatomic molecule, are affected when the molecule is coupled to either a metallic (graphene) or a topological (Kane-Mele) substrate. We find a greater dissociative capability in the topological substrate than in graphene, a difference mainly attributed to the localized nature of the edge states. The inclusion of vacancy disorder within the substrate further enhances this disparity in the dissociative force. Our findings highlight the role of topological protection in molecular dissociation under non-equilibrium conditions, pointing to new opportunities for robust catalysis in topological materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02831v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erika L. Mehring, Amparo Figueroa, Matias Berdakin, Hern\'an L. Calvo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Highly tunable band structure in ferroelectric R-stacked bilayer WSe$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02886</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02886v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Transition metal dichalcogenide homobilayers unite two frontiers of quantum materials research: sliding ferroelectricity, arising from rhombohedral (R) stacking, and moir\'e quantum matter, emerging from small-angle twisting. The spontaneous polarization of ferroelectric R-stacked homobilayers produces a highly tunable band structure, which, together with strain-induced piezoelectricity, governs the topology and correlated electronic phases of twisted bilayers. Here we present a systematic low-temperature optical spectroscopy study of R-stacked bilayer WSe$_2$ to quantitatively establish its fundamental electronic and ferroelectric properties. Exciton and exciton-polaron spectroscopy under doping reveals a pronounced electron-hole asymmetry that confirms type-II band alignment, with the conduction and valence band edges located at the $\Lambda$ and K valleys, respectively. Through distinct excitonic responses and tunable interlayer-intralayer exciton hybridization under displacement fields, we uncover the coexistence of AB and BA ferroelectric domains. Using exciton-polarons as a probe, we directly measure the intrinsic polarization field and extract the interlayer potential. Finally, we demonstrate electric-field-driven symmetric switching of the valence band maximum, attributed to ferroelectric domain switching. These results provide a complete experimental picture of the band alignment, spontaneous polarization field, and domain dynamics of R-stacked WSe$_2$, establishing key parameters to understand twisted bilayers and enabling new ferroelectric and excitonic device opportunities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02886v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhe Li, Prokhor Thor, George Kourmoulakis, Tatyana V. Ivanova, Takashi Taniguchi, Kenji Watanabe, Hongyi Yu, Mauro Brotons-Gisbert, Brian D. Gerardot</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of $\Gamma_7$ and $\Gamma_8$ Hybridizations on Three-Channel Kondo Phase Emerging from Ho Ions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02976</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02976v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: By employing a numerical renormalization group method, we analyze a seven-orbital impurity Anderson model for Ho$^{3+}$ ion with ten $4f$ electrons. This model includes both $V_7$ and $V_8$, which are hybridizations between localized $4f$- and conduction electrons in $\Gamma_7$ and $\Gamma_8$ orbitals, respectively. For the case of $V_7=V_8$ with the local $\Gamma_5$ triplet ground state, we have reported the discovery of a three-channel Kondo (TCK) phase, characterized by a residual entropy of $\log \phi$ with the golden ratio $\phi=(1+\sqrt{5})/2$. In this research, by depicting the ground-state phase diagram on the $(V_8, V_7)$ plane, we attempt to unveil the effect of $V_7$ and $V_8$ on the emergence of the TCK phase. After performing a lot of numerical calculations, we find that the TCK phase appears in a relatively wide region on the $(V_8, V_7)$ plane. The boundary curves surrounding the TCK phase are determined by the variation of the temperature dependence in entropy and the abrupt change in energy spectra. We consider that most of the phases surrounding the TCK phase are Fermi liquids, but the non-Fermi liquid two-channel Kondo phase is unexpectedly found to exist next to the TCK phase. Finally, we briefly comment on the actual material concerning the detection of the TCK phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02976v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takashi Hotta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anisotropic spin fluctuations in the triangular Kondo lattice compound CePtAl$_4$Ge$_2$ probed by site-selective $^{27}$Al NMR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03007</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03007v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A site-selective $^{27}$Al nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) study is carried out on the Kondo lattice compound CePtAl$_4$Ge$_2$, which crystallizes in a rhombohedral lattice with quasi-two-dimensional Ce layers forming a triangular lattice network. Two inequivalent Al sites, Al(1) and Al(2), are unambiguously assigned by comparing measured nuclear quadrupole parameters with electric field gradients obtained from electronic structure calculations. Knight shift analysis yields distinct hyperfine coupling constants, revealing that they arise predominantly from RKKY-type transferred hyperfine fields through conduction electrons. Spin-lattice relaxation measurements reveal pronounced anisotropic spin fluctuations, and comparison of the relaxation rates between the two Al sites clarifies the momentum-space structure of these fluctuations. At low magnetic fields, $(T_1T)^{-1}$ is strongly enhanced on cooling toward the N\'eel temperature, indicating the growth of in-plane antiferromagnetic correlations in the paramagnetic state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03007v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. Sakai, S. Shin, S. Kambe, Y. Tokunaga, H. Harima, E. Pomjakushina, T. Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ab initio spin Hamiltonians and magnetism of Ce and Yb triangular-lattice compounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03177</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03177v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We calculate the crystal-field splitting, ground-state Kramers doublet and intersite exchange interactions within the ground-state doublet manifold using an ab initio Hubbard-I based approach for a representative set of Ce and Yb triangular-lattice compounds. These include the putative quantum spin liquids (QSL) RbCeO$_2$ and YbZn$_2$GaO$_5$ and the antiferromagnets KCeO$_2$ and KCeS$_2$. The calculated nearest-neighbor (NN) couplings are antiferromagnetic and exhibit noticeable anisotropy. The next-nearest-neighbor (NNN) couplings are ferromagnetic in the Ce systems and dominated by classical dipole-dipole interactions in the Yb case. Solving the resulting effective spin-1/2 models by exact diagonalization up to $N=36$ sites, we predict ordered magnetic ground states for all systems, including the two QSL candidates. We explore the phase space of an anisotropic NN + isotropic NNN triangular-lattice model finding that a significant antiferromagnetic NNN coupling is required to stabilize QSL phases, while the NN exchange anisotropy is detrimental to them. Our findings highlight a possibly important role of deviations from the perfect triangular model - like atomic disorder - in real triangular-lattice materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03177v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonid V. Pourovskii, Rafael D. Soares, Alexander Wietek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of Magnetic Anisotropy on Magnetoelastic Waves in Ni/LiNbO3 Hybrid Device</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03254</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03254v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the effects of magnetic anisotropy and crystalline axes in surface acoustic waves (SAWs) driven magnetic resonances of Ni/LiNbO3 hybrid devices. SAW absorption from the interaction with magnons in Ni displays a strong anisotropic dependence on the direction of the applied in-plane magnetic field. Magnetic anisotropy is further investigated by magneto-optical Kerr effect measurements to show both uniaxial and biaxial anisotropy components in Ni films on LiNbO3. By introducing a dipolar interaction term in addition to the anisotropies, we successfully explain the anisotropic SAW absorption in our devices. These findings show the importance of substrate-induced anisotropy and long-range dipolar effects in SAW-magnons hybrid devices and indicate future directions for optimizing these spin-acoustic devices through comprehensive anisotropy engineering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03254v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minwoo Yu, Moojune Song, Minseok Kang, Mujin You, Yunyoung Hwang, Albert Min Gyu Park, Byong-Guk Park, Kab-Jin Kim, Junho Suh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Review on Phenomenological Models for Chromonic Liquid Crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03266v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Chromonic liquid crystals (CLCs) are lyotropic materials which are attracting growing interest for their adaptability to living systems. A considerable body of works has been devoted to exploring their properties and applications. In this paper, I endeavour to review some of the contributions concerning their theoretical modelling, aimed at rationalizing experimental observations. The elastic theory of CLCs is not completely established. Their ground state in the 3D space, as revealed by a number of recent experiments, is quite different from that of ordinary nematic liquid crystals: it is twisted instead of uniform. The common explanation provided for this state within the classical Oseen-Frank elastic theory demands that one Ericksen's inequality is violated. Since such a violation would make the Oseen-Frank stored energy density unbounded below, the legitimacy of these theoretical treatments is threatened by a number of mathematical issues. To overcome these difficulties, a novel elastic theory has been proposed and tested for CLCs; it extends the classical Oseen-Frank energy by incorporating a quartic twist term. Another key characteristic of CLCs is that they exhibit broad biphasic regions, in which the nematic and isotropic phases coexist. Mathematical models inspired by experimental settings have been developed for CLC droplets in 2D. The contributions reviewed here address the morphogenesis of nuclei and topological defects during phase transitions, the topological shape transformations arising from the interplay of nematic elastic constants, and the prediction of shape bistability (yet to be observed) where tactoids and smooth-edged discoids can coexist in equilibrium. General methods have also been applied to experimental data to extract estimates of the isotropic surface tension at the nematic isotropic interface and the chromonics' planar anchoring strength.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03266v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Silvia Paparini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Family of Unconventional Superconductivities in Crystalline Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03295</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03295v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Unconventional superconductors exhibit multiple broken symmetries and exceed the range of the Bardeen-Cooper-Schrieffer (BCS) theory. For instance, time-reversal symmetry can be broken in addition to the gauge symmetry, resulting in superconductors that can be enhanced or induced by a magnetic field. However, such unconventional superconductivities are more vulnerable to impurities than their BCS counterparts, requiring highly ordered and clean material systems to observe them. Crystalline rhombohedral multilayer graphene is a promising platform to explore unconventional superconductivity due to its superior material quality and gate-tunable strong correlation effects. Here we report transport measurements of rhombohedral tetralayer and pentalayer graphene, where a spectrum of superconductivities in a clean limit are observed. Three of them (SC2-4) show highly unusual enhancements by magnetic fields: 1. SC2 is strengthened by an in-plane field; 2. SC3 is boosted by a small out-of-plane field; 3. SC4 is induced by an in-plane field. All these superconductors are robust against an in-plane field up to 8.5 Tesla, exceeding the Pauli limit of conventional superconductors by tens of times and suggesting their unconventional nature. Moreover, we observed that proximitized spin-orbit coupling generates a plethora of new superconductors in the phase diagram, while maintaining the high quality of bare rhombohedral graphene. Our work establishes a family of new superconductors in rhombohedral multilayer graphene, which also provides an ideal platform to engineer non-Abelian quasiparticles by proximitizing with quantum anomalous Hall states existing in the same material system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03295v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junseok Seo, Armel A. Cotten, Mingchi Xu, Omid Sharifi Sedeh, Henok Weldeyesus, Tonghang Han, Zhengguang Lu, Zhenghan Wu, Shenyong Ye, Wei Xu, Jixiang Yang, Emily Aitken, Prayoga P. Liong, Zach Hadjri, Rasul Gazizulin, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Mingda Li, Dominik M. Zumb\"uhl, Long Ju</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigation of non-Hermitian and Hermitian models of Altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03320</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03320v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Insulating altermagnets like MnTe exhibit spin configurations where opposing spins are not only aligned antiparallel but also rotated relative to each other. This is an arrangement reminiscent of antiferromagnetism with a twist of spin canting. This study investigates a model Hamiltonian that captures the essential physics of such systems, incorporating key interactions including Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya and conventional exchange terms, relativistic spin-orbit coupling, and d-wave and g-wave orderings. Non-Hermitian dynamics are introduced through complex potentials that simulate energy dissipation and amplification. The paper delves into the behavior of the quantum geometric tensor and the emergence of the quantum anomalous Hall effect within the topologically insulating regime. It also broadens the scope to encompass non-Hermitian metallic altermagnets, focusing on phases characterized by symmetry-breaking d-wave and g-wave order parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03320v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Partha Goswami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Role of Fe intercalation on the electronic correlation in resistively switchable antiferromagnet Fe$_{x}$NbS$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03327v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Among the family of intercalated transition-metal dichalcogenides (TMDs), Fe$_{x}$NbS$_2$ is found to possess unique current-induced resistive switching behaviors, tunable antiferromagnetic states, and a commensurate charge order, all of which are tied to a critical Fe doping of $x_c$ = 1/3. However, the electronic origin of such extreme stoichiometry sensitivities remains unclear. Combining angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) with density functional theory (DFT) calculations, we identify and characterize a dramatic eV-scale electronic restructuring that occurs across the $x_c$. Moment-carrying Fe 3$d_{z^2}$ electrons manifest as narrow bands within 200 meV to the Fermi level, distinct from other transition metal intercalated TMD magnets. This state strongly interacts with the itinerant electron in TMD layer, and rapidly loses coherence above $x_c$. These observations resemble the exceptional electronic and magnetic sensitivity of strongly correlated systems upon charge doping, shedding light on the important role of electronic correlation in magnetic TMDs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03327v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenxin Li, Jonathan T. Reichanadter, Shan Wu, Ji Seop Oh, Rourav Basak, Shannon C. Haley, Elio Vescovo, Donghui Lu, Makoto Hashimoto, Christoph Klewe, Suchismita Sarker, James G. Analytis, Robert J. Birgeneau, Jeffrey B. Neaton, Yu He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The frustrated Ising model on the honeycomb lattice: Metastability and universality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03414v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the Ising model with competing ferromagnetic nearest- and antiferromagnetic next-nearest-neighbor interactions of strengths $J_1 &gt; 0$ and $J_2 &lt; 0$, respectively, on the honeycomb lattice. For $J_2 &gt; - J_1 / 4$ it has a ferromagnetic ground state, and previous work has shown that at least for $J_2 \gtrsim -0.2 J_1$ the transition is in the Ising universality class. For even lower $J_2$ some indicators pointing towards a first-order transition were reported. By utilizing population annealing Monte Carlo simulations together with a rejection-free and adaptive update, we can equilibrate systems with $J_2$ as low as $-0.23 J_1$. By means of a finite-size scaling analysis we show that the system undergoes a second-order phase transition within the Ising universality class at least down to $J_2 =-0.23 J_1$ and, most likely, for all $J_2 &gt; - J_1 / 4$. As we show here, there exist very long-lived metastable states in this system explaining the first-order like behavior seen in only partially equilibrated systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03414v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Denis Gessert, Martin Weigel, Wolfhard Janke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signatures of emergent surface states across a displacive topological phase transition in Bi$_4$I$_4$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03469</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03469v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Topological phase transitions involving crystalline symmetry breaking provide a fertile ground to explore the interplay between symmetry, topology, and emergent quantum phenomena. Recently discovered quasi-one-dimensional topological material, Bi$_4$I$_4$, has been predicted to host topologically non-trivial gapless surfaces at high temperature, which undergo a finite temperature phase transition to a low temperature gapped phase. Here we present experimental signatures of this room temperature phase transition from a high-temperature $\beta$-phase with a surface state to a gapped $\alpha$-phase hosting hinge states. Using real-space current mapping and resistance fluctuation spectroscopy, we identify signatures of a displacive topological phase transition mediated by a first-order thermodynamic structural change. Near the emergence of $\beta$-phase, we observe pronounced telegraphic noise, indicating fluctuating phase domains with topological surface states. The spatially resolved current map reveals electron transport via the gapless surface states in the $\beta$-phase, which vanishes upon transitioning to the $\alpha$-phase with localized conduction channels (or hinge modes). Our experimental results, supported by first principles estimates and effective theory of a topological displacive phase transition, establish Bi$_4$I$_4$ as a candidate material showing intricate interplay of classical thermodynamic phase transitions with topological quantum phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03469v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Deep Singha Roy, Sk Kalimuddin, Subrata Pachhal, Saikat Mondal, Soham Das, Sukanya Jana, Arnab Bera, Satyabrata Bera, Tuhin Debnath, Ankan Bag, Souvik Pramanik, Sudipta Chatterjee, Sanjib Naskar, Shishir Kumar Pandey, Adhip Agarwala, Mintu Mondal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissipationless dynamics of spin supersolid states in a spin-1/2 triangular antiferromagnet with impurities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03489</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03489v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by recent experimental observations of possible spin supersolid states in triangular lattice compounds, we study the dynamical properties of various ground states in the spin-1/2 easy-axis antiferromagnetic Heisenberg model with impurities under magnetic fields, using numerical Density Matrix Renormalization Group methods. For both spin supersolid states in the low and high fields, the gapless Goldstone mode at the $K$ points remains robust with impurities, which is related to the presence of spin superfluidity. As a comparison, we find a splitting of magnon band at the same impurity density level in the conventional magnetic state, the so-called up-up-down state. In addition, the finite superfluid stiffness probed by the twisted phase in the spin supersolid states is consistent with the excitation spectrum. We argue that this excitation spectrum with impurity provides direct evidence of the dissipationless dynamics in the spin supersolid states, which could be tested in neutron scattering experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03489v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yixuan Huang, Yuan Gao, Wei Li, Seiji Yunoki, Sadamichi Maekawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ambient-pressure superconductivity and electronic structures of engineered hybrid nickelate films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03502</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03502v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ruddlesden-Popper (RP) nickelates have emerged as a crucial platform for exploring the mechanisms of high-temperature superconductivity. However, the Fermi surface topology required for superconductivity remains elusive. Here, we report the thin film growth and ambient-pressure superconductivity of both hybrid monolayer-bilayer (1212) and pure bilayer (2222) structures, together with the absence of superconductivity in hybrid monolayer-trilayer (1313) structure, under identical compressive epitaxial strain. The onset superconducting transition temperature is up to 50 K, exceeding the McMillan limit, in the 1212 structure. Angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy reveals key Fermi surface differences in these atomically-engineered structures. In superconducting 1212 and 2222 films, a dispersive hole-like band (i.e. the {\gamma} band) crosses the Fermi level, surrounding the Brillouin zone corner. In contrast, the top of the {\gamma} flat band is observed ~70 meV below the Fermi level in the non-superconducting 1313 films. Our findings expand the family of ambient-pressure nickelate superconductors and establish a connection between structural configuration, electronic structure, and the emergence of superconductivity in nickelates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03502v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zihao Nie, Yueying Li, Wei Lv, Lizhi Xu, Zhicheng Jiang, Peng Fu, Guangdi Zhou, Wenhua Song, Yaqi Chen, Heng Wang, Haoliang Huang, Junhao Lin, Dawei Shen, Peng Li, Qi-Kun Xue, Zhuoyu Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct spatiotemporal imaging of a long-lived bulk photovoltaic effect in $BiFeO_{3}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01729</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01729v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The bulk photovoltaic effect (BPVE), a manifestation of broken centrosymmetry, has attracted interest as a probe of the symmetry and quantum geometry of materials, and for use in novel optoelectronic devices. Despite its bulk nature, the BPVE is typically measured with interfaces and metal contacts, raising concerns as to whether the observed signals are genuinely of bulk origin. Here, we use a contactless pump-probe microscopy method to observe the space- and time-resolved dynamics of photoexcited carriers in single-crystal, monodomain $BiFeO_{3}$. We observe asymmetric transport of carriers along the polar axis, confirming the intrinsic bulk and symmetry-driven nature of BPVE. This asymmetric transport persists for several nanoseconds after photoexcitation, which cannot be explained by the shift or phonon ballistic current BPVE mechanisms. Monte Carlo simulations show that asymmetric momentum scattering by defects under non-equilibrium conditions explains the long-lived carrier drift, while first principles calculations confirm that oxygen vacancies have an asymmetric electronic state that can cause such asymmetric scattering. Our findings highlight the critical role of defects in long-lived photoresponses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01729v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saptam Ganguly, Sebin Varghese, Aaron M. Schankler, Xianfei Xu, Kazuki Morita, Michel Viret, Andrew M. Rappe, Gustau Catalan, Klaas-Jan Tielrooij</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distinct effect of Kondo physics on crystal field splitting in electron and spin spectroscopies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09971</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09971v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Magnetic anisotropy is a key feature of rare earth materials from permanent magnets to heavy fermions. We explore the complex interplay of Kondo physics and anisotropy, and their effect on different experimental probes of magnetic anisotropy in a minimal J = 3/2 Anderson impurity model using numerical renormalization group. While anisotropy suppresses Kondo screening, virtual valence fluctuations enhance the anisotropy. We find distinct renormalization of the magnetic anisotropy measured via dynamical spin response (inelastic neutron scattering) versus electronic excitations in the impurity spectral function (resonant inelastic x-rays and scanning tunneling spectroscopy). The two measurement types have different responses and dependences on the temperature and Kondo scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09971v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Kornja\v{c}a, R. Flint</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anyon Superconductivity from Topological Criticality in a Hofstadter-Hubbard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18175v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We argue that the combination of strong repulsive interactions and high magnetic fields can generate electron pairing and superconductivity. Inspired by the large lattice constants of moir\'e materials, which make large flux per unit cell accessible at laboratory fields, we study the triangular lattice Hofstadter-Hubbard model at one-quarter flux quantum per plaquette, where previous literature has argued that a chiral spin liquid separates a weak-coupling integer quantum Hall phase and a strong-coupling topologically-trivial antiferromagnetic insulator at a density of one electron per site. We argue that topological superconductivity emerges upon doping in the vicinity of the integer quantum Hall to chiral spin liquid transition. We employ exact diagonalization and density matrix renormalization group methods to examine this theoretical scenario and find that electronic pairing indeed occurs on both sides of criticality over a remarkably broad range of interaction strengths. On the chiral spin liquid side, our results provide a concrete model realization of the long-hypothesized mechanism of anyon superconductivity. Our study thus establishes a beyond-BCS mechanism for electron pairing in a well-controlled limit, relying crucially on the interplay between electron correlations and band topology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18175v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1073/pnas.2426680122</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 122 (33) e2426680122 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Stefan Divic, Valentin Cr\'epel, Tomohiro Soejima, Xue-Yang Song, Andrew J. Millis, Michael P. Zaletel, Ashvin Vishwanath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fermi surface and pseudogap in highly doped Sr$_{2}$IrO$_{4}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18542</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18542v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The fate of the Fermi surface in bulk electron-doped Sr$_{2}$IrO$_{4}$ remains elusive, as does the origin and extension of its pseudogap phase. Here, we use high-resolution angle-resolved photoelectron spectroscopy (ARPES) to investigate the electronic structure of Sr$_{2-x}$La$_{x}$IrO$_{4}$ up to $x=0.2$, a factor of two higher than in previous work. We find that the antinodal pseudogap persists up to the highest doping level, and thus beyond the sharp increase in Hall carrier density to $\simeq 1+x$ recently observed above $x^{*}\simeq 0.16$ [Y.-T. Hsu et al., Nature Physics 20, 1593 (2024)]. This suggests that doped iridates host a unique phase of matter in which a large Hall density coexists with an anisotropic pseudogap, breaking up the Fermi surface into disconnected arcs. The temperature boundary of the pseudogap is $T^{*}\simeq 200$ K for $x=0.2$, comparable to cuprates and to the energy scale of short range antiferromagnetic correlations in cuprates and iridates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18542v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Y. Alexanian, A. de la Torre, S. McKweon Walker, M. Straub, G. Gatti, A. Hunter, S. Mandloi, E. Cappelli, S. Ricc\`o, F. Y. Bruno, M. Radovic, N. C. Plumb, M. Shi, J. Osiecki, C. Polley, T. K. Kim, P. Dudin, M. Hoesch, R. S. Perry, A. Tamai, F. Baumberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Saga of $\alpha$-RuCl$_3$: Parameters, Models, and Phase Diagrams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.08698</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.08698v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: RuCl$_3$ was likely the first ever deliberately synthesized ruthenium compound, following the discovery of the $_{44}$Ru element in 1844. For a long time it was known as an oxidation catalyst, with its physical properties being discrepant and confusing, until a decade ago when its allotropic form $\alpha$-RuCl$_3$ rose to exceptional prominence. This "re-discovery" of $\alpha$-RuCl$_3$ has not only reshaped the hunt for a material manifestation of the Kitaev spin liquid, but it has opened the floodgates of theoretical and experimental research in the many unusual phases and excitations that the anisotropic-exchange magnets as a class of compounds have to offer. Given its importance for the field of Kitaev materials, it is astonishing that the low-energy spin model that describes this compound and its possible proximity to the much-desired spin-liquid state is still a subject of significant debate ten years later. In the present study, we argue that the existing key phenomenological observations put strong natural constraints on the effective microscopic spin model of $\alpha$-RuCl$_3$, and specifically on its spin-orbit-induced anisotropic-exchange parameters that are responsible for the non-trivial physical properties of this material. These constraints allow one to focus on the relevant region of the multi-dimensional phase diagram of the $\alpha$-RuCl$_3$ model, suggest an intuitive description of it via a different parametrization of the exchange matrix, offer a unifying view on the earlier assessments of its parameters, and bring closer together several approaches to the derivation of anisotropic-exchange models. We explore extended phase diagrams relevant to the $\alpha$-RuCl$_3$ parameter space using quasi-classical, Luttinger-Tisza, exact diagonalization, and density-matrix renormalization group methods, demonstrating a remarkably c... (arxiv cutoff; for the rest, see the paper)</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.08698v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/hflp-41lj</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 104403 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Marius M\"oller, P. A. Maksimov, Shengtao Jiang, Steven R. White, Roser Valenti, A. L. Chernyshev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum geometry and low-frequency optical conductivity of nodal planes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11589</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11589v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Nodal planes, two-dimensional symmetry-enforced band crossings, can carry a topological charge, similar to Weyl points. While the transport properties of Weyl points are well understood, those of nodal planes remain largely unexplored. These properties are influenced not only by the Berry curvature, but also by other quantum geometric quantities. In this work we study the quantum geometry - specifically the Berry curvature and quantum metric - and the linear optical conductivity of topological nodal planes. We introduce a low-energy model and investigate its low-frequency optical responses to determine the unique signatures of nodal planes. By comparing these findings to the optical response in a tight-binding model with a topological nodal plane, we observe consistent low-frequency behavior with a cubic power law. This paves the way for the experimental detection of nodal planes through optical conductivity measurements for which we suggest suitable materials, most promisingly the material group $X$Mo$_3$S$_3$ ($X$ = Rb, K, Cs).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11589v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/2f4l-tz7p</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Raymond Wiedmann, Kirill Alpin, Moritz M. Hirschmann, Andreas P. Schnyder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High frequency permeability of the composite with ferromagnetic spherical shells</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10280</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.10280v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The paper studies high-frequency permeability of the composite materials consisting of hollow ferromagnetic particles embedded into the non-magnetic media. We model the ferromagnetic particles in composite by spherical shells: the thickness of the ferromagnetic region $d$ compared to the particles' diameter $D$ can vary in a wide range, from $d\ll D$ to $d\sim D$. We assume that the magnetization distribution in such a particle is non-uniform, but forms a vortex-like structure: the magnetization is twisted in some plane outside two vortex cores placed at the poles of the particle. We consider two types of magnetic anisotropy, which help to stabilize such a magnetic configuration: the easy-plane magnetic anisotropy and the ``circular'' uniaxial magnetic anisotropy with easy axis rotated together with the magnetization direction outside the vortex core. The high-frequency permeability of such a composite material has been studied in the limit of non-interacting particles. We study the dependence of the permeability on the ratio $d/D$. We showed that for $d\sim D$ the composite's permeability behaves in similar manner for both types of magnetic anisotropy. It was shown also that for the second type of magnetic anisotropy and in the limit $d/D\ll1$ the frequency dependence of the particle's susceptibility is quite similar to that for the thin film. At the same time, the magnetization oscillations in the ac field are non-homogeneous for both types of anisotropy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.10280v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. O. Sboychakov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry analysis of cross-circular and parallel-circular Raman optical activity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21824v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Raman scattering regarding the circularly-polarized incident and scattered lights is closely related to the circular activity of a given system. We investigate the symmetry of its activity, called the cross-circular and parallel-circular Raman optical activity. The analysis is systematically performed with the magnetic point groups and indicates that the response allows for a useful diagnosis of the symmetry of materials like chirality and (magneto-)axiality. It is also shown that the Stokes and anti-Stokes processes are related to each other by the conserved antiunitary symmetry for the time-reversal operation and that combined with the mirror reflection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21824v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/45jq-j23c</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Hikaru Watanabe, Rikuto Oiwa, Gakuto Kusuno, Takuya Satoh, Ryotaro Arita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital-selective two-gap superconductivity in kagome metal CsV3Sb5</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.17327v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent experiments have revealed anisotropic multi-gap superconductivity in the kagome metal CsV3Sb5. However, the impact of multi-orbital character and electron-phonon coupling (EPC) on the multiple superconducting gaps remains not fully understood. In this work, we theoretically investigate the multi-orbital electronic structure and superconducting gap properties of CsV3Sb5 by combining first-principles calculations with superconducting density functional theory (SCDFT). Our results demonstrate that orbital-selective pairing drives the observed two-gap superconductivity in CsV3Sb5. Specifically, the two distinct gaps exhibit strong orbital dependence: a large, highly anisotropic gap (average magnitude ~0.64 meV) primarily originates from V-3d orbitals, while a small, isotropic gap (~0.25 meV) is associated with the Sb-5pz orbital. The V-3d orbitals exhibit strong coupling to the in-plane V-V bond-stretching and out-of-plane V-Sb bending phonon modes, whereas the Sb-5pz orbitals show weak coupling to the out-of-plane vibrations of both Cs and the apical Sb atoms. These findings provide fundamental insights into the orbital-selective superconductivity and EPC mechanisms in kagome CsV3Sb5.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.17327v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Run Lv, Wenqian Tu, Dingfu Shao, Yuping Sun, Wenjian Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced Terahertz Thermoelectricity via Engineered van Hove Singularities and Nernst Effect in Moir\'e Superlattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02548</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02548v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Thermoelectric materials, long explored for energy harvesting and thermal sensing, convert heat directly into electrical signals. Extending their application to the terahertz (THz) frequency range opens opportunities for low-noise, bias-free THz detection, yet conventional thermoelectrics lack the sensitivity required for practical devices. Thermoelectric coefficients can be strongly enhanced near van Hove singularities (VHS), though these are usually difficult to access in conventional materials. Here we show that moir\'e band engineering unlocks these singularities for THz optoelectronics. Using 2D moir\'e structures as a model system, we observe strong enhancement of the THz photothermoelectric response in monolayer and bilayer graphene superlattices when the Fermi level is tuned to band singularities. Applying a relatively small magnetic field further boosts the response through the THz-driven Nernst effect, a transverse thermoelectric current driven by the THz-induced temperature gradient. Our results establish moir\'e superlattices as a versatile platform for THz thermoelectricity and highlight engineered band structures as a route to high-performance THz optoelectronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02548v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Elesin, A. L. Shilov, S. Jana, I. Mazurenko, P. A. Pantaleon, M. Kashchenko, N. Krivovichev, V. Dremov, I. Gayduchenko, G. Goltsman, T. Taniguchi, K. Watanabe, Y. Wang, E. I. Titova, D. A. Svintsov, K. S. Novoselov, D. A. Bandurin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
