<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 04:00:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Exchange tensors, generalized RKKY interactions, and magnetization dynamics in heterostructures of ferromagnets and topological insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03572v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive theoretical analysis of magnetic heterostructures composed of ferromagnetic (FM) layers interfaced with three-dimensional topological insulators (TIs). Integrating out the topological surface states and computing the spin determinant to second order in spins, we derive the effective generalized Ruderman-Kittel-Kasuya-Yosida (RKKY) exchange interactions mediated by topological surface states. These interactions inherently incorporate spin-momentum locking and anisotropic spin susceptibilities stemming from the Dirac-like dispersion of the TI surface electrons. The analysis reveals that the interplay between the spin-orbit coupling intrinsic to the TI and the magnetization texture in the FM layer induces highly nonlocal and retarded, chiral, and Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya (DM)-like contributions to the effective spin Hamiltonian. Furthermore, the spin dynamics is studied through a derivation of the LLG equation for this problem. The induced interactions renormalize many of the FM's intrinsic properties, but a term in the LLG equation is induced that is related to the rate of change of the magnetization's curl, which is relevant to skyrmion dynamics. The magnon dispersion exhibits modifications due to the TI-mediated interactions, including tunable magnon gaps, sensitive to a tunable chemical potential and interfacial exchange coupling strength. The results also apply to finite temperatures. They elucidate topologically induced magnetic phenomena and pave the way for engineering exotic spin textures, such as skyrmions and chiral domain walls, in TI/FM hybrid systems with tunable interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03572v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Svingen Johnsen, Asle Sudb\o</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ferromagnetism vs. Antiferromagnetism in Narrow-Band Systems: Competition Between Quantum Geometry and Band Dispersion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03575</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03575v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetism in narrow-band systems arises from the interplay between electronic correlations, quantum geometry, and band dispersion. In particular, both ferro and anti-ferro magnets are known to occur as ground states of (different) models featuring narrow bands. This poses the question of which is favored and under what conditions. In this work, we present a unified theoretical framework to investigate spin physics within narrow bands. By deriving an effective spin model, we show that the non-atomic wavefunction of the narrow bands generally favors ferromagnetic ordering, while band dispersion promotes antiferromagnetic correlations. We find that the competition between these effects gives rise to a tunable magnetic phase and rich spin phenomena. Our approach offers a systematic way to study the magnetic properties of narrow-band systems, integrating the roles of wave function, band structure, and correlation effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03575v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoyu Hu, Oskar Vafek, Kristjan Haule, B. Andrei Bernevig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magic continuum in multi-moir\'e twisted trilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03583</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03583v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Moir\'e lattices provide a highly tunable platform for exploring the interplay between electronic correlations and band topology. Introducing a second moir\'e pattern extends this paradigm: interference between the two moir\'e patterns produces a supermoir\'e modulation, opening a route to further tailor electronic properties. Twisted trilayer graphene generally exemplifies such a system: two distinct moir\'e patterns arise from the relative twists between adjacent graphene layers. Here, we report the observation of correlated phenomena across a wide range of twisted trilayer graphene devices whose twist angles lie along two continuous lines in the twist-angle parameter space. Depending on the degree of lattice relaxation, twisted trilayer graphene falls into two classes: moir\'e polycrystals, composed of periodic domains with locally commensurate moir\'e order, and moir\'e quasicrystals, characterized by smoothly varying local moir\'e configurations. In helically twisted moir\'e polycrystals, we observe an anomalous Hall effect, consistent with topological bands arising from domains with broken $xy$-inversion symmetry. In contrast, superconductivity appears generically in our moir\'e quasicrystals. A subset of these systems exhibits signatures of spatially modulated superconductivity, which we attribute to the supermoir\'e structure. Our findings uncover the organizing principles of the observed correlated phases in twisted trilayer graphene, highlight the critical roles of the supermoir\'e modulation and lattice relaxation, and suggest a broader framework in which magic conditions arise not as isolated points but as extended manifolds within the multi-dimensional twist-angle space of complex moir\'e materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03583v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Li-Qiao Xia, Aviram Uri, Jiaojie Yan, Aaron Sharpe, Filippo Gaggioli, Nicole S. Ticea, Julian May-Mann, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Liang Fu, Trithep Devakul, Jurgen H. Smet, Pablo Jarillo-Herrero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mott Glass and Criticality in a S=1/2 Bilayer Heisenberg Model with Interlayer Bond Dilution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03604</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03604v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We employ the stochastic series expansion quantum Monte Carlo (SSE-QMC) method to investigate the $S = 1/2$ antiferromagnetic Heisenberg model on a bilayer square lattice with diluted interlayer couplings. Both regular and random dilution patterns are considered. In systems with regular dilution, tuning the interlayer interaction drives a quantum phase transition from a N\'eel-ordered phase to a quantum disordered phase, consistent with the $O(3)$ universality class. In contrast, random dilution gives rise to a two-step transition: from the N\'eel phase to an intermediate Mott glass (MG) phase, followed by a transition to the quantum disordered phase. Within the MG phase, the uniform magnetic susceptibility exhibits a stretched-exponential temperature dependence $\chi_u \sim \exp(-b/T^\alpha)$, $0 &lt; \alpha &lt; 1$. At the N\'eel-to-glass transition, quenched disorder modifies the critical exponents in a manner consistent with the Harris criterion. These findings provide new insights into disorder-driven quantum phase transitions and the emergence of glassy phases in diluted bilayer quantum magnets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03604v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kunpeng Li, Han-Qing Wu, Dao-Xin Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three-channel charge Kondo model at high transparency</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03612v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum impurity models involving a localized charge that is weakly coupled to electronic leads usually map to Kondo-like Hamiltonians that exhibit various quantum critical behaviors. Here, we address the opposite regime of high contact transparency by solving the model of a quantum island coupled to three quantum Hall edge channels. Using a functional renormalization group (FRG) approach, we demonstrate that the low-energy physics is controlled by a nonperturbative fixed point. The universal energy crossover in both the linear conductance and the impurity entropy is obtained. We reproduce the zero-frequency conductance and the leading low-energy exponent of the three-channel Kondo model, confirming their universality across all transparencies. For interacting leads -- a model that continuously connects to the pseudo-gap Kondo model at low transparency -- we find a line of fixed points as the Luttinger parameter $K$, which encodes the strength of the interactions, changes. Our work demonstrates that FRG methods are an efficient tool for solving quantum impurity problems in regimes where standard approaches fail.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03612v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Paris, Nicolas Dupuis, Christophe Mora</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological edge states in a double isomeric Class-II oligo(indenoindene)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03618</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03618v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: I report the theoretical prediction of non-trivial physics in a one dimensional multiradical system consisting in fused six and five membered ${\pi}$-conjugated carbon rings, known as oligo(indenoindene) (OInIn). Topologically protected electronic states may emerge in fermionic chains if there is an alternation in the coupling of adjacent unpaired electrons, being described effectively by the Su-Schrieffer-Heeger (SSH) model. Class-II OInIn isomers act as tight-binding chains in the non-interacting regime, thus we can expect the emergence of SSH physics in an OInIn produced by the combination of two isomers that belong to this class. That is the case of the system studied in this manuscript, whose calculated non-interacting band structure shows a gap opening compared to the gapless pure isomeric forms, hosting ingap localized states at the chain termini depending on the termination, and a non-zero Zak phase that confirms the non-trivial topology. These results were consistent with spin unrestricted mean-field Hubbard and density functional theory calculations, showing antiferromagnetic unquenched local magnetic moments at the pentagons, and strong edge localization depending on the termination. This work advances in the understanding of the physics of non-alternant multiradical ${\pi}$-conjugated hydrocarbons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03618v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ricardo Ortiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric Effects on Tunneling in Driven Quantum Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03674</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03674v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We review quantum tunneling provoked by external field driving, focusing on the role of geometric effects. The discussion begins with an overview of tunneling phenomena, including the Landau-Zener model and the Schwinger effect, both of which are essential frameworks to describe the generation of elementary excitation of the system. We also refer to the relation between the modern theory of polarization and the geometry of the system, and introduce the shift vector via adiabatic perturbation theory. Then we introduce the twisted Landau-Zener model and shown how the shift vector modulates tunneling probability, followed by several illustrative applications of this model. We also explain the Keldysh crossover, which is the crossover from a quantum tunneling regime to photon absorption regime in driven systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03674v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shintaro Takayoshi, Takashi Oka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Twisted quantum doubles are sign problem-free</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03708v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The sign problem is one of the central obstacles to efficiently simulating quantum many-body systems. It is commonly believed that some phases of matter, such as the double semion model, have an intrinsic sign problem and can never be realized in a local sign problem-free Hamiltonian due to the non-positivity of the wavefunction. We show that this is not the case. Despite failing to be stoquastic - the standard criteria for the existence of a sign problem - the double semion model as well as all twisted quantum double phases of matter for finite groups $\mathcal{G}$ can be realized in local sign problem-free Hamiltonians. The lack of a sign problem is not fine-tuned and does not require the Hamiltonian to be exactly solvable, with sign problem-free perturbations allowing access to a variety of topological phase transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03708v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leyna Shackleton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Plasmons in a network of topological states in twisted bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03781v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study surface plasmons in minimally-twisted bilayer graphene that contains a triangular network of partial dislocations (or AB-BA domain walls) hosting one-dimensional electronic states. We calculate plasmon dispersion by solving classical equations of motion for charge dynamics on the network links with impedance boundary conditions at the network nodes. The plasmon band structure is shown to be quasi-periodic in frequency and damped everywhere except at high-symmetry points of the moir\'e Brillouin zone. We compare our network-based formalism with the conventional random phase approximation and discuss when each approach is valid. Calculations of plasmon waves launched by local scatterers are presented to simulate terahertz nano-imaging experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03781v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brian S. Vermilyea, Michael M. Fogler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin Splitting Nernst Effect in Altermagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03822</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03822v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Altermagnet is a distinctive magnet phase, which has spin-split energy band but with zero net magnetic moment. In this paper, we propose that altermagnet behaves spin splitting Nernst effect: Under a longitudinal temperature gradient, the electrons with opposite spins tend to split oppositely in the transverse direction, thus generating a transverse spin current. The spin splitting Nernst effect is understood from the contribution of the longitudinal wave vector to the transverse group velocity. Using the nonequilibrium Green's function method, we calculate the spin-dependent transmission coefficient in the four-terminal altermagnet device. From the spin-dependent transmission coefficient, the nonzero transverse spin current from longitudinal temperature gradient is obtained, and the spin splitting Nernst effect is verified. We systematically study the parameter dependence of the spin splitting Nernst effect, while also performing symmetry analysis. The spin splitting Nernst effect can be easily regulated by Fermi surface energy, temperature, transport direction, and system size. Furthermore, in altermagnet, the $xy$-response and $yx$-response spin splitting Nernst coefficients are equal with $N_{s,xy}=N_{s,yx}$, different from the conventional spin Nernst effect where they are opposite. Meanwhile, the spin splitting Nernst effect require neither spin-orbit coupling nor net magnetism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03822v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xing-Jian Yi, Yue Mao, Xiancong Lu, Qing-Feng Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strongly correlated electrons in superconducting islands with fluctuating Cooper pairs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03908v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a particle-number conserving theory for many-body effects in mesoscopic superconducting islands connected to normal electrodes, which explicitly includes quantum fluctuations of Cooper pairs in the condensate. Beyond previous BCS mean-field descriptions, our theory can precisely treat the pairing and Coulomb interactions over an unprecedentedly broad range of parameters by using the numerical renormalization group method. On increasing the ratio of pairing to Coulomb interactions, the low-energy physics of the system evolves from the spin Kondo to mixed valence regimes and eventually reaches an anisotropic charge Kondo phase, while a crossover from $1e$- to $2e$-periodic Coulomb blockade of transport is revealed at high temperatures. For weak pairing, the superconducting condensate is frozen in the local spin-flip processes but fluctuates in the virtual excitations, yielding an enhanced spin Kondo temperature. For strong pairing, massive fluctuations of Cooper pairs are crucial for establishing charge Kondo correlations whose Kondo temperature rapidly decreases with the pairing interaction. Surprisingly, a charge-exchange induced local field may occur even at the charge degenerate point, thereby destroying the charge Kondo effect. These are demonstrated in the spectral and transport properties of the island.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03908v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.106.075117</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 106, 075117 (2022)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tie-Feng Fang, Ai-Min Guo, Qing-Feng Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconducting lens and Josephson effect in AA-stacked bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03915v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the superconducting transport phenomena, involving lensing effect and supercurrent in AA-stacked bilayer graphene, which is characterized by a linear gapless band with two shifted Dirac cones. Our findings indicate that cross Andreev reflection and Josephson current occur exclusively within the intracone process, while intercone scatterings are strictly prohibited. The normal/superconductor/normal junction can act as a superconducting lens for the upper and lower cones. Depending on cone index, the transmitted electrons and holes can be focused, collimated or diverged by adjusting the gate voltages. In superconductor/normal/superconductor junction, due to interlayer coupling, the critical currents of the two cones exhibit distinct oscillation periods with junction width, leading to an irregular oscillation of the total critical current. Furthermore, the oscillations of critical currents with exchange field maintain a stable phase difference of one quarter period between the two cones. Consequently, a cone-dependent 0-\pi transition is achieved in this Josephson junction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03915v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review B 111, 165411 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Tao Lu, Tie-Feng Fang, Qing-Feng Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atomic collapse of high-order singular potentials in graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03921</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03921v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Artificial atoms in graphene hosting a series of quasi-bound states can serve as an excellent platform to explore atomic collapse and become a basis to design novel graphene nanodevices. We theoretically study behaviors of massless Dirac fermions in singular potentials with a general form of 1/r^{\gamma}. Different from the Coulomb potential that demands a supercritical charge Z &gt; Zc, a high-order singular potential ({\gamma} &gt; 1) is found to in principle induce atomic collapse with an infinitesimal charge Z. The energies of atomic collapse states (ACSs) within these potentials are arranged roughly as a power sequence. We also show that some special ACSs can exist even above the bulk Dirac point, which cannot appear in the Coulomb potential. These findings uncover the anomalies of massless Dirac fermions in diverse charge potentials and provide guidance for further experiments and graphene nanodevice applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03921v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/kxy7-ntsm</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review B Vol. 111, Iss. 24, L241407 June 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Chen Zhuang, Yue Mao, Qing-Feng Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antiferromagnetic superlattices: anisotropic band and spin-valley valve in buckled two-dimensional materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03923v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Antiferromagnetic superlattices (AFSL) are proposed based on the buckled hexagonal two-dimensional materials, which can be realized by the proximity effect of the periodically deposited antiferromagnets. It is found that the AF proximity effect can give rise to valley-polarized minibands and conductance, which are not held under ferromagnetic proximity. The spin degeneracy and valley degeneracy are lifted simultaneously in the presence of AF proximity and electric field. In consequence, both minibands and conductance could be spin-valley polarized completely in AFSL. The symmetry of spin-valley polarization is analysed by considering the pseudospin rotation operations and spatial inversion operations. Furthermore, AFSL also induce a highly anisotropic band structure due to the spin-orbit coupling (SOC). In particular, the group velocity parallel to the periodic direction of AFSL is greatly renormalized, while the velocity perpendicular to the periodic direction remains unaffected, contrary to that observed in graphene superlattices. With the increase of SOC, the anisotropy becomes more prominent, leading to flattened band and electron supercollimation. The direction of anisotropy can be regulated by adjusting the potential and SOC. These findings offer an alternative approach to engineering anisotropic two-dimensional materials. As an application, the AFSL may well work as a symmetry-protected spin-valley valve easily controlled by the gate voltages.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03923v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review B 110, 035426 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Tao Lu, Tie-Feng Fang, Qing-Feng Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frustration-enhanced persistent currents in correlated trimer nanorings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03924v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the persistent current in a correlated trimer nanoring comprising of three magnetic atoms, which sits on a metallic host and encloses a magnetic flux. In the molecular-orbital regime, charge fluctuations can reverse the aromaticity of the trimer molecule by driving quantum phase transitions between many-body states. It is shown that in frustrated trimers the superexchange-induced current as a function of interatom hopping is enhanced by the competition of conflicting magnetic orders, with an asymmetric peak at the quantum criticality separating the ferromagnetic and antiferromagnetic Kondo regimes. Interestingly, the critical current undergoes an anomalous rise with temperature before decaying, signaling the suppression of Kondo bound state at finite temperature. Our results demonstrate that the coherent current response to external flux indeed conveys important information on the states of strongly correlated systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03924v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.L081117</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, L081117 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tie-Feng Fang, Wei-Tao Lu, Ai-Min Guo, Qing-Feng Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-Dimensional Higher-Order Topological Metals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03944v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the energy band structure and energy levels of graphene with staggered intrinsic spin-orbit coupling and in-plane Zeeman fields. Our study demonstrates that staggered intrinsic spin-orbit coupling induces bulk band crossover at the the \( K \) and \( K' \) valleys and generates antihelical edge states at the zigzag boundaries, resulting in topological metallic phases. Quantized transport coefficients confirm the existence of these antihelical edge states. Furthermore, an in-plane Zeeman field, regardless of orientation, opens a gap in the antihelical edge states while preserving bulk band closure, leading to higher-order topological metals with corner states. We also validate the presence of these corner states in nanoflakes with zigzag boundaries and confirm the metallic phases with crossed bands through a continuum low-energy model analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03944v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lizhou Liu, Cheng-Ming Miao, Qing-Feng Sun, Ying-Tao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hubbard dimer physics and the magnetostructural transition in the correlated cluster material Nb$_3$Cl$_8$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03988</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03988v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a combined computational and experimental study of Nb$_3$Cl$_8$, a correlated layered material containing Nb trimers, through the lens of competing intra- and intercluster interactions. Different proposed explanations for its magnetostructural transition such as charge disproportionation, antiferromagnetic quenching, and interlayer singlet formation are investigated in light of the various reported low-temperature structures. Our findings rule out the previously proposed charge-disproportionation, suggest an intricate interplay between Mott physics and the formation of interlayer singlets, and also hint at a possible explanation of the observed intratrimer scissoring distortion. We suggest that the physics of Nb$_3$Cl$_8$ should be understood in the context of weakly coupled Hubbard dimers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03988v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Carta, Peter Mlkvik, Fabian Grahlow, Markus Str\"obele, H. -J\"urgen Meyer, Carl P. Romao, Nicola A. Spaldin, Claude Ederer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Band bending and zero-conductance resonances controlled by edge electric fields in zigzag silicene nanoribbons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03991v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the band structure and transport property of a zigzag silicene nanoribbon when the electric fields are applied to the edges. It is found that a band bending could be induced and controlled by the antisymmetric edge fields, which can be understood based on the wave functions of the edge states. The highest valence band and the lowest conduction band coexist in the band bending region. With the narrowing of edge potentials, the bending increases gradually. When the edge fields become symmetric, an asymmetric band gap at the Dirac points can be obtained due to the intrinsic spin-orbit interaction, suggesting a valley polarized quantum spin Hall state. The gap could reach a maximum value rapidly and then decrease slowly as the electric fields increase. Due to the combining effect of the band bending, band selective rule, and resonant states, many zero-conductance resonances and resonance peaks appear in different regions, which could be described by the Fano resonance effect. Furthermore, the band bending and zero-conductance resonances are robust against the Hubbard interaction. The Hubbard interaction could work as a spin-dependent edge field, together with the edge electric fields, leading to a spin-dependent band gap and various quantum phases such as metal and half-metal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03991v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.102.125426</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 102, 125426 (2020)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Tao Lu, Qing-Feng Sun, Hong-Yu Tian, Ben-Hu Zhou, Hong-Mei Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital hybridization in graphene-based artificial atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04012</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04012v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Intraatomic orbital hybridization and interatomic bond formation are the two fundamental processes when real atoms are condensed to form matter. Artificial atoms mimic real atoms by demonstrating discrete energy levels attributable to quantum confinement. As such, they offer a solid-state analogue for simulating intraatomic orbital hybridization and interatomic bond formation. Signatures of interatomic bond formation has been extensively observed in various artificial atoms. However, direct evidence of the intraatomic orbital hybridization in the artificial atoms remains to be experimentally demonstrated. Here we, for the first time, realize the orbital hybridization in artificial atoms by altering the shape of the artificial atoms. The anisotropy of the confining potential gives rise to the hybridization between quasibound states with different orbital quantum numbers within the artificial atom. These hybridized orbits are directly visualized in real space in our experiment and are well reproduced by both numerical calculations and analytical derivations. Our study opens an avenue for designing artificial matter that cannot be accessed on real atoms through experiments. Moreover, the results obtained inspire the progressive control of quantum states in diverse systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04012v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41586-025-08620-z</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature 639, 73 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yue Mao, Hui-Ying Ren, Xiao-Feng Zhou, Hao Sheng, Yun-Hao Xiao, Yu-Chen Zhuang, Ya-Ning Ren, Lin He, Qing-Feng Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunneling Magnetoresistance Effect in Altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04015</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04015v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As an unconventional magnet, altermagnetism attracts great interest in condensed matter physics and applies a new research platform for the spintronics. Since the tunneling magnetoresistance (TMR) effect is an important research aspect in spintronics, we theoretically propose a universal altermagnetic sandwich device to achieve the TMR effect and investigate its transport properties. Using the nonequilibrium Green's function method and the Landauer-B\"uttiker formula, we obtain the conductance and the TMR ratio. By systematically rotating the orientations of the altermagnet and spin, we investigate how the altermagnetic orientations affect the conductance and the TMR ratio, and comprehensively demonstrate the dependence of the conductance and the TMR ratio on a range of parameters in the system. By tuning the altermagnetism strength and the Fermi energy, as well as rotating the orientations in the altermagnet, the TMR ratio can reach a value of over 1000%. In addition, we analyze the detailed symmetry relations of the conductance and the TMR ratio in our system. Our approach provides a new design concept for the next-generation information technologies based on the altermagnetic platform, paving the way for the development of spintronics applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04015v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Fei Sun, Yue Mao, Yu-Chen Zhuang, Qing-Feng Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moir\'e spintronics: Emergent phenomena, material realization and machine learning accelerating discovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04045</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04045v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Twisted van der Waals (vdW) materials have emerged as a promising platform for exploring the exotic quantum phenomena and engineering the novel material properties in two dimensions, which could bring revolutionary developments in spintronics. This Review aims at providing an overview of recent progress on emerging moir\'e spintronics in twisted vdW materials, with a particular focus on two-dimensional magnetic materials. After a brief introduction to the general features of twisted vdW materials, we discuss recent theoretical and experimental studies on stacking-dependent interlayer magnetism, non-collinear spin textures, moir\'e magnetic exchange interactions, moir\'e skyrmions and moir\'e magnons. We further highlight the ability to accelerate the discovery and design multifunctional materials for moir\'e spintronics with the assistance of machine learning. We conclude with the most pressing challenges and potential opportunities in this rapidly expanding field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04045v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fengjun Zhuo, Zhenyu Dai, Hongxin Yang, Zhenxiang Cheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic behavior of $5d^1$ Re-based double perovskite Sr$_2$ZnReO$_6$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04071v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The subtle interplay between spin-orbit coupling, exchange interactions, and cation ordering can lead to exotic magnetic states in transition-metal ions. We report a comprehensive study of the Re-based (5$d^1$) ordered double perovskite oxide Sr$_2$ZnReO$_6$ combining synchrotron x-ray diffraction (XRD), magnetic susceptibility, muon spin relaxation ($\mu$SR) measurements, and density functional theory (DFT) calculations. XRD reveals that Sr$_2$ZnReO$_6$ crystallizes in the monoclinic structure (space group $P2_1/n$) at low temperature. Magnetic susceptibility data indicate a transition below $\sim$13 K, with $M$--$H$ loops showing ferromagnetic-like hysteresis and an unusually high coercive field of 23 kOe at 2 K. Zero-field $\mu$SR measurements detect static and spatially disordered internal fields below $T_M \simeq $ 12 K, consistent with a canted antiferromagnetic ground state determined by detailed DFT and force-theorem in Hubbard-I calculations. The reduced high-temperature effective moment ($\sim0.76~\mu_B$) and very small static moment ($\lesssim 0.222~\mu_B$) derived from $\mu$SR analysis and local-field simulations indicate a decisive role of spin-orbit coupling. Through a combined experimental and computational approach we unambiguously determine the canted antiferromagnetic order in Sr$_2$ZnReO$_6$, showing that a very small ordered moment coexists with an exceptionally large coercivity. These results underscore the crucial role of spin-orbit coupling and orbital ordering, providing new insights into magnetism in 5$d^1$ double perovskites.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04071v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Maikudi Isah, Biswajit Dalal, Xun Kang, Dario Fiore Mosca, Ifeanyi John Onuorah, Valerio Scagnoli, Pietro Bonf\`a, Roberto De Renzi, Alexei A. Belik, Cesare Franchini, Kazunari Yamaura, Samuele Sanna</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Hall Antidot as a Fractional Coulombmeter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04209v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The detection of fractionally charged quasiparticles, which arise in the fractional quantum Hall regime, is of fundamental importance for probing their exotic quantum properties. While electronic interferometers have been central to probe their statistical properties, their interpretation is often complicated by bulk-edge interactions. Antidots, potential hills in the quantum Hall regime, are particularly valuable in this context, as they overcome the geometric limitations of conventional designs and act as controlled impurities within a quantum point contact. Furthermore, antidots allow for quasiparticle charge detection through straightforward conductance measurements, replacing the need for more demanding techniques. In this work, we employ a gate-defined bilayer graphene antidot operating in the Coulomb-dominated regime to study quasiparticle tunneling in both integer and fractional quantum Hall states. We show that the gate-voltage period and the oscillation slope directly reveal the charge of tunneling quasiparticles, providing a practical method to measure fractional charge in graphene. Moreover, we report the first measurement of the $e/3$ fractional charge in a graphene-based device. The simplicity and tunability of this design open a pathway to extend AD-based charge measurements to other van der Waals materials, establishing antidots as a powerful and broadly applicable platform to study the quantum Hall effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04209v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mario Di Luca, Emily Hajigeorgiou, Zekang Zhou, Tengyan Feng, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Mitali Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nature of magnetic exchange interactions in kagome antiferromagnets FeGe and FeSn</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04228</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04228v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic exchange interactions (MEIs) in kagome magnets exhibit rich features due to the interplay of charge, spin, orbital and lattice degrees of freedom, giving rise to a variety of exotic quantum states. Through first-principles calculations, we systematically investigate the MEIs in kagome antiferromagnets FeGe and FeSn. While the antiferromagnetic order originates from the interlayer coupling between neighboring kagome layers, Fe atoms within each kagome layer couple ferromagnetically, driven by the competition between ferromagnetically favorable direct MEIs and antiferromagnetically favorable Ruderman-Kittel-Kasuya-Yosida (RKKY) interactions. The stronger direct MEIs but weaker RKKY interactions in FeGe result in a substantially higher N\'eel temperature with respect to FeSn. Interestingly, the nearest neighboring exchange energy in both materials approximately linearly depends on the Fe-Fe bond length, so that moderate compressive strain can significantly enhance their N\'eel temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04228v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yitao Zheng, Yan Zhu, Jun Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Specific features of the $\pi$-electron spectrum of narrow achiral $(2m,m)$ nanoribbons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04306</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04306v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: On the basis of the Su-Schrieffer-Heeger-H\"uckel-type Hamiltonian, we consider the tight-binding eigenvalue problem for a sequence of pyrene molecules forming a narrow $(2m,m)$ graphene nanoribbon. Specific features of the corresponding dispersion relation are analyzed and illustrated with several examples. It is shown that the $\pi$-electron spectrum of the pyrene oligomer includes local states, in contrast to the spectrum of linear acene, which consists only of extended states. We analyze and illustrate the difference in the behavior of
  the electron density distribution for extended and local electronic states. Explicit analytic expressions for the Green's function coefficients of the pyrene molecule are also presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04306v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lyuba Malysheva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unoccupied bands in the molybdenum dichalcogenides MoS$_2$, MoSe$_2$, and MoTe$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04411</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04411v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present angle-resolved reflected electron spectroscopy (ARRES) data for the three molybdenum-based transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) \mos, \mose, and \mote. To follow the changes as the series moves from S to Se to Te in more detail, we determine accurate IV-spectra for monolayers and bulk TMDs. These experimental data sets are then compared with theoretical predictions for both the unoccupied band structure and the scattering density of states. We find good agreement, especially for lower energies where inelastic effects are relatively unimportant. Furthermore, we identify a series of interlayer resonances for which the dependence of the hybridization effects on the layer count is observed. Although these resonances bear similarity to interlayer resonances in hBN and graphene, they differ in their character, being dominated by unoccupied $d$-states of the chalcogen-atoms. The unoccupied states studied and analyzed here play a key role in all processes that require an electron to temporarily reside in a state above the vacuum level, such as in photoemission and secondary electron emission experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04411v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Jobst, E. E. Krasovskii, R. Ribeiro, T. A. de Jong, C. R. Dean, R. M. Tromp, S. J. van der Molen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reversing non-Hermitian skin accumulation with a non-local transverse switch</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02686</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02686v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Asymmetrically directed couplings in non-Hermitian systems cause directional amplification that leads to boundary skin state accumulation. However, counter-intuitively, the direction of accumulation may not follow that of the directed couplings. In this work, we demonstrate new mechanisms where this accumulation can be systematically reversed without modifying the couplings at all, just by adjusting the system size or boundary conditions in a different, transverse direction. Moreover, the reversed skin dynamics can be made very robust by suppressing the amplification in the original non-reversed direction. We motivate our approach through a series of warm-up models, culminating in a designed non-Hermitian Kagome lattice whereby wavepacket simulations demonstrate how robust reversed skin dynamics can be switched on/off in a non-local transverse manner. Our findings highlight how the non-trivial entanglement between the spectral loops of different PBC directions can be harnessed as a directional amplification switch, paving the way for new avenues of non-Hermitian sensing and lasing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02686v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengjie Yang, Ching Hua Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Active Dual-Gated Graphene Transistors for Low-Noise, Drift-Stable, and Tunable Chemical Sensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04137</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04137v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Graphene field-effect transistors (GFETs) are among the most promising platforms for ultrasensitive chemical and biological sensing due to their high carrier mobility, large surface area, and low intrinsic noise. However, conventional single-gate GFET sensors in liquid environments suffer from severe limitations, including signal drift, charge trapping, and insufficient signal amplification. Here, we introduce a dual-gate GFET architecture that integrates a high-k hafnium dioxide local back gate with an electrolyte top gate, coupled with real-time feedback biasing. This design enables capacitive signal amplification while simultaneously suppressing gate leakage and low-frequency noise. By systematically evaluating seven distinct operational modes, we identify the Dual Mode Fixed configuration as optimal, achieving up to 20x signal gain, &gt; 15x lower drift compared with gate-swept methods, and up to 7x higher signal to noise ratio across a diverse range of analytes, including neurotransmitters, volatile organic compounds, environmental contaminants, and proteins. We further demonstrate robust, multiplexed detection using a PCB-integrated GFET sensor array, underscoring the scalability and practicality of the platform for portable, high-throughput sensing in complex environments. Together, these advances establish a versatile and stable sensing technology capable of real-time, label-free detection of molecular targets under ambient and physiological conditions, with broad applicability in health monitoring, food safety, agriculture, and environmental screening.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04137v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vinay Kammarchedu, Heshmat Asgharian, Hossein Chenani, Aida Ebrahimi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fermi surface and pseudogap in highly doped Sr$_{2}$IrO$_{4}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18542</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18542v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The fate of the Fermi surface in bulk electron-doped Sr$_{2}$IrO$_{4}$ remains elusive, as does the origin and extension of its pseudogap phase. Here, we use high-resolution angle-resolved photoelectron spectroscopy (ARPES) to investigate the electronic structure of Sr$_{2-x}$La$_{x}$IrO$_{4}$ up to $x=0.2$, a factor of two higher than in previous work. We find that the antinodal pseudogap persists up to the highest doping level, and thus beyond the sharp increase in Hall carrier density to $\simeq 1+x$ recently observed above $x^{*}\simeq 0.16$ [Y.-T. Hsu et al., Nature Physics 20, 1593 (2024)]. This suggests that doped iridates host a unique phase of matter in which a large Hall density coexists with an anisotropic pseudogap, breaking up the Fermi surface into disconnected arcs. The temperature boundary of the pseudogap is $T^{*}\simeq 200$ K for $x=0.2$, comparable to cuprates and to the energy scale of short range antiferromagnetic correlations in cuprates and iridates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18542v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Y. Alexanian, A. de la Torre, S. McKweon Walker, M. Straub, G. Gatti, A. Hunter, S. Mandloi, E. Cappelli, S. Ricc\`o, F. Y. Bruno, M. Radovic, N. C. Plumb, M. Shi, J. Osiecki, C. Polley, T. K. Kim, P. Dudin, M. Hoesch, R. S. Perry, A. Tamai, F. Baumberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Propylenidene: A Novel Metallic Carbon Monolayer with Unconventional Ring Topology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03494</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.03494v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2D) carbon allotropes have drawn significant interest owing to their impressive physical and chemical characteristics. Following graphene's isolation, a wide range of 2D carbon materials has been suggested, each with distinct electronic, mechanical, and optical traits. Rational design and synthesis of new 2D carbon structures hinge on experimentally reported precursors. Here, we present a 2D carbon allotrope, propylenidene (PPD), originating from bicyclopropylidene. PPD forms a rectangular lattice with 3, 8, and 10-membered carbon rings. Density functional theory (DFT) simulations investigate its structural, electronic, mechanical, and optical properties. Our study shows PPD to be metallic. PPD exhibits absorption in the infrared and visible range, showing directional dependence in its response. Mechanically, PPD exhibits marked anisotropy; Young's modulus ($Y$) varies between 205.83 N/m and 164.46 N/m. These findings underscore the potential of this novel monolayer in applications such as energy storage, gas sensing, and optoelectronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.03494v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jose A. S. Laranjeira, K. A. L. Lima, Nicolas F. Martins, Luis A. Cabral, L. A. Ribeiro Junior, Julio R. Sambrano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
