<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 05:00:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Electrical Modulation and Probing of Antiferromagnetism in Hybrid Multiferroic Heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15754v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The unique features of ultrafast spin dynamics and the absence of macroscopic magnetization in antiferromagnetic (AFM) materials provide a distinct route towards high-speed magnetic storage devices with low energy consumption and high integration density. However, these advantages also introduce challenges in probing and controlling AFM order, thereby restricting their practical applications. In this study, we demonstrate an all-electric control and probing of the AFM order in heavy metal (HM)/AFM insulator (AFMI) heterostructures on a ferroelectric substrate at room temperature (RT). The AFM order was detected by the anomalous Hall effect (AHE) and manipulated by the ferroelectric field effect as well as the piezoelectric effect in heterostructures of Pt/NiO/0.7Pb(Mg$_{1/3}$Nb$_{2/3}$)O$_{3}$--0.3PbTiO$_{3}$ (PMN--PT). The non-volatile control of AFM order gives rise to a 33\% modulation of AHE, which is further evidenced by synchrotron-based X-ray magnetic linear dichroism (XMLD). Combined with the $in$-$situ$ piezoelectric response of AHE, we demonstrate that ferroelectric polarization contributes mainly to the control of the AFM order. Our results are expected to have broader implications for efficient spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15754v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0274464</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Appl. Phys. Rev. 12, 041410 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yuhan Liang, Huiping Han, Hetian Chen, Yujun Zhang, Yi Zhang, Chao Li, Shun Lan, Fangyuan Zhu, Ji Ma, Di Yi, Jing Ma, Liang Wu, Tianxiang Nan, Yuan-Hua Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Floquet Bosonic Kitaev Chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15804</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15804v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a class of periodically driven (Hermitian) modified bosonic Kitaev chains that effectively hosts rich nonHermitian Floquet topological phenomena. Two particular models are investigated in details as case studies. The first of these represents a minimal topologically nontrivial model in which nonHermitian skin effect, topological zero modes, and topological $\pi$ modes coexist. The other displays a more sophisticated model that supports multiple topological zero modes and topological $\pi$ modes in a tunable manner. By subjecting both models to perturbations such as a finite onsite bosonic frequency and spatial disorder, these features exhibit distinct responses. In particular, while generally all topological edge modes are robust against such perturbations, the nonHermitian skin effect is easily suppressed and revived by, respectively, the onsite bosonic frequency and spatial disorder in the first model, but it could be insensitive to both perturbations in the second model. Our studies thus demonstrate the prospect of a periodically driven bosonic Kitaev chain as a starting point in exploring various nonHermitian Floquet topological phases through the lens of a Hermitian system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15804v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raditya Weda Bomantara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetostriction in the $J$-$K$-$\Gamma$ model: Application of the numerical linked cluster expansion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15811</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15811v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We apply the numerical linked cluster expansion (NLCE) to study thermodynamic properties of the proximate Kitaev magnet $\alpha$-RuCl$_3$ on the honeycomb lattice in the presence of a magnetic field. Using the extended spin-1/2 $J$-$K$-$\Gamma$ model and based on documented exchange and magnetoelastic coupling parameters, we present results for the internal energy, the specific heat, and the magnetization. Moreover, the linear magnetostriction coefficient perpendicular to the plane is calculated, which is sensitive to changes of the in-plane spin-spin correlations. We find the magnetostriction to display a dip-like feature, in line with the temperature dependent and field-driven suppression of magnetic order in $\alpha$-RuCl$_3$. Our results are consistent with previous findings, establishing NLCE also as a tool to study magnetoelastic features of quantum magnets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15811v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Schwenke, Wolfram Brenig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlocal Transport in Cr-doped (Bi,Sb)2Te3: Absence of Nonchiral Edge States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15930</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15930v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The quantum anomalous Hall effect shows great promise for realization of the ohm without the need for an external magnetic field. The most mature material platform is magnetically doped topological insulators. In these materials, precise quantization is limited to low temperatures, with the activation energy for dissipative transport typically in the range of 1 K. One potential source of dissipative transport is non-chiral edge states. These states are expected to be present in sufficiently thick samples. In this work, we perform extensive Hall and non-local resistance measurements in a Hall bar geometry at 2 K. By comparing 15 independent transport measurements to different transport models, we find that the system behavior is well-described by a simple continuum Ohm's law model. The addition of non-chiral edge states into the model does not significantly improve the fitting, and we conclude that there is not strong evidence for these states. We discuss the implications of our results for the prospect of high temperature quantized anomalous Hall effect in these materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15930v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valery Ortiz Jimenez, Paul M. Haney, Farzad Mahfouzi, Ngoch Thanh Mai Tran, Albert F. Rigosi, Curt A. Richter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conventional superconductivity in single-crystalline BiPt</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15944v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Binary Bi-Pd/Pt systems have attracted a lot of interest because of their topologically non-trivial nature along with superconductivity. We report the structural and superconducting properties of high-quality single-crystalline BiPt using a comprehensive range of experimental techniques, including X-ray diffraction, electron microscopy, muon spin rotation/relaxation ({\mu}SR), magnetization, resistivity, and heat capacity. Our findings establish that BiPt is a weak type-II superconductor with a transition temperature (Tc) of 1.2 K which exhibits pronounced anisotropic superconducting characteristics attributed to its hexagonal crystal structure. Magnetization and electronic transport studies reveal that BiPt lies within the dirty limit, while {\mu}SR and heat capacity data indicate conventional s-wave superconductivity that maintains time-reversal symmetry. This work provides valuable insights into the pairing symmetry and superconducting mechanism of topologically trivial BiPt, a sound comparison system for other Bi-based topologically nontrivial superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15944v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Sharma, M. Pula, Sajilesh K. P., J. Gautreau, B. S. Agboola, J. P. Clancy, J. E. Sonier, A. Ghara, S. R. Dunsiger, M. Greven, M. J. Lagos, A. Kanigel, G. M. Luke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skyrmionium meta-matter: a topologically heterogeneous magnetic crystal with emergent hybrid dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15999</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15999v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce and systematically investigate a new class of topological magnetic textures, skyrmionium meta-matter, composed of skyrmioniums (Skm, $Q=0$) and skyrmions (Sk, $Q=-1$) arranged in periodic lattices mimicking the richness of atomic materials. Pure skyrmionium lattices are unstable against elongation distortions and relax into the spiral phase, but even a small fraction of skyrmions acts as topological "pins" that stabilize diverse mixed Skm--Sk crystals. We classify these states by topological stoichiometry (Skm$_n$Sk$_m$) and show that each composition hosts multiple metastable polymorphs with distinct plane-group symmetries. Structural transformations between polymorphs are achieved by varying the lattice spacing, suggesting experimental control via pressure or strain. The collective spin dynamics is explored for both in-plane and out-of-plane AC magnetic fields. The resulting absorption spectra show resonant modes beyond the two rotational and one breathing mode of conventional skyrmion lattices. We identify hybrid excitations unique to Skm--Sk crystals, including (i) deformation-assisted rotations, where skyrmions acquire polygonal shapes and rotate, and (ii) orbital modes, where breathing skyrmioniums induce circular motion of confined skyrmions without changing their size. Mode frequencies span sub-GHz to above 10 GHz, consistent with exchange and DMI energy scales. Our results establish skyrmionium-based meta-matter as a versatile platform for tunable, topologically heterogeneous magnetic lattices with rich structural and dynamical properties, paving the way for reconfigurable magnonic and spintronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15999v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrey O. Leonov, Kaito Nakamura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral Spin-Split Magnons in the Metallic Altermagnet CrSb</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16086v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report the collective magnetism of the metallic altermagnet CrSb. Magnetic susceptibility and polarized neutron diffraction measurements show that CrSb is a perfectly compensated Ising altermagnet below a N\'eel temperature of $T_N = 733(4)$ K. Inelastic neutron scattering experiments reveal anisotropic and highly-dispersive antiferromagnetic spin waves with velocities of 61(2) km s$^{-1}$ and 58(2) km s$^{-1}$ along the in-plane and out-of-plane directions, respectively. The observed magnon dispersions along high-symmetry directions of the Brillouin zone are well described by a minimal Heisenberg model up to third nearest neighbors of alternating antiferromagnetic and ferromagnetic character, $J_1 = 23(4)$ meV, $J_2 = -5.4(8)$ meV, $J_3 = 5.2(8)$ meV, and an Ising single-ion anisotropy term $D = 0.15(4)$ meV. We observe clear signatures of chiral spin splitting along the low-symmetry $\Gamma$-$L$ direction, characteristic of higher-order altermagnetic exchange interactions, the first such observation in a metallic altermagnet.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16086v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashutosh K. Singh, Niclas Heinsdorf, Abraham A. Mancilla, J\"orn Bannies, Avishek Maity, Alexander I. Kolesnikov, Masaaki Matsuda, Matthew B. Stone, Marcel Franz, Jonathan Gaudet, Alannah M. Hallas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phonon Dichroisms Revealing Unusual Electronic Quantum Geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16141v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The quantum geometry tensor, intrinsic geometric characteristics of electronic states, plays a crucial role in the various nontrivial electromagnetic phenomena in quantum materials. Here, we reveal that quantum geometry significantly modifies phonon dichroisms through electron-phonon interactions in solids that break time-reversal and spatial inversion symmetries. Specifically, the circular phonon dichroism is primarily dominated by the heat magnetic moments, while the linear phonon dichroism depends on the heat Drude weight, a thermal analog of band Drude weight. Furthermore, we establish the f-sum rule for the heat magnetic moment that facilitates its experimental detections. We demonstrate our key findings in an archetypal model system: ferromagnetic two-dimensional electron gases with Rashba spin-orbit coupling. Our work uncovers the quantum-geometric origin of common phonon dichroisms and predicts the detectable signature of the heat magnetic moment of electrons in solids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16141v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ding Li, Guoao Yang, Tao Qin, Jianhui Zhou, Yugui Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synthetic Spatiotemporal Plasmonic Vortices On Chip</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16155</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16155v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spatiotemporal vortices are polychromatic modes that intertwine orbital angular momentum (OAM) in space and time. Here we introduce a new class of such vortices, spatiotemporal plasmonic vortices (STPVs), carrying nontrivial topological spin textures. They are generated by chronotopic interference of temporally delayed plasmonic eigen-vortices, where a $\pi$-phase dislocation in the space-frequency domain maps into a 2$\pi$ spiraling phase in space-time, with the resulting focus-defocus dynamics emulate U(1) gauge transitions. Using interferometric time-resolved photoemission electron microscopy (ITR-PEEM), we directly image their nanometer-attosecond (nano-atto) evolution and control vortex number and position. Quantum-path analysis of coherent two-photon photoemission (2PP) processes reveals the nonlinear plasmonic polarization fields and angular-momentum conservation, establishing STPVs as a platform for probing spatiotemporally structured quantum matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16155v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qian Chen, Shuoshuo Zhang, Guoyu Xian, Haoqiang Hu, Xiaohua Wu, Xiaofei Wu, Jer-Shing Huang, Chen-Bin Huang, Jin-Hui Zhong, Yuquan Zhang, Xiaocong Yuan, Changjun Min, Yanan Dai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrafast {\mu}eV-Precision Bandgap Engineering in Low-Dimensional Topological Insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16165</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16165v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Precise and ultrafast control of electronic band structures is a central challenge for advancing quantum functional materials and devices. Conventional approaches--such as chemical doping, lattice strain, or external gating--offer robust stability but remain confined to the quasi-static regime, far from the intrinsic femto- to picosecond dynamics that govern many-body interactions. Here, using cryogenic transient reflectance spectroscopy, we realize dynamic bandgap engineering in the anisotropic topological insulator $\alpha$-Bi$_4$Br$_4$ with unprecedented micro-electron-volt ($\mu$eV) precision. The exceptional sensitivity arises from the cooperative action of long-lived topological carriers, stabilized by restricted bulk-to-edge scattering phase space, together with symmetry-resolved coherent phonons that modulate inter-chain hopping. These channels jointly modify Coulomb screening and interband transitions, enabling both gradual and oscillatory control of the electronic structure. Supported by first-principles and tight-binding theory, we further demonstrate a dual-pump coherent control strategy for continuous, mode-selective tuning of electronic energies with $\mu$eV accuracy. This framework paves the way for ultrafast on-demand band-structure engineering, pointing toward new frontiers in quantum optoelectronics, precision measurement in molecular and biological systems, and attosecond control of matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16165v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peng Tan, Yuantao Chen, Yuqi Zhang, Hanyan Cheng, Guoyu Xian, Ming Cheng, Minghong Sun, Jiaxin Yin, Feifan Wang, Yaxian Wang, Yanjun Liu, Mingyuan Huang, Zhiwei Wang, Yugui Yao, Sheng Meng, Li Huang, Yanan Dai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Following the Long-Term Evolution of sp$^3$-type Defects in Tritiated Graphene using Raman Spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16168</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16168v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report on the evolution of tritium-induced sp$^3$-defects in monolayer graphene on a Si/SiO$_2$ substrate, by comparing large-area Raman maps of the same two samples, acquired just after fabrication and twice thereafter, about 9-12 months apart. Inbetween measurements the samples were kept under standard laboratory conditions. Using a conservative classification of sp$^3$-type spectra, based on the D/D' peak intensity ratio, we observed almost complete depletion of sp$^3$-type defects over the investigation period of about two years. This by far exceeds the ~5.5% annual reduction expected from tritium decay alone (~3x larger). This change in the defect composition is accompanied by a recovery of the 2D-band of graphene and an overall decrease in defect-density, as determined via the D/G intensity ratio. Hydogenated graphene is reported to be reasonably stable over several months, when kept under vacuum, but suffers substantial hydrogen loss under laboratory air conditions. While the results shown here for tritiated graphene exhibit similarities with hydrogenated graphene, however, some distinct differences are observed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16168v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Genrich Zeller, Magnus Schl\"osser, Helmut H. Telle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometrical properties of strained and twisted moir\'e heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16219</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16219v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The experimental observations of many interaction-driven electronic phases in moir\'e superlattices have stimulated intense theoretical and experimental efforts to understand and engineer these correlated physics. Strain is a powerful tool for manipulating and controlling the geometrical and electronic structures of moir\'e superlattices. This review provides a comprehensive introduction to the geometry of strained moir\'e superlattices. First, starting from the linear elasticity theory, we briefly introduce the general formalism of small deformations in two-dimensional materials, and discuss the particular cases of uniaxial, shear and biaxial strain. Then, we apply the theory to twisted and strained moir\'e materials, mainly focusing on the hexagonal homobilayers, hexagonal heterobilayers and monoclinic lattices. Special moir\'e geometries, like the quasi-unidimensional patterns, square patterns and hexagonal, are theoretically predicted by manipulating the strain and twist. Finally, we review recently developed strain techniques and the special moir\'e geometries realized via these approaches. This review aims at equipping the reader with a robust understanding on the description and implementation of strain in moir\'e materials, as well as highlight some major breakthroughs in this active field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16219v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Federico Escudero, Francisco Guinea, Zhen Zhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Preserving the Josephson Coupling of Twisted Cuprate Junctions via Tailored Silicon Nitride Circuits Boards</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16241</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16241v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Controlled fabrication of twisted van der Waals heterostructures is essential to unlock the full potential of moire materials. However, achieving reproducibility remains a major challenge, particularly for air-sensitive materials such as $Bi_{2}Sr_{2}CaCu_{2}O_{8+\delta}$ (BSCCO), where it is crucial to preserve the intrinsic and delicate superconducting properties of the interface throughout the entire fabrication process. Here, we present a dry, inert and cryogenic assembly method that combines silicon nitride nanomembranes (NMBs) with pre-patterned electrodes and the cryogenic stacking technique (CST) to fabricate high-quality twisted BSCCO Josephson junctions (JJs). This protocol prevents thermal and chemical degradation during both interface formation and electrical contact integration. We also find that asymmetric membrane designs, such as a double cantilever, effectively suppress vibration-induced disorder due to wire bonding, resulting in sharp and hysteretic current-voltage characteristics. The junctions exhibit a twist-angle-dependent Josephson coupling with magnitudes comparable to the highest-performing devices reported to date, but achieved through a straightforward and versatile contact method, offering a scalable and adaptable platform for future applications. These findings highlight the importance of both interface and contact engineering in addressing reproducibility in superconducting van der Waals heterostructures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16241v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/smll.202506520</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Small (2025): e06520</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tommaso Confalone, Flavia Lo Sardo, Domenico Montemurro, Davide Massarotti, Valerii M. Vinokur, Genda Gu, Francesco Tafuri, Kornelius Nielsch, Golam Haider, Nicola Poccia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite-temperature topological magnons in honeycomb ferromagnets with sublattice asymmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16284v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Comment [Y.-M. Li, B. Wei, and K. Chang, Phys. Rev. Lett. 132, 219601 (2024)] pointed out that it is incorrect to predict the temperature-driven topological phase transition of Dirac magnons in honeycomb ferromagnets with Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interactions based on the theory in Lu et al. [Y.-S. Lu, J.-L. Li, and C.-T. Wu, Phys. Rev. Lett. 127, 217202 (2021)]. Here we propose that by breaking the sublattice symmetries in honeycomb ferromagnets, increasing temperature could induce topological transitions from the trivial phase at zero temperature based on the linear spin wave theory to the Chern insulating phase above a critical temperature without changing any spin-spin interactions. The key to the finite-temperature topological magnons is considering the magnon-magnon interactions (MMIs) at a mean-field level. A self-consistently renormalized spin wave theory is employed to include self-energy corrections from MMIs, guaranteeing that the critical temperatures for topological transitions are below the Curi\'e temperatures. Across the critical temperatures, the magnon band gap closes and reopens at K or K? points in the Brillouin zone, accompanied by nontrivial Berry curvature transitions. However, in stark contrast to the work of Lu et al. [Phys. Rev. Lett. 127, 217202 (2021)], the topological transitions cannot be revealed by the thermal Hall effect of magnons. Our work provides a realistic scheme for achieving a finite-temperature topological phase in honeycomb ferromagnets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16284v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/qzjz-w3cj</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 174417(2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lin-Gang Wei, Yun-Mei Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological transition in spectrum of skyrmion crystal with uniaxial anisotropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16359v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The band structure of elementary excitations of skyrmion crystal in thin ferromagnetic film with Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction and uniaxial magnetic anisotropy under external magnetic field is studied. In the absence of anisotropy there is a topological transition in the spectrum of skyrmion crystal: the gap between breathing and counter-clock-wise modes closes, which is accompanied by changes of Berry curvature sign of these bands. In this work we demonstrate that such topological transition exists in some range of the uniaxial anisotropy values. We present a phase diagram showing that the value of the field of topological transition is higher in the easy-plane domain and lower in the easy-axis domain of anisotropy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16359v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. E. Timofeev, D. A. Bedyaev, D. N. Aristov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying Phase Transformations in Alloying Anodes via In-Situ Liquid Cell Hard X-ray Spectroscopy and Cryogenic Microscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16382</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16382v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding electrochemical phenomena at complex liquid solid interfaces requires linking real time structural dynamics with atomic scale interfacial chemistry. Here, we integrate operando synchrotron X-ray fluorescence and diffraction with high resolution cryogenic electron and ion multi model microscopy to provide a mechanistic understanding of Pt based alloying anodes across length scales. We directly observe the initial lithiation driven formation of Li2Pt and its evolution to a stable LiPt intermetallic phase during extended cycling via a solid solution type reaction mechanism. Simultaneously, the solid electrolyte interphase transitions from an unstable carbonate rich to a stable LiF dominated composition, confirmed by cryogenic scanning transmission electron microscopy and electron energy loss spectroscopy. Crucially, cryogenic atom probe tomography reveals spatially distinct compositional regimes within the alloy anode, including lithium flux limited, heterogeneous interfacial zone and a diffusion controlled, homogeneous LiPt alloy bulk. This nanoscale compositional gradient rationalises the emergent solid solution reaction mechanism and highlights how kinetic limitations and interface dynamics govern alloy formation and electrochemical stability. Our findings demonstrate a broadly applicable correlative framework bridging operando structural dynamics with near atomic resolution interfacial chemistry, advancing the rational design of durable alloy electrodes for next generation energy storage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16382v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Neil Mulcahy, Syeda Ramin Jannat, Yaqi Li, Tigran Simonian, Mariana Palos, James O. Douglas, Jessica M. Walker, Baptiste Gault, Mary P. Ryan, Michele Shelly Conroy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless transition with enhanced phase stiffness in $d$-wave strongly coupled two-dimensional superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16385v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We reveal the key role of the $d$-wave symmetry of the superconducting gap in strongly coupled two-dimensional superconductors in determining the properties of the Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless (BKT) transition, associated with a sizable enhancement of the phase stiffness compared to nodeless-gap superconductors. The enhanced stiffness originates from extended regions of vanishing gap around the nodal lines of the Brillouin zone (BZ). Our study, based on mean-field and BKT theory, presents a comparative analysis of $s$-wave and $d$-wave scenarios, highlighting the features of the latter that boost the stiffness and the BKT transition temperature (T$_{BKT}$). The comparison focuses on two quantities: the mean-field critical temperature and the maximum superconducting gap related to the pairing strengths. We present a phase diagram showing the scaling of T$_{BKT}$ with respect to the mean-field critical temperature across the BCS-BEC crossover and the evolution of the pseudogap. We also present a zero-temperature phase-stiffness intensity map over the Brillouin zone, displaying a two-component structure consisting of low- and high-stiffness regions whose extent depends on microscopic parameters. These results identify the nodal gap structure of strongly coupled two-dimensional superconductors as a key mechanism enabling enhanced stiffness and elevated T$_{BKT}$ compared to their $s$-wave counterparts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16385v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sathish Kumar Paramasivam, Andrea Perali, Milorad V. Milo\v{s}evi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arbitrary Control of Non-Hermitian Skin Modes via Disorder and Electric Field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16393</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16393v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The non-Hermitian skin effect (NHSE), characterized by the accumulation of a macroscopic number of bulk states at system boundaries, is a hallmark of non-Hermitian physics. However, effective control of skin-mode localization in higher-dimensional systems remains challenging. Here, we propose a versatile approach to manipulate the localization of skin modes in a two-dimensional nonreciprocal lattice by combining disorder and a static electric field. While the electric field alone suppresses the NHSE in a clean system, the introduction of disorder induces transverse wave-packet transport perpendicular to the field. When the nonreciprocal hopping direction is misaligned with the electric field, the hopping component perpendicular to the field guides the wave-packet propagation and leads to boundary localization. By tuning the relative orientations of the electric field and the nonreciprocal hopping, arbitrary control over the boundary localization position can be achieved. Our results demonstrate a robust and tunable mechanism for engineering boundary accumulation and directed transport in non-Hermitian systems, offering new opportunities for applications in classical platforms and quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16393v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhao-Fan Cai, Yang Li, Yu-Ran Zhang, Tao Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear magneto-birefringence as a probe of altermagnetism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16421v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Altermagnets are a class of collinear magnets that exhibit non-relativistic spin splitting (NRSS) of electronic bands in the absence of net magnetization. Their potential to generate large spin polarization without spin-orbit coupling has created strong interest in probes that access the underlying order parameter directly. In this Perspective, we show that linear magneto-birefringence (LMB) provides a natural and broadly applicable route to detecting altermagnetic order. Building on the correspondence between the momentum-space structure of NRSS and the ferroic ordering of magnetic multipoles in real space, we demonstrate how $d$-wave and $g$-wave NRSS textures yield distinct LMB responses. We present a symmetry-based framework that identifies the optical geometries and field configurations required to isolate specific multipole components, enabling domain imaging and providing benchmarks for theoretical models of LMB.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16421v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Sunko, J. Orenstein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissipation-Shaped Quantum Geometry in Nonlinear Transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16422v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The theory of the intrinsic nonlinear Hall effect, a key probe of quantum geometry, is plagued by conflicting expressions for the conductivity that is independent of the dissipation strength (rate, $\Gamma^0$). We clarify the origin of this ambiguity by demonstrating that the "intrinsic" response is not universal, but is inextricably linked to the dissipation mechanism that establishes the non-equilibrium steady state (NESS). We establish a benchmark by solving the exact NESS density matrix for a generic Bloch system coupled to a featureless fermionic bath. Our exact $\Gamma^0$ conductivity decomposes into two parts: (i) a geometric contribution, $\sigma^{\text{geo}}$, whose form recovers the intraband quantum metric dipole ($\sim\partial_k g$), providing an exact derivation that clarifies inconsistencies in the literature, and (ii) a novel, purely kinetic contribution, $\sigma^{\text{kin}} \propto v^3 f^{(4)}_0$, which is absent when dissipation is modeled by white-noise disorder (e.g., a constant-$\Gamma$ Green's function model). The discrepancy in $\sigma^{\text{kin}}$ between these distinct physical mechanisms is a proof that the $\Gamma^0$ nonlinear conductivity is not a unique property of the Bloch Hamiltonian, but is contingent on the physical system-bath coupling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16422v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhichao Guo, Xing-Yuan Liu, Hua Wang, Li-kun Shi, Kai Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-scale competition in the Majorana-Kondo system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16446</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16446v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A side-coupled Majorana zero mode in Kondo systems realizes a simple yet nontrivial hybridization that profoundly alters the low-energy physics, making such setups promising candidates for detecting Majorana zero modes. Recently, we demonstrated that the low-energy behavior of this system can be captured by a spin-charge-entangled screening process with an \(A\otimes N\) boundary condition. Here, we investigate the evolution of both the screening cloud and the boundary condition in the presence of competing terms that could break either the spin-charge-entangled \({\rm SU}_{\bf L}(2)\) rotation symmetry or the topological degeneracy. We introduce a temperature-dependent spatial integral of the screening cloud, which can be obtained from the numerical renormalization group. This quantity serves as a proper observable that unambiguously captures the properties of the screening process across temperatures. A clear crossover from conventional Kondo spin screening to spin-charge-entangled screening is observed. Taking into account the overlap between Majorana zero modes, the \(A\otimes N\) boundary condition reduces to a normal one, yet the spin-charge-entangled screening is protected by the \({\rm SU}_{\bf L}(2)\) symmetry. On the other hand, perturbation that breaks the \({\rm SU}_{\bf L}(2)\) symmetry can destroy the screening singlet, while leaving the low-temperature \(A\otimes N\) boundary condition intact.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16446v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yun Chen, Haojie Shen, Wei Su, Rui Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adiabatic charge transport through non-Bloch bands</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16480</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16480v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore the non-reciprocal intracell hopping mediated non-Hermitian topological phases of an extended Su-Schrieffer-Heeger model hosting second-nearest-neighbour hopping. We microscopically analyze the phase boundaries using the non-Bloch momentum while the off-critical (critical) phases are directly associated with the gapped (gapless) nature of the non-Bloch bands that we derive from the characteristic equation using the gauge freedom. The non-Bloch momentum accurately reflects the bulk boundary correspondence (BBC) explaining the winding number profile under open boundary conditions. We examine the adiabatic dynamics to promote the concept of adiabatic charge transport in a non-Hermitian scenario justifying the BBC in spatio-temporal Bott index and non-Bloch Chern number. Once the non-Bloch bands experience no (a) gap-closing during the evolution of time, quantized flow of is preserved (broken). Our study systematically unifies the concept of non-Bloch bands for both static and driven situations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16480v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dharana Joshi, Tanay Nag</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$c=-2$ conformal field theory in quadratic band touching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16496v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quadratic band touching in fermionic systems defines a universality class distinct from that of linear Dirac points, yet its characterization as a quantum critical point remains incomplete. In this work, I show that a $(d+1)$-dimensional free-fermion model with quadratic band touching exhibits spatial conformal invariance, and that its equal-time ground-state correlation functions are exactly captured by the $d$-dimensional symplectic fermion theory. I establish this correspondence by constructing explicit mappings between physical fermionic operators and the fields of the symplectic fermion theory. I further explore the implications of this correspondence in two spatial dimensions, where the symplectic fermion theory is a logarithmic conformal field theory with central charge $c=-2$. In the corresponding $(2+1)$-dimensional systems, I identify anyonic excitations originating from the underlying symplectic fermion theory, even though the Hamiltonian is gapless. Transporting these excitations along non-contractible loops generates transitions among topologically degenerate ground states, in close analogy with those in topologically ordered phases. Moreover, the action of a $2\pi$ rotation on these excitations is represented by a Jordan block, reflecting the logarithmic character of the associated conformal field theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16496v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rintaro Masaoka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Leveraging the Bi$_2$O$_3$--Fe$_2$O$_3$ Phase Diagram to Tailor BiFeO$_3$ Structure and Dielectric Response</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16513</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16513v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Bismuth ferrite ($BiFeO_3$, BFO) is a promising multiferroic oxide whose practical utilisation is limited by secondary-phase formation and defect-driven electrical inhomogeneity within the $Bi_2O_3$-$Fe_2O_3$ system. In this work, BFO was synthesised via solid-state reaction using 55:45 and 70:30 (mol%) of $Bi_2O_3$ $\colon$ $Fe_2O_3$ precursors sintered between 700$^O$C and 800$^\circ$C, and characterised through X-ray diffraction, Raman spectroscopy, SEM, and impedance spectroscopy. A refined phase diagram identifies the onset of liquid-phase formation near 835$^O$C, delineating a narrow thermal window for phase-pure BFO. The 55:45 composition evolves toward rhombohedral $R3c$ symmetry with lattice contraction, suppression of Sillenite- and Mullite-type impurities, and markedly reduced vibrational disorder, yielding homogeneous grains with near-Debye dielectric relaxation ($n &gt; 0.9$), low CPE prefactors, and a four-orders-of-magnitude increase in bulk AC conductivity upon sintering at 775$^\circ$C. In contrast, the Bi-rich 70:30 samples retain expanded lattice volumes, defective grain boundaries, and highly depressed Nyquist arcs ($n &lt; 0.5$), reflecting persistent structural disorder and stabilisation of insulating secondary phases. The convergence of structural, microstructural, and impedance signatures identifies the 55:45 precursor sintered at 775$^\circ$C as the optimal condition within the studied range, establishing a clear structure-property relationship that enables controlled synthesis and reliable dielectric performance in BFO-based multiferroic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16513v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subir Majumder, Paul Ben Ishai, Gilad Orr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing moire excitons in MoSe2/WSe2 heterobilayers by combined micro-photoluminescence and lateral force microscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16539v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study interlayer excitons in MoSe2/WSe2 heterobilayers, by combining lateral force microscopy and micro-photoluminescence spectroscopy. This allows us to correlate the spatial profile of the moir\'e superlattice with the distribution of optically active states accessible to interlayer excitons. In heterostructures where a few degrees twist angle is imposed between the MoSe and WSe crystallographic axes, we show that a continuous moir\'e lattice is realized across areas close to the optical diffraction limit. In such regions, the photoluminescence reduces to a few narrow-band lines only, energetically distributed consistently with the geometry of the moir\'e lattice. This correlation reveals that interlayer excitons explore a controlled periodic confinement, paving the way towards implementations of Bose-Hubbard models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16539v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Caussou, H. Moutaabbid, M. Bernard, F. Margaillan, T. Taniguchi, K. Watanabe, C. Lagoin, F. Dubin, V. Voliotis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pervasive spin-triplet superconductivity in rhombohedral graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16578</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16578v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic fields typically suppress superconductivity once the Zeeman energy exceeds the pairing gap, unless mechanisms such as unconventional pairing, strong spin-orbit coupling, or intrinsic magnetism intervene. Several graphene platforms realize such mitigating routes, exhibiting superconductivity resilient to magnetic fields. Here we report superconductivity in rhombohedral heptalayer graphene that is both induced and stabilized by in-plane magnetic field ($B_{\parallel}$), with critical fields far beyond the Pauli paramagnetic limit. The superconductivity spans a wide gate range and emerges from a sharp zero-field resistive ridge that tracks approximately constant conduction band filling. The presence of zero-field superconductivity and the evolution of the critical temperature with $B_{\parallel}$ are highly gate sensitive. We also observe a weak superconducting diode effect in several distinct regimes within the superconducting phase, including nearby to an integer quantum anomalous Hall state generated by a boron nitride moir\'e superlattice, indicating a potential coexistence of valley imbalance and superconductivity. These results establish several intriguing new properties of spin-triplet, field-induced superconductivity in a thick rhombohedral graphene stack.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16578v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manish Kumar, Derek Waleffe, Anna Okounkova, Raveel Tejani, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, \'Etienne Lantagne-Hurtubise, Joshua Folk, Matthew Yankowitz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charge-Ordered States and the Phase Diagram of the Extended Hubbard Model on the Bethe lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16603v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the extended Hubbard model (EHM) with both onsite Hubbard interaction and the intersite density-density interaction between nearest-neighbors using the standard Hartree mean-field approximation (MFA) on the Bethe lattice. We found that, at the ground state, the system can be in a charge-ordered insulating (COI), a charge-order metallic (COM) or a non-charge-ordered (NO) state. Moreover, the finite-temperature phase diagrams are presented. Several observables like a charge-order parameter, a spectral function, and particularly at finite temperatures, a charge carrier concentration (to visualize the degree of metallicity) are analyzed. The results show that increasing onsite repulsion suppresses charge order and change the properties of the system from insulating to metallic. Worth noting, that a number of phenomena can be found within the MFA, where their analysis is much simpler than in more advanced approaches. The method used for the EHM on the Bethe lattice also allows for a series of analytical derivations and simplification to see general geometry-independent features and analytical results, avoiding the numerical inaccuracies and other issues that appear with a purely numerical solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16603v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleksey Alekseev (Institute of Spintronics,Quantum Information, Faculty of Physics,Astronomy, Adam Mickiewicz University in Pozna\'n, Poland), Konrad Jerzy Kapcia (Institute of Spintronics,Quantum Information, Faculty of Physics,Astronomy, Adam Mickiewicz University in Pozna\'n, Poland)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying Twist Angles in Cuprate Heterostructures with Anisotropic Raman Signatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16610v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Artificially engineered twisted van der Waals (vdW) heterostructures have unlocked new pathways for exploring emergent quantum phenomena and strongly correlated electronic states. Many of these phenomena are highly sensitive to the twist angle, which can be deliberately tuned to tailor the interlayer interactions. This makes the twist angle a critical tunable parameter, emphasizing the need for precise control and accurate characterization during device fabrication. In particular, twisted cuprate heterostructures based on Bi2Sr2CaCu2O8+x have demonstrated angle-dependent superconducting properties, positioning the twist angle as a key tunable parameter. However, the twisted interface is highly unstable under ambient conditions and vulnerable to damage from conventional characterization tools such as electron microscopy or scanning probe techniques. In this work, we introduce a fully non-invasive, polarization-resolved Raman spectroscopy approach for determining twist angles in artificially stacked BSCCO heterostructures. By analyzing twist-dependent anisotropic vibrational Raman modes, particularly utilizing the out-of-plane A1g vibrational mode of Bi/Sr at 116 cm-1, we identify clear optical fingerprints of the rotational misalignment between cuprate layers. Our high-resolution confocal Raman setup, equipped with polarization control and RayShield filtering down to 10 cm-1, allows for reliable and reproducible measurements without compromising the material's structural integrity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16610v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/apxr.202500108</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Lo Sardo, F. et al (2025), Quantifying Twist Angles in Cuprate Heterostructures with Anisotropic Raman Signatures. Adv. Phys. Res. e00108</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Flavia Lo Sardo, Marina Esposito, Tommaso Confalone, Christophe Tremblay, Valerii M. Vinokur, Genda Gu, Domenico Montemurro, Davide Massarotti, Francesco Tafuri, Kornelius Nielsch, Nicola Poccia, Golam Haider</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stabilizing Fractional Chern States in Twisted MoTe2: Multi-band Correlations via Non-perturbative Renormalization Group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16641v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The observation of fraction quantum Hall states in twisted MoTe2 has sparked a lof of interest in this phenomenon. Most theoretical works to date rely on the brute-force exact diagonalization which is limited to the one partially occupied band. In this work, we present strong evidence that the effect of higher lying bands cannot be ignored due to strong interband interactions. To tackle these effects, we introduce a non-perturbative driven similarity renormalization group (DSRG) method, originally developed for problems in quantum chemistry. We apply this methodology to twisted MoTe2 at fractional hole fillings of {\nu} = 1/3 and 2/3 across a spectrum of twist angles. Our results show that at {\nu} = 1/3, the many-body excitation energy gaps are substantially reduced compared to the one-band treatment. For {\nu} = 2/3, we find that the dynamic correlations stemming from interband interactions stabilize fractional Chern insulating phases at larger twist angles, consistent with the experimental findings. By examining the correlated orbitals and their single-particle topological features, we demonstrate that this stabilization at higher twist angles arises predominantly from the dynamic correlations, rather than conditions on the single-particle quantum geometric tensor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16641v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Run Hou, Andriy H. Nevidomskyy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strained hyperbolic Dirac fermions: Zero modes, flat bands, and competing orders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16667v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Starting from the nearest-neighbor tight-binding model on {10,3} and {14,3} hyperbolic lattices that, for a uniform hopping amplitude, gives rise to emergent Dirac fermions on a curved space with a constant negative curvature, displaying a vanishing density of states, we propose spatially modulated hopping pattern therein that preserve the underlying 5- and 7-fold rotational symmetries, respectively, and effectively couples fermions to time-reversal symmetric axial magnetic fields. Such strain-induced axial fields produce a flat band near zero-energy, triggering nucleation of a charge density-wave, featuring a staggered pattern of fermionic density between two sublattices, and the Haldane phase fostering intra-sublattice circulating currents with a net zero magnetic flux for weak nearest- and next-nearest-neighbor Coulomb repulsions, respectively. Sufficiently weak on-site Hubbard repulsion destabilizes such flat bands toward the formation of a magnetic phase that simultaneously supports antiferromagnetic and ferromagnetic orders in the whole system. While the magnetization in the bulk and boundary cancel each other, the Ne\'el order is of the same sign everywhere, thereby yielding a global antiferromagnet. Throughout, we draw parallels between these findings and the well-studied qualitatively similar results on a 3-fold rotational symmetric strained honeycomb lattice, thereby unifying the phenomenon of axial magnetic catalysis for Dirac fermions, encompassing the ones living on the Euclidean plane. Finally, we show that with a specific class of non-Hermiticity, manifesting via an imbalance in the hopping amplitudes between two sublattices in the opposite directions, magnitudes of all these orders can be boosted substantially when all the eigenvalues in the noninteracting systems are real, staging a non-Hermitian amplification of axial magnetic catalysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16667v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher A. Leong, Bitan Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Engineering multi-mode bosonic squeezed states using Monte-Carlo optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15805</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15805v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Bosonic systems, such as photons and ultracold atoms, have played a central role in demonstrating quantum-enhanced sensing. Quantum entanglement, through squeezed and GHZ states, enables sensing beyond classical limits. However, such a quantum advantage has so far been confined to two-mode bosonic systems, as analogous multi-mode squeezed states are non-trivial to prepare. Here, we develop a Monte-Carlo based optimization technique which can be used to efficiently engineer a Hamiltonian control-sequence for multi-mode bosonic systems to prepare multi-mode squeezed states. Specifically, we consider a Bose-Einstein condensate in an optical lattice, relevant for applications in gravimetry and gradiometry, and demonstrate that metrologically useful squeezed states can be generated using the Bose-Hubbard Hamiltonian which includes on-site atomic interactions, tunable via Feshbach resonances. By analyzing the distribution (density) of the quantum Fisher information (QFI) over the Hilbert space, we identify a characteristic \textit{intermediate scaling} of the QFI: $\mathcal{O}(N^2 L+L^2 N)$, which lies between the standard quantum limit (SQL) and the Heisenberg limit (HL) for $N$ atoms in $L$ modes. We show that in general, within the Hilbert space there is a finite, $\mathcal{O}(1)$ measure subset of Hilbert space with an intermediate QFI scaling. Therefore, one can find a Hamiltonian control sequence using a Monte Carlo optimization over random control sequences, that produces a state with intermediate scaling of the QFI. We assume an experimentally accessible range of the control parameters in the Hamiltonian resources and show that the intermediate scaling can be readily achieved. Our results indicate that the HL can be approached in quantum gravimetry using realistic experimental parameters for systems with $L=\mathcal{O}(1)$ and $N\gg L$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15805v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jieqiu Shao, Diego A. R. Dalvit, Lukasz Cincio, Bharath Hebbe Madhusudhana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal work statistics in quenched gapless quantum systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15971</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15971v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the universality of work statistics performed during a quench in gapless quantum systems. We show that the cumulants of work scale separately in the fast and slow quench regimes, following a power law analogous to the universal scaling in the Kibble-Zurek mechanism for topological defect formation in phase transition. As an example, we analyze the nonequilibrium dynamics of a quenched Heisenberg XXZ chain at its critical gapless state using the bosonization picture, resulting in a Tomonaga-Luttinger liquid. The analytical scaling is in agreement with the exact numerical calculation for the fast and slow quench regimes. In finite systems, the characteristic function display an oscillatory pattern which disappears in the thermodynamic limit. This study is particularly useful for understanding the thermodynamics of adiabatic quantum computation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15971v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Donny Dwiputra, Mir Faizal, Francesco Marino, Freddy P. Zen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal features of non-analytical energy storage in quantum critical quantum batteries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16274</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16274v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum batteries are quantum mechanical systems able to store and release energy in a controlled fashion. Among them, a special role is played by quantum structures defined as networks of two-level systems. In this context, it has recently been shown that the energy stored in free fermion quantum batteries is sensitive to the quantum phase diagram of the battery itself. This sensitivity is relevant for stabilizing the stored energy and designing optimal charging protocols. In this article, we explore universal charging behaviors of free fermion quantum batteries across quantum phase transitions. We first analyze a Dirac cone-like model to extract general features. Then, we verify our findings by means of two relevant lattice models, namely the Ising chain in a transverse field and the Haldane model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16274v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riccardo Grazi, Dario Ferraro, Niccol\`o Traverso Ziani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calculation of the biquadratic spin interactions based on the spin cluster expansion for \textit{ab initio} tight-binding models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04369</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04369v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a calculation scheme using \textit{ab initio} tight-binding Hamiltonians to evaluate biquadratic magnetic interactions. This approach relies on the spin cluster expansion combined with the disordered local moment (DLM) method, originally developed within the multiple scattering Korringa-Kohn-Rostoker method. Applying it to a single-orbital Hubbard model with two sublattices, we show that the evaluated DLM biquadratic interactions are in good agreement with those obtained from the strongly correlated limit, demonstrating the wide applicability of the method to various magnetic systems with large local moments. We then apply it to the \textit{ab initio} tight-binding models for elemental magnetic metals; the resulting magnetic interactions align well with previous literature. Finally, we explore its performance in more complex compounds, such as transition metal dichalcogenides with intercalation of 3\textit{d} transition metals and potassium electrosodalite. The obtained results for both compounds show good agreement with experiments. The present approach offers a convenient \textit{ab initio} path for evaluating biquadratic interactions and understanding the electronic mechanisms controlling them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04369v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.7566/JPSJ.94.124709</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Tatsuto Hatanaka, Juba Bouaziz, Takuya Nomoto, Ryotaro Arita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissipation induced elastic-mode instability with topological excitation in holographic non-equilibrium steady cnoidal wave supersolid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12437</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12437v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The possible existence of an exotic phase of matter rigid like a solid but able to sustain persistent and dissipation-less flow like a superfluid, a "supersolid", has been the subject of intense theoretical and experimental efforts since the discovery of superfluidity in Helium-4. Recently, it has been proposed that nonlinear periodic modulations known as cnoidal waves, that naturally emerge in Bose-Einstein condensates, provide a promising platform to find and study supersolidity in non-equilibrium phases of matter. Nevertheless, so far the analysis has been limited to a one-dimensional zero-temperature system. By combining the dissipative Gross-Pitaevskii equation with a finite temperature holographic model, we show that the proposed cnoidal wave supersolid phases of matter are dynamically unstable at finite temperature. We ascribe this instability to the dynamics of the "elastic" Goldstone mode, which arises as a direct consequence of translational order in the presence of dissipation, and establish a direct connection between the elastic-mode instability of the supersolid state and the nucleation of topological excitations during the relaxation towards a homogeneous equilibrium state, which resembles the Landau instability in superfluids. Finally, we numerically confirm the dominant role of the elastic-mode instability in the collision between cnoidal waves in the strong dissipation limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12437v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11433-025-2820-5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>SCIENCE CHINA Physics, Mechanics &amp; Astronomy, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Peng Yang, Yu Tian, Matteo Baggioli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of Quantum-Criticality-Class Crossover at the LaAlO$_3$/KTaO$_3$ (111) Interface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19668</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19668v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In two-dimensional (2D) limit, the quantum fluctuation is significantly enhanced which could induce a quantum phase transition. Investigating the quantum criticality is an effective approach to elucidate the underlying physics of 2D superconductivity. Here we report the observation of different universality classes of quantum criticality at the superconducting LaAlO$_3$/KTaO$_3$ (111) interface, i.e. the normal quantum Griffiths singularity (QGS) and the anomalous QGS. The switch of the quantum criticality class is observed from the normal QGS in a low $T_c$ sample with weaker spin-orbit coupling (SOC) to the anomalous QGS in a high $T_c$ sample with stronger SOC. Moreover, owing to the remarkable SOC strength, the high $T_c$ sample exhibits an unprecedentedly enhanced quantum fluctuation at an unusually elevated temperature approaching the Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless (BKT) transition temperature $T_{BKT}$. This work provides comprehensive recognition of the different quantum criticality classes in the same superconducting LaAlO$_3$/KTaO$_3$ (111) system, which deepens the understanding of the superconducting mechanism of interfacial superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19668v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/qp2x-cl3q</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 216202 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jia Liu, Long Cheng, Mingyue Zhang, Junkun Zha, Fei Ye, Xiaofang Zhai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theory of intervalley-coherent AFM order and topological superconductivity in tWSe$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14296</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14296v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The recent observation of superconductivity in the vicinity of Fermi surface reconstructed insulating or metallic states has established twisted bilayers of WSe\textsubscript{2} as an exciting platform to study the interplay of strong electron-electron interactions, broken symmetries and topology. In this work, we use a first-principles, material-specific theoretical treatment that is unbiased with respect to electronic instabilities to study the emergence of electronic ordering in twisted WSe\textsubscript{2} driven by gate-screened Coulomb interactions. We construct exponentially localized moir\'e Wannier orbitals that faithfully capture the bandstructure and topology of the system, project the gate-screened Coulomb interaction onto them and use unbiased functional renormalization group techniques to resolve the momentum and orbital structure of the leading instabilities and the relevant energy scales. We find an interplay between intervalley-coherent antiferromagnetic (IVC-AFM) order and chiral, mixed-parity $d/p$-wave superconductivity for carrier concentrations near a displacement field and twist-angle-tunable van-Hove singularity. Our microscopic approach establishes incommensurate IVC-AFM spin fluctuations as the dominant electronic mechanism driving the formation of superconductivity in $\theta = 5.08^{\circ}$ twisted WSe\textsubscript{2} and explains key aspects of recent experiments including the asymmetric density dependence of the spin ordering with respect to the van-Hove line, the single and double-peak structure of the DOS in the ordered (hole-doped) IVC-AFM phase, the emergence of superconductivity as the density is varied across the van-Hove line and the evolution of the displacement field-density phase diagram with twist angles between $3.7^{\circ} \dots 5^{\circ}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14296v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/gfzx-rrcr</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Ammon Fischer, Lennart Klebl, Valentin Cr\'epel, Siheon Ryee, Angel Rubio, Lede Xian, Tim O. Wehling, Antoine Georges, Dante M. Kennes, Andrew J. Millis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ab Initio Theory of Phonon Magnetic Moment Induced by Electron-Phonon Coupling in Magnetic Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10160</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10160v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Circularly polarized phonons, characterized by nonzero angular momenta and magnetic moments, have attracted extensive attention. However, a long-standing critical issue in this field is the lack of an approach to accurately calculate phonon magnetic moments resulting from electron-phonon coupling (EPC) in realistic materials. Here, based on the linear response framework, we develop an ab initio theory for calculating EPC-induced magnetic properties of phonons, applicable to both insulating and metallic materials. Our method can precisely calculate phonon Zeeman splittings in magnetic metals with significant EPC, as demonstrated by the remarkable agreement with recent experimental observations of phonon Zeeman splitting in the ferromagnetic Weyl semimetal Co3Sn2S2. In addition, the long-sought magnetic phonon spectra across the entire Brillouin zone are obtained, facilitating the study of magnetic phonon transport and topology. Specifically, by constructing an inertially decoupled lattice model, we propose candidate materials exhibiting intrinsic phonon Chern states with robust unidirectional edge phonon currents. Our work paves the way for investigating novel phonon phenomena in magnetic quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10160v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/tpjd-dh1m</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Fuyi Wang, Xinqi Liu, Hong Sun, Huaiqiang Wang, Shuichi Murakami, Lifa Zhang, Haijun Zhang, Dingyu Xing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linked skyrmions in shifted magnetic bilayer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01491</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.01491v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a shifted magnetic bilayer that exhibits various magnetic phases and magnetic textures with arbitrarily large topological numbers. The proposed system is characterised by a mutually orthogonal Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction (DMI) in two different layers which can be induced by suitably placing non-magnetic atom with spin-orbit coupling. At weak interlayer coupling, the ground state resembles a checker-board pattern containing regions with unfavourable magnetic alignment which we call anti-aligned points. At finite interlayer coupling and finite external magnetic field, the bilayer can demonstrate a new class of magnetic solitons where multiple magnetic solitons can be connected by topological point defects which we call linked skyrmion. In addition to that the model also demonstrates conventional skyrmion-bags and $k\pi$-skyrmions. Finally, with rigorous first principle calculations, we propose a suitable material candidate where these magnetic configurations can be observed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.01491v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sumit Ghosh, Hiroshi Katsumoto, Gustav Bihlmayer, Moritz Sallermann, Vladyslav M. Kuchkin, Filipp N. Rybakov, Olle Eriksson, Stefan Bl\"ugel, Nikolai S. Kiselev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First-principles prediction of altermagnetism in transition metal graphite intercalation compounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18353v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report the emergence of altermagnetism, a magnetic phase characterized by the coexistence of compensated spin ordering and momentum-dependent spin splitting, in graphite intercalation compounds (GICs), a prototypical material system long investigated for its tunable electronic and structural properties. Through first-principles calculations, we demonstrate that vanadium-intercalated stage-1 graphite compounds, exhibit inherent altermagnetic properties. The hexagonal crystal system and antiferromagnetic ordering of V atoms generate a magnetic space group that enforces alternating spin polarization in momentum space while maintaining zero net magnetization. The calculated band structure reveals robust altermagnetic signatures: along the high-symmetry direction, we observe a pronounced spin splitting of ~270 meV with alternating spin polarization. Crucially, the spin splitting exhibits minimal sensitivity to spin-orbit coupling (SOC) effect, highlighting the dominance of exchange interactions over relativistic effects. From Monte Carlo simulations, we predict a magnetic transition temperature ($T_m$ ) of ~228 K, indicating stable magnetic ordering above liquid nitrogen temperatures. The combination of symmetry-protected spin textures, SOC-independent splitting, and elevated $T_m$ temperature makes V-GICs as a promising candidate for spintronic applications, particularly for zero-field spin-polarized current generation and topologically robust spin transport. As the first demonstration of carbon-based alternating magnetic systems, this work offers a design paradigm for engineering spin-polarized quantum states governed by crystalline symmetry constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18353v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weida Fu, Guo-Dong Zhao, Tao Hu, Wencai Yi, Hui Zhang, Alessandro Stroppa, Wei Ren, Zhongming Ren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electron-Phonon interaction and lattice thermal conductivity from metals to 2D Dirac crystals: a review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18477</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.18477v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Electron--phonon (e--ph) coupling governs electrical resistivity, hot-carrier cooling, and critically, thermal transport in solids. Recent first-principles advances now predict e--ph limited thermal conductivity from d-band metals and wide-band-gap semiconductors to 2D Dirac crystals without empirical parameters. In bulk metals, ab-initio lifetimes show that phonons, though secondary, still carry up to 40\% of the heat once e--ph scattering is included. We next survey coupled Boltzmann frameworks, exemplified by \textsc{elphbolt}, that capture mutual drag and ultrafast non-equilibrium in semiconductors. For 2D Dirac crystals, mirror symmetry, carrier density, strain, and finite size rearrange the scattering hierarchy: ZA modes dominate pristine graphene yet become the main resistive branch in nanoribbons once symmetry is broken. At low Fermi energies and high temperatures, the standard 3-particle decay is partially cancelled, elevating 4-particle processes and necessitating dynamically screened, higher-order theory. Throughout, we identify the microscopic levers such as the electronic density of states, phonon frequency, deformation potential, and show how doping, strain, or dielectric environment can tune e--ph damping. We conclude by outlining open challenges such as: developing coupled e--ph solvers, solving the full mode-to-mode Peierls--Boltzmann equation with 4-particle terms, embedding correlated electron methods in e--ph workflows, and leveraging higher-order e--ph coupling and symmetry breaking to realise phononic thermal diodes and rectifiers. Solving these challenges will elevate e--ph theory from a diagnostic tool to a predictive, parameter-free platform that links symmetry, screening, and many-body effects to heat and charge transport in next-generation electronic, photonic, and thermoelectric devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.18477v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sina Kazemian, Giovanni Fanchini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lattice Translation Modulated Symmetries and TFTs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03889</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03889v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Modulated symmetries are internal symmetries that are not invariant under spacetime symmetry actions. We propose a general way to describe the lattice translation modulated symmetries in 1+1D, including the non-invertible ones, via the tensor network language. We demonstrate that the modulations can be described by some autoequivalences of the categories. Although the topological behaviors are broken because of the presence of modulations, we can still construct the modulated version of the symmetry TFT bulks by inserting a series of domain walls described by invertible bimodule categories. This structure not only recovers some known results on invertible modulated symmetries but also provides a general framework to tackle modulated symmetries in a more general setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03889v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ching-Yu Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic Nonlinear Planar Thermal Hall Effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01748</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01748v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce the intrinsic nonlinear planar thermal Hall effect (NPTHE)-- a dissipationless thermal response proportional to $(\nabla T)^2B$, which arises when the temperature gradient $\nabla T$ and magnetic field $\mathbf{B}$ lie within the same plane. The effect originates from a thermal gradient induced correction to the Berry curvature, characterized by the thermal Berry connection polarizability (TBCP) tensor, leading to a nonlinear transverse heat current independent of scattering time. A symmetry analysis shows that the intrinsic NPTHE is permitted only in noncentrosymmetric crystal point groups lacking horizontal mirror symmetry. Using a tilted Dirac model, we demonstrate that its characteristic angular dependence provides an effective means to control the nonlinear thermal response. Our results establish a new class of quantum geometry driven intrinsic nonlinear thermal transport, offering both a sensitive probe of band geometry and a pathway toward nonlinear thermal functionalities in quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01748v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chanchal K. Barman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent Dynamical Translational Symmetry Breaking as an Order Principle for Localization and Topological Transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04360</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.04360v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Localization transitions represent a fundamental class of continuous phase transitions, yet they occur without any accompanying symmetry breaking. We resolve this by introducing the concept of dynamical translational symmetry (DTS), which is defined not by the Hamiltonian but by the long-time dynamics of local observables. Its order parameter, the time-averaged local translational contrast (TLTC), quantitatively diagnoses whether evolution restores or breaks translational equivalence. We demonstrate that the TLTC universally captures the Anderson localization transition, the many-body localization transition, and topological phase transitions, revealing that these disparate phenomena are unified by the emergent breaking of DTS. This work establishes a unified dynamical-symmetry framework for phases transitions beyond the equilibrium paradigm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.04360v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yucheng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic structure of relaxor ferroelectrics from first principles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11097v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We hybridize the swap Monte Carlo and geometric relaxation methods to determine the intrinsic compositional structure (CS) of the lead magnesium niobate (PMN) relaxor. We verify the stability of a Nb-rich sublattice in PMN, as prescribed by the prevailing random-site model. However, ions in the complementary sublattice are not randomly mixed. Most Nb ions collapse into a single percolating cluster with a mesh-like structure. This specific geometry serves to prevent large space charges, and this behavior differs from typical phase separation in metallic alloys. Subsequent molecular dynamics simulations predict a pair distribution function that is consistent with neutron scattering experiments. Analysis of dipolar structures in the Nb cluster sheds light on the unique dielectric properties of PMN.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11097v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinyu Xu, Kehan Cai, Pinchen Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$C^\ast$-categorical prefactorization algebras for superselection sectors and topological order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07960</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07960v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a conceptual and efficient geometric framework to encode the algebraic structures on the category of superselection sectors of an algebraic quantum field theory on the $n$-dimensional lattice $\mathbb{Z}^n$. It is shown that, under the typical assumption of Haag duality, the monoidal $C^\ast$-categories of localized superselection sectors carry the structure of a locally constant prefactorization algebra over the category of cone-shaped subsets of $\mathbb{Z}^n$. Employing techniques from higher algebra, one extracts from this datum an underlying locally constant prefactorization algebra defined on open disks in the cylinder $\mathbb{R}^1\times\mathbb{S}^{n-1}$. While the sphere $\mathbb{S}^{n-1}$ arises geometrically as the angular coordinates of cones, the origin of the line $\mathbb{R}^1$ is analytic and rooted in Haag duality. The usual braided (for $n=2$) or symmetric (for $n\geq 3$) monoidal $C^\ast$-categories of superselection sectors are recovered by removing a point of the sphere $\mathbb{R}^1\times(\mathbb{S}^{n-1}\setminus\mathrm{pt}) \cong\mathbb{R}^n$ and using the equivalence between $\mathbb{E}_n$-algebras and locally constant prefactorization algebras defined on open disks in $\mathbb{R}^n$. The non-trivial homotopy groups of spheres induce additional algebraic structures on these $\mathbb{E}_n$-monoidal $C^\ast$-categories, which in the case of $\mathbb{Z}^2$ is given by a braided monoidal self-equivalence arising geometrically as a kind of `holonomy' around the circle $\mathbb{S}^1$. The locally constant prefactorization algebra structures discovered in this work generalize, under some mild geometric conditions, to other discrete spaces and thereby provide a clear link between the geometry of the localization regions and the algebraic structures on the category of superselection sectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07960v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Benini, Victor Carmona, Pieter Naaijkens, Alexander Schenkel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
