<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 05:00:31 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Resolving the phase of a Dirac topological state via interferometric photoemission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09560v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The electronic wavefunction is at the heart of physical phenomena, defining the frontiers of quantum materials research. While the amplitude of the electron wavefunction in crystals can be measured with state-of-the-art probes in unprecedented resolution, its phase has remained largely inaccessible, obscuring rich electronic information. Here we develop a quantum-path electron interferometer based on time- and angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy, that enables the reconstruction of the phase of electronic states in quantum materials - with energy and momentum resolution. We demonstrate the scheme by resolving the phase along the Dirac electronic band of a prototypical topological insulator and observe a resonance-associated phase jump as well as a momentum and phase synchronized inversion revealing the helicity of the Dirac cone. We show the interferometer can be optically controlled by the polarization of the absorbed light, allowing a differential measurement of the phase - a crucial component for extracting phase information from an interferogram. This photo-electron-interferometer is a purely experimental scheme and does not rely on any specific theoretical model. It can be extended to a variety of materials, opening up the phase dimension in quantum materials research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09560v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shiri Gvishi, Ittai Sidilkover, Shaked Rosenstein, Nir Hen Levin, Adi Peled, Omer Pasternak, Costel R. Rotundu, Ido Biran, Sem\"en Gorfman, Naaman Amer, Hadas Soifer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superdiffusive transport protected by topology and symmetry in all dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09629</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09629v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Superdiffusion is an anomalous transport behavior. Recently, a new mechanism, termed the ``nodal mechanism," has been proposed to induce superdiffusion in quantum models. However, existing realizations of the nodal mechanism have so far been proposed on fine-tuned, artificial Hamiltonians, posing a significant challenge for experimental observation. In this work, we propose a broad class of models for generating superdiffusion potentially realizable in condensed matter systems across different spatial dimensions. A robust nodal structure emerges from the hybridization between the itinerant electrons and the local impurity orbitals, protected by the intrinsic symmetry and topology of the electronic band. We derive a universal scaling law for the conductance, $G \sim L^{-\gamma}$, revealing how the exponent is dictated by the dimensionality of the nodal structure ($D_{\text{node}}$) and its order $n$, and the dimensionality of the system $(D)$ at high temperatures or that of the Fermi surface ($D^F$) at low temperatures. Through numerical simulations, we validate these scaling relations at zero temperature for various models, including those based on graphene and multi-Weyl semimetals, finding excellent agreement between our theory and the computed exponents. Beyond the scaling of conductance, our framework predicts a suite of experimentally verifiable signatures, notably a new mechanism for linear-in-temperature resistivity ($\rho \sim T$) and a divergent low-frequency optical conductivity ($\sigma(\omega) \sim \omega^{\gamma -1}$), establishing a practical route to discovering and engineering anomalous transport in quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09629v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shaofeng Huang, Yu-Peng Wang, Jie Ren, Chen Fang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonequilibrium Probes of Quantum Geometry in Gapless Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09639v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Much of our understanding of gapless many-body quantum systems stems from their low-energy descriptions as conformal field theories. This is especially true in 1+1 dimensions, where such theories have an infinite-dimensional parameter space induced by their conformal symmetry. We reveal the associated quantum geometry by considering finite systems driven by time-dependent conformal transformations. For small deformations, perturbation theory predicts absorption rates and linear responses that are intrinsically related to components of the quantum geometric tensor. For arbitrarily large but adiabatic deformations, we show that periodic drives give rise to nontrivial return amplitudes involving the quantum metric, beyond the familiar leading order that only features a Berry phase. Our field-theoretic findings are universal, comprising general relations between measurable quantities and quantum geometry that only depend on the central charge of the conformal symmetry. This is supported by both analytical results for quantum dynamics under certain Floquet drives, and numerical simulations of gapless lattice models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09639v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bastien Lapierre, Per Moosavi, Blagoje Oblak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Functional renormalization group study of a dissipative Bose--Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09643</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09643v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the phase diagram of a one-dimensional dissipative Bose-Hubbard model using the nonperturbative functional renormalization group (FRG). Each lattice site is coupled to an independent bath, generating long-range temporal interactions that encode non-Markovian dissipation. For a broad class of bath spectra -- ohmic, sub-ohmic, and super-ohmic -- we identify two competing low-energy regimes: a Luttinger-liquid line of fixed points and a dissipative fixed point characterized by finite compressibility, vanishing superfluid stiffness, and universal scaling exponents, separated by a Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless transition. The FRG framework is essential here, as it provides access to the complete renormalization group flow and all fixed points from a single microscopic action, beyond the reach of perturbative or variational methods. This work establishes a unified and systematically improvable framework for describing dissipative quantum phases in one dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09643v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oscar Bouverot-Dupuis, Vincent Grison, Nicolas Paris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Topological Stability with Nonlocal Quantum Geometric Markers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09664</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09664v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spatially resolved local quantum geometric markers play a crucial role in the diagnosis of topological phases without long-range translational symmetry, including amorphous systems. Here, we focus on the nonlocality of such markers. We demonstrate that they behave as correlation functions independently of the material's structure, showing sharp variations in the vicinity of topological transitions and exhibiting a unique pattern in real space for each transition. Notably, we find that, even within the same Altland-Zirnbauer class, distinct topological transitions generate qualitatively different spatial signatures, enabling a refined, class-internal probe of topological stability. As such, nonlocal quantum geometric indicators provide a more efficient and versatile tool to understand and predict the stability of topological phase transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09664v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Quentin Marsal, Hui Liu, Emil J. Bergholtz, Annica M. Black-Schaffer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum fluctuations associated with first-order magnetic transition in a frustrated kagome lattice antiferromagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09860</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09860v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Intense quantum fluctuations arising from geometrical frustrations in kagome-lattice magnets provide a feasible approach to exotic quantum states. Here, we document an unexpected isosymmetric first-order magnetic transition in the recently synthesized frustrated kagome-lattice antiferromagnet Nd3ScBi5, which is characterized by significant latent heat and a pronounced magnetocaloric effect, as well as discontinuous Raman shifts and negligible hysteresis. Employing the magnetocaloric effect as a detection method, in conjunction with systematical field-dependent physical properties, we uncover a distinctive 1/2 magnetization plateau phase with significant quantum fluctuations. Our study unveils Nd3ScBi5 as a prototypical model with an emerging phase of enhanced quantum fluctuations triggered by first-order magnetic transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09860v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhongchen Xu, Xinyang Liu, Cuiwei Zhang, Shuai Zhang, Feng Jin, Junsen Xiang, Quansheng Wu, Xianmin Zhang, Peijie Sun, Youguo Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of Shapiro Steps in the Charge Density Wave State Induced by Strain on a Piezoelectric Substrate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09888v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent development in nanotechnology has enabled us to investigate the dynamic properties of van der Waals materials on a piezoelectric substrate. Here we report on the dynamics of charge density wave (CDW) in NbSe$_{3}$ nanowires induced by surface acoustic waves (SAWs). Clear peaks in the differential resistance were observed at the resonant frequency of the SAW device. These peaks known as Shapiro steps are typically observed by applying an rf current to NbSe$_{3}$ nanowires. We found that the Shapiro steps induced by SAWs show several distinct features from the ones induced by an rf current. Our detailed study revealed that a strain induced by SAWs plays a significant role in the Shapiro steps. The result clearly demonstrates the importance of the strain in CDW materials and paves the way for strain-induced device applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09888v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Koji Fujiwara, Takuya Kawada, Natsumi Nikaido, Jihoon Park, Nan Jiang, Shintaro Takada, Yasuhiro Niimi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Competition between Weak Localization and Antilocalization of Dirac-like Fermions in a Spin-Polarized Two-Dimensional Electron Gas at KTaO3 (111) Interface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09986</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09986v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum transport phenomena in two-dimensional electron gases (2DEGs) at oxide interfaces have garnered significant interest owing to their potential in spintronic and quantum information technologies. Here, we systematically investigate the quantum conductance corrections of spin-polarized 2DEGs formed at the interfaces between two insulating oxides, ferromagnetic EuTiO3 (ETO) films and (111)-oriented KTaO3 (KTO) substrates. The anomalous Hall effect and hysteretic magnetoresistance provide clear evidence for long-range ferromagnetic order in the 2DEGs, which could be attributed to interfacial Eu doping in combination with the magnetic proximity effect of the ETO layer. The breaking of time-reversal symmetry by ferromagnetism in the 2DEGs, and with the assistance of spin-orbit coupling effect, gives rise to a nontrivial Berry phase. This results in a competition between weak localization (WL) and weak antilocalization (WAL) in the quantum transport of Dirac-like fermions at the KTO (111) interfaces. Notably, this competitive behavior can be effectively tuned by optical gating via a photoexcitation-induced shift of the Fermi level. Our findings demonstrate a controllable platform based on spin-polarized oxide 2DEGs for quantum transport, opening new avenues for spin-orbitronic and topological electronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09986v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hui Zhang, Daming Tian, Xiaobing Chen, Lu Chen, Min Li, Yetong Bai, Fengxia Hu, Baogen Shen, Jirong Sun, Weisheng Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graphene assisted III-V epitaxy towards substrate recycling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10097v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Re-using the substrate is identified as a method for reducing the cost of high efficiency III-V solar cells. The approach investigated here consists in inserting a graphene layer onto a (001)GaAs substrate prior to the epitaxial growth of GaAs. To obtain a monocrystalline GaAs grown layer, the graphene layer is patterned, followed by a two-step epitaxial growth, here performed by molecular beam epitaxy (MBE). The first step is a selective area growth of GaAs in graphene openings, followed by a lateral overgrowth, under a modulated Ga flux. The second step, after reaching coalescence, consists in a regular growth under continuous Ga supply. It is observed that the pattern orientations relative to the crystallographic direction of the GaAs substrate below the graphene have an influence on GaAs morphology and quality. The best result was obtained for patterns oriented along [1__10]+22.5{\textdegree} with a graphene coverage of 50%, with a significantly reduced roughness down to 3.3 nm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10097v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>SPIE Photonics West, Jan 2025, San Francisco, France. pp.13</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Naomie Messudom (C2N), Antonella Cavanna (C2N), Ali Madouri (C2N), Carlos Macias (IPVF, C2N), Nathalie Bardou (C2N), Laurent Travers (C2N), St\'ephane Collin (C2N, IPVF, IPVF), Jean-Christophe Harmand (C2N, LPN, CNET Bagneux), Amaury Delamarre (C2N)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>pynxtools: A Python framework for generating and validating NeXus files in experimental data workflows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10105</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10105v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Scientific data across physics, materials science, and materials engineering often lacks adherence to FAIR principles (Barker et al., 2022; Jacobsen et al., 2020; M. D. Wilkinson et al., 2016; S. R. Wilkinson et al., 2025) due to incompatible instrument-specific formats and diverse standardization practices. pynxtools is a Python software development framework with a command line interface (CLI) that standardizes data conversion for scientific experiments in materials science to the NeXus format (Klosowski et al., 1997; K\"onnecke, 2006; K\"onnecke et al., 2015) across diverse scientific domains. NeXus defines data storage specifications for different experimental techniques through application definitions. pynxtools provides a fixed, versioned set of NeXus application definitions that ensures convergence and alignment in data specifications across, among others, atom probe tomography, electron microscopy, optical spectroscopy, photoemission spectroscopy, scanning probe microscopy, and X-ray diffraction. Through its modular plugin architecture pynxtools provides conversion of data and metadata from instruments and electronic lab notebooks to these unified definitions, while performing validation to ensure data correctness and NeXus compliance. pynxtools can be integrated directly into Research Data Management Systems (RDMS) to facilitate parsing and normalization. We detail one example for the RDM system NOMAD. By simplifying the adoption of NeXus, the framework enables true data interoperability and FAIR data management across multiple experimental techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10105v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sherjeel Shabih, Lukas Pielsticker, Florian Dobener, Andrea Albino, Theodore Chang, Carola Emminger, Lev Ginzburg, Ron Hildebrandt, Markus K\"uhbach, Rubel Mozumder, Tommaso Pincelli, Martin Aeschlimann, Marius Grundman, Walid Hetaba, Carlos-Andres Palma, Laurenz Rettig, Markus Scheidgen, Jos\'e Antonio M\'arquez Prieto, Claudia Draxl, Sandor Brockhauser, Christoph Koch, Heiko B. Weber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Frustration Enforced Electronic Reconstruction in Ni intercalated NbSe$_{2}$: Suppression of Electronic Orders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10160</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10160v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the single crystals of Ni$_{0.19}$NbSe$_2$, revealing that Ni intercalation profoundly alters the physical properties of NbSe$_2$. Magnetic measurements clearly show that the system is magnetically frustrated with antiferromagnetic ordering below 23.5\,K, with an irreversibility temperature near 10\,K, and a magnetic hysteresis with a small net magnetic moment. Overall, the system can be described as an inhomogeneous antiferromagnetic phase with magnetic disorder and magnetic frustration. We found two Curie-Weiss temperatures of -80\,K for the field in the {\it ab}-plane and -137\,K for the field out of plane, which are a consequence of anisotropic interactions in spin space and favor an orientation of the spin along the {\it c}-axis. Temperature-dependent resistivity shows a complete suppression of both charge density waves and superconducting order down to 300\,mK. Angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy at 84\,K reveals a $\overline{\Gamma}$-centered electron pocket in Ni$_{0.19}$NbSe$_2$, which is absent in pristine NbSe$_2$. The electronic structure results show a shift of the van Hove singularity (VHS), which is the main cause of the suppression of the electronic orders. These results align with recent theoretical predictions that Ni intercalation with cationic disorder favors frustrated antiferromagnetic stripe states, shifts the VHS and reconstructs the Fermi surface in NbSe$_2$. Our findings position Ni$_{0.19}$NbSe$_2$ within a magnetically frustrated, non-superconducting regime, highlighting how partial intercalation and disorder drive complex magnetic order and the Fermi surface reconstruction in low-dimensional quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10160v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashutosh S. Wadge, Alexander Kazakov, Xujia Gong, Daniel Jastrzebski, Bogdan J. Kowalski, Artem Lynnyk, Lukasz Plucinski, Amar Fakhredine, Ryszard Diduszko, Marta Aleszkiewicz, Jedrzej Korczak, Dawid Wutke, Marcin Rosmus, Rafal Kurleto, Natalia Olszowska, Carmine Autieri, Andrzej Wisniewski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct Raman observation of the quantum metric in a quantum magnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10246</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10246v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The quantum geometric tensor (QGT) unifies the Berry curvature (its imaginary part) and the quantum metric (its real part), yet Raman studies of chiral phonons have so far accessed only the former. We perform circularly polarized Raman spectroscopy on the quantum magnet K2Co(SeO3)2, where the field-odd chiral splitting and the field-even center-frequency shift collapse onto a single curve across temperature and magnetic field, revealing a common microscopic origin for both observables. Since the chiral splitting reflects the Berry curvature, the concomitant even component, arising from the same microscopic origin, captures the field-induced change of the quantum metric, corresponding to the diagonal Born-Oppenheimer correction. Across two resolvable Eg modes, the unified data are well captured by a simple empirical quadratic relation. These results establish Raman spectroscopy as a direct probe of the quantum metric and an operational decomposition of quantum geometry within a single measurement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10246v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chao-Fan Wang, Han Ge, Jun-Yang Chen, Liusuo Wu, Xiaobin Chen, Jia-Wei Mei, Mingyuan Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long-range propagating paramagnon-polaritons in organic free radicals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10294</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10294v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Materials are commonly distinguished by their magnetic response into diamagnetic, paramagnetic, and magnetically ordered (ferro-, ferri-, and antiferromagnetic) phases. Diamagnets and paramagnets lack spontaneous long-range order, whereas ordered magnets develop such order below their Curie or N\'eel temperature and support single spin-wave excitations (magnons). Magnons have found applications in radio-frequency technologies and computation, magneto-optics, and foundational quantum experiments. Above the Curie/N\'eel temperature, long-range order is lost and the material transitions to a paramagnetic phase, with localised spin alignment in small patches, producing paramagnons with only short-range propagation. Here we show that long-range coherence is preserved in the organic free radical 2,2,6,6-tetramethylpiperidin-1-oxyl above the N\'eel temperature using all-electrical propagating spin-wave spectroscopy in external magnetic fields. We observe coherently excited low-energy paramagnon-polaritons up to $\mathbf{23\,\mathrm{GHz}}$ , propagating over $\mathbf{8\,\mathrm{mm}}$ at supersonic group velocities exceeding $\mathbf{100\,\mathrm{km\,s^{-1}}}$. Using free radicals as magnon carriers integrates organic materials with spintronics and opens the way to organic electronics, dense information storage, and quantum technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10294v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Knauer, Roman Verba, Rostyslav O. Serha, Denys Slobodianiuk, David Schmoll, Andreas Ney, Sergej Demokritov, Andrii Chumak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Point defects and their dynamic behaviors in silver monolayer intercalated between graphene and SiC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10368</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10368v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Point defects or impurities can give rise to sharp local modifications in the structure and electronic properties of two-dimensional metals, serving as an intriguing atomic-level solid-state model for both fundamental and application research. In this work, we investigated atomic-scale defects in a two-dimensional silver monolayer intercalated at the interface between epitaxial graphene and SiC using a scanning tunneling microscope. Distinct dark and bright defects are identified as in-plane vacancies and substitutional impurities within the silver monolayer, each hosting a localized electronic state induced solely by the defect. Remarkably, under excitation of tunneling electrons assisted by a negative bias voltage, the defects can hop inelastically which is reminiscent of the hydrogen switching in the cavity of an organic molecule. The hopping can be reversibly controlled by the scanning tunneling microscope tip, allowing the defects to function as atomic-scale two-level conductance switches. Defect hopping further allows us to gain a deeper understanding of their origins and the relationship between dark and bright defect species. This study constitutes a pathway toward understanding and controlling defects in two-dimensional metals with atomic precision, revealing previously unexplored dynamic behavior with potential applications in nanoelectronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10368v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Van Dong Pham, Arpit Jain, Chengye Dong, Li-Syuan Lu, Joshua A. Robinson, Achim Trampert, Roman Engel-Herbert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin and lattice dynamics at the spin-reorientation transitions in the rare-earth orthoferrite Sm$_{0.55}$Tb$_{0.45}$FeO$_{3}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10396</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10396v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Linear and non-linear couplings of magnetic and lattice excitations are at the heart of many fascinating magnetophononic phenomena observed in rare-earth orthoferrites, the distinctive feature of which is the tendency to spin-reorientation transitions. Here we report the results of the experimental study of the spin and lattice dynamics in the Brillouin zone center of the rare-earth orthoferrite Sm$_{0.55}$Tb$_{0.45}$FeO$_{3}$ by using polarized infrared reflectivity and Raman scattering spectroscopic techniques. The obtained results were supported by the first-principles calculations, which allowed us to reliably identify the parameters of most infrared- and Raman-active phonons. We reveal the spin-reorientation transitions $\Gamma_{4}(G_{a}F_{c}) \overset{T_{1}}\longleftrightarrow \Gamma_{24}(G_{ac}F_{ac}) \overset{T_{2}}\longleftrightarrow \Gamma_{2}(G_{c}F_{a})$ at $T_{1} \simeq 220$ K and $T_{2} \simeq 130$ K and carefully studied the following evolution of Raman scattering on magnetic excitations at these transitions. Notably, the intermediate magnetic structure $\Gamma_{24}$ displays an exceptionally broad temperature range $\Delta{T} = T_{1} - T_{2} \simeq 90$ K in mixed Sm$_{0.55}$Tb$_{0.45}$FeO$_{3}$ compared to pure rare-earth orthoferrites. We attribute this broadening of the intermediate phase to the modification of the magnetocrystalline anisotropy as a result of the inhomogeneous magnetic structure caused by the random distribution of rare-earth $\mathrm{Sm}^{3+}$ and $\mathrm{Tb}^{3+}$ ions. We found neither change in the parameters of Raman-active $B_{1g}$ phonons nor the appearance of new phonons induced by spin-reorientation transitions, which have been reported in $\mathrm{SmFeO}_{3}$. We assume that our results provide a solid basis for more deeper understanding of magnetophononic phenomena in rare-earth orthoferrites.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10396v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/44m2-sq6k</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>R. M. Dubrovin, A. I. Brulev, N. R. Vovk, I. A. Eliseyev, N. N. Novikova, V. A. Chernyshev, A. N. Smirnov, V. Yu. Davydov, Anhua Wu, Liangbi Su, R. V. Mikhaylovskiy, A. M. Kalashnikova, R. V. Pisarev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The True Parent Phase of K1.9Fe4.2Se5: A Stripe-type Orthorhombic Phase Requiring a Superconducting Distortion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10443v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The origin of the four-fold Tc amplification in A_xFe_{2-y}Se_2 (&gt;30 K) compared to FeSe (8 K) remains a central puzzle, complicated by a debate over the true superconducting (SC) parent phase--the I4/m (245) insulating matrix or a supposed I4/mmm metallic phase. Here, we resolve this ambiguity by identifying a novel "stripe-type orthorhombic phase" as the true parent phase of the high-Tc state, whose diffraction signature is the d2 peaks. Through decisive experiments, we demonstrate that this d2 parent phase is not intrinsically superconducting. Instead, superconductivity emerges only after this stripe phase undergoes a subsequent structural distortion, the definitive signature of which is the asymmetric broadening of the d1 main peaks. Our findings establish that the d2 peaks signal the formation of the parent phase, while the broadening of d1 peaks signals the transition into the superconducting state. This discovery of a two-step transition--formation of a stripe parent phase, followed by a superconducting distortion--provides a new mechanism for Tc amplification via controlled heterogeneity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10443v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chih-Han Wang, Jie-Yu Yang, Wu Phillip M, Gwo-Tzong Huang, Ming-Jye Wang, Maw-Kuen Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Broadband nonlinear Hall response and multiple wave mixing in a room temperature altermagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10471v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Crystalline symmetries determine the linear and nonlinear response of materials to external stimuli such as mechanical pressure and electromagnetic fields, governing phenomena such as piezoelectricity, optical activity, and multiple wave mixing with wide ranging technological applications. Altermagnets present a new class of materials with magnetic crystalline order where specific crystal symmetry operations connect antiferromagnetic sublattices, leading to non-relativistic spin-splitting of the electronic band structure. Hence, the electric material properties of altermagnets should uniquely mirror these underlying symmetry properties, potentially giving rise to novel phenomena in response to external driving fields. Here, we report the discovery of a broadband third-order nonlinear anomalous Hall effect in altermagnetic CrSb at room temperature. The comparison of our observations with symmetry analyses and model calculations shows that this nonlinear Hall response is induced by the nonlinear electric susceptibility of a Berry curvature quadrupole, which exists within the spin-split band structure of CrSb and is characterized by the underlying crystalline and magnetic symmetries. We then utilize this third-order nonlinear electric susceptibility of CrSb to realize a multiple wave mixing device with pronounced four wave mixing output, which could, in principle, be extended to THz frequencies. Our study discovers that the crystalline magnetic order of altermagnets determines their nonlinear electric material properties, which could facilitate applications in high-frequency electronics, THz generation, communication networks, and energy harvesting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10471v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soumya Sankar, Xingkai Cheng, Xinyu Chen, Xizhi Fu, Takahiro Urata Wataru Hattori, Wenlong Lu, Zihan Lin, Dong Chen, Claudia Felser, Hiroshi Ikuta, Junzhang Ma, Junwei Liu, Berthold J\"ack</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Competition of fermion pairing, magnetism, and charge order in the spin-doped attractive Hubbard gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10605</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10605v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The tension between fermion pairing and magnetism affects numerous strongly correlated electron systems, from high-temperature cuprates to twisted bilayer graphene. Exotic forms of fermion pairing and superfluidity are predicted when attraction between fermions competes with spin doping. Here, we follow the evolution of fermion pairing and charge and spin order in a spin-imbalanced attractive Hubbard gas of fermionic $^{40}$K atoms, covering a wide range of densities, magnetizations, and interactions with single-atom resolution. At low spin imbalance and weak interactions, we find a mixture of nonlocal fermion pairs coexisting with itinerant excess fermions. For stronger interactions an effective hard-core Bose-Fermi mixture emerges. Spin doping drives a crossover from charge-density wave correlations to a Fermi liquid of polarons. Beyond a certain spin imbalance and interaction strength, we find evidence for the onset of combined spin- and pair-density wave order, a possible precursor for the existence of magnetized superfluidity in the attractive Hubbard system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10605v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Hartke, Botond Oreg, Chunhan Feng, Carter Turnbaugh, Jens Hertkorn, Yuan-Yao He, Ningyuan Jia, Ehsan Khatami, Shiwei Zhang, Martin Zwierlein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Broadband ultrafast self-heterodyned chiro-optical spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10574v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ultrafast chiro-optical spectroscopy provides unique access to the structural dynamics of molecules, spin-valley relaxation in semiconductors, and the non-equilibrium optical response of chiral nanophotonic systems. Yet, because chiral signals are intrinsically weak and time-resolved spectroscopy probes small photoinduced changes, transient chiro-optical responses are often difficult to isolate from parasitic achiral contributions. Here, we introduce a broadband ultrafast chiro-optical spectroscopy technique that integrates a birefringent common-path interferometer with an optical polarization bridge to sensitively detect photoinduced changes in the polarization state of light. Phase-sensitive self-heterodyned detection enables simultaneous measurement of transient circular dichroism and optical rotatory dispersion across a broad spectral range with ultrafast temporal resolution. Balanced detection suppresses excess laser noise, enabling exceptional sensitivity (&lt;50 ${\mu}$deg) close to shot-noise limit. We demonstrate this approach on an array of gold nano-helicoids, supported by a full-wave time-resolved model of the spatiotemporal dynamics of plasmonic non-equilibrium carriers and their associated optical nonlinearities. The model traces the system's transient chiro-optical response back to photoinduced modulations of the electric-magnetic dipole interaction in the nano-helicoid, elucidating the connection of near- and far-field dynamics in the non-equilibrium regime. We further investigate spin excitation, thermalization, and relaxation in a lead halide perovskite, establishing a novel approach to broadband time-resolved Faraday rotation. The simplicity, sensitivity, and wide applicability of this detection scheme provide a powerful platform for broadband ultrafast chiro-optical spectroscopy, opening new opportunities in biochemistry, solid-state physics, and nanophotonics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10574v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Gucci{\dag}, Andrea Iudica{\dag}, Andres Valladares Y Tacchi{\dag}, Andrea Schirato, Giulia Crotti, Ryeong Myeong Kim, Soo Min Lee, Jeong Hyun Han, Andrea Villa, Dawar Ali, Aurora Rizzo, Margherita Maiuri, Ki Tae Nam, Giuseppe Della Valle, Giulio Cerullo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strongly correlated physics in organic open-shell quantum systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.00282</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.00282v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Strongly correlated physics arises from electron-electron scattering within partially filled orbitals. Organic molecules in open-shell configurations are therefore good candidates to exhibit many-body effects. We focus on electron transport in a two-terminal single-molecule junction setup, in which the molecular bridge consists of an organic radical with a molecular orbital hosting a single unpaired electron (SOMO). We perform beyond state-of-the-art numerical simulations combining an ab-initio description of the chemical environment, with quantum field-theoretical techniques that account for many-body effects. The key observation is that the SOMO resonance is prone to splitting and we identify a giant electronic scattering rate as the driving many-body mechanism, akin to that of the Mott metal-to-insulator transition. By comparing linear and cyclic radicals, we show that the spatial distribution of the SOMO and its projection on the molecular backbone have dramatic consequences for the transport properties of the junction. We argue that the phenomenon and the underlying microscopic mechanism apply to a broad family of open-shell molecular systems, and can explain puzzling experimental observations such as suppressed conductance in radical junctions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.00282v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Gandus, A. Jayaraj, D. Passerone, R. Stadler, M. Luisier, A. Valli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Berry connection and quantum geometry in time-dependent systems with instantaneous quantum integrable field theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18396</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18396v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study many-body quantum geometric effects in time-dependent system with emergent quantum integrable field theory instantaneously. We establish a theorem stating that the Berry connection matrix thus all associated geometric quantities of the system can be precisely characterized by excitations up to two particles from the initial quantum integrable system. To illustrate the many-body geometric influence, we analyze an Ising chain subjected to both a small longitudinal field and a slowly rotating transverse field, whose low-energy physics in the scaling limit is instantaneously governed by the quantum $E_8$ integrable field theory. Focusing on the quantum geometric potential (QGP), we show the QGP continuously suppresses the instantaneous energy gaps with decreasing longitudinal field, thereby enhancing many-body Landau-Zener tunneling as evidenced by the Loschmidt echo and its associated spectral entropy. The critical threshold for the longitudinal field strength is determined,where the spectral entropy linearly increases with system size and exhibits hyperscaling behavior when approaching to the threshold. As the longitudinal field passes the threshold and decreases toward zero, the QGP continuously leads to vanishing instantaneous energy gaps involving more low-energy excitations, resulting in increasing spectral entropy indicative of many-body Landau-Zener tunneling. Our results unveil telltale quantum geometric signatures in time-dependent many-body systems, elucidating the intricate interplay between quantum geometry and dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18396v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/rw2m-33v6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, L201102 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xiao Wang, Xiaodong He, Jianda Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pair binding and Hund's rule breaking in high-symmetry fullerenes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21455</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21455v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Highly-symmetric molecules often exhibit degenerate tight-binding states at the Fermi edge. This typically results in a magnetic ground state if small interactions are introduced in accordance with Hund's rule. In some cases, Hund's rule may be broken, which signals pair binding and goes hand-in-hand with an attractive pair-binding energy. We investigate pair binding and Hund's rule breaking for the Hubbard model on high-symmetry fullerenes C$_{20}$, C$_{28}$, C$_{40}$, and C$_{60}$ by using large-scale density-matrix renormalization group calculations. We exploit the SU(2) spin symmetry, the U(1) charge symmetry, and optionally the Z(N) spatial rotation symmetry of the problem. For C$_{20}$, our results agree well with available exact-diagonalization data, but our approach is numerically much cheaper. We find a Mott transition at $U_c\sim2.2t$, which is much smaller than the previously reported value of $U_c\sim4.1t$ that was extrapolated from a few datapoints. We compute the pair-binding energy for arbitrary values of $U$ and observe that it remains overall repulsive. For larger fullerenes, we are not able to evaluate the pair binding energy with sufficient precision, but we can still investigate Hund's rule breaking. For C$_{28}$, we find that Hund's rule is fulfilled with a magnetic spin-2 ground state that transitions to a spin-1 state at $U_{c,1}\sim5.4t$ before the eventual Mott transition to a spin singlet takes place at $U_{c,2}\sim 11.6t$. For C$_{40}$, Hund's rule is broken in the singlet ground state, but is restored if the system is doped with one electron. Hund's rule is also broken for C$_{60}$, and the doping with two or three electrons results in a minimum-spin state. Our results are consistent with an electronic mechanism of superconductivity for C$_{60}$ lattices. We speculate that the high geometric frustration of small fullerenes is detrimental to pair binding.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21455v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Rausch, C. Karrasch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three-dimensional flat bands and possible interlayer triplet pairing superconductivity in the alternating twisted NbSe$_2$ moir\'e bulk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09109</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09109v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Moir\'e superlattices hosting flat bands and correlated states have emerged as a focal topic in condensed matter research. Through first-principles calculations, we investigate three-dimensional flat bands in alternating twisted NbSe$_2$ moir\'e bulk structures. These structures exhibit enhanced interlayer interactions compared to twisted bilayer configurations. Our results demonstrate that moir\'e bulks undergo spontaneous large-scale structural relaxation, resulting in the formation of remarkably flat energy bands at twist angles $\leq$ 7.31{\deg}. The $k_z$-dependent dispersion of flat bands across different moir\'e bulks reveals their intrinsic three-dimensional character. The presence of out-of-plane mirror symmetry in these moir\'e bulk structures suggests possible interlayer triplet superconducting pairing mechanisms that differ from those in twisted bilayer systems. Our work paves the way for exploring potential three-dimensional flat bands in other moir\'e bulk systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09109v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuang Liu, Peng Chen, Shihao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay between Hubbard interaction and charge transfer energy in three-orbital Emery model: implication on cuprates and nickelates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11028</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11028v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We use the numerically unbiased determinant quantum Monte Carlo (DQMC) method to systematically investigate the three-orbital Emery model in the normal state in a wide range of local interactions, charge transfer energy, and doping levels. We focus on the influence of the onsite Hubbard $U_{dd}$ and the charge transfer energy scale $\epsilon_p$ on the electronic properties via the orbital occupancies, local moments, spin correlations, and spectral properties. Rich features of the orbital-resolved local and momentum-dependent spectra are revealed to associate with the possible Zhang-Rice singlet (ZRS) breakdown reflected by the peak splitting near the Fermi level in the heavily overdoped regime. Moreover, the pseudogap features at a small charge transfer energy scale (relevant to cuprates) are shown to diminish at larger $\epsilon_p$, which implies the weakening or absence of the pseudogap in the infinite-layer nickelates. Besides, an optimal value of $\epsilon_p$ is identified for maximizing the antiferromagnetic (AFM) spin correlations. Our large-scale simulations provide new insights on the well-established Emery model, particularly in the regime of heavily overdoped and/or large charge transfer energy scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11028v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan Peng, Mi Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid light-matter boundaries of graphene in a chiral cavity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13373v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent advances in chiral cavities that can couple coherently to two-dimensional materials have opened a powerful route to reshape electronic topology without an external drive. Here we establish the bulk-boundary correspondence for graphene embedded in a circularly polarized cavity. By combining exact diagonalization (ED) of zigzag ribbons, a semi-analytic T-matrix for half-infinite lattices, and analytical insights from a Dirac-Jaynes-Cummings model, we show that (i) every light-matter interaction-induced gap hosts pairs of unidirectional light-matter edge currents depending on the Chern number of the band while some of them are even bright; (ii) these chiral states persist throughout the entire photon ladder; and (iii) their dispersion, localization length and photon distribution exhibit a universal scaling controlled by the light-matter interaction. Time-evolution simulations further demonstrate that a dark electronic edge excitation can be converted into a bright and unidirectionally propagating current that remains coherent over long time scales. Our results predict an experimental signature of the hybrid band topology and a blueprint for tunable chiral channels in next generation quantum optical solid-state devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13373v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Volker Karle, Oriana K. Diessel, Vasil Rokaj, Ceren B. Da\u{g}</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Berry Phase Calculation via Adaptive Variational Quantum Computing Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19150v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present an adaptive variational quantum algorithm to estimate the Berry phase accumulated by a nondegenerate ground state under cyclic, adiabatic evolution of a time-dependent Hamiltonian. Our method leverages cyclic adiabatic evolution of the Hamiltonian and employs adaptive variational quantum algorithms for state preparation and evolution, optimizing circuit efficiency while maintaining high accuracy. We benchmark our approach on dimerized Fermi-Hubbard chains with four sites, demonstrating precise Berry phase simulations in both noninteracting and interacting regimes. Our results show that circuit depths reach up to 106 layers for noninteracting systems and increase to 279 layers for interacting systems due to added complexity. Additionally, we demonstrate the robustness of our scheme across a wide range of parameters governing adiabatic evolution and variational algorithm. These findings highlight the potential of adaptive variational quantum algorithms for advancing quantum simulations of topological materials and computing geometric phases in strongly correlated systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19150v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Mootz, Yong-Xin Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
