<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 01:40:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic field-tuned magnetic order and metamagnetic criticality in non-stoichiometric CeAuBi$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23778</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23778v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a detailed study of magnetization, resistivity, heat capacity, and X-ray and neutron powder diffraction measurements performed on single crystals of non-stoichiometric CeAuBi$_2$, Au deficiency 18$\%$, a strongly correlated antiferromagnet with N\'eel temperature T$_N$ = 13.2 K. Field-dependent magnetization measurements reveal a large magnetic anisotropy at low temperatures with an easy axis along the crystallographic c-axis, in which direction a spin-flop transition exhibits strong features in magnetization, specific heat, and resistivity at H$_c$ = 75 kOe. The constructed temperature-field phase diagram connects this transition to the suppression of magnetic order, which evolves from a second-order nature into a first-order transition that bifurcates at the spin-flop into three transitions below 1 K. The smoothed nature of the metamagnetic transitions in non-stoichiometric CeAuBi$_2$ is well described by an Ising model with weak quenched disorder, suggesting that the presence of Au vacancies is sufficient to smear the complex metamagnetic behavior and tune the critical behavior of magnetic order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23778v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. Hodovanets, H. Kim, T. Metz, Y. Nakajima, C. J. Eckberg, K. Wang, J. Yong, S. R. Saha, J. Higgins, D. Graf, N. Butch, T. Vojta, J. Paglione</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metallic Electro-Optic Effect in Twisted Double-Bilayer Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23784v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent theoretical advances have highlighted the role of Bloch state intrinsic properties in enabling unconventional electro-optic (EO) phenomena in bulk metals, offering novel strategies for dynamic optical control in quantum materials. Here, we identify an alternative EO mechanism in bulk metallic systems that arises from the interplay between Berry curvature and the orbital magnetic moment of Bloch electrons. Focusing on twisted double-bilayer graphene (TDBG), we show that the enhanced intrinsic properties of moir\'e Bloch bands give rise to a sizable linear magnetoelectric EO response, a first-order, electric-field-induced non-Hermitian correction to the gyrotropic magnetic susceptibility. This mechanism dominates in $C_{3z}$-symmetric TDBG, where EO contributions originating from the Berry curvature dipole (BCD) are symmetry-forbidden. Our calculations reveal giant, gate-tunable linear and circular dichroism in the terahertz regime, establishing a robust and tunable platform for ultrafast EO modulation in two-dimensional materials beyond the BCD paradigm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23784v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. J. P. de Sousa, N. Roldan-Levchenko, C. O. Ascencio, J. D. S. Forte, Paul M. Haney, Tony Low</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of a pronounced Hebel-Slichter peak in the spin-lattice relaxation rate and implications for gap and pairing symmetry in LaNiGa$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23800</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23800v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report a pronounced Hebel-Slichter coherence peak in the zero field nuclear quadrupolar resonance (NQR) spin-lattice relaxation rate of the topological crystalline superconductor LaNiGa$_2$ in the superconducting state. Previously, a two-band internally antisymmetric non-unitary triplet pairing (INT) state was proposed for this system, with equal spin-pairing and two distinct gaps associated with different spins. A detailed examination of the temperature dependence of the NQR data shows that the data best fit an INT model if the two gaps are equal and the model is unitary. Even a tiny non-unitarity with two unequal gaps causes the coherence peak to diminish rapidly and deviate from the data. On the other hand, the data are well-fit by a two-band singlet BCS-like pairing with two distinct gaps consistent with previous measurements. This raises doubts on the identification of non-unitary triplet-pairing with time-reversal symmetry breaking in this material.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23800v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. Sherpa, R. Hingorani, A. Menon, I. Vinograd, C. Chaffey, A. P. Dioguardi, R. Yamamoto, M. Hirata, F. Ronning, J. R. Badger, P. Klavins, R. R. P. Singh, V. Taufour, N. J. Curro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thickness dependent rare earth segregation in magnetron deposited NdCo$_{4.6}$ thin films studied by Xray reflectivity and Hard Xray photoemission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23852v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The magnetic anisotropy of amorphous NdCo$_{4.6}$ compounds deposited by magnetron sputtering change with film thickness from in plane to out of plane anisotropy at thickness above 40 nm. Xray reflectivity measurements shows the progressive formation of an additional layer in between the 3 nm thick Si capping layer and the NdCo compound film. Hard Xray Photoemission spectroscoy (HAXPES) was used to analyze the composition and distribution of cobalt and neodymium at the top layers region of NdCo$_{4.6}$ films of thickness ranging from 5 nm to 65 nm using 7 keV, 10 keV and 13 keV incident photon energies, with inelastic electron mean free paths ranging from 7.2 nm to 12.3 nm in cobalt. The atomic cobalt concentration of the alloy deduced from HAXPES measurements at the Nd 3d and Co 2p excitations results to be bellow the nominal value, changing with thickness and incident photon energy. This proves a segregation of the rare earth at the surface of the NdCo$_{4.6}$ thin film which increases with thickness. The analysis of the background of the Co 2p and Nd 3d peaks was consistent with this conclusion. This demonstrates that neodymium incorporation in the cobalt lattice have a cost in energy which can be associated to strain due to the difference in volume between the two elements. The lowering of this strain energy will favor atomic anisotropic environments for neodymium that explains the perpendicular anisotropy and its thickness dependence of these thin film compounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23852v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. D\'iaz, J. Rodr\'iguez-Fern\'andez, J. Rubio-Zuazo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relativistic Spin-momentum locking in altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23855</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23855v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spin-momentum locking in altermagnets has been deeply explored in the non-relativistic limit. Including spin-orbit coupling, altermagnets exhibit antisymmetric exchange interactions, leading to spin cantings. Therefore, the spin-momentum locking differs among the three spin components Sx, Sy, and Sz, forming the relativistic spin-momentum locking. We consider orthorhombic YVO3 and hexagonal MnTe. For YVO3, the relativistic locking comprises s-, dxy -, and dxz-wave. In MnTe, the dominant component Sy of MnTe inherits the polarized charge distribution and the non-relativistic spin-momentum locking bulk g-wave, but the breaking of the C6z rotational symmetry by the Neel vector lowers the symmetry from g-wave to d-wave. The relativistic spin-momentum locking for MnTe is composed of dxz-, dyz- and s-wave. Despite small magnitudes in real space, the canted spin components contribute significant spectral weight in k-space, impacting k-space properties such as the spin-Hall conductivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23855v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carmine Autieri, Amar Fakhredine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ballistic transport in 1D Rashba systems in the context of Majorana nanowires</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23961v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent work on Majorana-bound states in semiconductor-superconductor hybrid structures has elucidated the key role of unintentional (and unknown) disorder (producing low-energy Andreev-bound states) in the system, which is detrimental to the emergence of Majorana-carrying topological superconductivity artificially engineered through the combination of superconductivity, Zeeman spin splitting, and Rashba spin-orbit coupling. In particular, the disorder must be smaller than the superconducting gap for the appearance of Majorana modes, but the disorder-induced appearance of subgap Andreev-bound states suppresses the Majorana modes. We theoretically investigate, as a function of disorder, the normal state ballistic transport properties of nanowires with and without superconductors in order to provide guidance on how to experimentally estimate the level of disorder. Experimentally, the superconductivity is suppressed simply by rotating the magnetic field appropriately, so both physics can be studied in the same set-up. In particular, the presence of spin-orbit coupling and Zeeman splitting produces a helical gap in the 1D electronic band structure, which should have clear signatures in ballistic transport unless these signatures are suppressed by disorder and/or Fabry-P\'erot resonances associated with the finite wire sizes. Our work provides a benchmarking of when and what signatures of the putative helical gap (which is essential for the emergence of Majorana modes by leading to a single Fermi surface) could manifest in realistic nanowires.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23961v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haining Pan, Jacob R. Taylor, Jay D. Sau, Sankar Das Sarma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear Layer Hall Effect and Detection of the Hidden Berry Curvature Dipole in $\mathcal{PT}$-Symmetric Antiferromagnetic Insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23971</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23971v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent experimental and theoretical studies have revealed the emergence of a linear layer Hall effect (LHE) induced by hidden Berry curvature in \textrm{MnBi}$_{2}$\textrm{Te}$_{4}$ thin films. This phenomenon underscores the layer degree of freedom as a novel mechanism for generating Hall transport in layered materials, providing a new pathway to probe and manipulate the internal structure of fully compensated topological antiferromagnets (AFMs). In this work, we predict a nonlinear LHE in $\mathcal{PT}$-symmetric layered AFMs, which manifests as a detectable nonlinear Hall conductivity even with respect to the AFM order and odd with respect to the vertical electric field, in contrast to the linear LHE. Furthermore, we demonstrate that the nonlinear Hall currents induced by the hidden BCD and quantum metric dipole (QMD) obey distinct symmetries and flow in different directions. Our proposed nonlinear LHE establishes an experimentally advantageous framework for exclusively probing the hidden BCD quantum geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23971v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhuo-Hua Chen, Hou-Jian Duan, Ming-Xun Deng, Rui-Qiang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-dependent photoluminescence in carbon-based quantum dots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24062</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24062v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ability to modulate the photoluminescence (PL) of nanomaterials via spin-related effects is vital for many emerging quantum technologies, with nanoscale quantum sensing and imaging being particular areas of focus. Carbon-based quantum dots (CQDs) are among the most common forms of luminescent nanomaterials, appealing due to their ease of synthesis, tunability through organic chemistry, high brightness, and natural biocompatibility. However, the observation of room temperature, spin-dependent PL has remained elusive. Here we report on the observation of PL modulation of CQDs by magnetic fields ($\sim 10$ mT) under ambient conditions. We synthesize a series of CQDs using 19 different amino acids, which have a range of PL emission spectra and exhibit a clear magneto-PL effect (up to $\sim 1$% change). Furthermore, an electron spin resonance is detected in the PL with a g-factor of g $\approx$ 2, suggesting a process similar to the radical pair mechanism is responsible. Finally, we show that the magneto-PL contrast decreases in the presence of paramagnetic species, which we attribute to an increase in magnetic noise-induced spin relaxation in the CQDs. Our work brings new functionalities to these commonly used and biocompatible luminescent nanoparticles, opening new opportunities for in situ quantum sensing and imaging of biological samples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24062v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erin S. Grant, Joseph F. Olorunyomi, Sam C. Scholten, Islay O. Robertson, Amanda N. Abraham, Nandish H. Srikantamurthy, Billy J. Murdoch, Edwin L. H. Maye, Blanca del Rosal Rabes, Alexander J. Healey, Cara M. Doherty, Philipp Reineck, Xavier Mulet, Jean-Philippe Tetienne, David A. Broadway</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Development of a 10.8-eV Tabletop Femtosecond Laser with Tunable Polarization for High-Resolution Angle-Resolved Photoemission Spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24158v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The development of extreme ultraviolet sources is critical for advancing angleresolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES), a powerful technique for probing the electronic structure of materials. Here, we report the construction of a tabletop 10.8-eV femtosecond laser through cascaded third-harmonic generation, which operates at a repetition rate of 1 MHz and delivers a photon flux of approximately 1012 photons/s. The system achieves a high energy resolution of approximately 11.8 meV and tunable polarization. This flexibility enables detailed studies of orbitaland (pseudo)spin characteristics in quantum materials. We demonstrate the capabilities of this laser-ARPES system by investigating several prototypical materials, showcasing its potential for elucidating complex phenomena in quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24158v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0268243</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Rev. Sci. Instrum. 96, 093004 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jisong Gao, Qiaoxiao Zhao, Wenbo Liu, Dong Li, Zhicheng Gao, Yudian Zhou, Xuegao Hu, Zhihao Cai, Zhilin Li, Youguo Shi, Peng Cheng, Zhaojun Liu, Lan Chen, Kehui Wu, Zhigang Zhao, Baojie Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Edge Magnetism in Colloidal MoS2 Triangular Nanoflakes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24229</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24229v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The control of localized magnetic domains at the nanoscale holds great promise for next-generation spintronic applications. Colloidal transition metal dichalcogenides nanostructures are experimentally accessible and chemically tunable platforms for spintronics, deserving dedicated research to assess their potential. Here, we investigate from first principles free-standing triangular MoS2 nanoflakes with sulfur-terminated, hydrogen-passivated edges, to probe intrinsic spin behavior at varying side lengths. We find a critical edge length of approximately 1.5 nm separating nonmagnetic nanoflakes from larger ones with a magnetic ground state emerging from several, energetically competing spin configurations. In these systems, the magnetic activity is not uniformly distributed along the edges but localized on specific "magnetic islands" around molybdenum edge atoms. The localization of magnetic moments is robust even in non-equilateral nanoflake geometries, highlighting their intrinsic stability regardless of the (high) symmetry of the hosting structure. These findings establish that the S-terminated, H-passivated triangular MoS2 nanoflakes are a stable and experimentally accessible platform via colloidal synthesis for low-dimensional, next-generation spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24229v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Surender Kumar, Stefan Velja, Muhammad Sufyan Ramzan, Caterina Cocchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identifying geometric third-order nonlinear transport in disordered materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24239v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In third-order nonlinear transport, a voltage can be measured in response to the cube of a driving current as a result of the quantum geometric effects, which has attracted tremendous attention. However, in realistic materials where disorder scattering also contributes to nonlinear transport, identifying the geometric mechanisms remains a challenge. We find a total of 20 mechanisms of third-order nonlinear transport by developing a comprehensive theory that treats the geometric effects and disorder scattering on an equal footing. More importantly, we find that 12 of these mechanisms can be unambiguously identified, by deriving a scaling law that expresses the third-order nonlinear Hall conductivity as a polynomial in the linear longitudinal conductivity. We apply this theory to identify the geometric mechanisms of third-order nonlinear transport in materials both with and without time-reversal symmetry, such as 2D materials, topological materials, and altermagnets. This theory further promotes nonlinear transport as a probe of geometric effects and phase transitions in quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24239v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhen-Hao Gong, Zhi-Hao Wei, Hai-Zhou Lu, X. C. Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrastrong Magnon-Photon Coupling in Superconductor/Antiferromagnet/Superconductor Heterostructures at Terahertz Frequencies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24264</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24264v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We predict the realization of ultrastrong coupling between magnons of antiferromagnets and photons in superconductor/antiferromagnet/superconductor heterostructures at terahertz frequencies, from both quantum and classical perspectives. The hybridization of the two magnon modes with photons strongly depends on the applied magnetic field: at zero magnetic field, only a single antiferromagnetic mode with a lower frequency couples to the photon, forming a magnon-polariton, while using a magnetic field activates coupling for both antiferromagnetic modes. The coupling between magnon and photon is ultrastrong with the coupling constant $\sim$ 100 GHz exceeding 10% of the antiferromagnetic resonant frequency. The superconductor modulates the spin of the resulting magnon-polaritons and the group velocity, achieving values amounting to several tenths of the speed of light, which promises strong tunability of magnon transport in antiferromagnets by superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24264v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. M. Gordeeva, Yanmeng Lei, Xiyin Ye, G. A. Bobkov, A. M. Bobkov, Tao Yu, I. V. Bobkova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signatures of superconducting pairing driven by electron-electron interactions in moir\'e WSe$_2$/WSe$_2$ homobilayer modelled by Hubbard Hamiltonian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24270v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Strong evidence of unconventional superconductivity has been very recently reported experimentally in twisted transition metal dichalcogenide bilayer and gathered a significant amount of interest. Here we consider the Hubbard model on a triangular lattice describing the hole-doped moir\'e superlattice emerging in WSe$_{2}$/WSe$_{2}$ twisted homobilayer in the moderately correlated regime. By applying the Density Matrix Renormalization Group, we diagonalize the spin-valley-polarized Hamiltonian and show signatures of coexisting singlet and triplet pairings in the range of hole dopings and displacement fields reported in the experiments. In this view, we show that the superconductivity in the WSe$_{2}$/WSe$_{2}$ twisted homobilayer is likely to be induced by electronic correlations and has a mixed-symmetry character. These predictions can shed light on the nature of the superconducting state observed in the twisted homobilayer of WSe$_{2}$/WSe$_{2}$. We also identify the emerging superconducting orders, which are $d_{xy}(d_{x^2-y^2} \pm id_{xy} )$ and $p_y(p_{x}\mp ip_{y})$ for the singlet and triplet channels in the cylinder of width three(four), respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24270v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/kdpn-5g9d</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Andrzej Biborski, Micha{\l} Zegrodnik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Soft and hard x-ray orbital-resolved photoemission study of a strongly correlated Cd-Ce quasicrystal approximant</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24277v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We have investigated the orbital-dependent electronic states of Cd6Ce, a prototype of strongly correlated rare-earth-based Tsai-type quasicrystals and approximants (ACs) by soft and hard x-ray photoemission spectroscopy. Our results reveal that the 4f orbitals are predominantly hybridized with the valence-band electrons far from the Fermi level EF, in sharp contrast to the hybridization with conduction electrons at EF seen for the intermetallic Ce-based compounds. This anomalous hybridization effect is likely responsible for the unresolved magnetic ground state in Cd6Ce. These findings suggest that Cd-based ACs, some of which show the multi-step magnetic transitions, provide a new platform for investigating exotic magnetic properties that cannot be understood within the conventional framework of hybridization at EF.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24277v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Goro Nozue, Hidenori Fujiwara, Satoru Hamamoto, Miwa Tsutsumi, Akane Ose, Takayuki Kiss, Atsushi Higashiya, Atsushi Yamasaki, Yuina Kanai-Nakata, Shin Imada, Masaki Oura, Kenji Tamasaku, Makina Yabashi, Tetsuya Ishikawa, Farid Labib, Shintaro Suzuki, Ryuji Tamura, Akira Sekiyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum geometric magnetic monopole and two-phase superconductivity in CeRh$_2$As$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24289</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24289v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) and density functional theory plus Hubbard $U$ (DFT+$U$) studies revealed that a heavy-fermion superconductor CeRh$_2$As$_2$ exhibits van Hove singularities and the Dirac point near the Fermi level $E_{\mathrm F}$, which are key signatures of strong-correlation effects and quantum geometry. We have constructed a two-dimensional 12-orbital \textit{Dirac-Anderson} model as an effective model for CeRh$_2$As$_2$. The band structure and Fermi-surface topology of the Dirac-Anderson model agree well with the ARPES data and the DFT+$U$ calculations. We show that the quantum geometry strongly favors magnetic-monopole fluctuations because of the Dirac point at the $M$ point. By solving the linearized \'{E}liashberg equation, we demonstrate that the $B_{1u}$ and $B_{2g}$ representations, spin-triplet states originating from the Dirac point, exhibit the leading superconducting instabilities. By comparing the random-phase approximation and the fluctuation-exchange approximation, we further demonstrate that strong-correlation effects mitigate the influence of quantum geometry. The phase diagram of CeRh$_2$As$_2$ under pressure is discussed in connection with the theoretical results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24289v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kosuke Nogaki, Youichi Yanase</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase-Rotated Altermagnets as Chern Valves for Topological Transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24294</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24294v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by the emerging control of Berry-curvature textures in altermagnets, we explore a two-terminal configuration where a topological-insulator film is interfaced with two altermagnetic electrodes whose crystalline phases can be rotated independently. The proximity coupling imprints each momentum-dependent of the altermagnet spin texture onto the Dirac surface states, giving rise to an angular mass whose sign follows the lattice orientation. Adjusting the phase of one electrode redefines this mass pattern, thereby tuning the number and spatial distribution of chiral edge channels. This results in discrete conductance steps and a reversible inversion of the thermoelectric coefficient-achieved without external magnetic fields or net magnetization. A compact Dirac model captures both the quantized switching and its resilience to moderate disorder. Overall, this symmetry-driven mechanism provides a practical and low-dissipation route to programmable topological transport via lattice rotation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24294v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlos Caro, Francisco Gamez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-equilibrium correlation effects in spin transport through the 2D ferromagnet Fe$_4$GeTe$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24322</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24322v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding non-equilibrium spin transport through 2D ferromagnets is a theoretical challenge, as correlations produce a complex electronic structure with coexisting itinerant and localized electrons. We have developed a fully non-equilibrium ab initio method, combining density functional theory, dynamical mean-field theory, and non-equilibrium Green's functions to investigate the transport in Fe$_4$GeTe$_2$, a prototypical high-temperature 2D ferromagnet. We show that, while spin transport remains essentially single-particle under moderate bias, inelastic spin-dependent scattering of carriers with particle-hole excitations drives a distinctive hot-correlated electron regime beyond a critical voltage. This regime is marked by incoherent features in both the electronic spectrum and the conductance, which are experimentally accessible. Our results demonstrates that material-specific many-body non-equilibrium methods are essential for a complete understanding of spin transport in 2D ferromagnets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24322v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Declan Nell, Stefano Sanvito, Andrea Droghetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrafast recovery dynamics of dimer stripes in IrTe2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24361</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24361v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The transition metal dichalcogenide IrTe2 displays a remarkable series of first-order phase transitions below room temperature, involving lattice displacements as large as 20 percents of the initial bond length. This is nowadays understood as the result of strong electron-phonon coupling leading to the formation of local multicentre dimers that arrange themselves into one-dimensional stripes. In this work, we study the out-of-equilibrium dynamics of these dimers and track the time evolution of their population following an infrared photoexcitation using free-electron lased-based time-resolved X-ray photoemission spectroscopy. First, we observe that the dissolution of dimers is driven by the transfer of energy from the electronic subsystem to the lattice subsystem, in agreement with previous studies. Second, we observe a surprisingly fast relaxation of the dimer population on the timescale of a few picoseconds. By comparing our results to published ultrafast electron diffraction and angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy data, we reveal that the long-range order needs tens of picoseconds to recover, while the local dimer distortion recovers on a short timescale of a few picoseconds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24361v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Rumo, G. Kremer, M. Heber, N. Wind, C. W. Nicholson, K. Y. Ma, G. Brenner, F. Pressacco, M. Scholz, K. Rossnagel, F. O. von Rohr, D. Kutnyakhov, C. Monney</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-energy magnons in the altermagnet $\alpha$-MnTe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24376</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24376v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report high-field electron spin resonance studies of the altermagnetic material $\alpha$-MnTe. In magnetic fields applied parallel to the triangular Mn$^{2+}$ layers we observed a single resonance line, corresponding to an antiferromagnetic resonance (AFMR) mode. The resonance fields of this excitation exhibit an isotropic behavior with $g_\mathrm{eff}=2.01$, which is close to the free-electron $g$-factor value and agrees with the absence of orbital momenta for the Mn$^{2+}$ ions. At low temperatures, the AFMR mode is remarkably sharp ($\sim50$ mT for the full width at the half-maximum). This mode exhibits a noticeable broadening with increasing temperature, indicating the enhanced effect of magnon-magnon interactions. Based on this behavior, we estimate the strength of these interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24376v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Yu. Povarov, J. Wosnitza, S. R\"o{\ss}ler, M. Schmidt, A. A. Tsirlin, S. A. Zvyagin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skyrmion-vortex pairing from duality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24404</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24404v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An interaction between ferromagnetic and superconducting order, to be realized in a 2d ferromagnetic superconductor, is proposed obeying necessary symmetry principles. This interaction allow us to formulate a duality, similar to the Boson-vortex duality in 2+1 dimensional superfluid. In the dual theory Skyrmion and vortex excitations interact with each other via an emergent gauge field. The static interaction potential is attractive for a Skyrmion and a vortex with opposite topological charges. This interaction can lead to formation of bound pairs of the mentioned topological excitations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24404v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shantonu Mukherjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charge stripe and superconductivity tuned by interlayer interaction in a sign-problem-free bilayer extended Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24405</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24405v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Competing orders represent a central challenge in understanding strongly correlated systems. In this work, we employ projector quantum Monte Carlo simulations to study a sign-problem-free bilayer extended Hubbard model. In this model, a charge stripe phase, characterized by a peak at momentum $k_x=2\pi\delta$ is induced by highly anisotropic interlayer spin-exchange coupling $J_z$, and strongly suppressed upon introducing the spin-flip term $J_\bot$; in contrast, \(J_\perp\) favors the emergence of interlayer pairing superconductivity. We further demonstrate that the anisotropy of the interlayer spin-exchange directly governs the competition between these two phases, while the on-site interaction \(U\) plays a complex role in tuning both the charge stripe and superconductivity. Our work identifies the key factors driving charge stripe formation, highlights the sensitivity of both the charge stripe and superconducting phases to interaction parameters, and thereby provides valuable insights into competing orders in strongly correlated systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24405v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Runyu Ma, Zenghui Fan, Hongxin Liu, Tianxing Ma, Hai-Qing Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous enhancement of magnetism by nonmagnetic doping in the honeycomb-lattice antiferromagnet ErOCl</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24409v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Tuning magnetic anisotropy through chemical doping is a powerful strategy for designing functional materials with enhanced magnetic properties. Here, we report an enhanced Er^3+ magnetic moment resulting from nonmagnetic Lu^3+ substitution in the honeycomb-lattice antiferromagnet ErOCl. Unlike the Curie-Weiss type divergence typically observed in diluted magnetic systems, our findings reveal a distinct enhancement of magnetization per Er^3+ ion under high magnetic fields, suggesting an unconventional mechanism. Structural analysis reveals that Lu^3+ doping leads to a pronounced contraction of the c axis, which is attributed to chemical pressure effects, while preserving the layered SmSI-type crystal structure with space group R-3m. High-resolution Raman spectroscopy reveals a systematic blueshift of the first and seventh crystalline electric field (CEF) excitations, indicating an increase in the axial CEF parameter B_2^0. This modification enhances the magnetic anisotropy along the c axis, leading to a significant increase in magnetization at low temperatures and under high magnetic fields, contrary to conventional expectations for magnetic dilution. Our work not only clarifies the intimate connection between magnetism and CEF in rare-earth compounds, but more importantly, it reveals a physical pathway to effectively tune magnetic anisotropy via anisotropic lattice distortion induced by chemical pressure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24409v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/rfly-9g6x</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review B 112, 134448 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yanzhen Cai, Mingtai Xie, Jing Kang, Weizhen Zhuo, Wei Ren, Xijing Dai, Anmin Zhang, Jianting Ji, Feng Jin, Zheng Zhang, Qingming Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noise Estimation and Suppression in Quantitative EMCD Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24445v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantitative electron magnetic circular dichroism (EMCD) in transmission electron microscopy (TEM) enables the measurement of magnetic moments with elemental and atomic site sensitivity, but its practical application is fundamentally limited by noise. This study presents a comprehensive methodology for noise estimation and suppression in EMCD measurements, demonstrated on Ti-doped barium hexaferrite lamellae. By employing a classical three-beam geometry and long-term acquisition of electron energy-loss spectra, we systematically analyze the signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) across individual energy channels using bootstrap statistics. A robust energy alignment procedure based on the neighboring Ba-M4,5 edges with an adequate energy upsampling is introduced to minimize systematic errors from energy misalignment. The impact of detector noise, particularly from CMOS-based EELS cameras, is evaluated through variance-to-mean analysis and described by the noise amplification coefficients, revealing that detector-amplified shot noise is the dominant noise source. We recommend a stricter SNR threshold for reliable EMCD detection and quantification, ensuring that critical spectral features such as the Fe-L2,3 peaks meet the requirements for quantitative analysis. The approach also provides a framework for determining the minimum electron dose necessary for valid measurements and can be generalized to scintillator-based or direct electron detectors. This work advances the reliability of EMCD as a quantitative tool for magnetic characterization at the nanoscale with unknown magnetic structures. The proposed procedures lay the groundwork for improved error handling and SNR optimization in future EMCD studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24445v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hitoshi Makino, Bernd Rellinghaus, Sebastian Schneider, Axel Lubk, Darius Pohl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strain Engineering of van Hove Singularity and Coupled Itinerant Ferromagnetism in Quasi-2D Oxide Superlattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24465</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24465v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Engineering van Hove singularities (vHss) near the Fermi level, if feasible, offers a powerful route to control exotic quantum phases in electronic and magnetic behaviors. However, conventional approaches, which rely primarily on chemical and electrical doping, focus mainly on local electrical or optical measurements, limiting their applicability to coupled functionalities. In this study, a vHs-induced insulator-metal transition coupled with a ferromagnetic phase transition was empirically achieved in atomically designed quasi-2D SrRuO3 (SRO) superlattices via epitaxial strain engineering, which has not been observed in conventional 3D SRO systems. Theoretical calculations revealed that epitaxial strain effectively modulates the strength and energy positions of vHs of specific Ru orbitals, driving correlated phase transitions in the electronic and magnetic ground states. X-ray absorption spectroscopy confirmed the anisotropic electronic structure of quasi-2D SRO modulated by epitaxial strain. Magneto-optic Kerr effect and electrical transport measurements demonstrated modulated magnetic and electronic phases. Furthermore, magneto-electrical measurements detected significant anomalous Hall effect signals and ferromagnetic magnetoresistance, indicating the presence of magnetically coupled charge carriers in the 2D metallic regime. This study establishes strain engineering as a promising platform for tuning vHss and resultant itinerant ferromagnetism of low-dimensional correlated quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24465v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0283547</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>published 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Seung Gyo Jeong, Minjae Kim, Jin Young Oh, Youngeun Ham, In Hyeok Choi, Seong Won Cho, Jihyun Kim, Huimin Jeong, Byungmin Sohn, Tuson Park, Suyoun Lee, Jong Seok Lee, Deok-Yong Cho, Bongjae Kim, Woo Seok Choi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crossover from self-trapped bound states to perturbative scattering in the Heisenberg-Kondo lattice model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24520</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24520v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We map out the complete transport phase diagram of the ferromagnetic Heisenberg-Kondo lattice model in two dimensions. The model involves tight-binding electrons with hopping $t$, coupled to classical spins with coupling $J'$, while the spins have a nearest neighbour coupling $J$ between them. We work with a fixed, small $J/t$, and study the temperature dependence of resistivity for varying electron density $n$ and coupling $J'/t$. Our magnetic configurations are generated by exact diagonalisation-based Langevin dynamics, while the conductivity is computed using the Kubo formula on exact eigenstates. We work on lattices of size $20 \times 20$ and can access electron density down to $n \sim 0.01$. The electron system remains homogeneous either when the mean density is large or when the coupling $J'$ is small. In these situations, the resistivity $\rho(T)$ displays a monotonic increase with temperature and can be understood within a perturbative framework. However, at very low density $n \lesssim 0.05$, strong coupling $J'/t \gtrsim 1$, and for $T \sim T_c$, the electrons can locally polarise the magnetic state, create a trapping potential, and form a bound state in it. The resistivity associated with this polaronic phase is distinctly non-monotonic, with a peak near $T_c$. We establish the boundary that separates the many-body polaronic window from traditional scattering and extract a universal form for the resistivity in the scattering regime. We suggest the origin of the `excess resistivity' in the polaronic regime in terms of an increasing fraction of localised states as the temperature tends to $T_c$. This pushes the mobility edge towards the chemical potential $\mu$ and results in enhanced scattering of momentum states near $k_F$. While our specific results are in two dimensions, the phenomenology we uncover should be valid even in three dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24520v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tanmoy Mondal, Pinaki Majumdar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic and phononic dynamics in the two-ladder quantum magnet (C5H9NH3)2CuBr4</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24556v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In quantum magnetic materials it is common to observe both static and dynamic lattice effects on the magnetic excitation spectrum. Less common is to find that the magnetic correlations have a significant impact on the phonon spectrum. Can such an interplay occur in a structurally soft system with comparable elastic and magnetic energy scales? Here we study the metal-organic material (C5H9NH3)2CuBr4 (Cu-CPA), in which an explanation of the low-lying excitations depends crucially on a full understanding of both the spin and lattice subsystems. We report high-resolution neutron spectroscopy enabled by large, deuterated single-crystals that reveal how both sectors are affected by the recently discovered structural phase transition. By measuring over several Brillouin zones, we disentangle the vibrational contribution to the spectrum in order to obtain an accurate estimate of the quasi-one-dimensional magnetic signal. The low-energy magnetic excitations are dominated by two gaps, $\Delta$ b = 0.41 meV and $\Delta$ a = 0.55 meV, which contribute with equal intensity ratios, confirming that Cu-CPA realizes a two-ladder spin Hamiltonian, and we deduce the magnetic interaction parameters of both ladders. The phonon spectrum contains a highly localized mode at an anomalously low-energy around 2 meV. This characteristic frequency drops by approximately 5 percent as magnetic correlations become established with decreasing temperature, and we connect this behavior with the location and structure of the cyclopentylammonium rings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24556v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Philippe, F. Elson, T. Arh, S. Sanz, M. Metzelaars, D. W. Tam, O. K. Forslund, O. Shliakhtun, C. Jiang, J. Lass, M. D. Le, J. Ollivier, P. Bouillot, T. Giamarchi, M. Bartkowiak, D. G. Mazzone, P. K\"ogerler, M. M{\aa}nsson, A. M. L\"auchli, Y. Sassa, M. Janoschek, B. Normand, G. Simutis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of electronic and magnetic properties in Mn- and Co-alloyed ferromagnetic kagome metal Fe3Sn2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24564v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Kagome metals are an intriguing class of quantum materials as the presence of both flat bands and Dirac points provides access to functional properties present in strongly correlated and topological materials. To fully harness these electronic features, the ability to tune the Fermi level relative to the band positions is needed. Here we explore the structural, electronic and magnetic impacts of substitutional alloying within ferromagnetic kagome metal Fe3Sn2 in thin films grown by molecular beam epitaxy. Transition metals Mn and Co are chosen as substitutes for Fe to reduce or increase the d-band electron count, thereby moving the Fermi level accordingly. We find that Co is not incorporated into the Fe3Sn2 structure but instead results in a two-phase Fe-Co and (Fe,Co)Sn composite. In contrast, Fe3-xMnxSn2 films are realized with x up to 1.0, retaining crystalline quality comparable to the parent phase. The incorporation of Mn repositions the flat bands relative to the Fermi level in a manner consistent with hole-doping, as revealed by hard x-ray photoemission and density functional theory. The Fe3-xMnxSn2 films retain room temperature ferromagnetism, with x-ray magnetic circular dichroism measurements confirming that the Fe and Mn moments are ferromagnetically aligned. The ability to hole-dope this magnetic kagome metal provides a platform for tuning properties such as anomalous Hall and Nernst responses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24564v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prajwal M. Laxmeesha, Rajesh Dutta, Rajeev Kumar Rai, Sharup Sheikh, Michael F. DiScala, Uditha M. Jayathilake, Alexander Veli\v{c}, Tarush Tandon, Christoph Klewe, Haile Ambaye, Timothy Charlton, Tien-Lin Lee, Eric A. Stach, Kemp W. Plumb, Alexander X. Gray, Steven J. May</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable magnetism in 2D organic-ion-intercalated MnPS3 via molecule-dependent vacancy generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24613</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24613v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The magnetic properties of van der Waals materials are profoundly influenced by structural defects. The layered antiferromagnet MnPS3 offers a unique opportunity to explore defect-related magnetism, as Mn2+ vacancies can be generated by the intercalation of specific guest molecules. However, the effectiveness of this process in atomically thin flakes and the extent of the magnetic tunability remain unclear. Here, we show that the magnetic properties of MnPS3 can be tailored through the intercalation of different guest molecules. Notably, the insertion of four alkylammonium ions introduces different populations of Mn2+ vacancies, leading to a transition from the pristine antiferromagnetic state to more complex magnetic textures, including a ferrimagnetic state displaying a magnetic saturation of 1 uB/atom. Moreover, we show that the intercalation of few-nm-thick flakes also leads to the emergence of a ferrimagnetic response. This in-flake intercalation, which can be monitored in real time using optical microscopy, can be interrupted before completion, generating lateral heterostructures between pristine and intercalated areas. This approach opens the way to the use of partial intercalation to define regions with distinct magnetic properties within a single flake.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24613v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/adfm.202412771</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Advanced Functional Materials, 35, 2412771 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Tezze, Jose M. Pereira, Dogukan Tutar, Maria Ramos, Jakub Regner, Pierluigi Gargiani, Frederik Schiller, Felix Casanova, Angel Alegria, Beatriz Martin-Garcia, Hasan Sahin, Zdenek Sofer, Maider Ormaza, Luis Hueso, Marco Gobbi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced Superconductivity in 2H-TaS2 Devices Through in-situ Molecular Intercalation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24627</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24627v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The intercalation of guest species into the gap of van der Waals materials often leads to the emergence of intriguing phenomena, such as superconductivity. While intercalation-induced superconductivity has been reported in several bulk crystals, reaching a zero-resistance state in flakes remains challenging. Here, we show a simple method for enhancing the superconducting transition in tens-of-nm thick 2H-TaS2 crystals contacted by gold electrodes through in-situ intercalation. Our approach enables measuring the electrical characteristics of the same flake before and after intercalation, permitting us to precisely identify the effect of the guest species on the TaS2 transport properties. We find that the intercalation of amylamine molecules into TaS2 flakes causes a suppression of the charge density wave and an increase in the superconducting transition, with an onset temperature above 3 K. Additionally, we show that a fully developed zero-resistance state can be achieved in flakes by engineering the conditions of the chemical intercalation. Our findings pave the way for the integration of chemically tailored intercalation compounds in scalable quantum technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24627v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acsami.4c04997</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces 16, 41626-41632 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jose M. Pereira, Daniel Tezze, Beatriz Mart\'in-Garc\'ia, F\`elix Casanova, Maider Ormaza, Luis E. Hueso, Marco Gobbi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Density-driven scattering and valley splitting in undoped Si/SiGe two-dimensional electron system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24641v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Undoped Si-SiGe two-dimensional electron gas (2DEG) provide an ideal platform for hosting quantum-dot spin-qubits owing enhanced spin dephasing times and compatibility with standard CMOS technology. The strained Si quantum well reduces the valley degeneracy into two closely spaced ones. The existence of a near-degenerate valley state act as a leakage channel and compromises gate fidelity. A robust and uniform valley splitting across the entire chip is crucial for achieving scalability in the architecture and reliability in operation. Imperfections such as broadened interfaces, alloy disorders and atomic steps significantly compromise the valley splitting. The associated scattering mechanisms play detrimental roles in the performance of the qubits. In this manuscript, exploiting low-temperature magnetotransport measurements, we investigate the scattering mechanisms and valley splitting in a high-mobility undoped Si-SiGe 2DEG. At lower carrier densities, transport is limited by remote impurity scattering, whereas at higher densities, background impurity scattering near the quantum well dominates. Both the transport and quantum lifetimes of the charge carriers increase with carrier concentration, due to the enhancement in the impurity screening. Magnetic-field-induced confinement effect also is found to improve the valley splitting. Current-biasing measurements reveals the role of carrier heating in the visibility of valley splitting and reveal a temperature limited valley splitting of approximately 100 micro-eV. These results provide critical insight into scattering-dominated regimes and valley splitting in undoped Si-SiGe, advancing its potential for silicon-based quantum devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24641v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucky Donald Lyngdoh Kynshi, Umang Soni, Chithra H Sharma, Yu Cheng, Kristian Deneke, Robert Zierold, Shengqiang Zhou, Robert H Blick, Anil Shaji, Madhu Thalakulam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flat bands in ultra-wide gap two-dimensional germanium dioxide</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24685</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24685v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We employ first principles density-functional theory (DFT) and the Bethe-Salpeter equation (BSE) in the framework of tight-binding based maximally localized Wannier functions (MLWF-TB) model to investigate the electronic and optical properties of free-standing two-dimensional (2D) germanium dioxide phases. All investigated 2D GeO2 polymorphs exhibit ultra-wide band gaps and strong excitonic effects, with flat O-p-derived valence bands tunable under strain. These features allow the design of flat band materials with ultra large electronic gaps in low-dimensional systems, making these materials promising for devices operation at higher voltages and temperatures than conventional semiconductor materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24685v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael Franco Ribeiro Reis, Gabriel Elyas Gama Araujo, Danilo Kuritza, Alexandre Cavalheiro Dias, Andreia Luisa da Rosa, Renato Borges Pontes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A light-induced charge order mode in a metastable cuprate ladder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24686</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24686v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report the observation of an emergent charge order mode in the optically-excited cuprate ladder Sr$_{14}$Cu$_{24}$O$_{41}$. Near-infrared light in the ladder plane drives a symmetry-protected electronic metastable state together with a partial melting of the equilibrium charge order. Our time-resolved resonant inelastic x-ray scattering measurements at the upper Hubbard band reveal a gapless collective excitation dispersing from the charge-order wavevector up to 0.8 eV with a slope on the order of the quasiparticle velocity. These findings reveal a regime where correlated carriers acquire itinerant character at finite momentum, and charge order becomes dynamically fluctuating, offering a platform to explore light-induced pairing instabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24686v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hari Padma, Prakash Sharma, Sophia F. R. TenHuisen, Filippo Glerean, Antoine Roll, Pan Zhou, Sarbajaya Kundu, Arnau Romaguera, Elizabeth Skoropata, Hiroki Ueda, Biaolong Liu, Eugenio Paris, Yu Wang, Seng Huat Lee, Zhiqiang Mao, Mark P. M. Dean, Edwin W. Huang, Elia Razzoli, Yao Wang, Matteo Mitrano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Scalable Superconducting Circuit Framework for Emulating Physics in Hyperbolic Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23827</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23827v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Theoretical studies and experiments in the last six years have revealed the potential for novel behaviours and functionalities in device physics through the synthetic engineering of negatively-curved spaces. For instance, recent developments in hyperbolic band theory have unveiled the emergence of higher-dimensional eigenstates -- features fundamentally absent in conventional Euclidean systems. At the same time, superconducting quantum circuits have emerged as a leading platform for quantum analogue emulations and digital simulations in scalable architectures. Here, we introduce a scalable superconducting circuit framework for the analogue quantum emulation of tight-binding models on hyperbolic and kagome-like lattices. Using this approach, we experimentally realize three distinct lattices, including, for the first time to our knowledge, a hyperbolic lattice whose unit cell resides on a genus-3 Riemann surface. Our method encodes the hyperbolic metric directly into capacitive couplings between high-quality superconducting resonators, enabling tenable reproduction of spectral and localization properties while overcoming major scalability and spectral resolution limitations of previous designs. These results set the stage for large-scale experimental studies of hyperbolic materials in condensed matter physics and lay the groundwork for realizing hyperbolic quantum processors, with potential implications for both fundamental physics and quantum computing</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23827v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xicheng Xu, Ahmed Adel Mahmoud, Noah Gorgichuk, Ronny Thomale, Steven Rayan, Matteo Mariantoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Engineering 2D square lattice Hubbard models in 90$^\circ$ twisted Ge/SnX (X=S, Se) moir\'e supperlattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05626</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05626v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Due to the large-period superlattices emerging in moire two-dimensional (2D) materials, electronic states in such systems exhibit low energy flat bands that can be used to simulate strongly correlated physics in a highly tunable setup. While many investigations have thus far focused on moire flat bands and emergent correlated electron physics in triangular, honeycomb and quasi-one-dimensional lattices, tunable moire realizations of square lattices subject to strong correlations remain elusive. Here we propose a feasible scheme to construct moire square lattice systems by twisting two or more layers of 2D materials in a rectangular lattice by 90 degrees. We demonstrate the concept with twisted GeX/SnX (X=S, Se) moire superlattices and calculate their electronic structures from first principles. We show that the lowest conduction flat band in these systems can be described by a square lattice Hubbard model with parameters which can be controlled by varying the choice of host materials, number of layers, and external electric fields. In particular, twisted double bilayer GeSe realizes a square lattice Hubbard model with strong frustration due to the next nearest neighbour hopping that could host unconventional superconductivity{, in close analogy to the Hubbard model for copper-oxygen planes of cuprate high-temperature superconductors}. The presented scheme uses 90-degree twisted 2D materials with rectangular unit cells as a promising platform for realizing the physical phenomena of square lattice Hubbard models, establishing a new route for studying its rich phase diagram of magnetism, charge order, and unconventional superconductivity in a highly tunable setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05626v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiaoling Xu, Ammon Fischer, Nicolas Tancogne-Dejean, Tao Zhang, Emil Vi\~nas Bostr\"om, Martin Claassen, Dante M. Kennes, Angel Rubio, Lede Xian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced superconducting properties of Bi$_2$Sr$_2$CaCu$_2$O$_{8+x}$ films with sub-50-nm thickness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17367</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17367v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Few-unit cell thick Bi$_2$Sr$_2$CaCu$_2$O$_{8+x}$ (Bi-2212) layers have recently attracted much interest due to their extreme anisotropy and two-dimensional superconductivity, although they are typically susceptible to ambient conditions. In this study, we report on thin films approximately 13 unit cells thick that are stable in air, exhibit high anisotropy, and demonstrate extraordinarily high critical currents. By examining the superconducting transition under magnetic fields applied in both out-of-plane and in-plane orientations, we estimate key parameters such as pinning potentials, coherence lengths, London penetration depth, anisotropy factor, and the Ginzburg-Landau parameter. The volume pinning force is better described by a model incorporating an exponential decay term attributed to pronounced thermally-assisted flux flow. The Hall effect in the Bi-2212 films exhibits an extensive anomaly with a double sign change that may challenge existing theoretical explanations for this poorly understood phenomenon in copper-oxide superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17367v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41598-025-95932-9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Scientific Reports 15 (2025) 11855</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Bernd Aichner, Sandra Keppert, Johannes D. Pedarnig, Wolfgang Lang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perpendicular magnetic anisotropy in thin films enables extraordinary spin-wave phenomena: anti-Larmor precession, negative reflection and refraction, multi-reflection and multi-refraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10085</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10085v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a theoretical and numerical investigation of the role of perpendicular magnetic anisotropy (PMA) in shaping spin-wave (SW) dynamics under low magnetic fields in thin and ultrathin magnetic films. PMA introduces an in-plane torque that counteracts exchange, dipolar, and Zeeman contributions, fundamentally modifying SW dispersion and inducing a local minimum that, under specific conditions, becomes the lowest frequency across all geometric configurations. This results in a sombrero-shaped dispersion in ultrathin films and a cowboy-hat-like shape in thicker films, where dipolar interactions dominate. Using isofrequency contour (IFC) analysis, we demonstrate that these PMA-induced dispersion shapes enable nontrivial wave phenomena unprecedented in uniform media: bireflection and negative reflection in ultrathin films, and trireflection in thicker films--where a single incident beam splits into three reflected components, two with negative angles. Most remarkably, we predict and demonstrate tri-refraction, where one incident beam generates three refracted beams with two exhibiting negative refraction angles. We further show anti-Larmor precession of magnetization near the dispersion minimum in thicker films, arising from the interplay between PMA-induced and dipolar torques. Systematic simulations across diverse material systems--metallic films, ferrimagnetic garnets, hybrid structures, and multilayers--confirm the universal nature of these phenomena in any PMA system supporting stripe domain transitions. These results open new opportunities to explore wave phenomena beyond magnonics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10085v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikodem Le\'sniewski, Yuliya S. Dadoenkova, Florian F. L. Bentivegna, Pawe{\l} Gruszecki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multimagnon and multispinon $L_3$-edge RIXS spectra of an effective $\tilde{J}_1-\tilde{J}_2-\tilde{J}_3$ square lattice Heisenberg model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15354</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.15354v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the multimagnon and the multispinon $L_3$-edge resonant inelastic x-ray scattering (RIXS) spectra of a spin-1/2 effective $\tilde{J}_1-\tilde{J}_2-\tilde{J}_3$ square lattice Heisenberg model in its N\'{e}el ordered phase. Motivated by the observation of satellite intensity peaks above the single magnon dispersion in the $L$-edge RIXS spectrum, we propose a resonating valence bond (RVB) inspired RIXS mechanism that incorporates the local site ultrashort core-hole lifetime (UCL) expansion. We compute the multimagnon and the multispinon excitations using $\mathcal{O}(1/S)$ interacting spin wave theory and Schwinger boson mean-field theory (SBMFT) formalism, respectively. We treat the x-ray scattering process up to second order in the UCL expansion. Our calculations of two-magnon, bimagnon, and three-magnon RIXS intensities reveal that interacting spin wave theory fails to fully capture all the quantum correlations in the antiferromagnetic ordered phase. However utilizing the SBMFT framework, with a ground state that combines N\'{e}el order and fluctuating RVB components, we demonstrate that a RIXS bond-flipping mechanism provides an alternative deeper physical explanation of the satellite intensities. Specifically, we find that the spin correlation spectra predicted by the fluctuating RVB mechanism aligns with higher order UCL expansion results. We further show that the satellite intensity above the single-magnon mode can originate both from a one-to-three-magnon hybridization vertex process and from condensed spinons exhibiting Higgs mechanism. These features reflect the interplay of quantum fluctuation, entanglement, and gauge interaction effects of quantum magnetism probed by RIXS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.15354v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/vc7b-15sf</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 134438 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kai-Yuan Qi, Shangjian Jin, Trinanjan Datta, Dao-Xin Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pressure-induced trans-proximate correlation in La$_4$Ni$_3$O$_{10}$ and possible routes to enhance its superconductivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13442v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report an unexpected trans-proximate interlayer correlation (stronger correlation between disjoint layers than the adjacent ones) in the high-pressure phase of the recently discovered La$_4$Ni$_3$O$_{10}$ superconductors. Accompanied by an unusual pressure-induced fractionalization of Ni$^{2+}$ ionic spin from the standard spin-1 to spin-$\frac{1}{2}$, this trans-proximate correlation results from the emergence of a cross-layer trimer in our multi-energy-scale derivation of the electron dynamics. The resulting low-energy effective description resembles that of the cuprates and suggests a universal superconducting mechanism in all existing nickelate and cuprate superconductors. The rare trans-proximate correlation not only explains the weaker superconductivity in comparison with the related La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ samples, but it also indicates a viable strategy to improve superconductivity in this trilayer nickelate by lowering layer symmetry. Such pressure-induced trans-proximate correlation is expected in many materials and examplifies the engineering of rich uncharted quantum states of matter through pressure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13442v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruoshi Jiang, Zhiyu Fan, Bartomeu Monserrat, Wei Ku</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable hyperbolic Landau-level polaritons in charge-neutral graphene nanoribbon metasurfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.23786v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Magnetized charge-neutral graphene supports collective hybrid electronic excitations - polaritons - which have quantum origin. In contrast to polaritons in doped graphene, which arise from intraband electronic transitions, those in charge-neutral graphene originate from interband transitions between Landau levels, enabled by the applied magnetic field. Control of such quantum polaritons and shaping their wavefronts remains totally unexplored. Here we design an artificial two-dimensional quantum material formed by charge-neutral graphene nanoribbons exposed to an external magnetic field. In such metasurface, quantum polaritons acquire a hyperbolic dispersion. We find that the topology of the isofrequency curves of quantum hyperbolic magnetoexciton polaritons excited in this quantum material can change, so that the shape of isofrequency curves transforms from a closed to open one by tuning the external magnetic field strength. At the topological transition, we observe canalization phenomena, consisting of the propagation of all the polaritonic plane waves in the continuum along the same direction when excited by a point source. From a general perspective, our fundamental findings introduce a novel type of actively-tunable quantum polaritons with hyperbolic dispersion and can be further generalized to other types of quantum materials and polaritons in them. In practice, quantum hyperbolic polaritons can be used for applications related to quantum sensing and computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.23786v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acsphotonics.5c01482</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ACS Photonics 2025, 12, 9, 5264-5270</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kateryna Domina, Tetiana Slipchenko, D. -H. -Minh Nguyen, Alexey B. Kuzmenko, Luis Martin-Moreno, Dario Bercioux, Alexey Y. Nikitin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Majorana zero modes in semiconductor-superconductor hybrid structures: Defining topology in short and disordered nanowires through Majorana splitting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.00128</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.00128v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Majorana zero modes (MZMs) are bound midgap topological excitations at the ends of a 1D topological superconductor, which must come in pairs. If the two MZMs in the pair are sufficiently well-separated by a distance much larger than their individual localization lengths, then the MZMs behave as non-Abelian anyons which can be braided to carry out fault-tolerant topological quantum computation. In this `topological' regime of well-separated MZMs, their overlap is exponentially small, leading to exponentially small Majorana splitting, thus enabling the MZMs to be topologically protected by the superconducting gap. In real experimental samples, however, the existence of disorder and the finite length of the 1D wire considerably complicate the situation, leading to ambiguities in defining `topology' since the Majorana splitting between the two end modes may not necessarily be small in disordered wires of short length. We theoretically study this situation by calculating the splitting in experimentally relevant short disordered wires, and explicitly investigating the applicability of the `exponential protection' constraint as a function of disorder, wire length, and other system parameters in realistic models of nanowires currently being used experimentally. We find that the exponential regime is highly constrained, and is suppressed for disorder somewhat less than the topological superconducting gap. We provide detailed results and discuss the implications of our theory for the currently active experimental search for MZMs in superconductor-semiconductor hybrid platforms. A general consequence of our work is that `topology' in finite disordered wires may not be uniquely defined, necessitating a careful analysis which depends on the context.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.00128v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haining Pan, Sankar Das Sarma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Field-Tailoring Quantum Materials via Magneto-Synthesis: Metastable Metallic and Magnetically Suppressed Phases in a Trimer Iridate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.07545v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We demonstrate that applying modest magnetic fields during high-temperature crystal growth can profoundly alter the structure and ground state of a spin-orbit-coupled, antiferromagnetic trimer lattice. Using BaIrO3 as a model system, whose ground state is intricately dictated by the trimer lattice, we show that magneto-synthesis, a field-assisted synthesis approach, stabilizes a structurally compressed, metastable metallic and magnetically suppressed phases inaccessible via conventional methods. These effects include a 0.85% reduction in unit cell, 4-order-of-magnitude decrease in resistivity, a 10-fold enhancement of the Sommerfeld coefficient, and the collapse of long-range magnetic order -- all intrinsic and bulk in origin. First-principles calculations confirm that the field-stabilized structure lies substantially above the ground state in energy, highlighting its metastable character. These large, coherent and correlated changes across multiple bulk properties, unlike those caused by dilute impurities, defects or off-stoichiometry, point to an intrinsic field-induced mechanism. The findings establish magneto-synthesis as a powerful new pathway for accessing non-equilibrium quantum phases in strongly correlated materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.07545v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tristan R. Cao, Hengdi Zhao, Xudong Huai, Arabella Quane, Thao T. Tran, Feng Ye, Gang Cao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-Orbit Coupling-Driven Chirality Switching of Spin Waves in Altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18585</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.18585v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Altermagnets host intrinsically chirality-splitting spin waves, which offer an ideal platform for chirality-based computing with low energy consumption and fast dynamics. However, achieving precise and efficient control over spin-wave chirality remains a challenge. Here, we propose a mechanism to switch the chirality of spin waves in altermagnets via electrically induced Rashba spin-orbit coupling (SOC), which is free of tuning external fields. For in-plane spin polarization, SOC introduces a splitting effect opposite to the altermagnetism, leading to spin inversion in the electronic energy bands and chirality reversal in the spin-wave dispersion. By tuning SOC strength, the chirality splitting of spin waves can be controllably modified, enabling chirality switching at fixed resonance conditions, which results in the reversal of transverse spin susceptibility. We further design an experimental setup based on an altermagnet/antiferromagnet heterostructure to realize this mechanism. Our work establish a pathway toward efficient electrical control of spin-wave chirality in altermagnets, facilitating the development of chirality-based spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.18585v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Tong Li, Yu-Biao Wu, Lin Zhuang, Jian-Tao Wang, Wu-Ming Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electrically Controlled 0-$\pi$ Oscillations and Josephson Giant Magnetoresistor with PT-Symmetric Antiferromagnetic Bilayers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08262v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose that unconventional Josephson effects can typically emerge in {\it PT}-symmetric antiferromagnetic (AFM) bilayer systems. When proximitized by a conventional superconductor, these heterostructures host dominant interlayer Cooper pairing that features a distinctive spin texture enabled by the strong exchange field. Specifically, we demonstrate a novel mechanism for electrically tunable 0-$\pi$ oscillations in lateral Josephson junctions, controlled by an out-of-plane electric displacement field. This behavior originates from field-induced finite-momentum Cooper pairing, a hallmark of the unique layer-pseudospin structure in {\it PT}-symmetric AFM bilayers. Furthermore, we introduce a Josephson giant magnetoresistor based on these exotic spin-layer-locked Cooper pairs, in which the supercurrent exhibits a strong dependence on the internal N\'{e}el order. Our findings establish {\it PT}-symmetric AFM bilayers as a versatile platform for phase-controllable Josephson junctions and superconducting magnetic random-access memory, with promising applications in superconducting circuits and ultralow-power computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08262v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jin-Xin Hu, Mengli Hu, Ying-Ming Xie, K. T. Law</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral charge conservation and ballistic magnetotransport in a disordered Weyl semimetal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25330v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We demonstrate that in an ideal Weyl semimetal, in which the Fermi energy coincides with the band-touching nodes, weak direct inter-nodal scattering is irrelevant and, as a result, the chiral charge is (almost) exactly conserved. This leads to an experimentally-observable effect: in an applied magnetic field, the charge transport along the field becomes purely ballistic, with the conductance given by $e^2/h$ per magnetic flux quantum through the sample cross-section. This is the strongest experimental manifestation of nontrivial topology in Weyl and Dirac semimetals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25330v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. A. Burkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-Locked Helical Currents and Pure Spin Pumping in Altermagnetic Nanotubes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19700</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19700v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Altermagnetism has been widely explored in 3D and 2D crystals, but its one-dimensional realization remains largely unexplored. Here we propose an altermagnetic nanotube formed by rolling a 2D altermagnet, which converts momentum-odd spin polarization into spin-chirality locking enforced by the screw axis. Unlike curvature-induced magnetization in bent films, the nanotube is mirror-antisymmetric and produce no net magnetization. Two reciprocal effects emerge: (i) a single-spin injection drives a helical current whose handedness is fixed by the spin, yielding opposite-sign axial magnetic fields; and (ii) a time-varying axial flux generates a circumferential Faraday field that drives equal-magnitude but opposite axial charge currents in the two spin channels, producing a pure spin current under open-circuit conditions. As an implication, spin accumulation programs the tube's handedness and can imprint it onto otherwise achiral coaxial nanotubes in one-dimensional van der Waals assemblies. First-principles results for V2Se2O confirm spin-dependent helical wave functions near both band edges, establishing a nonrelativistic route to spin-programmable chiral nanodevices and compact flux generators/charge-neutral spin injectors without static magnetic bias.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19700v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Chen, Zhen Han, Linyang Li, Mingwen Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Control of Transition Metal Networks for Reversible High-Capacity Li-rich Cathodes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23098</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23098v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Developing high-energy-density batteries is essential for advancing sustainable energy technologies. However, leading cathode materials such as Li-rich oxides, including Li$_2$MnO$_3$, suffer from capacity loss due to irreversible oxygen release and structural degradation, both consequences of the oxygen redox activity that also enables their high capacity. The atomic-scale mechanisms behind this degradation, and whether it can be made reversible, remain open questions. Here, using submicrosecond-scale molecular dynamics simulations with first-principles accuracy, we directly visualize the entire charge-discharge cycle of Li$_2$MnO$_3$, uncovering the full lifecycle of the O$_2$-filled nanovoids responsible for degradation and identifying the critical size limit for voids to remain fully repairable upon discharge. Our results reveal that the topology of the Mn cation network is the key factor governing void growth, coalescence, and reparability. Based on a structural topology-informed design principle, we computationally develop a novel Li$_2$MnO$_3$ structure featuring a Mn lattice with a Kagome-like pattern, demonstrating full electrochemical reversibility even under extreme 80% delithiation. Our work establishes a new paradigm for designing high-energy cathodes, shifting the focus from mitigating damage to engineering inherent stability through atomic-level topological control of transition metal network.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23098v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Changming Ke, Yudi Yang, Minjun Wang, Jianhui Wang, Shi Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>All-Altermagnetic Tunnel Junction of RuO2/NiF2/RuO2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23269v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Emerging altermagnets offer a promising avenue for spintronics, yet their integration into magnetic tunnel junctions has been hindered by reliance on ferromagnetic electrodes (introducing stray fields) or limited functionality (non-tunable magnetoresistance without spin filtering). Here, we propose an all-altermagnetic tunnel junction (AAMTJ) paradigm composed exclusively of altermagnets-exemplified by experiment-feasible RuO2/NiF2/RuO2. Giant tunneling magnetoresistance of 11704%, and high spin-filtering of ~90% in both spin channels are achieved. This architecture unlocks tunable multistate magnetoresistance and spin filtering via magnetization control of electrode and barrier, stemming from their synergistic and antagonistic alignments of momentum-dependent altermagnetic spin-splitting. Our AAMTJ inherently exhibits low consumption and no stray field, with nonrelativistic spin splitting and zero magnetic moment, combining advantages of both ferromagnetic and antiferromagnetic tunnel junctions. This AAMTJ paradigm provides a realistically versatile platform to develop revolutionarily potential of altermagnets for reconfigurable magnetic memory devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23269v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Long Zhang, Guangxin Ni, Guoying Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
