<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 04:00:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Direct Comparison of Static and Dynamic Measurements of Spin Generation in a Topological Insulator Thin Film</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22682</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22682v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The competition between intrinsic spin-orbit physics, magnetic phenomena, and the quality of materials and interfaces governs the charge-to-spin conversion processes that are essential to the implementation of spintronic devices. Direct comparisons of spin parameters, which serve as metrics of device quality, obtained by different measurement techniques are scarce, leading to uncertainty regarding discrepancies and the reliability of the methods. Here, we directly compare the spin Hall coefficient (${\theta}_{SH}$) in molecular beam epitaxy grown films of $(Bi_{1-x}Sb_{x})_{2}Te_{3-y}Se_{y}$ (BSTS, x = 0.58, y = 1) at room temperature using two complementary techniques: a static method using non-local voltage (NLV) measurements in BSTS Hall bars with DC charge current, and a dynamic method using spin-torque ferromagnetic resonance (ST-FMR) measurement in $BSTS/Ni_{80}Fe_{20}$ heterostructures at GHz frequencies. We obtain comparable spin Hall coefficients in angular-dependent ST-FMR (${\theta}_{SH}$=$4.7\pm1.1$) and in NLV (${\theta}_{SH}$=$2.8\pm0.6$). The complex effects of ferromagnetic interfaces while determining spin Hall coefficients using static or dynamic techniques becomes evident by contrasting our results to literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22682v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vinay Sharma, Sharadh Jois, Ryan Van Haren, Gregory M. Stephen, M. Tomal Hossain, M. Benjamin Jungfleisch, Patrick J. Taylor, Aubrey T. Hanbicki, Adam L. Friedman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unraveling the role of disorder in the electronic structure of high entropy alloys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22809v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Disorder in high entropy alloys, arising from the random distribution of multiple elements, plays a crucial role in their novel properties desirable for various advanced engineering applications. We investigate the role of compositional and structural disorder on the electronic structure of osmium-based superconducting high entropy alloys, (Ru/Re)$_{0.35}$Os$_{0.35}$Mo$_{0.10}$W$_{0.10}$Zr$_{0.10}$, using photoemission spectroscopy and density functional theory (DFT). Elemental and cumulative core level shifts are found to be commensurate with elemental electronegativities and valence electron counts (VEC), respectively. Valence band spectra together with DFT results indicate that the crystal structure plays an important role in deciding the electronic structure of these high entropy alloys. Through temperature dependent high-resolution spectra, we unveil strongly suppressed spectral density of states (SDOS) in the close vicinity of Fermi level. Energy and temperature dependence of the SDOS in accordance with Altshuler-Aronov theory confirms localization of charge carriers in the presence of strong intrinsic disorder. Computed electron-phonon coupling strength and superconducting transition temperature aligning reasonably well with experiments further shed light on phonon-mediated pairing mechanism and role of disorder in these systems. Our results provide a way forward to the understanding of superconducting high entropy alloys through strategic control of disorder, VEC and crystal structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22809v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/lsjr-wcr1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Materials 9, L092001 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Neeraj Bhatt, Deepali Sharma, Asif Ali, Kapil Motla, Sonika Jangid, Ravi Prakash Singh, Ravi Shankar Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Altermagnetic Origin of Exchange Bias Behaviors in Incoherent RuO$_2$/Fe Bilayer Heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22866v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Initially identified as a promising altermagnetic (AM) candidate, rutile RuO$_2$ has since become embroiled in controversy due to contradictory findings of modeling and measurements of the magnetic properties of bulk crystals and thin films. For example, despite observations of a bulk non-magnetic state using density functional theory, neutron scattering, and muon spin resonance measurements, patterned RuO$_2$ Hall bars and film heterostructures display magnetotransport signatures of magnetic ordering. Among the characteristics routinely cited as evidence for AM is the observation of exchange bias (EB) in an intimately contacted Fe-based ferromagnetic (FM) layer, which can arise due to interfacial coupling with a compensated antiferromagnet. Within this work, the origins of this EB coupling in Ru-capped RuO$_2$/Fe bilayers are investigated using polarized neutron diffraction, polarized neutron reflectometry, cross-sectional transmission electron microscopy, and super conducting quantum interference device measurements. These experiments reveal that the EB behavior is driven by the formation of an iron oxide interlayer containing Fe$_3$O$_4$ that undergoes a magnetic transition and pins interfacial moments within Fe at low temperature. These findings are confirmed by comparable measurements of Ni-based heterostructures, which do not display EB coupling, as well as magnetometry of additional Fe/Ru bilayers that display oxide-driven EB coupling despite the absence of the epitaxial RuO$_2$ layer. While these results do not directly refute the possibility of AM ordering in RuO$_2$ thin films, they reveal that EB, and related magnetotransport phenomena, cannot alone be considered evidence of this characteristic in the rutile structure due to interfacial chemical disorder.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22866v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shelby S. Fields, Joseph C. Prestigiacomo, Cory D. Cress, Nicholas G. Combs, Olaf van 't Erve, Patrick G. Callahan, Keith E. Knipling, Michelle E. Jamer, Frank M. Abel, Feng Ye, Arianna Minelli, Zachary J. Morgan, Haile Ambaye, Masaaki Matsuda, Avishek Maity, Valeria Lauter, Steven P. Bennett</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust quantum Hall resistance standard from uniform wafer-scale epitaxial graphene on SiC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22882v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report high-precision resistance measurements on quantum Hall resistance devices fabricated from uniform epitaxial graphene grown by propane-hydrogen chemical vapor deposition on a two-inch silicon carbide substrate. Through molecular doping, we achieve a low carrier density regime ($n_\mathrm s &lt; $ 1.5 \textperiodcentered 10$^{11}$ cm$^{-2}$) combined with high mobility ($\upmu \geq$ 6000 cm$^2$ V$^{-1}$ s$^{-1}$) at low temperature. Accurate quantization of the Hall resistance is demonstrated at magnetic flux densities as low as 3.5 T, temperatures up to 8 K, and measurement currents up to 325 $\upmu$A, with relative measurement uncertainties of a few parts per billion. A stability diagram mapping dissipation as a function of temperature and current provides insight into optimal doping conditions that maximize the breakdown current. All measurements were carried out in a pulse-tube-based cryomagnetic system, enabling simplified and continuous operation of the quantum Hall resistance standard without liquid helium consumption.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22882v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fran\c{c}ois Cou\"edo, Chiara Mastropasqua, Aur\'elien Theret, Dominique Mailly, Adrien Michon, Mathieu Taupin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunneling spectroscopy of two-dimensional superconductors with the quantum twisting microscope</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22902</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22902v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ongoing discoveries of graphene-based superconductors underscore the quest to understand the structure of new superconducting orders. We develop a theory that facilitates the use of the quantum twisting microscope (QTM) for that purpose. This work investigates momentum-conserving tunneling across a planar junction formed by a normal monolayer graphene tip and a superconducting graphene sample within the QTM setting. We show that the bias dependence of the zero-temperature tunneling conductance exhibits singularities that provide momentum-resolved information about the Bogoliubov quasiparticle spectra, including the superconducting gap. Using a model of superconducting twisted bilayer graphene (TBG), we illustrate that simultaneously tuning the tip doping level and the tip-sample twist angle allows for measuring the momentum-resolved superconducting gap in TBG. Our results indicate that momentum-conserving tunneling spectroscopy with the QTM is a promising method for exploring superconductivity in two-dimensional van der Waals materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22902v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nemin Wei, Felix von Oppen, Leonid I. Glazman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monte Carlo Diagonalization for Hubbard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22975</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22975v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Hubbard model has often been studied with exact diagonalization (ED). This impurity solver is fundamentally limited by the exponential scaling of the Fock space. To address this problem, we introduce Monte Carlo diagonalization. Using a truncated Fock space constructed with a Monte Carlo approach, we reduce the size of the basis required to represent the Hamiltonian. We can then apply the Lanczos and band Lanczos algorithms in this truncated basis to find the ground state and the Green function. This results in a significant economy of resources and the capacity to break the $\sim$20-site limit of ED. Our results suggest that there is a threshold on the number of states needed to capture the physics. This allows us to reach clusters of size up to 32 sites and reproduce the expected physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22975v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. Bernard, M. Charlebois</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hund's physics extends to actinide f electron systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23033v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Uranium 5f electrons often yield heavy-fermion behavior via Kondo screening. However, the pronounced bad-metallic transport of uranium mononitride (UN) defies an incoherent Kondo explanation. Using density-functional theory combined with dynamical mean-field theory, we show that UN is a strongly correlated bad metal. The dominant correlations arise from intra-atomic Hund's exchange interaction between two 5f electrons, which aligns local magnetic moments and produces large quasiparticle mass renormalization. This identifies UN as a 5f-electron analogue of a Hund's metal-a paradigm chiefly associated with transition-metal d systems. Our results motivate a re-examination of the interplay between Mott, Kondo, and Hund-driven correlations across actinide correlated materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23033v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Byungkyun Kang, Roy N. Herrera-Navarro, Stephen S. Micklo, Mark R. Pederson, Eunja Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evanescent-mode-assisted Klein tunneling in dual-gated bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23096v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We theoretically investigate the electron tunneling in dual-gated bilayer graphene-based $n/p$ junctions. It is shown that a band gap is introduced by tuning the gate voltage, which modifies the pseudospin polarization and breaks anti-Klein tunneling at normal incidence. Specifically, when the pseudospin polarization vectors for the propagating and evanescent wave modes on the left and right regions of the junction are orthogonal, a revival of Klein tunneling is achieved. The Berry phase associated with Klein tunneling in dual-gated bilayer graphene is not limited to $\pi$ but varies with the junction parameters. Furthermore, the Klein tunneling is accompanied by a $\pi$ jump in the reflection phase around the normal incidence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23096v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yupeng Huang, W. Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noncollinear Magnetic Multipoles in Collinear Altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23117v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Altermagnets host an array of magnetic multipoles, which are often visualized and studied in the reciprocal space. In the real space, the relative phase of the multipoles of the spin-density around atoms determines whether a system is an altermagnet or a conventional antiferromagnet. In this study, we approach these real space multipoles in altermagnets using a combination of first principles calculations and group theory. We show that even in collinear magnets, the local spin density is necessarily noncollinear due to spin-orbit coupling. Moreover, the noncollinear contributions often provide a more direct illustration of the magnetic multipolar character of altermagnetism than the collinear contribution, which is dominated by the dipolar term. Our first principles calculations also show that 32-poles, in addition to the octupoles, can be visible in spin-density of d-wave altermagnets, and they must be taken into account in discussions of the macroscopic response. Finally, we elucidate the interplay between magnetism and subtle crystal structural distortions in perovskite altermagnets, which provide a fertile playground for studying phase transitions between antiferromagnetic and altermagnetic phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23117v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Buiarelli, Rafael M. Fernandes, Turan Birol</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Magnetic Phases in Dual-Species Mott insulating Spinor Lattice Gases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23142</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23142v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore the Mott insulating phases of dual-species bosonic spinor lattice gases, emphasizing the intriguing interplay between synthetic flux and inter-species spin exchange interaction. One of the species is subjected to Raman assisted tunneling, which leads to a synthetic flux within the framework of synthetic dimensions. In the deep Mott regime, the low energy physics is governed by an unconventional and highly tunable spin model, which is characterized by two distinct spin chains. The synthetic flux serves as an effective spin-orbit coupling, inducing Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interactions in one of the spin chains. The inter-species spin exchange interaction gives rise to the inter-chain coupling embodied as an isotropic XX interaction. Using time-evolving block decimation method for tensor network states, we compute order parameters, correlation functions and structure factors to identify the ground state magnetic phases. The DM interaction in one species, when combined with the inter-species spin-exchange interaction, can induce spiral magnetic order in the second, otherwise non-chiral species. Besides, the interplay of a transverse field applied to one spin chain and the inter-species coupling can drive both spin chains into a paramagnetic phase simultaneously. These results reveal that inter-species coupling serves as a powerful conduit for transmitting magnetic correlations, enabling exotic phases beyond the single-component perspective.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23142v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rui-Shan Li, Zong-Zhen Pan, Shi-Jie Yang, Yi Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence of electronic instability driven structural distortion in the nodal line semimetal CoSn$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23221</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23221v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding the mechanisms that drive spontaneous rotational symmetry breaking in correlated electron systems is a central challenge in condensed matter physics. Although such symmetry breaking phases have been studied in low-dimensional and strongly correlated materials, its emergence in structurally simpler compounds remains less explored. Here, we investigate non-magnetic CoSn$_2$ that is a centrosymmetric intermetallic compound crystallizing in a tetragonal structure at ambient conditions, and discover an electronically driven symmetry breaking instability. Electrical resistivity reveals a distinct change in the slope below 25 K, deviating from the expected Bloch-Gr\"uneisen behavior. This anomaly is attributed towards a structural change as at 22 K single crystal X-ray diffraction using synchrotron radiation uncovers weak superlattice reflections that leads to a doubling of $\textbf{a}$ and $\textbf{c}$, resulting in a 4-fold superstructure. The symmetry of the lattice reduces from tetragonal to acentric monoclinic but without any discernible monoclinic distortion down to 10 K. This structural transition is accompanied by a twofold symmetry in angular magnetoresistance, contrasting the fourfold symmetry observed at higher temperatures. First-principles calculations show no phonon softening but reveal enhanced electronic susceptibility, suggesting an electronic instability. Polarization-dependent ARPES measurements further identify a strong orbital anisotropy dominated by the in-plane Co-$d_{xy}$ states. Collectively, our results point to an electronic instability driven structural distortion in CoSn$_2$, offering a rare platform to study symmetry breaking in a non-magnetic metallic system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23221v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suman Nandi, Bishal Maity, Shovan Dan, Khadiza Ali, Bikash Patra, Anshuman Mondal, Gaston Garbarino, Pierre Rodi\`ere, Sitaram Ramakrishnan, Bahadur Singh, Arumugam Thamizhavel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Splitting of electronic spectrum in paramagnetic phase of itinerant ferromagnets and altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23396</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23396v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study self-energy effects, induced by strong magnetic fluctuations in paramagnetic phase of strongly-correlated itinerant magnets within the density functional theory combined with the dynamical mean field theory (DFT+DMFT approach) and its non-local extension. As concrete examples, we consider $\alpha$-iron, half metal CrO$_2$, van der Waals material CrTe$_2$, and altermagnet CrSb. We show that both local and non-local magnetic correlations yield splitting of the electronic spectrum in the paramagnetic phase, such that it closely resembles the DFT band structure in the ordered phase and suppresses spectral weight at the Fermi level. The relative importance of non-local vs. local correlations depends on the proximity to half filling of $d$ states: closer to half filling, the role of local correlations increases. Although the obtained split bands do not possess a certain spin projection, their splitting suppresses spectral weight at the Fermi level. The obtained electronic states are also expected to be easily spin polarized by a weak external magnetic field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23396v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. A. Katanin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revealing a hidden magnetic order in the triangular lattice antiferromagnet CuNdO$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23523</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23523v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the magnetic ground state of CuNdO$_2$, which is a delafossite with a triangular lattice of magnetic Nd$^{3+}$ ions that are well separated by non-magnetic Cu spacer layers. From inelastic neutron scattering measurements of the crystal electric field, we determine the strong Ising character of the pseudo-spin $\frac{1}{2}$ Nd$^{3+}$ moments. Magnetic susceptibility and heat capacity measurements reveal the onset of long-range antiferromagnetic order at $T_N=0.78$ K. While the magnetic transition is definitively observed with muon spin relaxation, accompanied by the formation of a weakly dispersing spin wave excitation, no dipole-ordered moment is detected with neutron diffraction. We show that the apparent absence of a dipolar ordered moment is a consequence of the dominant Ising character of the Nd$^{3+}$ moments, which experience extreme frustration on the triangular lattice. Consequently, the frustration in CuNdO$_2$ is relieved through in-plane ordering of the substantially smaller perpendicular component of the Nd$^{3+}$ moments into a 120\textdegree\ structure, with a nearly vanishing ordered moment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23523v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Gaudet, Dalmau Reig-i-Plessis, Bogeng Wen, Thomas J. Hicken, Jonas A. Krieger, Jan Peter Embs, Hubertus Luetkens, Adam A. Aczel, Stuart A. Calder, Matthew B. Stone, Hae-Young Kee, Alannah M. Hallas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable quantum metric and band topology in bilayer Dirac model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23622v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum metric, a fundamental component of quantum geometry, has attracted broad interest in recent years due to its critical role in various quantum phenomena. Meanwhile, band topology, which serves as an important framework in condensed matter physics, has led to the discovery of various topological phases. In this work, we introduce a bilayer Dirac model that allows precise tuning of both properties. Our approach combines two Dirac Hamiltonians with distinct energy scales; one producing relatively dispersive bands and the other yielding relatively flat bands. The dispersive and flat bands are weakly coupled via hybridization $\lambda$. By inducing a band inversion in the layer subspace, we achieve flexible tuning of band topology across all Altland-Zirnbauer symmetry classes and quantum metric scaling as $g \propto 1/\lambda^2$ near band inversion point. Using the bilayer Su-Schrieffer-Heeger model, we investigate the localization properties of gapless boundary states, which are affected by quantum metric. Our work lays a foundation for exploring the interplay between band topology and quantum metric.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23622v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xun-Jiang Luo, Xing-Lei Ma, K. T. Law</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Twist-Free Enhancement of Strength and Modulus in Electrospun Yarns via Liquid-Assisted Capillary Densification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23658</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23658v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Electrospun yarns often fall short of the strength and stiffness of their constituent nanofibers because of loose packing and inter-fiber slip. We report a simple, twist-free route to close this gap by liquid-assisted rolling: yarns are briefly wetted (water or ethanol) and subjected to gentle rolling action (mechanical strokes perpendicular and parallel to the yarn axis), then dried under controlled conditions so that meniscus forces compact the assembly into tightly bound bundles. The treatment yields large gains in tensile strength and modulus, and as yarn diameter decreases the properties of liquid-treated yarns approach single-fiber limits, indicating more efficient load transfer. Dry-rolling controls produce negligible changes compared to as-spun yarns, confirming that capillarity-driven consolidation, rather than mechanical pressing, dominates the improvement. Water consistently outperforms ethanol, reflecting its larger elastocapillary driving term gamma*(1 + cos theta) on PAN and thus stronger capillary compaction; a short post-treatment anneal near Tg further increases stiffness with a corresponding reduction in ductility. To rationalize these trends, we quantify microstructure via SEM-derived alignment and packing density and show that these complementary descriptors jointly explain variability in mechanical response. A compact constitutive framework, grounded in distributed fiber recruitment and adhesion/frictional contact, captures the observed strengthening-ductility trade-off across processing routes. The results establish capillarity-driven consolidation as a scalable pathway to engineer processing-structure-property relationships in hierarchical polymer fiber assemblies and provide practical guidance for upgrading electrospun yarns, alone or as precursors to twisted and composite architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23658v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saujatya Mandal, Sonu Dhiman, Debashish Das</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Power-Law Spectra and Asymptotic $\omega/T$ Scaling in the Orbital-Selective Mott Phase of a Three-Orbital Hubbard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23758</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23758v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum materials whose properties lie beyond the celebrated Landau Fermi-liquid paradigm have been observed for decades across diverse material platforms. Finding microscopic lattice models for metallic states that exhibit such peculiar behavior remains a major theoretical challenge, as these features often originate from strong quantum fluctuations in strongly interacting electron systems. Here we investigate a three-orbital Hubbard model at a high-symmetry point that hosts a transition from a metallic to an orbital-selective Mott (OSM) phase. Employing single-site dynamical mean-field theory combined with full-density-matrix numerical renormalization group, we chart the $T-U$ phase diagram and obtain high-resolution real-frequency dynamics. In the OSM regime we find asymptotically scale-invariant (power-law) single-particle spectra and asymptotic $\omega/T$ scaling in both charge and spin channels, spanning several decades in frequency and temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23758v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabian Eickhoff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconductivity Proximate to Non-Abelian Fractional Spin Hall Insulator in Twisted Bilayer MoTe$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23904v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Twisted bilayer MoTe$_2$ near two-degree twists has emerged as a platform for exotic correlated topological phases, including ferromagnetism and a non-Abelian fractional spin Hall insulator. Here we reveal the unexpected emergence of an intervalley superconducting phase that intervenes between these two states in the half-filled second moir\'{e} bands. Using a continuum model and exact diagonalization, we identify superconductivity through multiple signatures: negative binding energy, a dominant pair-density eigenvalue, finite superfluid stiffness, and pairing symmetry consistent with a time-reversal-symmetric nodal extended $s$-wave state. Remarkably, our numerical calculation suggests a continuous transition between superconductivity and the non-Abelian fractional spin Hall insulator, in which topology and symmetry evolve simultaneously, supported by an effective field-theory description. Our results establish higher moir\'{e} bands as fertile ground for intertwined superconductivity and topological order, and point to experimentally accessible routes for realizing superconductivity in twisted bilayer MoTe$_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23904v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheong-Eung Ahn, Gyeoul Lee, Donghae Seo, Youngwook Kim, Gil Young Cho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strain-induced Dynamic Spin-Phonon Coupling in Epitaxial RuO2 Films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23969v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic order parameters in altermagnets can couple to quantized lattice vibration via both piezomagnetic and magnetoelastic effects, leading to the renormalization of phonon dispersion. Here, we demonstrate photo-induced dynamic frequency modulation of THz phonons excited in anisotropically-strained epitaxial RuO2 thin films using ultrafast coherent phonon spectroscopy and time-resolved magneto-optic Kerr effect measurement. A coherent oscillation of a transverse acoustic phonon appears in the sub-THz range with increasing film thickness above 4 nm due to local dislocation arising from the anisotropic strain relaxation, which hosts large non-zero shear strain. Interestingly, this phonon mode exhibits a time-varying mode hardening below ~ 500 K. Furthermore, an optical phonon oscillation emerges in magnetization dynamics of the photo-induced non-equilibrium state, and it becomes significantly softened near the critical temperature, while there is no observable magneto-optic signal in fully-strain-relaxed films. Such notable dynamic frequency modulations in acoustic and optical phonons offer an opportunity to manipulate phonons in the THz range through the spin-phonon coupling controlled by epitaxial design, which can inspire the new class of altermagnetic applications in the ultrafast quantum opto-spintronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23969v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>In Hyeok Choi, Seung Gyo Jeong2, Jae Hyuck Lee, San Kang, Sreejith Nair, Changyoung Kim, Dirk Wulferding, Bharat Jalan, Jong Seok Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Demagnetization-Driven Nanoscale Chirality-Selective Thermal Switch</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24205</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24205v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Chiral-lattice degrees of freedom can offer novel chirality-selective functionalities for thermotronic applications. Chiral phonons, carrying both heat and angular momentum, can emerge through a breaking of chiral degeneracy in the phonon bands, either via an intrinsic chiral crystal structure or by angular momentum transfer from photons or spins. This chiral controllability of the lattice dynamics enables a design of chiral thermo-devices by integrating ferromagnets with chiral materials. Here, we present a nanoscale chirality-selective thermal switch realized using a simple heterostructure composed of ferromagnetic [Co/Pt] multilayers and insulating chiral $\alpha$-SiO2, where an external magnetic field can control thermal transport properties. Our experimental results based on the magneto-optic thermometry reveal that the thermal conductivity of $\alpha$-SiO2 exhibits a clear dependence on both the magnetization direction of [Co/Pt] multilayers and the structural chirality of $\alpha$-SiO2, which is supported well by the first-principles-based molecular dynamic simulations. The magnetization-dependent thermal on/off ratio amounts to 1.07 at room temperature and increases to about 1.2 as temperature decreases to 50 K, due to a reduction of Umklapp phonon-phonon scattering rate in $\alpha$-SiO2. These findings provide the first experimental demonstration of the nanoscale chirality-selective thermal switch based on the ferromagnetic/chiral material heterostructure, highlighting its potential as a key technology for addressing heat dissipation challenges in nanoscale electronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24205v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>In Hyeok Choi, Daeheon Kim, Yeon Jong Jin, Seungmo Yang, Tae-Seong Ju, Changsoo Kim, Chanyong Hwang, Dongbin Shin, Jong Seok Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bose glass in Ca$_2$RuO$_4$ nanofilms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24300v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Weak localization of bosons can give rise to an exotic quantum phase known as a Bose glass, characterized by the absence of global phase coherence yet finite conductivity. This phase is crucial in understanding the interplay between disorder, interactions, and superconductivity, especially in two-dimensional and strongly correlated systems. Here we report the presence of the Bose glass phase in the weak localization region of ruthenium oxide Ca$_2$RuO$_4$. The electrical resistance exhibits a characteristic logarithmic temperature dependence in this phase, $\rho \sim \ln(1/T)$. Through $\beta$-function scaling analysis, we observed "vertical flow" indicating unconventional scaling behavior associated with localized bosonic states. Our results suggest the existence of bosons-Cooper pairs-persisting up to high temperatures around 220 K and that these bosons undergo weak localization. In the Bose glass phase, vortices are found to have a dual relationship with the localized Cooper pairs, enabling their motion and resulting in finite resistance despite the presence of bosonic order. We identified two quantum critical points: one between the Bose glass and superconducting phases and another between the Bose glass and Mott insulating phases, allowing us to extract the corresponding quantum sheet resistances. We revealed that the ground state of the Ca$_2$RuO$_4$ changes depending on the localization strength. Thinning the Ca$_2$RuO$_4$ corresponds to controlling the electronic correlation by relieving the distortion in RuO$_6$ octahedra. These findings offer significant insights into the interplay between electronic correlations and bosonic transport, with important implications for studying high-temperature superconductors based on perovskite structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24300v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroyoshi Nobukane, Koki Hirose, Kakeru Isono, Mizuki Higashiizumi, Masahito Sakoda, Korekiyo Takahashi, Satoshi Tanda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong enhancement of d-wave superconductivity in an extended checkerboard Hubbard ladder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24415v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: By employing the density-matrix renormalization group method, we study an extended checkerboard Hubbard model on the two-leg ladder, which includes an intraplaquette nearest-neighbour attraction V. The simulated results show that V plays a significant role in enhancing the d-wave superconductivity when the electron density is close to half-filling. In the homogeneous case t'=t (t and t' are the intraplaquette and interplaquette hopping integrals), large critical |Vc| is required to induce the superconducting ground state. With decreasing t', |Vc| is substantially diminished and the pair state has a nearly C4 symmetry. In the extremely inhomogeneous case t'&lt;0.2t, the system transits to the d-wave superconducting phase at V\sim-0.3t and V\sim-0.4t for U=8t and U=12t, respectively, accompanying with a shift of spin and single-particle excitations from gapless to gapped type.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24415v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xichen Huang, Saisai He, Jize Zhao, Zhong-Bing Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-stripes in the Hubbard model: a combined DMFT and Bethe-Salpeter analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24439</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24439v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Hubbard model is known to accommodate various electronic orders, including stripes, which are important for understanding the physics of cuprates. We study spin-stripe order in the square lattice Hubbard model as a function of doping and temperature, by solving the Bethe-Salpeter equa- tion with the local vertex from dynamical mean field theory (DMFT), both inside and outside the antiferromagnetic phase. We find broad regions of horizontal/vertical spin stripes at low tempera- tures for the model with and without next-nearest neighbor hopping. Their wavelength depends on hole doping in a nonlinear fashion, and is highly sensitive to the ratio of nearest and next-nearest neighbor hoppings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24439v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruslan Mushkaev, Francesco Petocchi, Shintaro Hoshino, Philipp Werner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong Correlations and Superconductivity in the Supermoir\'e Lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24670</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24670v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The supermoir\'e lattice, arising from the interference of multiple moir\'e patterns, dramatically reshapes the electronic band structure by introducing new minibands and modifying band dispersion. Concurrently, strong electronic interactions within moir\'e flat bands lead to the emergence of various correlated states. However, the impact of the supermoir\'e lattice on the flat band systems with strong interactions remains largely unexplored. Here, we report the existence of the supermoir\'e lattice in the mirror-symmetry-broken twisted trilayer graphene, elucidating its role in generating mini-flat bands and mini-Dirac bands. Furthermore, we demonstrate interaction-induced symmetry-broken phases in the supermoir\'e mini-flat bands alongside the cascade of superconductor-insulator transitions enabled by the supermoir\'e lattice. Our work shows that robust superconductivity can exist in the mirror-symmetry-broken TTG and underscores the significance of the supermoir\'e lattice as an additional degree of freedom for tuning the electronic properties in twisted multilayer systems, sheds light on the correlated quantum phases such as superconductivity in the original moir\'e flat bands, and highlights the potential of using the supermoir\'e lattice to design and simulate novel quantum phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24670v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zekang Zhou, Cheng Shen, Kry\v{s}tof Kol\'a\v{r}, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Cyprian Lewandowski, Mitali Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetoelectric Switching of Competing Magnetic Orders in Rhombohedral Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24672</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24672v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A finite Hall conductance under zero magnetic field implies time reversal symmetry (TRS) breaking due to magnetic ordering. In rhombohedral (RH) stacked graphene, the angular momentum breaking TRS can result from the orbital degree of freedom at the $K$ and $K'$ valleys. This leads to valley polarization and occupation-dependent anomalous Hall resistance (AHR) due to the chirality in Berry curvature between the valleys. We report magnetoelectric control of orbital magnetic order in crystalline rhombohedral hexalayer graphene (RHG), achieved without the introduction of a moir\'e superlattice. At moderate displacement fields and low carrier densities, we observe a non-volatile and hysteretic AHR that can be electrically toggled by sweeping either the carrier density or the displacement field. Upon the application of small perpendicular magnetic fields, the system reveals a characteristic double sign reversal of the AHR, indicating a competition between distinct magnetic ground states. This interplay between valley polarization, orbital magnetism, and electric and magnetic field tuning demonstrates the rich multiferroic behavior of RHG. Our findings present crystalline RHG as a minimal, tunable platform for studying symmetry-breaking phases and magnetic order in flat-band systems, offering insight into the coupling between electronic structure and magnetoelectric response.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24672v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kilian Kr\"otzsch, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Arnaud Magrez, Mitali Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum superconducting diode effect with perfect efficiency above liquid-nitrogen temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24764</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24764v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The superconducting diode is an emergent device that juggles between the Cooper-paired state and the resistive state with unpaired quasiparticles. Here, we report a quantum version of the superconducting diode, which operates solely between Cooper-paired states. This type of quantum superconducting diode takes advantage of quantized Shapiro steps for digitized outputs. The devices consist of twisted high-temperature cuprate superconductors, and exhibit the following distinguished characteristics: (1) a non-reciprocal diode behavior can be simply initiated by current training without applying an external magnetic field; (2) perfect diode efficiency is achieved under microwave irradiations at a record-high working temperature; (3) the quantized nature of the output offers high resilience against input noises. These features open up unprecedented opportunities toward developing practical dissipationless quantum circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24764v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Heng Wang, Yuying Zhu, Zhonghua Bai, Zhaozheng Lyu, Jiangang Yang, Lin Zhao, X. J. Zhou, Genda Gu, Qi-Kun Xue, Ding Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrable Spherical Brane Model at Large $N$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23869v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study one of the simplest integrable two-dimensional quantum field theories with a boundary: $N$ free non-compact scalars in the bulk, constrained non-linearly on the boundary to lie on an $(N-1)$-sphere of radius $1/\sqrt{g}$. The $N=1$ case reduces to the single-channel Kondo problem, while larger $N$ is analogous to multi-channel or higher-spin impurity scenarios. Adding a boundary magnetic field -- a linear boundary coupling to the scalars -- enriches the model's structure while preserving integrability. Lukyanov and Zamolodchikov (2004) conjectured an expansion for the boundary free energy on the infinite half-cylinder in powers of the magnetic field. Using large-$N$ saddle-point techniques, we confirm their conjecture to next-to-leading order in $1/N$. Renormalization of the subleading solution turns out to be highly instructive, and we connect it to the RG running of $g$ studied by Giombi and Khanchandani (2020).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23869v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohsen Gheisarieha, Ramtin M. Yazdi, Arash Arabi Ardehali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General Framework for Twisted Bilayer Photonic Crystal with Interlayer Coupling and Far-Field Response</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23952</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23952v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a general theory for twisted bilayer photonic crystals that takes into account both far-field response and near-field coupling. The theory is based on the framework of a generalized Rayleigh-Schr\"odinger perturbation theory for non-Hermitian Hamiltonians. A universal form for interlayer coupling is derived, which relates the hopping strength to the Fourier transforms of the Wannier functions in the single layer photonic crystal. For low energy states at the K point in hexagonal lattices, the interlayer coupling reduces to that in the Bistritzer-MacDonald model for graphene. As an example, we study a twisted bilayer photonic crystal slab with air holes arranged in a honeycomb lattice in each layer. The first order solution of our model predicts a four-fold band splitting in the far-field spectrum compared to the single-layer case, which is confirmed by numerical simulations. Moreover, our theory reveals that for low energy states at K points, scattering towards the {\Gamma} point via the moir\'e potential is suppressed. Based on our theory, we propose a wide-angle, high-Q tunable flat band cavity by combining the bilayer at a large twist angle with a Brillouinzone-folding perturbation within each layer. The cavity behaves like a collection of quasi-bound states in the continuum with a divergent density of states, with potential applications in nonlinear optics, lasing and quantum optics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23952v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shupeng Xu, Dun Wang, Ritesh Agarwal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generation of C-band entangled photon pairs by biexciton-exciton cascade from symmetric InAs/InP quantum dots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24500</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24500v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Hereby, we study the generation of pairs of polarization-entangled photons at telecom C-band by biexciton-exciton cascade from non-resonantly excited epitaxial InAs/InP quantum dots (QDs). It is realized without external tuning of the fine structure splitting (FSS), which does not exceed 10 $\mu$eV in as-grown nanostructures, due to their high in-plane symmetry. Excitonic complexes are identified by means of excitation power-dependent and polarization-resolved magneto)microphotoluminescence. Their origin from different carrier configurations confined in the same QD is confirmed by time correlations of emitted photons. Experimental results are supported by 8-band kp calculations, followed by the configuration interaction method to include excitonic effects. This comparison reveals the structure of higher energy states, allowing for the reconstruction of the QD structural parameters. To verify and quantify the entanglement, we perform quantum state tomography and reconstruct the two-photon density matrix. Its diagonalization allows a detailed analysis of the entangled state and reveals an unfavourable interplay between phase accumulation and decoherence, pointing to a clear route for boosting entanglement by using a XX resonant, pulsed excitation scheme and shortening the radiative lifetimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24500v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna Musia{\l}, Maja Wasiluk, Katarzyna Roszak, Micha{\l} Gawe{\l}czyk, Wojciech Rudno-Rudzi\'nski, Pawe{\l} Wyborski, Johann P. Reithmaier, Mohamed Benyoucef, Grzegorz S\k{e}k</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Twisting Hubbard into the Momentum-Mixing Hatsugai-Kohmoto Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.08746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.08746v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Hubbard model is a standard theoretical tool for studying materials with strong electron-electron interactions, such as the cuprate superconductors. Unfortunately, interaction-driven phenomena such as the transition into the strongly correlated Mott insulator phase are difficult to treat with established theoretical techniques. However, the exactly solvable Hatsugai-Kohmoto model displays similar Mott physics. Here we show how the Hatsugai-Kohmoto model can be deformed continuously into the Hubbard model. The trick is to systematically re-introduce all the momentum mixing the original Hatsugai-Kohmoto model omits. This can be accomplished by grouping $n$-momenta into a cell and hybridizing them resulting in the momentum-mixing Hatsugai-Kohmoto (MMHK) model. We recover the Bethe ansatz ground state energy of the one-dimensional Hubbard model to within 1$\%$ from only ten mixed momenta. Overall the convergence scales as $1/n^2$ as opposed to the inverse linear behaviour of standard finite-cluster techniques. Our results for a square lattice reproduce all known features from state-of-the-art simulations also with only a few mixed momenta. Consequently, we believe the MMHK model offers an alternative tool for strongly correlated quantum matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.08746v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peizhi Mai, Jinchao Zhao, Gaurav Tenkila, Nico A. Hackner, Dhruv Kush, Derek Pan, Philip W. Phillips</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A defect-chemistry-informed phase-field model of grain growth in oxide ceramics: application to Fe-doped SrTiO3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17650</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17650v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dopants can significantly affect the properties of oxide ceramics through their impact on the property-determined microstructure characteristics such as grain boundary (GB) segregation, space charge layer formation in the GB vicinity, and the grain growth deviating from normal patterns. To support the rational design of oxide ceramics, we propose a defect-chemistry-informed phase-field grain growth model to simulate the microstructure evolution of oxide ceramics. It fully respects the defect-chemistry theory by accounting for the distinct segregation energies and available site densities of charged point defects (oxygen vacancies and acceptor dopants) in both the grain interior and boundaries, and it considers the competing kinetics of defect diffusion and GB movement. The proposed phase-field model is benchmarked against well-known bicrystal models, including the Mott-Schottky and Gouy-Chapman models. Various simulation results are presented to reveal the effect of different defect-chemistry parameters on the space charge layer formation and key microstructural aspects. In particular, simulation results confirm that the solute drag effect alone can lead to skewed grain size distribution that do not follow the log-normal distribution, without any contribution from grain misorientation and other anisotropy. Interestingly, simulations also demonstrate that grain boundary potentials can vary substantially: GBs of larger grains tend to have lower potentials than those of smaller grains. Such heterogeneous GB potential distribution may inspire a new material optimization strategy through microstructure design. This study provides a comprehensive framework for defect-chemistry-consistent investigations of microstructure evolution in polycrystalline oxide ceramics, offering fundamental insights into microscopic processes during critical manufacturing stages.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17650v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kai Wang, Roger A. De Souza, Xiang-Long Peng, Rotraut Merkle, Wolfgang Rheinheimer, Karsten Albe, Bai-Xiang Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flat-band Fulde-Ferrell-Larkin-Ovchinnikov State from Quantum Geometric Discrepancy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00548</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00548v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a new scheme for realizing Fulde-Ferrell-Larkin-Ovchinnikov (FFLO) Cooper pairing states within flat bands, in contrast to the conventional paradigm such as the Zeeman effect. Central to our scheme is the concept of ``quantum geometric discrepancy'' (QGD) that measures differences in the quantum geometry of paired electrons and drives the flat-band FFLO instability. Remarkably, we find that this instability is directly related to a quantum geometric quantity known as ``anomalous quantum distance'', which formally captures QGD. To model both QGD and the anomalous quantum distance, we examine a flat-band electronic Hamiltonian with tunable spin-dependent quantum metrics. Utilizing the band-projection method, we analyze the QGD-induced FFLO instability from pairing susceptibility. Furthermore, we perform mean-field numerical simulations to obtain the phase diagram of the BCS-FFLO transition, which aligns well with our analytical results. Our work demonstrates that QGD offers a general and distinctive mechanism for stabilizing the flat-band FFLO phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00548v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zi-Ting Sun, Ruo-Peng Yu, Shuai A. Chen, Jin-Xin Hu, K. T. Law</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eigenstate thermalization to non-monotonic distributions in strongly-interacting chaotic lattice gases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08967</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08967v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We find non-monotonic equilibrium energy distributions, qualitatively different from the Fermi-Dirac and Bose-Einstein forms, in strongly-interacting many-body chaotic systems. The effect emerges in systems with finite energy spectra, supporting both positive and negative temperatures, in the regime of quantum ergodicity. The results are supported by exact diagonalization calculations for chaotic Fermi-Hubbard and Bose-Hubbard models, when they have Wigner-Dyson statistics of energy spectra and demonstrate eigenstate thermalization. The proposed effects may be observed in experiments with cold atoms in optical lattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08967v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir A. Yurovsky (School of Chemistry, Tel Aviv University), Amichay Vardi (Department of Chemistry, Ben-Gurion University,ITAMP, Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phonon thermal Hall as a lattice Aharonov-Bohm effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18236</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18236v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In a growing list of insulators, experiments find that magnetic field induces a misalignment between the heat flux and the thermal gradient vectors. This phenomenon, known as the phonon thermal Hall effect, implies energy flow without entropy production along the orientation perpendicular to the temperature gradient. The experimentally-measured thermal Hall angle in various insulators does not exceed a bound and becomes maximal at the temperature of peak longitudinal thermal conductivity. The present paper aims to propose a scenario providing and explanation for these two experimental facts. It begins by noticing that at this temperature, $T_{max}$, Normal phonon-phonon collisions become most frequent in comparison with Umklapp and boundary scattering events. Furthermore, the Born-Oppenheimer approximated molecular wave functions are known to acquire a phase in the presence of a magnetic field. In an anharmonic crystal, in which tensile and compressive strain do not cancel out, this field-induced atomic phase gives rise to a phonon Berry phase and generates phonon-phonon interference. The rough amplitude of the thermal Hall angle expected in this picture is set by the phonon wavelength, $\lambda_{ph}$, and the crest atomic displacement, $\delta u_m$ at $T_{max}$. The derived expression is surprisingly close to what has been experimentally found in black phosphorus, germanium and silicon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18236v5</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.21468/SciPostPhysCore.8.3.06</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>SciPost Phys. Core 8, 061 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kamran Behnia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ideal quantum geometry of the surface states of rhombohedral graphite and its effects on the surface superconductivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03617</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.03617v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The interplay of quantum geometry and interactions determines the correlated state properties of flat bands. Here, we investigate the ideal quantum geometry (IQG), i.e., the property that the trace of quantum metric equals the Berry curvature, in the surface flat bands of rhombohedrally stacked graphene (RG) multilayers. We show that RG represents a class of semimetals with IQG, among which only RG has a nonvanishing IQG at the center of the surface bands. In the presence of long-range hoppings, a displacement field polarizes the electron density to one of the two surfaces, stabilizing the IQG and boosting transitions to correlated phases like superconductivity. Analyzing the superfluid stiffness of the superconducting state in a many-layer RG, we reveal a heavy-fermion picture where the "heavy electrons" carry a nonzero supercurrent. This unusual behavior arises from the IQG of the surface states, which suggests a large fraction of supercurrent running on the surface of RG.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.03617v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guodong Jiang, Tero Heikkil\"a, P\"aivi T\"orm\"a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infinite randomness criticality and localization of the floating phase in arrays of Rydberg atoms trapped with non-perfect tweezers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.11985</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.11985v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Chains of Rydberg atoms have emerged as a powerful platform for exploring low-dimensional quantum physics. This success originates from the precise control of lattice geometries provided by optical tweezers, which allows access to a wide range of synthetic quantum phases. Experiments on one-dimensional arrays have stimulated tremendous progress in understanding quantum phase transitions into crystalline phases. However, the finite width of tweezers introduces small variations in interatomic distances, leading to quenched disorder in the interactions. In this letter, we numerically study how such disorder alters the nature of two critical regimes observed in experiments. Firstly, following experimental protocols, we analyze Kibble-Zurek dynamics and find a crossover from the clean Ising transition to the infinite-randomness fixed point as system size and disorder strength increase. Secondly, we show that the floating phase (an incommensurate Luttinger liquid phase emerging at stronger interactions) is localized by the disorder, yet preserves short-range incommensurate correlations with the same leading wave vector. Our results clearly reveal an additional technical challenge in the scalability of Rydberg-based quantum simulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.11985v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jose Soto-Garcia, Natalia Chepiga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin non-Collinear Real-Time Time-Dependent Density-Functional Theory and Implementation in the Modern GPU-Accelerated INQ code</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21908v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Time-dependent density functional theory (TDDFT) is a theory that describes the time evolution of quantum mechanical many-electron systems under the influence of external time-dependent electric and magnetic fields. INQ is a specially designed software to efficiently solve the real-time TDDFT equations on graphics processing units (GPUs), which aim to overcome the computational limitation of time and size scales of non-equilibrium quantum dynamics. In this work we will present an implementation of non-collinear TDDFT for the INQ code to simulate spin dynamics in real time and discuss the implementation of non-collinear magnetic effects into the code. We will discuss the implementation of exchange-correlation magnetic fields, spin-orbit coupling, and the interaction between the electronic system and external magnetic fields. We will then consider several prototypical examples of spin dynamics in magnetic clusters and solids after light excitation. Potential applications range from the study of real-time dynamics of magnons to ultrafast spin dynamics under linear and circularly polarized laser excitation, as well as spectroscopic signatures such as magnetic circular dichroism and pump-probe Kerr rotation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21908v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacopo Simoni, Xavier Andrade, Wuzhang Fang, Andrew C. Grieder, Alfredo A. Correa, Tadashi Ogitsu, Yuan Ping</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time- and Polarization-Resolved Extreme Ultraviolet Momentum Microscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.02371v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report the development of an instrument combining an ultrafast, high-repetition-rate, polarization-tunable monochromatic extreme ultraviolet (XUV, 21.6 eV) beamline and a next-generation momentum microscope endstation. This setup enables time- and angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy of quantum materials, offering multimodal photoemission dichroism capabilities. The momentum microscope simultaneously detects the full surface Brillouin zone over an extended binding energy range. It is equipped with advanced electron optics, including a new type of front lens that supports multiple operational modes. Enhanced spatial resolution is achieved by combining the small XUV beam footprint (33 $\mu$m by 45 $\mu$m) with the selection of small regions of interest using apertures positioned in the Gaussian plane of the momentum microscope. This instrument achieves an energy resolution of 44 meV and a temporal resolution of 144 fs. We demonstrate the capability to perform linear, Fourier, and circular dichroism in photoelectron angular distributions from photoexcited 2D materials. This functionality paves the way for time-, energy-, and momentum-resolved investigations of orbital and quantum geometrical properties underlying electronic structures of quantum materials driven out of equilibrium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.02371v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sotirios Fragkos, Quentin Courtade, Olena Tkach, J\'er\^ome Gaudin, Dominique Descamps, Guillaume Barrette, St\'ephane Petit, Gerd Sch\"onhense, Yann Mairesse, Samuel Beaulieu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CoS++: Towards More General and Explicit Implementations for Sampling High-Order Feynman Diagrammatic Series</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.12349v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Diagrammatic Monte Carlo methods provide robust routines for accurate computations of correlated electronic systems in the thermodynamical limit. Recently, its versatility was extended to SU(N) Hubbard model, where the core is a novel dynamical programming approach to the summation of all connected Feynman diagrams. We present several generalizations of it with more interaction vertices and symmetry broken terms. The framework treats SU(N) symmetry breaking both from nonuniform, flavor-dependent chemical potentials and from spontaneously broken phases induced by shift parameters. We also provide an end-to-end GPU acceleration path with dedicated CUDA C++ optimizations independent of a previous CUDA acceleration approach, where the parallelization strategy is different. We performed detailed numerical study of new algorithms involved in this article and exposed numerical instabilities of connected determinant formalism, which we solved in multiple ways. Together, these advances establish a scalable, high-performance DiagMC toolbox for multi-flavor correlated systems with and without symmetry breaking.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.12349v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boyuan Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Topological Phases Controlled via Strain in Two-Dimensional Altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22474</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.22474v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Altermagnets (AMs) are an emergent class of magnetic materials that combine properties of ferromagnets and antiferromagnets, exhibiting spin-polarized Fermi surfaces and zero net magnetic moment due to combined time-reversal and crystal symmetry. Here, we construct a Kondo-lattice model on a two-dimensional square Lieb lattice to investigate the topological properties of AMs. We identify a type-II quantum spin Hall state characterized by spin-polarized counterpropagating edge states. Breaking the $C_{4z}\mathcal{T}$ symmetry, which connects magnetic sublattices, induces a transition to a quantum anomalous Hall state. We further establish a strain-induced mechanism to control these topological phase transitions and present the corresponding phase diagram. Finally, we demonstrate the predicted transitions in monolayer CrO, a realistic altermagnetic candidate, using first-principles calculations. Our findings highlight the potential of 2D AMs as a versatile platform for topological spintronics, enabling strain-tunable helical and chiral edge states within a single system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.22474v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zesen Fu, Mengli Hu, Aolin Li, Haiming Duan, Junwei Liu, Fangping Ouyang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intertwined Electron Pairing in the Bilayer Two-orbital Kanamori-Hubbard Model: a Unified Picture of Two Superconductivities in $\mathrm{La_3Ni_2O_7}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04554</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.04554v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The mechanism of superconductivity in $\mathrm{La_3Ni_2O_7}$ bulk and film superconductors remains actively debated. Here, we investigate the bilayer two-orbital Kanamori-Hubbard model for $\mathrm{La_3Ni_2O_7}$ using cellular dynamical mean-field theory. We discover two intertwined $s_{\pm}-$ wave superconductivities with distinct physical origins. We show that when the $d_{z^2}$ orbital is under-doped, electron pairing associated to Hund's coupling $J_H$ prevails. As $d_{z^2}$ hole-doping $\delta_z$ increases, a second superconductivity, which is largely insensitive to $J_H$ but exhibiting a critical reliance on the $d_{z^2}$ - $d_{x^2-y^2}$ hybridization $V$, arises. These two primary pairing states exhibit comparable maximum transition temperatures $T_c$, and evolve from one to the other following a smooth $T_c$ versus $\delta_z$ relation. A stark particle-hole asymmetry is observed in the superconducting phase diagram, indicating the crucial role played by the $\gamma-$ band of $d_{z^2}$ orbital in pairing. Our results present a picture unifying the two possible pairing mechanisms in $\mathrm{La_3Ni_2O_7}$ superconductors. We discuss the implications of our findings to recent experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.04554v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shi-cong Mo, Yao-yuan Zheng, W\'ei W\'u</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Odd-parity longitudinal magnetoconductivity in time-reversal symmetry broken materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13277v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Magnetotransport measurements are a sensitive probe of symmetry and electronic structure in quantum materials. While conventional metals exhibit longitudinal magnetoconductivity that is even in a magnetic field ($B$) for small $B$, we show that magnetic materials which intrinsically break time-reversal symmetry (TRS) show an {\it odd-parity magnetoconductivity} (OMC), with a leading linear-$B$ response. Using semiclassical transport theory, we derive explicit expressions for the longitudinal and transverse conductivities and identify their origin in Berry curvature and orbital magnetic moment. Crystalline symmetry analysis shows that longitudinal OMC follows the same point-group constraints as the anomalous Hall effect, while transverse OMC obeys distinct rules, providing an independent probe of TRS breaking. In the large $B$ quantum oscillation regime, we uncover both odd- and even-$B$ contributions, demonstrating OMC beyond the semiclassical picture. Explicit calculations in valley-polarized gapped graphene show that OMC peaks near the band edges, vanish in the band gap and follow the temperature dependence of the magnetic order parameter. Our results explain the odd-parity magnetoresistance recently observed in magnetized graphene and establish OMC as a robust transport signature of intrinsic TRS breaking in metals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13277v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sunit Das, Akash Adhikary, Divya Sahani, Aveek Bid, Amit Agarwal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancement of superconducting pairing via quantum Lyapunov control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20426</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20426v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate that quantum Lyapunov control provides an effective strategy for enhancing superconducting correlations in the Fermi-Hubbard model without requiring careful parameter tuning. While photoinduced superconductivity is sensitive to the frequency and amplitude of a monochromatic laser pulse, our approach employs a simple feedback-based protocol that prevents the decrease of superconducting correlations once they begin to form. This method enables robust enhancement of pairing across a broad range of initial pumping conditions, eliminating the need for intricate frequency and amplitude optimization. We also show that an alternative implementation, asymptotic quantum control, achieves comparable results. Furthermore, our approach can be adapted to suppress previously induced superconducting correlations, providing bidirectional control over quantum pairing states. These findings suggest practical pathways for manipulating quantum correlations in strongly interacting systems with minimal experimental complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20426v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/7dz3-2wlk</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 112, 033117 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Oleksandr Povitchan, Denys I. Bondar, Andrii G. Sotnikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lieb's Theorem for Bose Hubbard Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.10319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.10319v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Using a cone-theoretical method, we prove the uniqueness of the ground state for two Bose Hubbard models. The first model is the usual Bose Hubbard model with real hopping coefficients and attractive interactions. The second model is a two-component Bose Hubbard model. Under certain conditions, we show that the ground state in the subspace with particle number $N=2n$($n$ is a positive integer) is unique for both models. For the second model, we show that the ground state has spin along the z-axis $S^{z}=0$. When the hopping coefficients are real, it has zero spin quantum number, i.e., it is a singlet. Our proofs work equally well for any arbitrary finite-size lattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.10319v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhong-Chao Wei, Chong Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
