<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 01:43:31 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-spiral instability of the Nagaoka ferromagnet in the crossover between square and triangular lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05226</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05226v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the hard-core Fermi-Hubbard model in the crossover between square and triangular lattices near half-filling. As was recognized by Nagaoka in the 1960s, on the square lattice the presence of a single hole leads to ferromagnetic spin ordering. On the triangular lattice, geometric frustration instead leads to a spin-singlet ground state, which can be associated with a 120-degree spiral order. On lattices which interpolate between square and triangular, there is a phase transition at which the ferromagnetic order becomes unstable to a spin spiral. We model this instability, finding the exact critical point.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05226v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Darren Pereira, Erich J. Mueller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergence of nematic loop-current bond order in vanadium Kagome metals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05234</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05234v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The family of layered Kagome metals $\mathrm{A}\mathrm{V}_3\mathrm{Sb}_5$ $(\mathrm{A}=\mathrm{K,Rb,Cs})$ has recently attracted significant interest due to reports of charge-bond order, orbital magnetism, and superconductivity. Some of these phases may exhibit time-reversal symmetry breaking, as suggested by their response to magnetic fields. More recently, experiments have reported the emergence of nematic order that lowers the rotational symmetry of the system from sixfold to twofold. Here we investigate the mechanism behind a nematic phase that breaks both rotational and time-reversal symmetries. Starting from a nine-band tight-binding model and nearest-neighbour Coulomb interactions, we find nematic order to emerge in a narrow region of phase space within mean-field theory. The nematic state is a superposition of charge-bond order along one Kagome bond and loop-current order on the other two, preserving one of the three mirror planes. To understand this behaviour, we examine an effective patch model that captures one $p$-type and one $m$-type van Hove singularity at each $M$ point on the Brillouin zone boundary. Within the effective model, nematic order is stabilized by the coupling between the complex phases of the three bond order parameters. As a consequence, the nematic phase develops an elongated Fermi surface distinct from those of competing phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05234v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex Friedlan, Hae-Young Kee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semiconductor Meta-Graphene and Valleytronics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05250</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05250v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nano-patterned semiconductor interfaces offer a versatile platform for creating quantum metamaterials and exploring novel electronic phenomena. In this study, we illustrate this concept using artificial graphene--a metamaterial featuring distinctive properties including Dirac and saddle points. We demonstrate that introducing additional nano-patterning can open a Dirac band gap, giving rise to what we term artificial hexagonal boron nitride (AhBN). The calculated valley Chern number of AhBN indicates the presence of topological valley Hall states confined to Dirac-gap domain walls. A key question is whether these one-dimensional edge states are topologically protected against disorder, given their vulnerability to Anderson localization. To this end, we perform band structure and electronic transport simulations under experimentally relevant disorder, including charge puddles and geometric imperfections. Our results reveal the resilience of the domain wall states against typical experimental disorder, particularly while the AhBN band gap remains open. The localization length along the domain wall can reach several microns--several times longer than the bulk electron mean free path--even though the number of bulk transport channels is greater. To enhance the effectiveness of the low-dissipation domain wall channel, we propose ribbon geometries with a large length-to-width ratio. These findings underscore both the potential and challenges of AhBN for low-energy, power-efficient microelectronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05250v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Praveen Pai, Aron W. Cummings, Alexander Cerjan, Wei Pan, Fan Zhang, Catalin D. Spataru</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fermi surface and Berry phase analysis for Dirac nodal line semimetals: cautionary tale to SrGa$_2$ and BaGa$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05304v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A Berry phase of odd multiples of $\pi$ inferred from quantum oscillations (QOs) has often been treated as evidence for nontrivial reciprocal space topology. However, disentangling the Berry phase values from the Zeeman effect and the orbital magnetic moment is often challenging. In centrosymmetric compounds, the case is simpler as the orbital magnetic moment contribution is negligible. Although the Zeeman effect can be significant, it is usually overlooked in most studies of QOs in centrosymmetric compounds. Here, we present a detailed study on the non-magnetic centrosymmetric $\mathrm{SrGa_2}$ and $\mathrm{BaGa_2}$, which are predicted to be Dirac nodal line semimetals (DNLSs) based on density functional theory (DFT) calculations. Evidence of the nontrivial topology is found in magnetotransport measurements. The Fermi surface topology and band structure are carefully studied through a combination of angle-dependent QOs, angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES), and DFT calculations, where the nodal line is observed in the vicinity of the Fermi level. Strong de Haas-van Alphen fundamental oscillations associated with higher harmonics are observed in both compounds, which are well-fitted by the Lifshitz-Kosevich (LK) formula. However, even with the inclusion of higher harmonics in the fitting, we found that the Berry phases cannot be unambiguously determined when the Zeeman effect is included. We revisit the LK formula and analyze the phenomena and outcomes that were associated with the Zeeman effect in previous studies. Our experimental results confirm that $\mathrm{SrGa_2}$ and $\mathrm{BaGa_2}$ are Dirac nodal line semimetals. Additionally, we highlight the often overlooked role of spin-damping terms in Berry phase analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05304v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/6tq6-sr6w</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yuxiang Gao, Yichen Zhang, Shiming Lei, Neil Harrison, Mun Keat Chan, Jonathan D. Denlinger, Sergey Gorovikov, Sanu Mishra, Yan Sun, Ming Yi, Emilia Morosan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum oscillations and anisotropic magnetoresistance in the quasi-two-dimensional Dirac nodal line superconductor $\mathrm{YbSb_2}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05401v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent interest in quantum materials has focused on systems exhibiting both superconductivity and non-trivial band topology as material candidates to realize topological or unconventional superconducting states. So far, superconductivity in most topological materials has been identified as type II. In this work, we present magnetotransport studies on the quasi-two-dimensional type I superconductor $\mathrm{YbSb_2}$. Combined ab initio DFT calculations and quantum oscillation measurements confirm that $\mathrm{YbSb_2}$ is a Dirac nodal line semimetal in the normal state. The complex Fermi surface morphology is evidenced by the non-monotonic angular dependence of both the quantum oscillation amplitude and the magnetoresistance. Our results establish $\mathrm{YbSb_2}$ as a candidate material platform for exploring the interplay between band topology and superconductivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05401v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxiang Gao, Kevin Allen, Rose Albu Mustaf, Yichen Zhang, Sanu Mishra, Christopher Lane, Marta Zonno, Sergey Gorovikov, Jian-Xin Zhu, Ming Yi, Emilia Morosan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Imaging Nanoscale Carrier, Thermal, and Structural Dynamics with Time-Resolved and Ultrafast Electron Energy-Loss Spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05413v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Time-resolved and ultrafast electron energy-loss spectroscopy (EELS) is an emerging technique for measuring photoexcited carriers, lattice dynamics, and near-fields across femtosecond to microsecond timescales. When performed in either a specialized scanning transmission electron microscope or ultrafast electron microscope (UEM), time-resolved and ultrafast EELS can directly image charge carriers, lattice vibrations, and heat dissipation following photoexcitation or applied bias. Yet recent advances in theoretical calculations and electron optics are often required to realize the full potential of ultrafast EEL spectrum imaging. In this review, we present a comprehensive overview of the recent progress in the theory and instrumentation of time-resolved and ultrafast EELS. We begin with an introduction to the technique, followed by a physical description of the loss function. We outline approaches for calculating and interpreting ground-state and transient EEL spectra spanning low-loss plasmons to core-level excitations analogous to X-ray absorption. We then survey the current state of time-resolved and ultrafast EELS techniques beyond photon-induced near-field electron microscopy, highlighting abilities to image carrier and thermal dynamics. Finally, we examine future directions enabled by emerging technologies, including electron beam monochromation, in situ and operando cells, laser-free UEM, and high-speed direct electron detectors. These advances position time-resolved and ultrafast EELS as a critical tool for uncovering nanoscale dynamic processes in quantum materials and solar energy conversion devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05413v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wonseok Lee, Levi D. Palmer, Thomas E. Gage, Scott K. Cushing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Valley-dependent topological interface states in biased armchair nanoribbons in gapless graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05653</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05653v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate an electrical bias-controlled, topological kind discontinuity in valley polarization, in a two-segment armchair nanoribbon of gapless graphene, where the discontinuity is created at the interface by applying opposite in-plane, transverse electrical biases to the two segments. In particular, using an efficient tight-binding theoretical formulation, we explicitly obtain energy eigenvalues and probability distributions of discontinuity-induced, interface-confined electron eigenstates, in a reference configuration. Moreover, implications of the confinement for electron transport are explored. A configurational variation is introduced to transform the eigenstates into transport-active, quasi-localized ones. Such states are shown to result in Fano "anti-resonances" in transmission spectra. The resilience of the quasi-localized states and their associated Fano fingerprints is also illustrated with respect to configurational fluctuations, demonstrating their potential detectability in realistic devices and suggesting transport spectroscopy as a practical probe of valley-dependent topological interface physics in graphene nanoribbons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05653v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zheng-Han Huang, Jing-Yuan Lai, Yu-Shu G. Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Confinement-Controlled Morphology and Stability of One-Dimensional CrI3 Nanotubes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05889</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05889v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Integrating monolayers derived from 2D van der Waals (vdW) magnetic materials into next-generation technological applications remains a significant challenge due to their structural and magnetic instability issues. Template-assisted encapsulation is a potential route for the growth of stable 2D monolayers aimed at designing novel 1D heterostructures, opening new avenues for studying low-dimensional quantum effects and spin-related phenomena. In this study, we explored the diameter-dependent encapsulation of 2D CrI3 crystals using multi-walled carbon nanotubes as nanoscale host templates. Advanced microscopic analysis revealed distinct structural transitions, ranging from internal nanorod encapsulation to external shell formation, directly influenced by the host nanotube diameter. Furthermore, statistical analysis of structural morphologies indicates that CrI3 nanorods preferentially form within MWCNTs with inner diameters up to 5 nm, while single-walled CrI3 nanotubes are stabilized in CNTs with diameters up to 8 nm. For host CNTs exceeding 10 nm in diameter, CrI3 predominantly forms surface coatings rather than confined one-dimensional structures. In situ electron beam irradiation demonstrates the superior structural stability of single-walled CrI3 confined within MWCNTs, while externally coated CrI3 undergoes decomposition into metallic Cr clusters. Prolonged irradiation induces a morphological transformation of CrI3 nanotubes into nanorods. These insights lay the groundwork for engineering robust, tunable 1D magnetic heterostructures of CrI3 for spintronic and data storage applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05889v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ihsan Caha, Aqrab ul Ahmad, Francis Leonard Deepak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Commensurate-incommensurate Mott transition without magnetic field: emergence of nematic Luttinger liquid in XXZ chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05988</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05988v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the zero-magnetization phase diagram of a spin-1/2 chain with competing ferromagnetic nearest-neighbor and antiferromagnetic next-nearest-neighbor exchange couplings in the strongly interacting regime. Using density matrix renormalization group (DMRG) simulations, we discover two successive commensurate-incommensurate transitions of the non-conformal Pokrovsky-Talapov universality class, occurring (even) at zero magnetic field. The first transition marks the condensation of bound pairs of magnons into a critical phase with central charge $c=2$, emerging from a gapped period-4 phase. At the second transition, an incommensurate quadrupolar (or nematic) Luttinger liquid forms out of a gapped phase separation state, via the pairwise condensation of domain walls. We argue that both transitions involve the same underlying incommensurate nematic Luttinger liquid, and that the $c=2$ phase can be understood as a coexistence of a conventional (single-magnon type) and quadrupolar (two-magnon type) Luttinger liquids. Our results demonstrate that frustration alone is sufficient to drive continuous commensurate-incommensurate transitions of Mott type and stabilise incommensurate quasi-long-range order without doping.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05988v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julien Fitouchi, Natalia Chepiga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identifying chiral topological order in microscopic spin models by modular commutator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06086v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The chiral central charge $c_-$ is a key topological invariant of the edge characterizing the bulk two-dimensional chiral topological order, but its direct evaluation in microscopic spin models has long been a challenge, especially for non-abelian topological order. Building on the recently developed modular commutator formalism, we numerically obtain $c_-$ directly from single ground-state wave functions of two-dimensional interacting spin models that have chiral topological order. This provides a geometry-independent and bulk diagnostic of chirality. We study two nonintegrable systems -- the Zeeman-Kitaev honeycomb model and the kagome antiferromagnet -- both subjected to scalar spin chirality perturbations. We find that the modular commutator yields results consistent with the expected topological quantum field theories. We also compute the topological entanglement entropy which provides an independent diagnostic of the topological orders. Our work establishes modular commutators as a powerful numerical probe of chiral topological order in strongly correlated quantum magnets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06086v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Avijit Maity, Aman Kumar, Vikram Tripathi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Origin of trapped intralayer Wannier and charge-transfer excitons in moir\'e materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06137</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06137v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Moir\'e materials offer a versatile platform for engineering excitons with unprecedented control, promising next-generation optoelectronic applications. While continuum models are widely used to study moir\'e excitons due to their computational efficiency, they often disagree with ab initio many-body approaches, as seen for intralayer excitons in WS$_2$/WSe$_2$ heterobilayers. Here, we resolve these discrepancies using an atomistic, quantum-mechanical framework based on the Bethe-Salpeter equation with localized Wannier functions as the basis for the electronic structure. We show that inclusion of dielectric screening due to hexagonal boron nitride (hBN) encapsulation is essential to reproduce the full set of experimentally observed features of moir\'e intralayer excitons. Our analysis reveals a competition between Wannier and charge transfer characters, driven by variations between direct and indirect band gaps at high symmetry stacking regions due to atomic relaxations and environmentally tunable electron-hole interactions. Building on this insight, we demonstrate that the lowest-energy bright excitons are Wannier-like in WS2/WSe2 heterobilayers but charge-transfer-like in twisted WSe2 homobilayers, despite having comparable moir\'e lengths when encapsulated in hBN. In the absence of hBN encapsulation, the lowest-energy bright exciton in twisted WSe$_2$ becomes Wannier-like. These results establish atomistic modeling as a powerful and efficient approach for designing and controlling excitonic phenomena in moir\'e materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06137v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Indrajit Maity, Johannes Lischner, Arash A. Mostofi, \'Angel Rubio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frieze charge-stripes in a correlated kagome superconductor CsCr$_3$Sb$_5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06168</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06168v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Kagome metals have developed into a vibrant playground for materials physics, where geometric frustration, electronic correlations and band topology come together to create a variety of exotic phenomena. Recently synthesized CsCr$_3$Sb$_5$ has provided a rare opportunity to explore unconventional superconductivity in a strongly correlated kagome system with hints of frustrated magnetism and quantum criticality. Using spectroscopic imaging scanning tunneling microscopy, we reveal a cascade of density wave transitions with different symmetries in bulk single crystals of CsCr$_3$Sb$_5$. In particular, we discover a new electronic state $-$ a unidirectional density wave that breaks all mirror symmetries akin to a chiral density wave, but in contrast retains a mirror-glide symmetry. We term this state a frieze charge-stripe order phase, because its symmetry properties agree with one of the fundamental frieze symmetry groups. A combination of high-resolution imaging, Fourier analysis and theoretical simulations uncovers the crucial role of sublattice degrees of freedom in forming this phase, with internal chiral textures of opposite handedness. Our experiments reveal that superconductivity in CsCr$_3$Sb$_5$ develops from a new type of a unidirectional density wave, and set the foundation for exploring electronic states with frieze symmetry groups in quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06168v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siyu Cheng, Keyu Zeng, Yi Liu, Christopher Candelora, Ziqiang Wang, Guang-Han Cao, Ilija Zeljkovic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-dual bivariate bicycle codes with transversal Clifford gates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05211</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05211v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Bivariate bicycle codes are promising candidates for high-threshold, low-overhead fault-tolerant quantum memories. Meanwhile, color codes are the most prominent self-dual CSS codes, supporting transversal Clifford gates that have been demonstrated experimentally. In this work, we combine these advantages and introduce a broad family of self-dual bivariate bicycle codes. These codes achieve higher encoding rates than surface and color codes while admitting transversal CNOT, Hadamard, and $S$ gates. In particular, we enumerate weight-8 self-dual bivariate bicycle codes with up to $n \leq 200$ physical qubits, realized on twisted tori that enhance code distance and improve stabilizer locality. Representative examples include codes with parameters $[[n,k,d]]$: $[[16,4,4]]$, $[[40,6,6]]$, $[[56,6,8]]$, $[[64,8,8]]$, $[[120,8,12]]$, $[[152,6,16]]$, and $[[160,8,16]]$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05211v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zijian Liang, Yu-An Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid quantum-classical analog simulation of two-dimensional Fermi-Hubbard models with neutral atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05897</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05897v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We experimentally study the two-dimensional Fermi-Hubbard model using a Rydberg-based quantum processing unit in the analog mode. Our approach avoids encoding directly the original fermions into qubits and instead relies on reformulating the original model onto a system of fermions coupled to spins and then decoupling them in a self-consistent manner. We then introduce the auxiliary spin solver: this hybrid quantum-classical algorithm handles a free-fermion problem, which can be solved efficiently with a few classical resources, and an interacting spin problem, which can be naturally encoded in the analog quantum computer. This algorithm can be used to study both the equilibrium Mott transition as well as non-equilibrium properties of the original Fermi-Hubbard model, highlighting the potential of quantum-classical hybrid approaches to study strongly correlated matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05897v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergi Juli\`a-Farr\'e, Antoine Michel, Christophe Domain, Joseph Mikael, Jacques-Charles Lafoucriere, Joseph Vovrosh, Ahmed Chahlaoui, Dorian Claveau, Guillaume Villaret, Julius de Hond, Lo\"ic Henriet, Antoine Browaeys, Thomas Ayral, Alexandre Dauphin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A formula for the generation of shaking induced insulator-conductor transition in atomtronic transistors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11355</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11355v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Mott insulator of atomic transport can be realized in driven optical lattices by choosing particular ratio of driving frequency and amplitude, which has been studied as Floquet engineering with time-independent effective Hamiltonian approach. Here, we give general conditions of frequency-amplitude radio for realization of the driving induced insulator-conductor transition in a double-well open system, using instantaneous eigenstates approach. As we proved here, the instantaneous eigenstates approach is applicable in more wide parameter range compared with the time-independent effective Hamiltonian approach. Analysis from the results of quantum master equation shows that the insulator effect is originated from coherent localization of atom wave packets in optical wells.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11355v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenxi Lai, Yu-Quan Ma, Yi-Wen Wei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topologically Driven Spin-Orbit Torque in Dirac Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16359v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We unveil novel spin-orbit torque mechanisms driven by topological edge states in magnetic graphene-based devices. Within the energy gap, a damping-like torque plateau emerges within the quantum anomalous Hall phase upon breaking particle-hole symmetry, while for energies at the spin-split Dirac points located within the bands, a large damping-like torque develops as a result of a vanishing Fermi contour. Such torques are tunable by the degree of spin-pseudospin entanglement dictated by proximity-induced spin-orbit coupling terms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16359v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joaqu\'in Medina Due\~nas, Jos\'e H. Garc\'ia, Stephan Roche</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Catalog of cubic, symmetry-protected, non-Fermi liquid, Kondo-type exchange models for doublet impurities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05401v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: To identify what types of non-Fermi liquid (NFL) behavior are most likely to occur in cubic metals due to doublet impurities, we derive every cubic symmetry-allowed, NFL, Kondo-type exchange coupling that does not need accidental degeneracy for its realization. We find three distinct types of NFL behavior: two-channel Kondo (2CK) behavior for a non-Kramers doublet impurity coupled to local $\Gamma_8$ conduction electrons; topological Kondo physics for a Kramers doublet impurity and $\Gamma_4$ or $\Gamma_5$ conduction electrons; and lastly, spin-half impurity spin-$\frac{3}{2}$ conduction electron Kondo behavior for a Kramers doublet impurity and $\Gamma_8$ conduction electrons. The first two critical behaviors are not straightforward to realize. In the first case, 2CK physics is not guaranteed, since cubic symmetry does not prevent an effective spatial anisotropy from exceeding the 2CK coupling, which restores a Fermi liquid behavior. In the second case, the topological Kondo interaction is guaranteed to dominate, however, the spin degeneracy of the conduction electrons needs to be lifted e.g. by a magnetic field$-$so that they can be represented by $\Gamma_4$ or $\Gamma_5$ triplets$-$which then also lifts the degeneracy of the Kramers doublet. We find that the spin-half impurity spin-$\frac{3}{2}$ conduction electron, NFL, Kondo behavior has the greatest chance of existing in diluted, cubic compounds. We compute the thermodynamics of the topological Kondo model using the numerical renormalization group, and discuss the thermodynamics of the spin-half impurity spin-$\frac{3}{2}$ conduction electron Kondo model. We also identify candidate materials where the corresponding NFL behaviors could be observed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05401v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/j67z-1lj4</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Anna I. Toth, Andrew D. Huxley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic origin of reorganization energy in interfacial electron transfer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11619</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.11619v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Electron transfer (ET) reactions underpin energy conversion and chemical transformations in both biological and abiological systems. The efficiency of any ET process relies on achieving a desired ET rate within an optimal driving force range. Marcus theory provides a microscopic framework for understanding the activation free energy, and thus the rate, of ET in terms of a key parameter: the reorganization energy. For electrified solid-liquid interfaces, it has long been conventionally understood that only factors in the electrolyte phase are responsible for determining the reorganization energy and the electronic density of states (DOS) of the electrode serves only to dictate the number of thermally accessible channels for ET. Here we show instead that the electrode DOS plays a central role in governing the reorganization energy, far outweighing its conventionally assumed role. Using atomically layered heterostructures, we tune the DOS of graphene and measure outer-sphere ET kinetics. We find the ensuing variation in ET rate arises from strong modulation in a reorganization energy associated with image potential localization in the electrode. This work redefines the traditional paradigm of heterogeneous ET kinetics, revealing a deeper role of the electrode electronic structure in interfacial reactivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.11619v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sonal Maroo, Leonardo Coello Escalante, Yizhe Wang, Matthew P. Erodici, Jonathon N. Nessralla, Ayana Tabo, Takashi Taniguchi, Kenji Watanabe, Ke Xu, David T. Limmer, D. Kwabena Bediako</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electron correlations in kagome metals $AV_3Sb_5$ (A= K, Rb, Cs)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.09864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.09864v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The investigation of electronic order-quantum phase interplay in kagome lattices commonly employs the extended Kagome-Hubbard model, where the critical parameters comprise on-site $(U)$ and intersite $(V)$ Coulomb interactions. In prototypical kagome metals \ch{AV3Sb5} (A = K, Rb, Cs), the geometrically frustrated quasi-2D architecture induces pressure-dependent complexity in vanadium d-electron correlations, necessitating systematic theoretical scrutiny. Utilizing the $d-dp$ model within constrained random phase approximation (cRPA), we quantified $U$, $V$, and Hund's coupling $J$ under hydrostatic pressure (0-9 GPa). While \ch{KV3Sb5} and \ch{RbV3Sb5} exhibit pressure-insensitive interaction parameters, \ch{CsV3Sb5} manifests anomalous discontinuities in $U$ and $V$ near $0.2$ GPa, suggesting a first-order electronic phase transition. This work establishes cRPA-derived interaction landscapes as critical predictors for pressure-tunable quantum phenomena in correlated kagome systems, offers a new insight into the understanding of the interplay between the CDW transition and the double superconductivity dome in \ch{CsV3Sb5} at low pressure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.09864v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Feihu Liu, Changxu Liu, Maolin Zeng, Qiyi Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kondo-Peierls transition with nonsymmorphic zone boundary gap formation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21313v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study nonsymmorphic space group symmetry breakings in correlated electron systems. Under nonsymmorphic symmetry, it is well known that there are degeneracies in the electronic Bloch states at the Brillouin zone boundaries. When the system undergoes a phase transition into an ordered phase with breaking the nonsymmorphic symmetry, the degeneracy is lifted. This happens even when the order parameter is uniform. We point out that this general feature leads to various {\it uniform} Peierls transition in nonsymmorphic systems. In particular, we show that such mechanism of the Peierls gap formation can be realized accompanying with uniform anisotropic Kondo singlet formations. This explains the hidden electric order observed in CeCoSi.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21313v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.7566/JPSJ.94.113702</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. 94, 113702 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kazumasa Hattori, Hiroaki Kusunose</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoupling thermoelectric coefficients of multilayer graphene by nanomeshing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03436v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Nanostructuring materials at small scales enables control over their physical properties, revealing behaviors not observed at larger dimensions. This strategy is particularly effective in two-dimensional (2D) materials, where surface effects dominate, and has been applied in the thermoelectric field. Here, we use multilayer graphene (4-6 nm thick) as a test platform to study the effect of nanomeshing on its thermoelectric properties. The nanomesh consists of a hexagonal array of holes, with a measured diameter and neck-width of ~360 nm and ~160 nm, respectively. The multilayer graphene is integrated into field-effect transistor-like devices supported by hexagonal boron nitride (hBN), allowing simultaneous electric and thermoelectric measurements, with nanomeshing applied to only part of the material. We use modulated thermoreflectance to investigate thermal transport in equivalent nanomeshed and pristine graphene flakes, extracting key parameters that affect thermoelectric performance. The nanomesh geometry suppresses thermal transport without significantly impacting charge transport, highlighting the different scattering lengths of phonons and electrons while enhancing the thermopower response. We observe a twofold improvement in the device power factor, PF = S^2 sigma (with S the Seebeck coefficient and sigma the electrical conductivity), at room temperature, along with a nearly threefold reduction in thermal conductivity k. The results show that nanomeshing can significantly improve the thermoelectric performance of multilayer graphene, paving the way for novel energy conversion strategies using 2D materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03436v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mehrdad Rahimi, Nunzia Lubertino, Roberto Bellelli, Linsai Chen, Fran\c{c}ois Mallet, Philippe Lafarge, Cl\'ement Barraud, PAscal Marti, Julien Chaste, Dani\`ele Fournier, Maria Luisa Della Rocca</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic nonlinear valley Nernst effect in the strained bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01961v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We theoretically analyze the nonlinear valley Nernst effect (NVNE) as the second-order response of temperature gradient through the semiclassical framework of electron dynamics. Our study shows that an intrinsic nonlinear pure valley current can be generated vertically to the applied temperature in the materials with both inversion and time-reversal symmetries. This intrinsic NVNE has a quantum origin from the quantum metric and shows independence from the relaxation time. We find that the local largest symmetry near the valleys for the nonvanishing intrinsic NVNE is a single mirror symmetry in two-dimensional systems. We theoretically investigate the intrinsic NVNE in the uniaxially strained gapless bilayer graphene and find the intrinsic NVNE can emerge when applying the temperature gradient vertically to the direction of strain. Interestingly, a transition from the compressive strain to the tensile one results in the sign reversal of the intrinsic NVNE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01961v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/7j4p-4snc</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Ying-Li Wu, Jia-Liang Wan, Xiao-Qin Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite temperature dopant-induced spin reorganization explored via tensor networks in the two-dimensional $t$-$J$ model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04756v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Doped Mott insulators host intertwined spin-charge phenomena that evolve with temperature and can culminate in stripe order or superconductivity at low temperatures. The two-dimensional $t$-$J$ model captures this interplay yet finite-temperature, infinite-size calculations remain difficult. Using purification represented by a tensor network - an infinite projected entangled-pair state (iPEPS) ansatz - we simulate the $t$-$J$ model at finite temperature directly in the thermodynamic limit, reaching temperatures down to one tenth of the hopping rate and hole concentrations up to one quarter of the lattice sites. Beyond specific heat, uniform susceptibility, and compressibility, we introduce dopant-conditioned multi-point correlators that map how holes reshape local exchange. Nearest-neighbor hole pairs produce a strong cooperative response that reinforces antiferromagnetism on the adjacent parallel bonds, and single holes weaken nearby antiferromagnetic bonds; d-wave pairing correlations remain short-ranged over the same window. These results provide experiment-compatible thermodynamic-limit benchmarks and establish dopant-conditioned correlators as incisive probes of short-range spin-texture reorganization at finite temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04756v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yintai Zhang, Aritra Sinha, Marek M. Rams, Jacek Dziarmaga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing the Kitaev honeycomb model on a neutral-atom quantum computer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18554</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18554v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum simulations of many-body systems are among the most promising applications of quantum computers. In particular, models based on strongly-correlated fermions are central to our understanding of quantum chemistry and materials problems, and can lead to exotic, topological phases of matter. However, due to the non-local nature of fermions, such models are challenging to simulate with qubit devices. Here we realize a digital quantum simulation architecture for two-dimensional fermionic systems based on reconfigurable atom arrays. We utilize a fermion-to-qubit mapping based on Kitaev's model on a honeycomb lattice, in which fermionic statistics are encoded using long-range entangled states. We prepare these states efficiently using measurement and feedforward, realize subsequent fermionic evolution through Floquet engineering with tunable entangling gates interspersed with atom rearrangement, and improve results with built-in error detection. Leveraging this fermion description of the Kitaev spin model, we efficiently prepare topological states across its complex phase diagram and verify the non-Abelian spin liquid phase by evaluating an odd Chern number. We further explore this two-dimensional fermion system by realizing tunable dynamics and directly probing fermion exchange statistics. Finally, we simulate strong interactions and study dynamics of the Fermi-Hubbard model on a square lattice. These results pave the way for digital quantum simulations of complex fermionic systems for materials science, chemistry, and high-energy physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18554v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41586-025-09475-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature 645, 341-347 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Simon J. Evered, Marcin Kalinowski, Alexandra A. Geim, Tom Manovitz, Dolev Bluvstein, Sophie H. Li, Nishad Maskara, Hengyun Zhou, Sepehr Ebadi, Muqing Xu, Joseph Campo, Madelyn Cain, Stefan Ostermann, Susanne F. Yelin, Subir Sachdev, Markus Greiner, Vladan Vuleti\'c, Mikhail D. Lukin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
