<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 01:35:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical localization of interacting ultracold atoms in one-dimensional quasi-periodic potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19421v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present numerically exact non-equilibrium dynamics of a one-dimensional Bose gas in quasi-periodic lattice that plays an intermediate role between the long-ranged order and truly disordered systems exhibiting unusual correlated phases. Precision control over lattice depth, interaction strength and filling factor enables the exploration of various correlated phases in a finite periodic lattice. We investigate the system dynamics when the secondary incommensurate lattice is abruptly switched on. To solve the many-body Schroedinger equation, we employ the multiconfigurational time-dependent Hartree method for bosons (MCTDHB). The many-body dynamics are analyzed through distinct measures of the Glauber correlation functions and dynamical fragmentation. Our study reveals four distinct scenarios of localization process in the non-equilibrium dynamics. Weakly interacting non-fragmented superfluid of incommensurate filling in the primary lattice exhibits collapse-revival dynamics of localization. In contrast, a fragmented superfluid with commensurate filling exhibits dynamical Mott localization. A strongly correlated, fully fragmented Mott state shows a subtle competition with localization introduced by the secondary lattice that merely melts the Mott correlations. Interestingly, in the fermionized Mott regime, where the density in each well is fragmented, the intra-dimer correlations exhibit unexpected robustness. These findings provide new insights into many-body correlation dynamics and novel localization mechanisms in quasi-periodic lattices, paving the way for engineering exotic quantum behaviors in ultracold atomic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19421v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Attis V. M. Marino, M. A. Caracanhas, V. S. Bagnato, B. Chakrabarti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical correlation effects in twisted bilayer graphene under strain and lattice relaxation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19436v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the impact of lattice effects due to heterostrain and relaxation on the correlated electron physics of magic-angle twisted bilayer graphene, by applying dynamical mean-field theory to the topological heavy fermion model. Heterostrain is responsible for splitting the 8-fold degenerate flat bands into two 4-fold degenerate subsets, while relaxation breaks the particle-hole symmetry of the unperturbed THF model. The interplay of dynamical correlation effects and lattice symmetry breaking enables us to satisfactorily reproduce a wide set of experimentally observed features: splitting the flat band degeneracy has observable consequences in the form of a filling-independent maximum in the spectral density away from zero bias, which faithfully reproduces scanning tunneling microscopy and quantum twisting microscopy results alike. We also observe an overall reduction in the size and degeneracy of local moments upon lowering the temperature, in agreement with entropy measurements. The absence of particle-hole symmetry has as a consequence the stronger suppression of local moments on the hole-doped side relatively to the electron-doped side, and ultimately causes the differences in existence and stability of the correlated phases for negative and positive doping. Our results show that even fine-level structures in the experimental data can now be faithfully reproduced and understood.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19436v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Crippa, Gautam Rai, Dumitru C\u{a}lug\u{a}ru, Haoyu Hu, Jonah Herzog-Arbeitman, B. Andrei Bernevig, Roser Valent\'i, Giorgio Sangiovanni, Tim Wehling</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable Electronic Interactions and Weak Antilocalization in Bulk Ge$_2$Sb$_2$Te$_{5-5x}$Se$_{5x}$ Phase Change Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19510</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19510v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Phase change materials (PCMs) are well-known for their reversible and rapid switching between crystalline and amorphous phases through thermal excitations mediated by strong electrical or laser pulses. This crystal-to-amorphous transition is accompanied by a remarkable contrast in optical and electronic properties, making PCMs useful in nonvolatile data storage applications. Here, we combine electrical transport and angle resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) measurements to study the electronic structure of bulk Ge$_2$Sb$_2$Te$_{5-5x}$Se$_{5x}$ (GSST) for $0\le x \le 0.8$, where $x$ represents the amount of Se substituting Te in Ge$_2$Sb$_2$Te$_5$ (GST)-- a prototypical PCM. The single-particle density of states (SDOS) derived from the integrated ARPES data displays metallic behavior for all $x$, as evidenced by the presence of a finite density of states in the vicinity of the chemical potential. Transport measurements also display clear signatures of metallic transport, consistent with the SDOS data. The temperature dependence of the resistance indicates the onset of moderate electron-electron Coulomb interaction effects at low temperatures for $x\geq 0.6$. At the same time, the magnetoresistance data shows signatures of weak antilocalization for $x\geq 0.6$. An analysis on the temperature dependence of the phase coherence length suggests that electron dephasing is primarily due to inelastic electron-electron scattering. We find that these effects are enhanced with increasing $x$, portraying GSST as a novel PCM where electronic interactions can be tuned via chemical doping.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19510v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicholas Mazzucca, Junjing Zhao, Zhenyang Xu, Despina Louca, Utpal Chatterjee, Marc Bockrath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytical analysis of the spin wave dispersion in the cycloidal spin structures under the influence of magneto-electric coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19543v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spin waves and coupling of the spin waves with electromagnetic waves are considered in the multiferroic materials with the electric dipole moment proportional to the scalar product of spins. Dispersion dependence for the spin waves propagating as the perturbation of the equilibrium state described by spin cycloid is found. The dielectric permeability as the response on the electromagnetic perturbations associated with the magneto-electric coupling for the same equilibrium state is calculated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19543v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pavel A. Andreev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strain-tunable anomalous Hall effect in hexagonal MnTe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19582</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19582v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ability to control and manipulate time-reversal ($T$) symmetry-breaking phases with near-zero net magnetization is a sought-after goal in spintronic devices. The recently discovered hexagonal altermagnet manganese telluride ($\alpha$-MnTe) is a prime example. It has a compensated $A$-type antiferromagnetic (AFM) ground state where the in-plane ferromagnetic (FM) moments in each layer are stacked antiferromagnetically along the $c$ axis, yet exhibits a spontaneous anomalous Hall effect (AHE) that breaks the $T$-symmetry with a vanishingly small $c$-axis FM moment. However, the presence of three 120$^\circ$ separated in-plane magnetic domains presents a challenge in understanding the origin of AHE and the effective control of the altermagnetic state. Here we use neutron scattering to show that a compressive uniaxial strain along the next-nearest-neighbor Mn-Mn bond direction detwins $\alpha$-MnTe into a single in-plane magnetic domain, aligning the in-plane moments along the same direction. Furthermore, we find that uniaxial strain (-0.2% to 0.1%) significantly sharpens the magnetic hysteresis loop and switches the sign of the AHE near room temperature. Remarkably, this is achieved without altering the AFM phase-transition temperature, which can only be explained by a strain-induced modification of the electronic band structure. Our work not only unambiguously establishes the relationship between the in-plane moment direction and the AHE in $\alpha$-MnTe but also paves the way for future applications in highly scalable, strain-tunable magnetic sensors and spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19582v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhaoyu Liu, Sijie Xu, Jonathan M. DeStefano, Elliott Rosenberg, Tingjun Zhang, Jinyulin Li, Matthew B. Stone, Feng Ye, Rong Cong, Siyu Pan, Ching-Wu Chu, Liangzi Deng, Emilia Morosan, Jiun-Haw Chu, Pengcheng Dai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Knight shift measurements probing Fermi surface changes under pressure in CeRhIn$_5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19634v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) Knight shift measurements of the In(1) and In(2) sites in CeRhIn$_5$ as a function of pressure. In contrast to the $c$ axis, the in-plane components of the In(1) Knight shift tensor exhibit little to no pressure dependence. These results indicate that the dipolar component of the tensor is strongly suppressed at the In(1) site, while it remains constant with pressure at the In(2) site. We analyze the hyperfine coupling in terms of a tight binding model for the electronic structure, and determine that the pressure dependence of the In(1) shift cannot be explained in terms of changes to the crystal field parameters, but rather can be understood in terms of an increase in the 4f electron content at the Fermi surface. Our results indicate that the hyperfine coupling reflects changes in the electronic structure near a Kondo breakdown quantum critical point.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19634v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Y. -H. Nian, C. Chaffey, P. Sherpa, L. Santillan, K. Nagashima, Peter Klavins, V. Taufour, N. J. Curro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybridization gap and $f$-electron effect evolutions with Cd- and Sn-doping in CeCoIn$_5$ via infrared spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19684</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19684v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigated hole (Cd)- and electron (Sn)-doped CeCoIn$_5$ (CeCo(In$_{1-x}T_x$)$_5$ ($T$ = Cd or Sn)) using infrared spectroscopy. Doping-dependent hybridization gap distribution functions were obtained from the optical conductivity spectra based on the periodic Anderson model formalism. The hybridization gap distribution exhibits two components: in-plane and out-of-plane hybridization gaps. The doping-dependent evolution of the two gaps indicated that the out-of-plane gap was more sensitive to doping. Furthermore, the magnetic optical resistivity exhibited a doping-dependent evolution of the $f$-electron amplitude. The two dopant types exhibited different physical properties depending on the level of doping. The Sn dopant increases the $f$-electron amplitude, whereas the Cd dopant does not affect the $f$-electron amplitude. Doping-dependent effective mass is peaked at pure (or undoped) CeCoIn$_5$. Our spectroscopic results may help understand the doping-dependent electronic evolution of one of the canonical heavy fermion systems, CeCoIn$_5$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19684v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review B 109, 125147/1-9 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Myounghoon Lee, Yu-Seong Seo, Seulki Roh, Seokbae Lee, Jihyun Kim, Tuson Park, Jungseek Hwang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holographic Aspects of Dynamical Mean-Field Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19704</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19704v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dynamical mean-field theory (DMFT) is one of the most standard theoretical frameworks for addressing strongly correlated electron systems. Meanwhile, the concept of holography, developed in the field of quantum gravity, provides an intrinsic relationship between quantum many-body systems and space-time geometry. In this study, we demonstrate that these two theories are closely related to each other by shedding light on holographic aspects of DMFT, particularly for electrons with a semicircle density of states. We formulate a holographic renormalization group for the branch Green's function from the outer edge to the interior of the Bethe lattice network, and then find that its fixed point can be interpreted as a self-consistent solution of Green's function in DMFT. By introducing an effective two-dimensional anti-de Sitter space, moreover, we clarify that the scaling dimensions for the branch Green's function and the boundary correlation functions of electrons at the outer edge of the Bethe lattice network are characterized by the fixed-point Green's function. We also perform DMFT computations for the Bethe-lattice Hubbard model, which illustrate that the scaling dimensions capture the Mott transition in the deep interior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19704v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kouichi Okunishi, Akihisa Koga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A General Many-Body Perturbation Framework for Moir\'e Systems: Application to Rhombohedral Pentalayer Graphene/hBN Heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19764</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19764v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Moir\'e superlattices host a rich variety of correlated topological states, including interaction-driven integer and fractional Chern insulators. A common approach to study interacting ground states at integer fillings is the Hartree-Fock mean-field method. However, this method neglects dynamical correlations, which often leads to an overestimation of spontaneous symmetry breaking and fails to provide quantitative descriptions of single-particle excitations. This work introduces a general many-body perturbation framework for moir\'e systems, combining all-band Hartree-Fock calculations with random phase approximation (RPA) correlation energies and $GW$ quasiparticle corrections. We apply this framework to moir\'e superlattice consisted of rhombohedral pentalayer graphene aligned with hexagonal boron nitride. Our all-band Hartree-Fock calculations, which include all plane-wave components up to the high-energy cutoff of the continuum model, reveal a phase diagram at moir\'e filling $\nu=1$ that qualitatively aligns with experimental measurements. Incorporating RPA correlation energy further yields quantitative agreement with the evolution of transport properties across electric fields. The $GW$ quasiparticle bands exhibit significantly reduced gaps and bandwidths compared to Hartree-Fock results, while quasiparticle weights close to unity indicate that the ground state is well-described by a Slater determinant, justifying the qualitative effectiveness of mean-field approaches for integer fillings in this system. Our versatile framework provides a systematic beyond-mean-field approach applicable to generic moir\'e systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19764v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Lu, Yuanfan Yang, Zhongqing Guo, Jianpeng Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploration of Altermagnetism in $\mathrm{RuO_{2}}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19932</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19932v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The fundamental role of magnetic materials in modern science and technology has driven a rapid surge in research on unconventional magnetism in recent years. In particular, altermagnets, which simultaneously exhibit zero net magnetization in real space and anisotropic spin splitting in momentum space, have garnered significant interest for both fundamental physics and technological applications. Among these, $\mathrm{RuO_{2}}$ stands as the pioneering and most extensively studied altermagnet. While the intrinsic magnetic order of $\mathrm{RuO_{2}}$ is still a subject of active debate, numerous exotic phenomena characteristic of altermagnetism have been observed in $\mathrm{RuO_{2}}$ samples. In this review, we explore each facet of the altermagnetism through specific case studies in $\mathrm{RuO_{2}}$, systematically surveying its crystal and magnetic structures, electronic band properties, and transport phenomena. We critically assess the debate surrounding the intrinsic magnetism in $\mathrm{RuO_{2}}$, incorporating evidence from altermagnetic signatures in transport, as well as contrasting results from magnetic and spectroscopic measurements. Finally, possible future research directions in this field are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19932v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Xin Li, Yiyuan Chen, Liqing Pan, Shuai Li, Song-Bo Zhang, Hai-Zhou Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-ohmic to ohmic crossover in the breakdown of the quantum Hall states in graphene under broadband excitations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19978</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19978v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Graphene, through the coexistence of large cyclotron gaps and small spin and valley gaps, offers the possibility to study the breakdown of the quantum Hall effect across a wide range of energy scales. In this work, we investigate the breakdown of the QHE in high-mobility graphene Corbino devices under broadband excitation ranging from DC up to 10 GHz. We find that the conductance is consistently described by variable range hopping (VRH) and extract the hopping energies from both temperature and field-driven measurements. Using VRH thermometry, we are able to distinguish between a cold and hot electron regime, which are dominated by non-ohmic VRH and Joule heating, respectively. Our results demonstrate that breakdown in the quantum Hall regime of graphene is governed by a crossover from non-ohmic, field-driven VRH to ohmic, Joule-heating-dominated transport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19978v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Torsten R\"oper, Aifei Zhang, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Olivier Maillet, Fran\c{c}ois D. Parmentier, Erwann Bocquillon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multipole analysis of spin currents in altermagnetic MnTe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20120</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20120v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Altermagnets, a class of unconventional antiferromagnets where antiparallel spins are connected by combined rotational and translational symmetries, have recently emerged as promising candidates for spintronic applications, as they can efficiently generate spin currents while maintaining vanishing net magnetization. Here, we investigate charge transport and spin currents in $\alpha$-MnTe, a prototypical altermagnet, using symmetry analysis within the multipole framework and fully relativistic first-principles calculations using the Kubo formalism. Our results show that different magnetic configurations with N\'eel vectors $\hat{N}\parallel y$ and $\hat{N}\parallel x$ in MnTe induce distinct order parameters. This distinction gives rise to spin-momentum locking with different parities and magnetic spin Hall effects (magnetic SHEs) with different anisotropies. Strikingly, our calculations show that the combination of intrinsic spin-orbit coupling and altermagnetic spin splitting yields a large magnetic spin Hall angle of up to 16 \% rivaling or exceeding that of heavy metals such as Pt. On the other hand, the anisotropy of the magnetic SHE provides a practical means to identify the type of order parameter. This establishes, through the powerful framework of multipoles, a general approach for studying transport phenomena that extends to a broader class of altermagnets beyond MnTe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20120v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryosuke Hirakida, Karma Tenzin, Chao Chen Ye, Berkay Kilic, Carmine Autieri, Jagoda S{\l}awi\'nska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lateral disorder in Langmuir monolayers: theoretical derivations and grazing-incidence X-ray diffraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20130</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20130v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent studies of the self-assembly of Langmuir monolayers have revealed novel forms of lateral molecular ordering. Such studies typically involve the use of grazing-incidence synchrotron radiation scattering, and the lateral order manifests itself as distinct diffraction patterns. The more intricate the molecular organization, the more complicated the corresponding diffraction pattern is. To the point where standard analysis, i.e., identifying peak positions and solving the crystal structure, is insufficient to describe the system. In such cases, a physics-based simulation of the diffraction is required. In this article, we present a versatile theoretical framework for simulating complex structural molecular ordering in Langmuir monolayers. We begin by applying the formalism to a simple case of solid-state monolayers and extend the analysis to describe the structural organization in the collapsed state. The applicability of the method is validated through comparison with experimental data collected at the bending magnet synchrotron beamline.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20130v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. R. Muftakhova, K. V. Nikolaev, A. V. Rogachev, N. N. Novikova, B. I. Ostrovskii, S. N. Yakunin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single crystal growth, structural and physical properties, and absence of a charge density wave in Ti_{0.85}Fe6Ge6</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20142</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20142v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Kagome materials with charge density waves (CDWs) are fascinating quantum systems, offering an ideal platform to explore intertwined orders and to uncover novel mechanisms behind CDW formation. Chemical models have been developed and applied to predict CDW in $AM_6X_6$-type kagome materials, such as the rattling chain model based on ScV6Sn6 and the magnetic energy-saving model based on FeGe. In this study, we successfully synthesized Ti_{0.85}Fe6Ge6 single crystals using the vapor transport method. As predicted by the rattling chain model, these crystals are expected to exhibit kagome CDW behavior. Magnetization measurements indicate that Ti_{0.85}Fe6Ge6 is an easy-axis antiferromagnet with T_N = 488 K and transport measurements reveal metallic behavior primarily driven by electron-type carriers. However, no clear signatures of a CDW were observed in Ti_{0.85}Fe6Ge6. Density functional theory calculations demonstrate a markedly distinct electronic structure compared to related compounds: instead of a carrier-doping-induced rigid shift, the density of states shifted away from the Fermi level. Consistent with our structural investigations, the absence of a CDW and the unusual band structure can be attributed to the bonding characteristic within Ti_{0.85}Fe6Ge6. The strong covalent bonds of Ti-Ge1b, along with the solid Ge1b-Ge1b dimers, prevent the Ti-Ge1b-Ge1b-Ti chain from rattling. The presence of Fe-Fe antibonding state at the Fermi level enhances the spin polarization and depletes the electronic density around the Fermi level. Our results suggest that both the ionic radius and the bonding characteristics of the filler atom are crucial for the formation of CDWs in kagome materials. These factors can serve as supplementary terms to the rattling chain model, providing new insights for the discovery of novel kagome CDW materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20142v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dechao Cheng, Nour Maraytta, Xiuhua Chen, Xizhi Li, Xueliang Wu, Xiangxiang Jing, Yong Hu, Youpin Gong, Mingquan He, Yisheng Chai, Xiaoyuan Zhou, Pengfei Jiang, Yilin Wang, Michael Merz, Aifeng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-universal localization transition in the quantum Hall effect probed through broken-symmetry states of graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20163</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20163v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The quantum Hall effect hosts quantum phase transitions in which the localization length, that is the size of disorder-induced bulk localized states, is governed by universal scaling from percolation theory. However, this universal character is not systematically observed in experiments, including very recent ones in extremely clean devices. Here we explore this non-universality by systematically measuring the localization length in broken-symmetry quantum Hall states of graphene. Depending on the nature and gap size of these states, we observe differences of up to a tenfold in the minimum localization length, accompanied by clear deviations from universal scaling. Our results, as well as the previously observed non-universality, are fully captured by a simple picture based on the co-existence of localized states from two successive sub-Landau levels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20163v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aifei Zhang, Torsten R\"oper, Manjari Garg, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Carles Altimiras, Patrice Roche, Erwann Bocquillon, Olivier Maillet, Fran\c{c}ois D. Parmentier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of correlated hopping on thermoelectric response of a quantum dot strongly coupled to ferromagnetic leads</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20243v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We theoretically investigate the impact of correlated hopping on thermoelectric transport through a quantum dot coupled to ferromagnetic leads. Using the accurate numerical renormalization group method, we analyze the transport characteristics, focusing on the interplay between electronic correlations, spin-dependent transport processes, and thermoelectric response. We calculate the electrical conductance and thermopower as functions of the dot energy level, lead polarization, and the amplitude of correlated hopping. Moreover, we analyze the effect of competing correlations on the Kondo resonance and discuss the asymmetry of conductance peaks under the influence of the exchange field. We demonstrate that the presence of correlated hopping is responsible for asymmetric spin-dependent transport characteristics. Our results provide valuable insight into how correlated hopping affects spin-dependent transport and thermoelectric efficiency in quantum dot systems with ferromagnetic contacts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20243v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/andp.202500236</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Ann. Phys. Vol. 537 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kacper Wrze\'sniewski, Ireneusz Weymann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4D-QENS Analysis of Correlated Ionic Conduction in SrCl$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20312</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20312v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Methods of elucidating the mechanisms of fast-ion conduction in solid-state materials are pivotal for advancements in energy technologies such as batteries, fuel cells, sensors, and supercapacitors. In this study, we examine the ionic conduction pathways in single crystal SrCl$_2$, which is a fast-ion conductor above 900~K, using four-dimensional Quasi-Elastic Neutron Scattering (4D-QENS). We explore both coherent and incoherent neutron scattering at temperatures above the transition temperature into the superionic phase to explore the correlated motion of hopping anions. Refinements of the incoherent QENS yield residence times and jump probabilities between lattice sites in good agreement with previous studies, confirming that ionic hopping along nearest-neighbor directions is the most probable conduction pathway. However, the coherent QENS reveals evidence of de Gennes narrowing, indicating the importance of ionic correlations in the conduction mechanism. This highlights the need for improvements both in the theory of ionic transport in fluorite compounds and the modeling of coherent 4D-QENS in single crystals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20312v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jared Coles, Omar Chmaissem, Matthew Krogstad, Daniel M. Pajerowski, Feng Ye, Duck Young Chung, Mercouri G. Kanatzidis, Stephan Rosenkranz, Raymond Osborn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-polaron fingerprints in the optical conductivity of iridates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20337v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As a consequence of their spin-orbit entangled ground state, many $5d^{5}$ iridate materials display a peculiar double peak structure in optical transport quantities, such as absorption and conductivity. Their common interpretation is based on the presence of Hubbard subbands in the half-filled $j_{\mathrm{eff}}=1/2$ manifold. Herein, we challenge this picture, proposing a scenario based on the presence of spin-polaron (SP) quasiparticles, and assigning a dominant SP character to the first peak. We illustrate it by taking the materials Ba$_2$IrO$_4$ and Sr$_2$IrO$_4$ as paradigmatic examples, which we investigate within the dynamical mean-field theory and the self-consistent Born approximation. Both theories reproduce nontrivial features revealed by angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy and optical transport measurements, supporting our interpretation. In the case of Sr$_2$IrO$_4$, we show how the SP scenario survives in the low-doped regime. Similar optical transport fingerprints are expected to be found in the wider class of $5d^5$ iridates and more generally in strongly correlated antiferromagnetic regimes, such as those found in cuprates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20337v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Cassol, L\'eo Gaspard, Cyril Martins, Michele Casula, Benjamin Lenz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superfluid-Mott transition in a frustrated triangular optical lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20352</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20352v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Geometric frustration can significantly increase the complexity and richness of many-body physics and, for instance, suppress antiferromagnetic order in quantum magnets. Here, we employ ultracold bosonic $^{39}$K atoms in a triangular optical lattice to study geometric frustration by stabilizing the gas at the frustrated upper band edge using negative absolute temperatures. We find that geometric frustration suppresses the critical interaction strength for the (chiral-)superfluid to Mott insulator ($\chi$-SF-MI) quantum phase transition by a factor of 2.7(3) and furthermore changes the critical dynamics of the transition. Although the emergence of coherence during fast ramps from MI to the ($\chi$-)SF regime is continuous in both cases, for ramps longer than a few tunnelling times, significant differences emerge. In the \frs case, no long-range order emerges on the studied timescales, highlighting a significantly reduced rate or even saturation of the emerging coherence. This work opens the door to quantum simulations of frustrated systems that are often intractable by classical simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20352v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mehedi Hasan, Luca Donini, Sompob Shanokprasith, Daniel Braund, Tobias Marozsak, Moritz Epping, Daniel Reed, Max Melchner, Tiffany Harte, Ulrich Schneider</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Particle-hole asymmetric phases in doped twisted bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03123</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.03123v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Despite much theoretical work, developing a comprehensive ab initio model for twisted bilayer graphene (TBG) has proven challenging due to the inherent trade-off between accurately describing the band structure and incorporating the interactions within the Hamiltonian, particularly given the topological obstruction -- so-called fragile topology -- to the description of the model in terms of localized symmetric Wannier functions within the flat band manifold. Here, we circumvent this obstruction by using an extended 8-orbital model, for which localized Wannier orbitals have been formulated by Carr et al. [1]. We constructed an extended multi-orbital Hubbard model, and performed Hartree-Fock (HF) calculations to explore its phase diagram across commensurate fillings from -3 to 3. We found several nearly-degenerate insulating states at charge neutrality, all of which exhibit orbital orders. Crucially, TBG near magic angle is known to be particle-hole asymmetric, which is naturally captured by the single-particle band structure of our model and is reflected in the distinction between the symmetry broken states obtained at electron and hole dopings away from the charge neutral point. At filling -1 and +2, quantum anomalous hall states are obtained, while for the rest of the integer fillings away from charge neutrality, we found the system to realize metallic states with various orbital, valley and spin orderings. We also observed that most of the Hartree--Fock ground states exhibit a generalized valley Hund's-like rule, resulting in valley polarization. Importantly, we show that the incorporation of the intra-valley and inter-valley exchange interactions is crucial to properly stabilize the ordered symmetry-broken states. In agreement with experiments, we find significant particle-hole asymmetry, which underscores the importance of using particle-hole asymmetric models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.03123v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.125140</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review B 111.12 (2025): 125140</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Run Hou, Shouvik Sur, Lucas K. Wagner, Andriy H. Nevidomskyy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Abelian Fractional Chern Insulators and Competing States in Flat Moir\'e Bands</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.08887</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.08887v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Breakthrough experiments have recently realized fractional Chern insulators (FCIs) in moir\'e materials. However, all states observed are Abelian, the possible existence of more exotic non-Abelian FCIs remains controversial both experimentally and theoretically. Here, we investigate the competition between charge density wave (CDW) order, gapless composite fermion liquid (CFL), and non-Abelian Moore-Read states at half-filling of a moir\'e band. Although groundstate (quasi-)degeneracies and spectral flow are not sufficient for distinguishing between charge order and Moore-Read states, we find evidence using entanglement spectroscopy that both these states of matter can be realized with Coulomb interactions. By further analyzing the graviton excitations of Moore-Read states, we unveil that the ground states exhibit a mixed behavior of Pfaffian and anti-Pfaffian, despite the weak breaking of particle-hole symmetry. In a double twisted bilayer graphene model, transitions between these phases can be driven by the coupling strength between the layers: at weak coupling there is a CFL phase and at strong coupling a CDW order emerges. Remarkably, however, there is compelling evidence for a non-Abelian Moore-Read FCI phase at intermediate coupling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.08887v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/43nq-ntqm</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 106604 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hui Liu, Zhao Liu, Emil J. Bergholtz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interaction dependence of the Hall response for the Bose-Hubbard triangular ladder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.15276</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.15276v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explore the behavior of the Hall response of a Bose-Hubbard triangular ladder in a magnetic field as a function of the repulsive on-site atomic interactions. We consider a wide range of interaction strengths, from the weakly interacting limit to the hardcore regime. This is realized by computing the Hall polarization following the quench of a weak linear potential which induces the flow of a current through the system, using time-dependent matrix product state numerical simulations. We complement our understanding in the regime of small magnetic fields by analytical calculations of the equilibrium value of the Hall polarization for non-interacting bosonic atoms, or under a mean-field assumption. The Bose-Hubbard triangular flux ladder exhibits a rich phase diagram, containing Meissner, vortex and biased-chiral superfluid phases. We show that the Hall response can be employed to fingerprint the various chiral state, the frustration effects occurring in the limit of strong interactions, and the phase boundaries of the equilibrium phase diagram.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.15276v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.7.023112</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 7, 023112 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Catalin-Mihai Halati, Thierry Giamarchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
