<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 04:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Electron-beam-induced Contactless Manipulation of Interlayer Twist in van der Waals Heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03347</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03347v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ability to dynamically control the relative orientation of layers in two dimensional (2D) van der Waals (vdW) heterostructures represents a critical step toward the realization of reconfigurable nanoscale devices. Existing actuation methods often rely on mechanical contact, complex architectures, or extreme operating conditions, which limit their applicability and scalability. In this work, we present a proof-of-concept demonstration of contactless electrostatic actuation based on electron-beam-induced charge injection. By locally charging an insulating hexagonal boron nitride (hBN) flake on an electrically grounded graphene layer, we create an interfacial electric field that generates in-plane electrostatic torque and induces angular displacement. We validate the induced rotation through in-situ scanning electron microscopy (SEM) and twist-dependent Raman spectroscopy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03347v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicola Curreli, Tero S. Kulmala, Riya Sebait, Nicol\`o Petrini, Matteo Bruno Lodi, Roman Furrer, Alessandro Fanti, Michel Calame, Ilka Kriegel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bloch Oscillations and Landau-Zener Transitions in Flat-Band Lattices with Quadratic and Linear Band Touchings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03530</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03530v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Bloch oscillations (BOs) describe the coherent oscillatory motion of electrons in a periodic lattice under a constant external electric field. Deviations from pure harmonic wave packet motion or irregular Bloch oscillations can occur due to Zener tunneling (Landau-Zener Transitions or LZTs), with oscillation frequencies closely tied to interband coupling strengths. Motivated by the interplay between flat-band physics and interband coupling in generating irregular BOs, here we investigate these oscillations in Lieb and Kagome lattices using two complementary approaches: coherent transport simulations and scattering matrix analysis. In the presence of unavoidable band touchings, half-fundamental and fundamental BO frequencies are observed in Lieb and Kagome lattices, respectively -- a behavior directly linked to their distinct band structures. When avoided band touchings are introduced, distinct BO frequency responses to coupling parameters in each lattice are observed. Scattering matrix analysis reveals strong coupling and potential LZTs between dispersive bands and the flat band in Kagome lattices, with the quadratic band touching enhancing interband interactions and resulting in BO dynamics that is distinct from systems with linear crossings. In contrast, the Lieb lattice -- a three level system -- shows independent coupling between the flat band and two dispersive bands, without direct LZTs occurring between the two dispersive bands themselves. Finally, to obtain a unifying perspective on these results, we examine BOs during a strain-induced transition from Kagome to Lieb lattices, and link the evolution of irregular BO frequencies to changes in band connectivity and interband coupling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03530v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenhaoyue Wang, Carlos J. Garcia-Cervera, Amartya S. Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strain Effects on Electronic Properties of Cobalt-Based Coordination Nanosheets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03549</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03549v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We theoretically study the strain effects on the electronic properties of
  cobalt-based benzenehexathiol (CoBHT) coordination nanosheets using
  first-principles calculations. Two distinct crystal structures,
  high-density structure (HDS) and low-density structure (LDS), are
  explored. Our results reveal that HDS behaves as a metal, while LDS
  exhibits semiconducting. Spin-polarized electronic band structures highlight the presence of energy band structures of Kagome lattice, and
  the inclusion of spin-orbit coupling (SOC) results in band gap openings
  at high-symmetric K points. Furthermore, we construct the tight-binding
  model to investigate the topological properties of CoBHT,
  demonstrating anomalous Hall conductivity driven by the intrinsic
  Berry curvature. The impact of uniaxial
  strain on the electronic and magnetic properties of CoBHT is also studied. Strain
  induces significant modifications in magnetic moments and density
  of states, particularly in the HDS. Anomalous Hall conductivity is
  enhanced under hole-doping conditions, suggesting that strain can be
  used to tailor the electronic properties of CoBHT for specific
  applications. Our findings underscore the potential of CoBHT nanosheets
  for use in next-generation electronic, optoelectronic, and catalytic
  devices with tunable properties through strain engineering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03549v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kento Nishigomi, Yu Yi, Souren Adhikary, Kazuhito Tsukagoshi, Katsunori Wakabayashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The magnon spectra of g-type altermagnet bulk CrSb</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03759v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a calculation of the magnon spectra and chiral lifetimes of altermagnons in bulk CrSb using the many-body perturbation theory. The spin-split band structure is evident in the magnon spectra. Altermagnons attain an energy of 275 meV at the K point of the Brillouin zone. Due to large spin splitting at a specific ${\bf q}$ point along the A - M direction, lifetime differences of chiral altermagnons reach approximately 20 fs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03759v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Murat Tas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of a Novel CDW Superstructure in Monolayer 1T-$VS_{2}$ at Room Temperature and its Evolution in Multilayers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03800</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03800v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spontaneous formation of charge density wave (CDW) superstructures in monolayers (MLs) of a two-dimensional (2D) crystal lattice is fundamental in understanding its complex quantum states. We report a successful top-down liquid phase exfoliation and stamp transfer process (LPESTP) to create ML VS\textsubscript{2}, undergoing a CDW transition at room temperature. Using high-resolution transmission electron microscopy (HRTEM) and electron diffraction (ED), we observed the coexistence of 1T and 2H polymorphic phases in VS\textsubscript{2} at room temperature, and only the 1T phase undergoes CDW transition. We discovered a novel incommensurate CDW superstructure ($\sqrt{7} \times \sqrt{7}$) R19.1\textsuperscript{o} in ML 1T-VS\textsubscript{2}. With an increase in the number of layers, the CDW order changes to a commensurate ($2 \times 2$) superstructure. Using angle-dependent photoelectron spectroscopy, we have shown that vanadium atoms self-intercalate as V\textsuperscript{3+} ions in multilayer VS\textsubscript{2} and are responsible for the evolution of the CDW superstructure from the incommensurate $\sqrt{7} \times \sqrt{7}$) R 19.1\textsuperscript{o} to the commensurate ($2\times2$) order. We also report the observation of novel Moir\'e superlattices in twisted bilayer 1T-VS\textsubscript{2} flakes with trapped CDW superstructure of the monolayer. Our findings provide an important platform for understanding the evolution of CDW superstructures in 1T-VS\textsubscript{2} with thickness and V self-intercalation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03800v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samanta Pal, Kaustuv Chatterjee, A. K. Raychaudhuri, Prabir Pal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantized Piezospintronic Effect in Moir\'e Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03841</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03841v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel approach for generating and controlling spin currents in an antiferromagnetic twisted honeycomb bilayer in response to an elastic deformation. Utilizing a continuum model, closely based upon the seminal Bistritzer-MacDonald model, that captures the essential physics of low-energy moir\'e bands, we calculate the spin current response to the deformation in terms of the familiar Berry phase formalism. The resulting moir\'e superlattice potential modulates the electronic band structure, leading to emergent topological phases and novel transport properties such as quantized piezo responses both for spin and charge transport. This approach allows us to tune the system across different topological regimes and to explore the piezo-spintronic responses as a function of the band topology. When inversion symmetry is broken either by a sublattice potential $V$, alignment with an hBN substrate, uniaxial strain, or structural asymmetry present in the moir\'e superlattice, the system acquires a finite Berry curvature that is opposite in the $K$ and $K'$ valleys (protected by valley time reversal symmetry). In contrast, for strain, the valley-contrasting nature of the pseudo-gauge field ensures that the quantized response is robust and proportional to the sum of the valley Chern numbers. These notable physical properties make these systems promising candidates for groundbreaking spintronic and valleytronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03841v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mario Castro, Benjam\'in Mancilla, Fabian Wolff, Alvaro S. Nunez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct observation of band structure modifications from monolayer WSe2 to Janus WSSe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04113</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04113v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Janus monolayer transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs), created by post-growth substitution of the top chalcogen layer, represent a new direction for engineering 2D crystal properties. However, their rapid ambient degradation and the difficulty of obtaining large-area monolayer samples have limited the available experimental probes, leaving their detailed electronic structure near the Fermi level largely unexplored. In this work, by performing micro-focused angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy ({\mu}-ARPES) on an identical sample transformed from monolayer WSe2 to Janus WSSe via a H2 plasma-assisted chalcogen-exchange method, we reveal the evolution of its electronic band structure. We observe ARPES signature consistent with the Rashba-type spin splitting due to broken horizontal mirror symmetry, and a significant upward shift of the highest valence band at the {\Gamma}-point by approximately 160 meV. These direct observations clarify the key electronic modifications that govern the material's properties and provide a pathway for band engineering in Janus TMDs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04113v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masato Sakano, Shunsuke Akatsuka, Takato Yamamoto, Tianyishan Sun, Dingkun Bi, Hiroto Ogura, Naoya Yamaguchi, Fumiyuki Ishii, Natsuki Mitsuishi, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Miho Kitamura, Koji Horiba, Kenichi Ozawa, Katsuaki Sugawara, Seigo Souma, Takafumi Sato, Yuta Seo, Satoru Masubuchi, Tomoki Machida, Toshiaki Kato, Kyoko Ishizaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More bridging ligands activate direct exchange: the case of anisotropic Kitaev effective magnetic interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04149</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04149v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A magnet is a collection of magnetic moments. How those interact is determined by what lies in between. In transition-metal and rare-earth magnetic compounds, the configuration of the ligands around each magnetic center and the connectivity of the ligand cages are therefore pivotal -- for example, the mutual interaction of magnetic species connected through one single ligand is qualitatively different from the case of two bridging anions. Two bridging ligands are encountered in Kitaev magnets. The latter represent one of the revelations of the 21st century in magnetism research: they feature highly anisotropic intersite couplings with seemingly counterintuitive directional dependence for adjacent pairs of magnetic sites and unique quantum spin-liquid ground states that can be described analytically. Current scenarios for the occurrence of pair-dependent magnetic interactions as proposed by Kitaev rely on $indirect$ exchange mechanisms based on intersite electron hopping. Analyzing the wavefunctions of Kitaev magnetic bonds at both single- and multi-configuration levels, we find however that $direct$, Coulomb exchange may be at least as important, in 5$d$ and 4$d$ $t_{2g}^5$, 3$d$ $t_{2g}^5e_g^2$, and even rare-earth 4$f^1$ Kitaev-Heisenberg magnets. Our study provides concept clarification in Kitaev magnetism research and the essential reference points for reliable computational investigation of how novel magnetic ground states can be engineered in Kitaev, Kitaev-Heisenberg, and Heisenberg edge-sharing systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04149v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pritam Bhattacharyya, Nikolay A. Bogdanov, Liviu Hozoi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pronounced orbital-selective electron-electron correlation and electron-phonon coupling in V2Se2O</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04657v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Orbital-selective many-body effects, in which electrons occupying different orbitals experience distinct interaction strengths, play a crucial role in correlated multiorbital materials. However, these effects usually manifest in a complex manner, obscuring their microscopic origins. Here, by combining angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy measurements with theoretical calculations, we reveal pronounced orbital selectivity in both electron-electron correlation and electron-phonon coupling in the van der Waals material V2Se2O. Electron correlation induces distinct bandwidth renormalization exclusively in the V d_xy-derived band, while the bands mainly composed of the other d orbitals remain essentially unrenormalized. Orbital-resolved analyses identify that the filling number and the bandwidth are decisive factors governing orbital-dependent correlation. Simultaneously, the d_(xz/yz)-derived band exhibits a sharp kink anomaly, arising from enhanced coupling to high-energy phonon modes dominated by oxygen vibrations. Such pronounced orbital selectivity positions V2Se2O as a rare and prototypical platform for unravelling the microscopic mechanisms of orbital-selective electron-electron and electron-phonon interactions, and offers guiding principles for the design of correlated multiorbital materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04657v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingzhe Hu, Ziyin Song, Jingwen Cheng, Gexing Qu, Zhanghuan Li, Yu Huang, Jundong Zhu, Guangyu Zhang, Dacheng Tian, Lan Chen, Zhijun Tu, Hechang Lei, Xiaoping Ma, Huaixin Yang, Zhongxu Wei, Genfu Chen, Hongming Weng, Tian Qian, Hang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-resonant spin injection of exciton-polaritons with halide perovskites at room temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04679</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04679v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Exciton-polaritons, hybrid photon-exciton quasiparticles, constitute a useful platform for the study of light-matter interaction and nonlinear photonic applications. In this work, we realize a monolithic Tamm-plasmon microcavity embedding a thin film of two-dimensional halide perovskites with a tunable polymer spacer that controls the exciton-photon detuning. Angle-resolved optical spectroscopy at room temperature reveals the lower polariton branch dispersions in the linear regime for several detunings. Under circularly polarized, non-resonant laser excitation, the spin injection of high-energy excitons and their relaxation towards the lower polariton branch demonstrates its preservation, in contrast to the bare exciton case. The spin-polarized emission survives due to the fast decay of polaritons. Our results provide promising insights into the non-resonant spin control of polaritonic devices, including chiral lasers and switches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04679v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pablo Vaquer de Nieves, Elena Sendarrubias Arias-Camis\'on, Jorge Cuadra, Maksim Lednev, Ra\'ul Gago, Luis Vi\~na, Francisco Jos\'e Garc\'ia Vidal, Johannes Feist, Ferry Prins, Carlos Ant\'on Solanas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of graphene hyperbolic pseudospheres under harsh conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04699</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04699v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate the high stability of simulated graphene hyperbolic pseudospheres under large externally imposed deformations and high temperature annealing. Hyperbolic pseudospheres are produced in a two-step Molecular Dynamics simulation process. First, carbon atoms are forced down a thin three-dimensional volume of a chosen shape. During this extrusion process the carbon atoms form a precursor to graphene that is unrealistically less stable than graphite or diamond. Then the unstable carbon structure is annealed inside the thin volume at high temperature, turning the carbon into realistic polycrystalline, curved graphene. Point defects naturally appear in numbers and places that stabilize the graphene in the desired shape, without high residual stresses. We applied this new methodology to the creation of graphene hyperbolic pseudosphere surfaces, which reproduce analogs to some aspects of classical or quantum gravity. The free edges of the pseudosphere cause bending of the graphene. When these free edges are removed from the simulations by attaching periodic flat graphene sheets to the pseudosphere edges, the carbon atoms assume positions just some tenths of \r{A} from the mathematical hyperbolic pseudosphere surface. In demanding tests of their stability, the hyperbolic pseudospheres proved stable against $20^\circ$ shearing or $20\%$ elongation and then being released, which eventually raised their temperatures by $\sim 300 \ \text{K}$. Our methodology is relatively easy to use and offers a practical way to create simulated curved graphene surfaces of almost any shape. It allows for thorough testing in advance of the stability of graphene shapes that are to be produced experimentally.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04699v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. P. C. Klaver, R. Gabbrielli, V. Tynianska, A. Iorio, D. Legut</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlative Analysis of Iron-Driven Structural, Optical, and Magnetic Properties in Natural Biotite Crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04752</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04752v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Biotite crystals are phyllosilicate trioctahedral micas with the general chemical formula K(Mg,Fe)3AlSi3O10(OH)2 that form a solid-solution series with iron-poor phlogopite and iron-rich annite endmembers. With a wide band gap energy and a layered structure with free surface charges, biotite nanosheets can be readily obtained by cleavage methods and used as dielectrics in nanodevice fabrication for the next generation of electronics and energy harvesting. Here, a comprehensive study of biotite samples with different iron concentrations and oxidation states is presented. Structural, optical, magneto-optical, and magnetic characterizations were performed using several experimental techniques, including state-of-the-art synchrotron-based techniques, to correlate the iron chemistry (content and oxidation state) with the macroscopic properties of both minerals. The study reveals a nanoscale-homogeneous Fe distribution via synchrotron X-ray fluorescence mapping, defect-mediated optical transitions modulated by Fe3+/Fe2+ ratios, and temperature-dependent magnetic transitions from paramagnetism to competing ferro-/antiferromagnetic interactions. Furthermore, the use of these biotite crystals as substrates for ultrathin heterostructures incorporating monolayer (ML) MoSe2 is explored by magneto photoluminescence at cryogenic temperatures. The results show that the presence of iron impurities in different oxidation states significantly impacts the valley properties for ML-MoSe2. Overall, these findings offer a comprehensive interpretation of the physical properties of bulk biotites in a correlative approach, serving as a robust reference for future studies aiming to explore biotites in their ultrathin form.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04752v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raphaela de Oliveira, Yara Galv\~ao Gobato, Ronei C. de Oliveira, Jos\'e R. de Toledo, Ver\^onica C. Teixeira, Angelo Malachias, Cesar R. Rabahi, Chunwei Hsu, Adilson J. A. de Oliveira, Herre. S. J. van der Zant, Ingrid D. Barcelos, Alisson R. Cadore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite temperature dopant-induced spin reorganization explored via tensor networks in the two-dimensional $t$-$J$ model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04756v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Doped Mott insulators host intertwined spin-charge phenomena that evolve with temperature and can culminate in stripe order or superconductivity at low temperatures. The two-dimensional $t$-$J$ model captures this interplay yet finite-temperature, infinite-size calculations remain difficult. Using purification represented by a tensor network - an infinite projected entangled-pair state (iPEPS) ansatz - we simulate the $t$-$J$ model at finite temperature directly in the thermodynamic limit, reaching temperatures down to one tenth of the hopping rate and hole concentrations up to one quarter of the lattice sites. Beyond specific heat, uniform susceptibility, and compressibility, we introduce dopant-conditioned multi-point correlators that map how holes reshape local exchange. Nearest-neighbor hole pairs produce a strong cooperative response that reinforces antiferromagnetism on the adjacent parallel bonds, and single holes weaken nearby antiferromagnetic bonds; d-wave pairing correlations remain short-ranged over the same window. These results provide experiment-compatible thermodynamic-limit benchmarks and establish dopant-conditioned correlators as incisive probes of short-range spin-texture reorganization at finite temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04756v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yintati Zhang, Aritra Sinha, Marek M. Rams, Jacek Dziarmaga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Refined spin Hamiltonian on the Cairo pentagonal lattice of Bi2Fe4O9</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04793</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04793v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The frustrated magnet Bi2Fe4O9 has been reported to exhibit complex spin dynamics coexisting with conventional spin wave excitations. The magnetic Fe3+ (S = 5/2) ions are arranged into a distorted two-dimensional Cairo pentagonal lattice with weak couplings between the layers, developing long-ranged non-collinear antiferromagnetic order below 245 K. In order to enable studies and modelling of the complex dynamics close to TN, we have reexamined the magnetic excitations across the complete energy scale (0 &lt; E &lt; 90 meV) at 10 K. We discover two distinct gaps, which can be explained by introducing, respectively, easy axis and easy plane anisotropy on the two unequivalent Fe-sites. We develop a refined spin Hamiltonian that accurately accounts for the dispersion of essentially all spin-wave branches across the full spectral range, except around 40 meV, where a splitting and dispersion are observed. We propose that this mode is derived from phonon hybridization. Polarisation analysis shows that the system has magnetic anisotropic fluctuations, consistent with our model. A continuum of scattering is observed above the spin wave branches and is found to principally be explained by an instrumental resolution effect. The full experimental mapping of the excitation spectrum and the refined spin Hamiltonian provides a foundation for future quantitative studies of spin waves coexisting with unconventional magnetic fluctuations in this frustrated magnet found at higher temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04793v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emma Y. Lenander, Frida B. Nielsen, Jakob Lass, Ursula B. Hansen, Kristine M. L. Krighaar, Asbj{\o}rn Preuss, Tobias Weber, Mechthild Enderle, Henrik Jacobsen, Uwe Stuhr, Ryoichi Kajimoto, Mitsutaka Nakamura, Manfred Burianek, Andrea Kirsch, Henrik M. R{\o}nnow, Kim Lefmann, Pascale P. Deen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Systematic cRPA study of two-dimensional MA$_2$Z$_4$ materials: From unconventional screening to correlation-driven instabilities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04804</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04804v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding the interplay between screening, electronic correlations, and collective excitations is essential for the design of two-dimensional quantum materials. Here, we present a comprehensive first-principles study of more than 60 MA$_2$Z$_4$ monolayers, encompassing semiconducting, metallic, cold-metallic, magnetic, and topological phases. Using the constrained random phase approximation (cRPA), we compute material-specific effective Coulomb interaction parameters $U$, $U'$, and $J$, including their spatial dependence across distinct correlated subspaces defined by local coordination and crystal symmetry. In semiconducting compounds, long-range nonlocal interactions persist, revealing unconventional screening and suggesting strong excitonic effects beyond simple dielectric models. In cold-metallic systems, sizable long-range Coulomb interactions remain despite the presence of free carriers, highlighting their atypical metallic screening. Among 33-valence-electron compounds, we find $U_{\mathrm{eff}} &gt; W$ in the $\beta_2$ phase, indicating proximity to charge-density-wave or Mott instabilities. Several V- and Nb-based systems exhibit intermediate-to-strong correlation strength, with $U/W &gt; 1 $ in multiple cases. Using cRPA-derived Stoner parameters, we identify magnetic instabilities in various V-, Nb-, Cr-, and Mn-based compounds. Finally, selected cold-metallic systems display plasmon dispersions that deviate from the conventional $\sqrt{q}$ behavior, revealing nearly non-dispersive low-energy modes. These results position MA$_2$Z$_4$ monolayers as a versatile platform for investigating correlation-driven instabilities and emergent collective behavior in two dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04804v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Bagherpour, Y. Yekta, H. Hadipour, E. Sasioglu, A. Khademi, S. A. Jafari, I. Mertig, S. Lounis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental observation of frustration and large anomalous Nernst effect in metallo-molecular spin Kondo lattice interfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04824v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Frustration in Kondo spin lattice systems has led to the emergence of both spin liquids that could be chiral and strange metals that deviate from Fermi liquid behaviour when not in their antiferromagnetic ground state. In two dimensions (2D), where deviations from bulk systems are expected, Kondo spin lattice emergence have recently been observed in van der Waals systems. Metallo-molecular interfaces of supramolecular lattices have also been suggested as an alternative 2D Kondo spin lattice system where a single-ion Kondo effect as well as an inter spin-site Ruderman-Kittel-Kasuya-Yosida (RKKY) coupling has been demonstrated in scanning tunnelling spectroscopy (STS) studies. Here, going beyond ultrahigh vacuum STS studies on metallo-molecular interfaces, we report a metastable frustrated antiferromagnetic state, with ultra-high spin freezing temperatures (T_f), ranging from 240 K to 300 K on the interfaces of highly textured Pt(111) and Pt(111)/Co films with organic molecules grown in ultra-high vacuum 10^(-10) mbar. In the vicinity of the spin-freezing transition, we measure a large anomalous Nernst effect (ANE) in the Pt/Co/molecular heterostructure, with a Nernst coefficient of at least 3 microV per K. Our results suggest a 2D metallo-molecular Kondo spin lattice with high temperature quantum correlations where an ANE beyond magnetisation is manifested around room temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04824v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Servet Ozdemir, Matthew Rogers, Conor J. McCluskey, Raymond G. McQuaid, Mannan Ali, Gavin Burnell, Joseph Barker, B J Hickey, Oscar Cespedes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational optimization of projected entangled-pair states on the triangular lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04907v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a general corner transfer matrix renormalization group algorithm tailored to projected entangled-pair states on the triangular lattice. By integrating automatic differentiation, our approach enables direct variational energy minimization on this lattice geometry. In contrast to conventional approaches that map the triangular lattice onto a square lattice with diagonal next-nearest-neighbour interactions, our native formulation yields improved variational results at the same bond dimension. This improvement stems from a more faithful and physically informed representation of the entanglement structure in the tensor network and an increased number of variational parameters. We apply our method to the antiferromagnetic nearest-neighbour Heisenberg model on the triangular and kagome lattice, and benchmark our results against previous numerical studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04907v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Naumann, Jens Eisert, Philipp Schmoll</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The two conduction bands of monolayer CrSBr on Au</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04925</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04925v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report the electronic structure of monolayer CrSBr exfoliated onto mica template-stripped gold substrates. Angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy reveals charge transfer from the substrate, populating the conduction band of monolayer CrSBr, accompanied by a pronounced reduction in the quasiparticle band gap. Furthermore, we observe two separate conduction bands that exhibit a splitting at the X point. This indicates a breaking of glide-mirror symmetry, which in the bulk or in a free-standing monolayer protects the band degeneracies at the Brillouin zone boundary. Our results demonstrate that ultraflat gold substrates do more than modify carrier densities and screening: they can lift symmetry-protected degeneracies and thus fundamentally reshape the band topology of 2D materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04925v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yogal Prasad Ghimirey, Laxman Nagireddy, Cephise Cacho, Neil R. Wilson, Matthew D. Watson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controlling an altermagnetic spin density wave in the kagome magnet CsCr3Sb5</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05018</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05018v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The interplay of charge and spin orders lies at the heart of correlated electron physics and plays a critical role in the emergence of unconventional quantum phases. Kagome magnets provide a particularly promising platform to investigate these phenomena, owing to their geometrically frustrated lattice structure. However, resolving spin and charge orders microscopically and establishing ways to control them remain fundamental challenges. Here, we demonstrate magnetic field control of an altermagnetic spin density wave order intertwined with charge density wave order in kagome magnet CsCr3Sb5. Scanning tunneling microscopy down to deep cryogenic temperature of 50 mK reveals two previously unreported charge density wave orders in the Sb surface. Density functional theory confirms that one of them is coupled to a spin density wave with an altermagnetic ground state. The charge density waves can be tuned in both amplitude and phase by an external magnetic field, reflected in domain switching and stripe sliding of the charge density wave. Our findings deepen the understanding of symmetry-breaking in kagome systems, providing a tunable platform to explore the interplay of electronic correlation with emergent quantum magnetism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05018v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zihao Huang, Chenchao Xu, Yande Que, Yi Liu, Ranjith Shivajirao, Zheng Jue Tong, Amit Kumar, Chao Cao, Guang-Han Cao, Hong-Jun Gao, Bent Weber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum-critical transport in marginal Fermi-liquids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.11982</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.11982v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We use the Kubo response functions to calculate the electrical and thermal conductivity and Seebeck coefficient at low temperatures and frequencies in the quantum-critical region for fermions on a lattice. The theory uses scattering of the fermions with the previously derived collective fluctuations due to topological defects of the quantum xy model coupled to fermions. The microscopic model is applicable to the fluctuations of the loop-current order in cuprates as well as to a class of quasi-two dimensional heavy-fermion and other metallic antiferromagnets, and proposed recently also for the possible loop-current order in Moir\'{e} twisted bi-layer graphene and bi-layer WSe$_2$. All these metals have a linear in temperature electrical resistivity in the quantum-critical region of their phase diagrams, often termed ``Planckian" resistivity. The solution of the Kubo equation for transport shows that vertex renormalizations to the external fields, beside those due to Aslamazov-Larkin (A-L) processes, are absent. A-L appears as an Umklapp scattering matrix, which gives a temperature independent multiplicative factor for the electrical resistivity but does not affect the thermal conductivity. We also show that the mass renormalization which gives a logarithmic enhancement of the marginal Fermi-liquid specific heat does not appear in the electrical resistivity and, more remarkably, in the thermal conductivity. On the other hand the mass renormalization $\propto \ln \omega_c/T$ appears in the Seebeck coefficient. We also discuss in detail the conservation laws which play a crucial role in all transport properties. We calculate exactly, the numerical coefficients of the transport properties for a circular Fermi-surface. The leading temperature dependences is shown to remain the same for a general Fermi-surface, but it is too messy to calculate the numerical coefficient.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.11982v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hideaki Maebashi, Chandra M. Varma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fingerprints of Mott and Slater gaps in the core-level photoemission spectra of antiferromagnetic iridates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12646</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12646v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present Ir $4f$ core-level hard-x-ray photoemission spectroscopy (HAXPES) experiments conducted across antiferromagnetic (AFM) ordering transition in Ruddlesden-Popper iridates Sr$_2$IrO$_4$ and Sr$_3$Ir$_2$O$_7$. The Ir $4f$ spectra exhibit distinct changes between the AFM and paramagnetic (PM) phases, with the spectral difference $I_\text{PM}-I_\text{AFM}$ showing a contrasting behavior in the two compounds. By employing computational simulations using the local-density approximation combined with the dynamical mean-field theory method, we elucidate that $I_\text{PM}-I_\text{AFM}$ primary reflects the Slater or Mott-Hubbard character of the AFM insulating state rather than material specific details. This sensitivity to fine low-energy electronic structure arises from the dependence of charge-transfer responses to the sudden creation of a localized core hole on both metal-insulator transitions and long-range AFM ordering. Our result broadens the applications of core-level HAXPES as a tool for characterization of electronic structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12646v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.195114</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>K. Nakagawa, A. Hariki, T. Okauchi, H. Fujiwara, K. -H. Ahn, Y. Murakami, S. Hamamoto, Y. Kanai-Nakata, T. Kadono, A. Higashiya, K. Tamasaku, M. Yabashi, T. Ishikawa, A. Sekiyama, S. Imada, J. Kune\v{s}, K. Takase, A. Yamasaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic band structure from quasiparticle interference and Landau quantization in WTe$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.13837</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.13837v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: WTe$_2$ stands out as a semimetal presenting Fermi level quantum oscillations in most measured quantities under magnetic fields. However, the electronic band structure above and below the Fermi level has not been explored completely. Here we study the electronic band structure of WTe$_2$ by quasiparticle interference with Scanning Tunneling Microscopy (STM) and observe, with the support of Density Functional Theory (DFT), the electron and hole bands around the Fermi level. We also report on the observation of Landau quantization in atomically resolved measurements and discuss the possible connection with band structure calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.13837v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/7xnv-8wvt</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 165401 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Raquel S\'anchez-Barquilla, Francisco Mart\'in Vega, Alberto M. Ruiz, Na Hyun Jo, Edwin Herrera, Jos\'e J. Baldov\'i, Masayuki Ochi, Ryotaro Arita, Sergey L. Bud'ko, Paul C. Canfield, Isabel Guillam\'on, Hermann Suderow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-equilibrium transport and phonon branch-resolved size effects based on a multi-temperature kinetic model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02411</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02411v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Non-equilibrium transport and phonon branch-resolved size effects in single-layer graphene materials are studied under a multi-temperature kinetic model, which is developed for capturing the branch-dependent electron-phonon coupling. Compared with typical macroscopic multi-temperature models, the assumption of diffusive phonon transport is abandoned in this model and replaced by the free migration and scattering of particles. The phonon branch- and size-dependent effective thermal conductivity is predicted in nanosized graphene as well as the temperature slips near the boundaries. Compared with other phonon branches, the ZA branch contributes the most to thermal conduction regardless of system sizes. Furthermore, in nanosized homogeneous graphene with a hotspot at the center, the branch-dependent thermal conductivity increases from the inside to the outside even if the system size is fixed. The thermal conductivity of ZA branch is even higher than the lattice thermal conductivity when the system size is hundreds of nanometers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02411v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chuang Zhang, Houssem Rezgui, Meng Lian, Hong Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interaction effects on electronic Floquet spectra: Excitonic effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07428v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Floquet engineering of electronic states by light is a central topic in modern experiments. However, the impact of many-body interactions on the single-electron properties remains unclear in this non-equilibrium situation. We propose that interaction effects could be reasonably understood by performing perturbative expansion in both the pump field and the electron-electron interaction when computing physical quantities. As an example, we apply this approach to semiconductors and show analytically that excitonic effects, i.e., effects of electron-hole interaction, lead to dramatic corrections to the single-electron Floquet spectra even when the excitons are only virtually excited by the pump light. We compute these effects in phosphorene and monolayer MoS$_2$ for time- and angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy and ultrafast optical experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07428v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/b1pl-nf2r</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, L161106(2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Teng Xiao, Tsan Huang, Changhua Bao, Zhiyuan Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Giant orbital magnetization in two-dimensional materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18563</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18563v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Orbital magnetization typically plays a minor role in compounds where the magnetic properties are governed by transition metal elements. However, in some cases, the orbital magnetization may be fully unquenched, which can have dramatic consequences for magnetic anisotropy and various magnetic response properties. In the present work, we start by summarizing how unquenched orbital moments arise from particular combinations of crystal field splitting and orbital filling. We exemplify this for the cases of two-dimensional (2D) VI$_3$ and FePS$_3$, and show that Hubbard corrections as well as self-consistent spin-orbit coupling are crucial ingredients for predicting correct orbital moments from first principles calculations. We then search the Computational 2D Materials Database (C2DB) for monolayers having tetrahedral or octahedral crystal field splitting of transition metal $d$-states and orbital occupancy that is expected to lead to large orbital moments. We identify 112 monolayers with octahedral crystal field splitting and 62 monolayers with tetrahedral crystal field splitting and for materials with partially filled $t_{2g}$ bands, we verify that inclusion of Hubbard corrections as well as self-consistent spin-orbit coupling typically increases the magnitude of predicted orbital moments by an order of magnitude.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18563v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Ovesen, Thomas Olsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing thermoelectric efficiency of multilayer graphene by nanomeshing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03436v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Nanostructuring materials at small scales enables control over their physical properties, revealing behaviors not observed at larger dimensions. This strategy is particularly effective in two-dimensional (2D) materials, where surface effects dominate, and has been applied in the thermoelectric field. Here, we use multilayer graphene (4-6 nm thick) as a test platform to study the effect of nanomeshing on its thermoelectric properties. The nanomesh consists of a hexagonal array of holes, with a measured diameter and neck-width of ~360 nm and ~160 nm, respectively. The multilayer graphene is integrated into field-effect transistor-like devices supported by hexagonal boron nitride (hBN), allowing simultaneous electric and thermoelectric measurements, with nanomeshing applied to only part of the material. We use modulated thermoreflectance to investigate thermal transport in equivalent nanomeshed and pristine graphene flakes, extracting key parameters that affect thermoelectric performance. The nanomesh geometry suppresses thermal transport without significantly impacting charge transport, highlighting the different scattering lengths of phonons and electrons while enhancing the thermopower response. We observe a twofold improvement in the device power factor, PF = S^2 sigma (with S the Seebeck coefficient and sigma the electrical conductivity), at room temperature, along with a nearly threefold reduction in thermal conductivity k. The results show that nanomeshing can significantly improve the thermoelectric performance of multilayer graphene, paving the way for novel energy conversion strategies using 2D materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03436v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mehrdad Rahimi, Nunzia Lubertino, Roberto Bellelli, Linsai Chen, Fran\c{c}ois Mallet, Philippe Lafarge, Cl\'ement Barraud, PAscal Marti, Julien Chaste, Dani\`ele Fournier, Maria Luisa Della Rocca</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal relations between thermoelectrics and noise in mesoscopic transport across a tunnel junction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.05413v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a unified theory of weakly probed differential observables for currents and noise in transport experiments. Our findings uncover a set of universal transport relations between thermoelectric and noise properties of a system probed through a tunnel contact, with the Wiedemann-Franz law being just one example of such universality between charge and heat currents. We apply this theory to various quantum dot systems, including multichannel Kondo, quantum Hall and Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev quantum dots, and demonstrate that each of the microscopic theories is characterized by a set of universal relations connecting conductance and thermoelectrics with noise. Violations of these relations indicate additional energy scales emerging in a system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.05413v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei I. Pavlov, Mikhail N. Kiselev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Boundary-Modes Localization from Quantum Metric Length</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05114v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The presence of localized boundary modes is an unambiguous hallmark of topological quantum matter. While these modes are typically protected by topological invariants such as the Chern number, here we demonstrate that the {\it quantum metric length} (QML), a quantity inherent in multi-band topological systems, governs the spatial extent of flat-band topological boundary modes. We introduce a framework for constructing topological flat bands from degenerate manifolds with large quantum metric and find that the boundary modes exhibit dual phases of spatial behaviors: a conventional oscillatory decay arising from bare band dispersion, followed by another exponential decay controlled by quantum geometry. Crucially, the QML, derived from the quantum metric of the degenerate manifolds, sets a lower bound on the spatial spread of boundary states in the flat-band limit. Applying our framework to concrete models, we validate the universal role of the QML in shaping the long-range behavior of topological boundary modes. Furthermore, by tuning the QML, we unveil extraordinary non-local transport phenomena, including QML-shaped quantum Hall plateaus and anomalous Fraunhofer patterns. Our theoretical framework paves the way for engineering boundary-modes localization in topological flat-band systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05114v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xing-Lei Ma, Jin-Xin Hu, K. T. Law</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-phonon coupling and isotope-related pseudo-molecule vibrations in layered Cr$_2$Ge$_2$Te$_6$ ferromagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01881</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.01881v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The vibrational structure of chromium germanium telluride (Cr$_2$Ge$_2$Te$_6$, CGT) is investigated and a strong spin-phonon coupling is revealed. The measured high-resolution Raman scattering (RS) spectra are composed of the 10 Raman-active modes: 5A$_\textrm{g}$ and 5E$_\textrm{g}$, predicted by calculation using the density functional theory and identified using polarization-resolved RS measurements. We also studied the effect of temperature on the RS spectra of CGT from 5~K to 300~K. A strong magneto-phonon coupling in CGT is revealed at temperatures of about 150~K and 60~K, which are associated with the appearance of the local magnetic order in the material and the transition to the complete ferromagnetic phase, respectively. Moreover, a unique shape of the A$_g^5$ mode composed of a set of very narrow Raman peaks is simulated using a model that takes into account vibrations of Ge-Ge pseudo-molecules for various Ge isotopes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.01881v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grzegorz Krasucki, Katarzyna Olkowska-Pucko, Tomasz Wo\'zniak, Mihai I. Sturza, Holger Kohlmann, Adam Babi\'nski, Maciej R. Molas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-dependent orbital selectivity and partial Kondo-screening in magnetically ordered Hund's metal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02593v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Hund's metallicity in 3$d$ transition metal oxides constitutes a rare class of compounds, since they have been long understood considering the dominance of Hubbard $U$. $\mathrm{LiV_2O_4}$\&amp; $\mathrm{Sr_2CoO_4}$ belong to this rare class of metals; among them, $\mathrm{LiV_2O_4}$ has been the subject of extensive investigations for its unconventional heavy-fermion behavior, while studies on $\mathrm{Sr_2CoO_4}$ remain limited despite its anomalous ferromagnetic ground state. In this study, we report an unusual spin-orbital selective localization in $\mathrm{Sr_2CoO_4}$ leading to a sharp Kondo resonance at $\sim$70 K in the spin-$up$ channel of orbitals of $t_{2g}$ symmetry using a combination of Density functional theory and Dynamical mean field theory (DFT+DMFT) calculations. Correspondingly, an appreciable reduction in the magnetization below $T$=100 K further suggests partial Kondo screening of local moments active at low temperatures, explaining its effective spin magnetization state and upturn in its resistivity observed in experimental reports. We note a significant effect of Hund's induced spin-orbital selective incoherence in dictating the temperature evolution of its macroscopic observables e.g. spin-spin correlation function and effective local moment. Our results reveal a potentially distinct/new form of spin-dependent selectivity induced via Hund's coupling in addition to the conventional orbital-selectivity in the Hund's metals, as a plausible key mechanism in stabilizing their long-range magnetic order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02593v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shivani Bhardwaj, Sudhir K. Pandey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropic convergence and the linearized limit for the Boltzmann equation with external force</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1612.05096</link>
      <description>arXiv:1612.05096v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper extends the results regarding entropic convergence and the strong linearized limit for the Boltzmann equation (without external force) in [C. David Levermore. Entropic convergence and the linearized limit for the Boltzmann equation. Communications in Partial Differential Equations, 18(7-8):1231--1248, 1993] to the case of the Boltzmann equation with external force. Our starting point is the Boltzmann equation with an external force introduced in [Diogo Ars\'enio and Laure Saint-Raymond. From the Vlasov--Maxwell--Boltzmann System to Incompressible Viscous Electro-magneto-hydrodynamics, EMS Press, 2019], we then find new conditions on the force and rigorously prove the maintaining result by Levermore. More specifically, any sequence of DiPerna-Lions renormalized solutions of the Boltzmann equation with external force are shown to have fluctuations (about the global Maxwellian equilibrium $M$) that converge entropically (and hence strongly in $L^1$) to the solution of the linearized Boltzmann equation for any positive time, given that its initial fluctuations about $M$ converge entropically to the provided $L^2$ initial data of the linearized equation, where the force can be physically significant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1612.05096v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tina Mai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglemons: Cross-platform protected qubits from entanglement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13019</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.13019v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A crucial ingredient for scalable fault-tolerant quantum computing is the construction of logical qubits with low error rates and intrinsic noise protection. We propose a cross-platform construction for such hardware-level noise-protection in which the qubits are protected from depolarizing (relaxation) and dephasing errors induced by local noise. These logical qubits arise from the entanglement between two internal degrees of freedom, hence - entanglemons. Our construction is based on the emergence of collective degrees of freedom from a generalized coherent state construction, similar in spirit to spin coherent states, of a set of such internally entangled units. These degrees of freedom, for a finite number of units, parametrize the quantized version of complex projective space $\mathbb{C}$P(3). The noise protection of the entanglemon qubit is then a consequence of a weakly coupled emergent degree of freedom arising due to the non-linear geometry of complex projective space. We present two simple models for entanglemons which are platform agnostic, provide varying levels of protection and in which the qubit basis states are the two lowest energy states with a higher energy gap to other states. We end by commenting on how entanglemons could be realized in platforms ranging from superconducting circuits and trapped ion platforms to possibly also quantum Hall skyrmions in graphene and quantum dots in semiconductors. The inherent noise protection in our models combined with the platform agnosticism highlights the potential of encoding information in additional weakly coupled emergent degrees of freedom arising in non-linear geometrical spaces and curved phase spaces, thereby proposing a different route to achieve scalable fault-tolerance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.13019v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/qjhp-8x6z</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 155111 (2025); Editors' suggestion</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nilotpal Chakraborty, Roderich Moessner, Benoit Doucot</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
