<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 01:35:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of Anomalous Thermal Hall Effect in a Kagome Superconductor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10630</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.10630v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Broken time-reversal symmetry (TRS) in superconductors can induce not only spontaneous magnetization by the finite angular momentum of Cooper pairs, but also anomalous thermal Hall effects (ATHEs), whose detection has been extremely challenging. Here we report the successful observation of an ATHE developing below the superconducting transition temperature at zero magnetic field in the kagome-lattice superconductor CsV3Sb5. This finding is verified by the absence of a signal in a conventional type-II superconductor using the same setup and by ruling out the trapped-vortex effects through micro-Hall array measurements. Remarkably, both the temperature dependence and the magnitude of the observed anomalous thermal Hall conductivity are quite different from those expected for the quantized thermal edge current of an intrinsic ATHE, but consistent with extrinsic impurity-induced ATHEs in chiral superconductivity. Our study of ATHE offers an alternative approach to probe TRS breaking in the superconducting states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.10630v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroki Yoshida, Hikaru Takeda, Jian Yan, Yui Kanemori, Brenden R. Ortiz, Yuzki M. Oey, Stephen D. Wilson, Marcin Konczykowski, Kota Ishihara, Takasada Shibauchi, Minoru Yamashita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Design and Optimization of Spin Dynamics in Ge Quantum Dots: g-Factor Modulation, Dephasing Sweet Spots, and Phonon-Induced Relaxation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10731</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.10731v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate modeling of spin dynamics in hole-based quantum dot qubits demands high-fidelity simulations that capture realistic device geometries, material interfaces, and self-consistent electrostatics. Here, we present a comprehensive three-dimensional study of gate-defined quantum dot hole spin qubits in strained Si$_{0.2}$Ge$_{0.8}$/Ge heterostructures. In contrast to prior work relying on idealized confinement or decoupled Poisson-Schr\"odinger treatments, our approach combines self-consistent electrostatics with a four-band Luttinger-Kohn Hamiltonian to resolve spin-orbit interactions, wavefunction asymmetries, and g-tensor anisotropies in realistic device structures. We quantify the impact of device size and gate bias on wavefunction localization, electric-field-induced g-factor modulation, and identify "sweet spots" in vertical electric field where g-factor sensitivity to charge noise is minimized, enhancing spin dephasing times. Spin relaxation due to phonon coupling is also modeled, revealing size-dependent T1 behavior consistent with strong Rashba-type spin-orbit coupling and a magnetic-field scaling near $B^{-8}$. This work establishes a predictive modeling framework for optimizing spin coherence in planar Ge quantum dots and provides quantitative design guidance for scalable, electrically controlled hole spin qubits in group-IV semiconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.10731v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ngoc Duong, Daryoosh Vashaee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct Observation of the Lindhard Continuum using Resonant Inelastic X-ray Scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10741</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.10741v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding the excitations of quantum materials is essential for unraveling how their microscopic constituents interact. Among these, particle-hole excitations form a particularly important class, as they govern fundamental processes such as screening, dissipation, and transport. In metals, the continuum of electron-hole excitations is described by the Lindhard function. Although central to the theory of Fermi liquids, the corresponding Lindhard continuum has remained experimentally elusive. Here, we report its direct observation in the weakly correlated metal MgB$_{2}$ using ultra-soft resonant inelastic X-ray scattering (RIXS). We resolve a linearly dispersing excitation with velocity comparable to the Fermi velocity and find quantitative agreement with simulations of the non-interacting charge susceptibility. A detailed analysis and decomposition of the simulations reveal the intra-band origin of this low-energy excitation, confirming it as the Lindhard continuum. Our results establish ultra-soft RIXS as a momentum-resolved probe of the fermiology in metals and call for deeper investigations of continuum features in RIXS and related spectroscopy of other materials beyond MgB$_{2}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.10741v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eder G. Lomeli, Sarbajaya Kundu, Yi-De Chuang, Zengqing Zhuo, Ke Chen, Xiaoxing Xi, Lingjia Shen, Georgi L. Dakovski, Stephan Gepr\"ags, Brian Moritz, Thomas P. Devereaux, John Vinson, Matthias F. Kling, Edwin W. Huang, Daniel Jost</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gaussian fixed lines of $S=1/2$ XXZ chain with next-nearest neighbor interaction and $sl_2$ loop algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10808</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.10808v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spin systems are important to understand various physical properties in quantum many-body systems. We numerically study the Gaussian fixed lines (GFLs) of the $S=1/2$ XXZ chain with next-nearest neighbor (NNN) interaction in the XY phase. The GFLs are the set of points where the coefficient of the umklapp scattering vanishes. We show that the GFLs pass through the ``special points'', which are defined as the points where the $sl_2$ loop algebra symmetry governs in low-energy physics. In addition, we have discussed the Tomonaga-Luttinger parameter K, and the metamagnetism influences the shape of the GFLs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.10808v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daiki Yomatsu, Kiyohide Nomura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlated interlayer quantum Hall state in alternating twisted trilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10930</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.10930v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Trilayer graphene allows systematic control of its electronic structure through stacking sequence and twist geometry, providing a versatile platform for correlated states. Here we report magnetotransport in alternating twisted trilayer graphene with a twist angle of about 5$^{\circ}$. The data reveal an electron-hole asymmetry that can be captured by introducing layer-dependent potential shifts. At charge neutrality ($\nu_{\mathrm{tot}}=0$), three low-resistance states appear, which Hartree-Fock mean-field analysis attributes to emerging spin-resolved helical edge modes similar to those of quantum spin Hall insulators. At $\nu_{\mathrm{tot}}=-1$, we also observe suppressed resistance when the middle and bottom layers are each half filled while the top layer remains inert at $\nu=-2$, consistent with an interlayer excitonic quantum Hall state. These results demonstrate correlated interlayer quantum Hall phases in alternating twisted trilayer graphene, including spin-resolved edge transport and excitonic order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.10930v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dohun Kim, Gyeoul Lee, Nicolas Leconte, Seyoung Jin, Takashi Taniguchi, Kenji Watanabe, Jeil Jung, Gil Young Cho, Youngwook Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large Chern-Number Quantum Anomalous Hall Effect from Canted Antiferromagnetic Order in $d$-Electron System on Kagome Lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10976</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.10976v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Electrons of $d$-symmetry in a kagome lattice are considered which interact with non-collinear antiferromagnetic order in the absence of spin-orbit coupling. The non-collinearity of spin texture gives rise to non-relativistic spin splitting and the associated intrinsic Berry curvature. The integral of the latter over the Brillouin zone becomes nontrivial for non-coplanar (canted) non-collinear spin order even without explicit on-site or transfer spin-orbit coupling. That gives rise to a nonzero (scalar) spin chirality, and a record value for the Chern number of $C=\pm 5$ can appear when the Fermi level is in an appropriate gap for isotropic electron hopping integrals, or nearly isotropic ones. The numerical results for this topological quantum anomalous Hall effect are supported by an analytical formula. It is possible to split the $C=\pm 5$ plateau into different possible nonzero values for the Chern number by varying the onsite energies. The topological phase transitions between Hall plateaus can be driven by flipping the Zeeman-like exchange field or controlling the onsite energies, alluding to the potential of this system to quantum information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.10976v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Waquar Ahmed, Steffen Schaeffer, Pierre Lombardo, Roland Hayn, Imam Makhfudz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay between Hubbard interaction and charge transfer energy in three-orbital Emery model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11028</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11028v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We use the numerically unbiased determinant quantum Monte Carlo (DQMC) method to systematically investigate the three-orbital Emery model in the normal state in a wide range of local interactions, charge transfer energy, and doping levels. We focus on the influence of the onsite Hubbard $U_{dd}$ and charge transfer energy scale $\epsilon_p$ on the electronic properties via the orbital occupancies, local moments, spin correlations, and spectral properties. Rich features of the orbital-resolved local and momentum-dependent spectra are revealed to associate with the possible Zhang-Rice singlet (ZRS) breakdown reflected by the peak splitting near the Fermi level in the heavily overdoped regime. Moreover, the pseudogap features at small charge transfer energy scale (relevant to cuprates) are shown to diminish at larger $\epsilon_p$, which implies the weakening or absence of the pseudogap in the infinite-layer nickelates. Besides, an optimal value of $\epsilon_p$ is identified for maximizing the antiferromagnetic (AFM) spin correlations. Our large-scale simulations provide new insights on the well-established Emery model, particularly in the regime of heavily overdoped and/or large charge transfer energy scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11028v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan Peng, Mi Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological excitonic insulators in electron bilayers modulated by twisted hBN</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11041</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11041v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Equilibrium interlayer exciton condensation is common in bilayer quantum Hall systems and is characterized by spontaneous phase coherence between isolated layers. It has been predicted that similar physics can occur in the absence of a magnetic field in some two-dimensional semiconductor bilayers. In this work we consider the case of two transition metal dichalcogenide (TMD) monolayers separated by a twisted hexagonal boron nitride (hBN) bilayer or multilayer. The hBN layers suppress tunneling between the TMD layers so that phase coherence is spontaneous when it is present. When twisted, the hBN layers also form a ferroelectric moir\'e pattern that applies opposite triangular-lattice modulation potentials to the two TMD layers. We show via mean-field theory that at total hole filling per moir\'e unit cell $\nu=1$, this geometry can favor a chiral p-wave exciton condensate state in which the quantum anomalous Hall effect coexists with counter-flow superfluidity. We present a mean-field phase diagram for TMD hole bilayers modulated by twisted hBN, discuss the conditions needed for the realization of the p-wave condensate state, and propose experiments that could confirm its presence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11041v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yongxin Zeng, Allan H. MacDonald, Nemin Wei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antiferromagnetic ordering and critical behavior induced giant magnetocaloric effect in distorted kagome lattice Gd$_3$BWO$_9$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11091</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11091v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We synthesize the high-quality Gd$_3$BWO$_9$ single crystal and investigate its lowtemperature magnetic and thermodynamic properties. Below $T\rm_{N}$ = 1.08 K, the anisotropic behavior of magnetic susceptibilities reveals that the Gd$^{3+}$ moments exhibit the dominant antiferromagnetic coupling along the $c$-axis, while displaying a ferromagnetic arrangement in kagome plane. With pronounced magnetic frustration, in adiabatic demagnetization refrigeration experiments starting from initial conditions of 9 T and 2 K, Gd$_3$BWO$_9$ polycrystal reaches a minimum temperature of 0.151 K, significantly lower than its $T\rm_{N}$. Due to the high density of Gd$^{3+}$ ions ($S$=7/2), the maximum magnetic entropy change reaches over 50 J kg$^{-1}$ K$^{-1}$ under fields up to 7 T in Gd$_3$BWO$_9$, nearly 1.5 times as large as commercial sub-Kelvin magnetic coolant Gd$_3$Ga$_5$O$_{12}$(GGG). The H-T phase diagram of Gd$_3$BWO$_9$ under $H$//$c$ exhibits field-induced critical behavior near the phase boundaries. This observation aligns with the theoretical scenario in which a quantum critical point acts as the endpoint of a line of classical second-order phase transitions. Such behavior suggests the importance of further investigations into the divergence of magnetic Gr\"uneisen parameter in the vicinity of critical field at ultralow temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11091v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/7l6y-hdw5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Mater. 9, 094407 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zhuoqun Wang, Xueling Cui, Tim Treu, Jiesen Guo, Xinyang Liu, Marvin Klinger, Christian Heil, Nvsen Ma, Xianlei Sheng, Zheng Deng, Xingye Lu, Xiancheng Wang, Wei Li, Philipp Gegenwart, Changqing Jin, Kan Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>"Adiabatic" Elastic Constants in Hubbard-Corrected Density-Functional Theory DFT+U: case UO$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11200v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Since in DFT+U there are multiple self-consistent electronic solutions, the so called metastable states, the elastic constants computed from stress-vs-strain will be incorrect if some of the strained configurations fall into a different local electronic minimum than the equilibrium non-strained state. So, it is crucial to carefully take steps to keep the same electronic Hubbard occupation branch when computing the stresses for small strained geometries. In this work, we have explained this "adiabatic" method of calculation for elastic constants and applied for UO$_2$ crystal described within two different unit cells of cubic 12-atom and tetragonal 6-atom basis sets. The calculation results for the two different unit cells are the same within 0.1 GPa, and agreement with experiment is excellent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11200v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahmoud Payami, Samira Sheykhi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Glimpsing at Electron's Form Factor through Quasiparticle Interference in Twisted Bilayer Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11223</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11223v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that characteristics of the electron's form factor in two-dimensional materials are observable in quasiparticle interference (QPI) spectrum. We study QPI in twisted bilayer graphene using real-space tight-binding calculations combined with the kernel polynomial method, which agrees excellently with the form factor norm obtained from the continuum Hamiltonian. The QPI signals, displaying a chiral structure, reveal all distinct interference processes between states near the Dirac points. We propose pseudospin textures of twisted bilayer graphene to explain all the interference mechanisms. Our results provide microscopic insights into electronic eigenstates of twisted bilayer graphene and suggest QPI as a potential method for probing the form factor, which governs the material's quantum geometry and many-body states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11223v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. -H. -Minh Nguyen, Francisco Guinea, Dario Bercioux</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic Quantum Clusters in Kagome Weyl Semimetal Co3Sn2S2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11230v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Impurities and intrinsic point defects, which profoundly influence spin, charge, and topological degrees of freedom, are crucial parameters for tuning quantum states in quantum materials. The magnetic Weyl semimetal Co3Sn2S2 with its strong spin-orbit coupling, intrinsic ferromagnetism, and kagome lattice of correlated electrons, provides a compelling platform for studying impurity excited states. Yet, the role of intrinsic impurities in shaping its quantum states remains elusive. Here, we uncover intrinsic quantum clusters-localized intrinsic point defects that act as tunable quantum perturbations capable of reshaping electronic states and order parameters, on the surface of Co3Sn2S2 via scanning tunneling microscopy/spectroscopy and non contact atomic force microscopy, combined with scanning transmission electron microscopy/electron energy loss spectroscopy. These clusters are identified as native oxygen defects that dominate the intrinsic defect landscape on both cleaved surface terminations. On the Sn-terminated surface, oxygen impurities occupy hollow sites between three Sn atoms, and tune the flat band near the Fermi level, which exhibits orbital magnetism induced unconventional Zeeman effect under an applied magnetic field. On the S-terminated surface, oxygen interstitials reside slightly off center relative to the S lattice and generate occupied impurity states that retain sixfold symmetry at higher energies but reduce to C2 symmetry at lower energies. In contrast, these impurity states show no measurable magnetic response. Our findings establish that intrinsic oxygen-related quantum clusters act as tunable local perturbations in a topological kagome magnet, offering a versatile platform to probe and engineer impurity-driven phenomena in correlated and topological systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11230v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuqing Xing, Hui Chen, Li Huang, Roger Guzman, Qi Zheng, Senhao Lv, Jinan Shi, Haitao Yang, Wu Zhou, Hong-Jun Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Realization of large magnetocaloric effect in the Kagome antiferromagnet Gd3BWO9 for Sub-Kelvin cryogenic refrigeration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11300v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rare-earth (RE) based frustrated magnets have attracted great attention as excellent candidates for magnetic refrigeration at sub-Kelvin temperatures, while the experimental identification on systems exhibiting both large volumetric cooling capacity and reduced working temperatures far below 1 K remain to be a challenge. Here, through the ultra-low temperature magnetism and thermodynamic characterizations, we unveil the large magnetocaloric effect (MCE) realized at sub-Kelvin temperatures in the frustrated Kagome antiferromagnet Gd3BWO9 with TN~1.0 K. The isothermal magnetization curves indicate the existence of field (B) induced anisotropic magnetic phase diagrams, where four distinct magnetic phases for B // c-axis and five magnetic phases for B // ab-plane are identified at T&lt; TN. The analysis of magnetic entropy S(B, T) data and direct adiabatic demagnetization tests reveal a remarkable cooling performance at sub-Kelvin temperatures featured by a large volumetric entropy density 502.2 mJ/K/cm3 and a low attainable minimal temperature Tmin~168 mK from the initial cooling condition of 2 K and 6 T, surpassing most of Gd-based refrigerants previously documented in temperature ranges of 0.25-4 K. The realized Tmin~168 mK far below TN ~ 1.0 K in Gd3BWO9 is related to the combined effects of magnetic frustration and criticality-enhanced MCE, which together leave a substantial magnetic entropy at reduced temperatures by enhancing spin fluctuations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11300v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fangyuan Song, Xinyang Liu, Chao Dong, Jin Zhou, Xinlong Shi, Yuyan Han, Langsheng Ling, Huifen Ren, Songliu Yuan, Shun Wang, Junsen Xiang, Peijie Sun, Zhaoming Tian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weak-coupling theory for partial condensation of mobile excitons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11304v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We studied formation of charge density wave between valleys in a system with a double-well-like dispersive valence band relevant for the rhombohedral graphene trilayer. In a regime with 2 Fermi surfaces, electron- and hole-like: one of radius $p_i$, another of $p_o$, an instability in particle-hole channel appears at $q=q_c+\delta q$, where $q_c=p_o-p_i$. In a weak coupling regime ($x/\epsilon_F\ll 1$) presence of an additional energy scale $\propto m q_c\delta q$ gives rise to several regimes with distinct spectrum and transport properties: in a regime with small order parameter $x\lessapprox m p_F \delta q$ Fermi arcs show up and substantially change conductance. At larger values of the order parameter Fermi arcs are gapped out. Regimes are also distinguished by different effective exponents $\gamma$ in conductance correction $\sigma\propto \tau_D^\gamma$ where $\tau_D$ is scattering time off disorder and $1\leq\gamma\leq 2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11304v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Igor V. Blinov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electron Hydrodynamics in Graphene : Experimental and Theoretical Status</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11315v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The present work comprehensively reviews electron hydrodynamics in graphene, highlighting both experimental observations and theoretical developments. Key experimental signatures such as negative vicinity resistance, Poiseuille flow, and significant violation of the Wiedemann-Franz (WF) law have been discussed, with special emphasis on Lorenz ratio measurements. In the theoretical direction, recent efforts have focused on developing hydrodynamic frameworks for calculating the thermodynamic and transport coefficients of electrons in graphene. The present work has briefly addressed the theoretical framework adopted by our group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11315v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subhalaxmi Nayak, Cho Win Aung, Thandar Zaw Win, Ashutosh Dwibedi, Sabyasachi Ghosh, Sesha Vempati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phases and phase transitions of an $S=3/2$ chain on metallic and semi-metallic surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11392v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by recent scanning tunneling microscopy experiments on chains of Co adatoms on Cu surfaces, we investigate the physics of a spin-$3/2$ Heisenberg chain with single-ion anisotropy ($D$) on metallic and semi-metallic surfaces. In the strong Kondo coupling ($J_k$) limit, a perturbative analysis maps the system onto a Haldane spin-1 chain with single-ion anisotropy, ferromagnetically coupled to the metallic surface. This Haldane state, arising from underscreening of the $S=3/2$ chain, is stable against small $D$ and characterized by topological edge modes. The nature of the $D$-driven transitions out of this state depends on the environment. Coupling to a metal (semi-metal) is a relevant (irrelevant) perturbation at the decoupled fixed point between the spin-1 chain and the two-dimensional electron gas. In the large positive $D$ limit, the system maps onto an anisotropic spin-$1/2$ Kondo system. For large negative $D$, in the Ising phase, spins are frozen. For small $J_k$, the nature of the metallic phase dominates. On a two-dimensional semi-metal, the Kondo coupling is irrelevant at the decoupled fixed point ($J_k= 0$), leading to a Kondo breakdown phase at weak coupling, irrespective of $D$. In contrast, on a two-dimensional metal, the resulting dissipative Ohmic bath is a marginally relevant perturbation, inducing antiferromagnetic ordering along the chain. In this case, $D$ drives a spin-flop transition between Ising and XY ordered phases. At $D=0$, we observe continuous transitions between the Kondo breakdown or dissipation-induced long-range ordered phases and the underscreened Haldane phase. These phase diagrams are supported by scaling arguments and sign-free auxiliary-field quantum Monte Carlo simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11392v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bimla Danu, Fakher F. Assaad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric Analysis of Magnetic Labyrinthine Stripe Evolution via U-Net Segmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11485</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11485v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Labyrinthine stripe patterns are common in many physical systems, yet their lack of long-range order makes quantitative characterization challenging. We investigate the evolution of such patterns in bismuth-doped yttrium iron garnet (Bi:YIG) films subjected to a magnetic field annealing protocol. A U-Net deep learning model, trained with synthetic degradations including additive white Gaussian and Simplex noise, enables robust segmentation of experimental magneto-optical images despite noise and occlusions. Building on this segmentation, we develop a geometric analysis pipeline based on skeletonization, graph mapping, and spline fitting, which quantifies local stripe propagation through length and curvature measurements. Applying this framework to 444 images from 12 annealing protocol trials, we analyze the transition from the "quenched" state to a more parallel and coherent "annealed" state, and identify two distinct evolution modes (Type A and Type B) linked to field polarity. Our results provide a quantitative analysis of geometric and topological properties in magnetic stripe patterns and offer new insights into their local structural evolution, and establish a general tool for analyzing complex labyrinthine systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11485v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vin\'icius Yu Okubo, Kotaro Shimizu, B. S. Shivaran, Gia-Wei Chern, Hae Yong Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exchange and spin-orbit proximity driven topological and transport phenomena in twisted graphene/CrI$_3$ heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11670</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11670v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present results of comprehensive first-principles and kp-method studies of electronic, magnetic, and topological properties of graphene on a monolayer of CrI$_3$. First, we identify a twist angle between the graphene and CrI$_3$, that positions the graphene Dirac cones within the bandgap of CrI$_3$. Then, we derive the low-energy effective Hamiltonian describing electronic properties of graphene Dirac cones. Subsequently, we examine anomalous and valley Hall conductivity and discuss possible topological phase transition from a quantum anomalous Hall insulator to a trivial insulating state, concomitant a change in the magnetic ground state of CrI$_3$. These findings highlight the potential of strain engineering in two-dimensional van der Waals heterostructures for controlling topological and magnetic phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11670v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Jafari, M. Gmitra, A. Dyrda{\l}</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrafast cooperative electronic, structural, and magnetic switching in an altermagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11722v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Femtosecond laser control of antiferromagnetic order is a cornerstone for future memory and logic devices operating at terahertz clock rates. The advent of altermagnets -- antiferromagnets with unconventional spin-group symmetries -- creates new opportunities in this evolving field. Here, we demonstrate ultrafast laser-induced switching in altermagnetic $\alpha$-MnTe that orchestrates the concerted dynamics of charge, lattice, and spin degrees of freedom. Time-resolved reflectivity and birefringence measurements reveal that the transient melting of spin order is accompanied by pronounced structural and electronic instabilities, as evidenced by phonon nonlinearity and accelerated band gap shrinkage. Theoretical modeling highlights the key roles of robust magnetic correlations and spin-charge coupling pathways intrinsic to this altermagnet.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11722v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tiangao Lu, Ao Wu, Junxiang Li, Meng Zeng, Di Cheng, Chang Liu, Jiangbin Gong, Xinwei Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generic continuum model formalism for moir\'e superlattice systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11747v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The moir\'e superlattice system provides an excellent platform for exploring various novel quantum phenomena. To theoretically tackle the diverse correlated and topological states emerging from moir\'e superlattices, one usually adopts an effective low-energy continuum model based on which the electron-electron effects are further considered. However, the construction of an accurate continuum model remains a challenging task, particularly for complex moir\'e superlattices such as twisted transition metal dichalcogenides. In this work, we develop a formalism for constructing generic continuum models that are in principle applicable for arbitrary moir\'e superlattices and are extrapolatable to any twist angles. Our key insight is that the microscopic electronic properties are intrinsic properties of the system, which should remain invariant across all twist angles; the lattice relaxations act as external inputs that vary with twist angles and are coupled with the electrons, and the coupling coefficients are characterized by intrinsic parameters. This partition enables a universal description of the angle variation of the continuum model using a single set of model parameters. To extract the model parameters, we design a numerical workflow based on data from first principles density functional theory calculations. We apply this framework to twisted bilayer MoTe$_{2}$, and obtain a single set of model parameters that accurately reproduce first-principles results, including electronic band structures, charge density distributions and Chern numbers, at three different twist angles. Furthermore, the model extrapolates robustly to smaller twist angles. Our work not only provides a more precise understanding of the microscopic properties of moir\'e superlattices, but also lays a foundation for future theoretical studies of low-energy electronic properties in generic moir\'e superlattice systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11747v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bo Xie, Jianqi Huang, Jianpeng Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Hermitian quantum geometric tensor and nonlinear electrical response</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11765v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate that the non-Hermitian quantum geometric tensor (QGT) governs nonlinear electrical responses in systems with a spectral line gap. The quantum metric, which is a component of the QGT and takes complex values in non-Hermitian systems, generates an intrinsic nonlinear conductivity independent of the scattering time, while the complex Berry curvature induces a wavepacket-width-dependent response. Using one-dimensional and two-dimensional non-Hermitian models, we establish a universal link between nonlinear dynamics and the QGT, thereby connecting quantum state geometry to observable transport phenomena. Crucially, our analysis indicates that the wavepacket width significantly affects non-Hermitian transport -- a feature absent in Hermitian systems. This framework unifies non-Hermitian response theory by revealing how geometric degrees of freedom encode transport in open and synthetic quantum matter. Our results bridge fundamental quantum geometry with emergent functionality, offering pathways to exploit geometric effects in topological devices and engineered materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11765v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kai Chen, Jie Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bose-Einstein condensates in a spin-twisted harmonic trap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11769</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11769v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the ground-state phases and spin-scissors dynamics of binary Bose-Einstein condensates confined in a twisted two-dimensional harmonic trap. The ground state hosts three distinct phases-phase-separated, polarized, and phase-mixed-determined by the Rabi coupling, interaction ratio G (between inter-component and intra-component interactions), and spin-twisting which induces edge-localized polarization through position-dependent detuning. In the phase-mixed regime, the ground state is characterized by a finite spin-scissors susceptibility and can be accurately described using local density approximation. In the dynamics, the system exhibits stable periodic beating in the phase-mixed state for G&lt;1. For G&gt;1, its evolution progresses from beat damping (phase-separated state) to polarized relaxation (polarized state), finally reaching stable periodic beating (phase-mixed state) after a finite waiting time. The dependence of the waiting time contrasts sharply with the monotonic behavior of one-dimensional spin-dipole dynamics, revealing qualitatively distinct mechanisms governed by geometry and interactions. In summary, these results establish a unified link between ground-state properties and nonequilibrium responses in twisted spinor condensates, offering a versatile platform for exploring spin-related quantum many-body phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11769v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huaxin He, Fengtao Pang, Xianchao Zhang, Yongping Zhang, Chunlei Qu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radio-frequency charge detection on graphene electron-hole double quantum dots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12061v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High-fidelity detection of charge transitions in quantum dots (QDs) is a key ingredient in solid state quantum computation. We demonstrate high-bandwidth radio-frequency charge detection in bilayer graphene quantum dots (QDs) using a capacitively coupled quantum point contact (QPC). The device design suppresses screening effects and enables sensitive QPC-based charge readout. The QPC is arranged to maximize the readout contrast between two neighboring, coupled electron and hole QDs. We apply the readout scheme to a single-particle electron-hole double QD and demonstrate time-resolved detection of charge states as well as magnetic field dependent tunneling rates. This promises a high-fidelity readout scheme for individual spin and valley states, which is important for the operation of spin, valley or spin-valley qubits in bilayer graphene.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12061v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katrin Hecker, Samuel M\"oller, Hubert Dulisch, \c{S}iyar Duman, Leon Stecher, Lucca Valerius, Tobias Deu{\ss}en, Saketh Ravuri, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Florian Libisch, Christian Volk, Christoph Stampfer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From hidden order to skyrmions: Quantum Hall states in an extended Hofstadter-Fermi-Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12184</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12184v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The interplay between topology and strong interactions gives rise to a variety of exotic quantum phases, including fractional quantum Hall (FQH) states and their lattice analogs - fractional Chern insulators (FCIs). Such topologically ordered states host fractionalized excitations, which for spinful systems are often accompanied by ferromagnetism and skyrmions. Here, we study a Hofstadter-Hubbard model of spinful fermions on a square lattice, extended by nearest-neighbor interactions. Using large-scale density matrix renormalization group (DMRG) simulations, we demonstrate the emergence of a spin-polarized $\frac{1}{3}$-Laughlin-like FCI phase, characterized by a quantized many-body Chern number, a finite charge gap, and hidden off-diagonal long-range order. We further investigate the quantum Hall ferromagnet at $\nu=1$ and its skyrmionic excitations upon doping. In particular, we find that nearest-neighbor repulsion is sufficient to stabilize both particle- and hole-skyrmions in the ground state around $\nu=1$, whereas we do not find such textures around $\nu=\frac{1}{3}$. The diagnostic toolbox presented in this work, based on local densities, correlation functions, and spin-resolved observables, is directly applicable in quantum gas microscopy experiments. Our results open new pathways for experimental exploration of FCIs with spin textures in both ultracold atom and electronic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12184v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabian J. Pauw, Ulrich Schollw\"ock, Nathan Goldman, Sebastian Paeckel, Felix A. Palm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-polarization and diode effect in thermoelectric current through altermagnet-based superconductor heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12198v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The recent advent of a new class of magnetic material named as altermagnet (AM), characterized by a combination of momentum-dependent spin-splitting with zero net magnetization, has opened up promising prospects for spintronic applications. We theoretically explore how the altermagnetic spin-splitting affects the thermoelectric quasiparticle current in AM-based superconducting heterostructures. Our setup comprises of a bilayer system where a $d$-wave AM is proximity coupled to an ordinary $s$-wave superconductor (SC). We calculate the thermoelectric current carried by the quasiparticles applying a finite thermal bias accross the junction. The behavior of the thermoelectric current with the system's base temperature and chemical potential is very similar to that in traditional SC heterostructures. Remarkably, the dissipative thermoelectric current found in the AM junction is spin-split and thus generates finite spin-polarization in the AM-based junction, which can approach $100\%$ spin-polarization in the strong altermagnetic phase. We further investigate the thermoelectric current in AM-based Josephson junction (JJ) and illustrate how to achieve the diode effect in this AM-based JJ. The efficiency of our proposed thermoelectric diode reaches upto $\sim 80\%$ and changes its sign depending on the strength of the AM, enhancing the potential for spin-calotronics applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12198v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Debika Debnath, Arijit Saha, Paramita Dutta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-block exceptional points in open quantum systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11856</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11856v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Open quantum systems can be approximately described by non-Hermitian Hamiltonians (NHHs) and Lindbladians. The two approaches differ by quantum jump terms corresponding to a measurement of the system by its environment. We analyze the emergence of exceptional points (EPs) in NHHs and Lindbladians. In particular, we show how EPs in NHHs relate to a novel type of EPs -- multi-block EPs -- in the non-Hermitian Liouvillian, i.e. the Lindbladian in absence of quantum jump terms. We further analyze how quantum jump terms modify the multi-block structure. To illustrate our general findings, we present two prime examples: qubits and qutrits coupled to additional ground state levels that serves as sinks of the population. In those examples, we can navigate through the EP block structure by a variation of physical parameters. We analyze how the dynamics of the population of the states is affected by the order of the EPs. Additionally, we demonstrate that the quantum geometric tensor serves as a sensitive indicator of EPs of different kinds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11856v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aysel Shiralieva, Grigory A. Starkov, Bj\"orn Trauzettel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Symmetries and Deformations of Symmetric Product Orbifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12180v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct generalized symmetries in two-dimensional symmetric product orbifold CFTs $\text{Sym}^N(\mathcal{T}),$ for a generic seed CFT $\mathcal{T}$. These symmetries are more general than the universal and maximally symmetric ones previously constructed. We show that, up to one fine-tuned example when the number of copies $N$ equals four, the only symmetries that can be preserved under twisted sector marginal deformations are invertible and maximally symmetric. The results are obtained in two ways. First, using the mathematical machinery of $G$-equivariantization of fusion categories, and second, via the projector construction of topological defect lines. As an application, we classify all preserved symmetries in symmetric product orbifold CFTs with the seed CFT given by any $A$-series $\mathcal{N}=(2,2)$ minimal model. We comment on the implications of our results for holography.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12180v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nathan Benjamin, Suzanne Bintanja, Yu-Jui Chen, Michael Gutperle, Conghuan Luo, Dikshant Rathore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grain boundary-limited thermal transport in suspended thin graphite across an unexplored thickness regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.10704</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.10704v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present systematic thermal conductivity measurements of suspended thin graphite ribbons, 234-527 nm thick, using a four-probe 3-omega method. Unlike recent reports of phonon hydrodynamics and exceptionally high thermal conductivity in micrometer-thick graphite (Science, 2020),we observe significantly lower thermal conductivity and no signatures of collective phonon flow in this intermediate thickness regime. Instead, our measured thermal conductivity lies between few-layer graphene and bulk graphite.These results agree with a first-principles-informed Peierls-Boltzmann transport model with spatially resolved Monte Carlo sampling. Additionally, the temperature for the peak thermal conductivity shifts lower with increasing thickness, due to the interplay of phonon-boundary and phonon-isotope scattering. Incorporating grain boundary scattering into simulations is necessary to replicate the experimental trends. These findings delineate the boundary between ballistic, hydrodynamic, and diffusive transport regimes in graphite, and underscore the dominant role of disorder and geometry in phonon transport in quasi-two-dimensional materials, offering insights for nanoscale thermal management.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.10704v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.nanolett.5c03214</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nano Lett. 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Wonjae Jeon, Yu Pei, Xun Li, Lucas Lindsay, Sangyeop Lee, Renkun Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlated Phases in Spin-Orbit-Coupled Rhombohedral Trilayer Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.12486</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.12486v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent experiments indicate that crystalline graphene multilayers exhibit much of the richness of their twisted counterparts, including cascades of symmetry-broken states and unconventional superconductivity. Interfacing Bernal bilayer graphene with a WSe$_2$ monolayer was shown to dramatically enhance superconductivity -- suggesting that proximity-induced spin-orbit coupling plays a key role in promoting Cooper pairing. Motivated by this observation, we study the phase diagram of spin-orbit-coupled rhombohedral trilayer graphene via self-consistent Hartree-Fock simulations, elucidating the interplay between displacement field effects, long-range Coulomb repulsion, short-range (Hund's) interactions, and substrate-induced Ising spin-orbit coupling. In addition to generalized Stoner ferromagnets, we find various flavors of intervalley coherent ground states distinguished by their transformation properties under electronic time reversal, $\text{C}_3$ rotations, and an effective anti-unitary symmetry. We pay particular attention to broken-symmetry phases that yield Fermi surfaces compatible with zero-momentum Cooper pairing, identifying promising candidate orders that may support spin-orbit-enhanced superconductivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.12486v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.035113</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 109, 035113 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jin Ming Koh, Jason Alicea, \'Etienne Lantagne-Hurtubise</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Helical Luttinger liquid on a space-time lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.10828</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.10828v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Luttinger model is a paradigm for the breakdown due to interactions of the Fermi liquid description of one-dimensional massless Dirac fermions. Attempts to discretize the model on a one-dimensional lattice have failed to reproduce the established bosonization results, because of the fermion-doubling obstruction: A local and symmetry-preserving discretization of the Hamiltonian introduces a spurious second species of low-energy excitations, while a nonlocal discretization opens a single-particle gap at the Dirac point. Here we show how to work around this obstruction, by discretizing both space and time to obtain a \textit{local} Lagrangian for a helical Luttinger liquid with Hubbard interaction. The approach enables quantum Monte Carlo simulations that preserve the topological protection of an unpaired Dirac cone.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.10828v5</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.116501</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.Lett. 133, 116501 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>V. A. Zakharov, J. Tworzydlo, C. W. J. Beenakker, M. J. Pacholski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forestalled Phase Separation as the Precursor to Stripe Order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.15158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.15158v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Stripe order is a prominent feature in the phase diagram of the high-temperature cuprate superconductors. It has been confirmed as the lowest-energy state of the two-dimensional Fermi Hubbard model in certain parameter regimes. Upon increasing the temperature, stripes and the superconducting state give way to the enigmatic strange-metal and pseudogap regimes, whose precise nature remains a long-standing puzzle. Using modern tensor network techniques, we discover a crucial aspect of these regimes. Infinite projected entangled pair states (iPEPS) simulations in the fully two-dimensional limit reveal a maximum in the charge susceptibility at temperatures above the stripe order. This maximum is located around filling $n=0.9$ and intensifies upon cooling. Using minimally entangled typical thermal states (METTS) on finite cylinders, we attribute the enhanced charge susceptibility to the formation of charge clusters, reminiscent of phase separation where the system is partitioned into hole-rich and hole-depleted regions. In contrast to genuine phase separation, the charge cluster sizes fluctuate without a divergent charge susceptibility. Hence, while this precursor state features clustering of charge carriers, true phase separation is ultimately forestalled at lower temperatures by the onset of stripe order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.15158v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aritra Sinha, Alexander Wietek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On polarons and dimerons in the two-dimensional attractive Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19725</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19725v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A two-dimensional spin-up ideal Fermi gas interacting attractively with a spin-down impurity in the continuum undergoes, at zero temperature, a first-order phase transition from a polaron to a dimeron state. Here we study a similar system on a square lattice, by considering the attractive 2D Fermi-Hubbard model with a single spin-down and a finite filling fraction of spin-up fermions. We study polaron and dimeron quasi-particle properties via variational Ansatz up to one particle-hole excitation. Moreover, we develop a determinant diagrammatic Monte Carlo algorithm for this problem based on expansion in bare on-site coupling $U$. This algorithm turns out to be sign-problem free at any filling of spin-up fermions, allowing one to sample very high diagram order (larger than $200$ in our study) and to do simulations for large $U/t$ (we go up to $U/t=-20$ with $t$ the hopping strength). Both methods give qualitatively consistent results. With variational Ansatz we go to even larger on-site attraction. In contrast with the continuum case, we do not observe any polaron-to-dimeron transition for a range of spin-up filling fractions $\rho_{\uparrow}$ between $0.1$ and $0.4$. % (away from the low-filling limit). The polaron state always gives a lower energy and has a finite quasi-particle residue.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19725v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gerard Pascual, Jordi Boronat, Kris Van Houcke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revealing trends in catalytic activity of adatoms for hydrogen adsorption on carbon: a case study of graphene and carbon nanotube</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11960</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11960v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The increasing demand for sustainable energy solutions necessitates advancements in hydrogen storage technologies. This study investigates the hydrogen adsorption characteristics of graphene and a (8,0) carbon nanotube (CNT) decorated with adatoms of various elements. Using molecular dynamics (MD) simulations and the universal interatomic potential 'PreFerred Potential' (PFP) implemented in the Matlantis framework, we explore the hydrogen storage capabilities of these doped carbon structures at 77K. We analyze the adsorption efficiency based on the position of adatoms (top, bridge, and hollow sites) and find that the group II elements, such as calcium and strontium, exhibit significant hydrogen uptake. Additionally, light elements like lithium and sodium demonstrate enhanced gravimetric hydrogen storage due to their low atomic mass. Our findings provide insights into the potential of doped graphene and CNTs for efficient hydrogen storage applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11960v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Leiner, David Holec</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interfacial spin-orbit coupling in superconducting hybrid systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10911v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the effects of interfacial spin-orbit coupling (ISOC) on superconductors, focusing on its impact on electronic transport and spin-charge conversion. Using a symmetry-based nonlinear sigma model, we derive effective boundary conditions for the Usadel and Maxwell equations that account for the spin-galvanic effect, spin relaxation, and spin precession. This approach allows for the analysis of various interfaces without relying on specific microscopic models. We apply these boundary conditions to derive ISOC-induced terms in the Ginzburg-Landau functional, which is then used to compute the critical temperature of superconducting films with ISOC subjected to an external magnetic field. Our findings show that, contrary to a recent prediction, the critical temperature of a film cannot be enhanced by an external magnetic field. Additionally, we demonstrate that the combination of ISOC and an external magnetic field leads to a superconducting diode effect. Its efficiency strongly depends on the interplay between the spin-galvanic and the spin relaxation terms. Our results provide a framework for understanding ISOC in superconducting systems and highlight the potential for optimizing diode efficiency through careful interface engineering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10911v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/dsxt-phyk</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 024514 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>A. A. Mazanik, Tim Kokkeler, I. V. Tokatly, F. Sebastian Bergeret</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Green's Function Zeros by Co-tunneling through Mott Insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19479</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19479v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum tunneling experiments have provided deep insights into basic excitations occurring as Green's function poles in the realm of complex quantum matter. However, strongly correlated quantum materials also allow for Green's functions zeros (GFZ) that may be seen as an antidote to the familiar poles, and have so far largely eluded direct experimental study. Here, we propose and investigate theoretically how co-tunneling through Mott insulators enables direct access to the shadow band structure of GFZ. In particular, we derive an effective Hamiltonian for the GFZ that is shown to govern the co-tunneling amplitude and reveal fingerprints of many-body correlations clearly distinguishing the GFZ structure from the underlying free Bloch band structure of the system. Our perturbative analytical results are corroborated by numerical data both in the framework of exact diagonalization and matrix product state simulations for a one-dimensional model system consisting of a Su-Schrieffer-Heeger-Hubbard model coupled to two single level quantum dots.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19479v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/jnq4-sykq</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 106303 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Carl Lehmann, Lorenzo Crippa, Giorgio Sangiovanni, Jan Carl Budich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coherent Phonon Pairs and Rotational Symmetry Breaking of Charge Density Wave Order in the Kagome Superconductor CsV$_3$Sb$_5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.07442v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we perform ultrafast time-resolved reflectivity measurements to study the symmetry breaking in the charge-density wave (CDW) phase of CsV$_3$Sb$_5$. By extracting the coherent phonon spectrum in the CDW phase of CsV$_3$Sb$_5$, we discover close phonon pairs near 1.3 THz and 3.1 THz, as well as a new mode at 1.84 THz. The 1.3 THz phonon pair and the 1.84 THz mode are observed up to the CDW transition temperature. Combining density-functional theory calculations, we point out these phonon pairs arise from the coexistence of Star-of-David and inverse Star-of-David distortions combined with six-fold rotational symmetry breaking. An anisotropy in the magnitude of transient reflectivity change is also revealed at the onset of CDW order. Our results thus indicate broken six-fold rotational symmetry in the charge-density wave state of CsV$_3$Sb$_5$, along with the absence of nematic fluctuation above T$_{\text{CDW}}$. Meanwhile, the measured coherent phonon spectrum in the CDW phase of CsV$_3$Sb$_{5-\text{x}}$Sn$_\text{x}$ with x = 0.03-0.04 matches with staggered inverse Star-of-David with interlayer $\pi$ phase shift. This CDW structure contrasts with undoped CsV$_3$Sb$_5$ and explains the evolution from phonon pair to a single mode at 1.3 THz by x = 0.03-0.04 Sn-doping.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.07442v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/gmdl-qz2t</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 125127 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Qinwen Deng, Hengxin Tan, Brenden R. Ortiz, Andrea Capa Salinas, Stephen D. Wilson, Binghai Yan, Liang Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coupling between small polarons and ferroelectricity in BaTiO3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.12693</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.12693v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this study, we investigate the formation of electron and hole small polarons in the prototypical ferroelectric material BaTiO3, with a focus on their interaction with ferroelectric distortive fields. To accurately describe the ferroelectric phase in electronically correlated BaTiO3, we employ the HSE06 hybrid density functional, which addresses the limitations of conventional density functional theory (DFT) and Hubbard-corrected DFT+U models, providing a more precise depiction of both ferroelectric and polaronic behaviors. Our analysis spans three structural phases of BaTiO3: cubic, tetragonal, and rhombohedral. We uncover a unique phase-dependent trend in electron polaron stability, which progressively increases across the structural phases, peaking in the rhombohedral phase due to the constructive coupling between the polaron and ferroelectric phonon fields. In contrast, hole polarons exhibit a stability pattern largely unaffected by the phase transitions. Furthermore, we observe that polaron self-trapping significantly alters the local ferroelectric distortive pattern, which propagates to neighboring sites but has a minimal effect on the long-range macroscopic spontaneous polarization. Charge trapping is also associated with localized spin formation, opening new possibilities for enhanced functionalities in multiferroic materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.12693v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/5z43-rm34</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Darin Joseph, Cesare Franchini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nagaoka ferromagnetism in semiconductor artificial graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.01492v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the emergence of Nagaoka ferromagnetism in semiconductor-based artificial graphene with realistic Coulomb interaction using high-precision variational and diffusion Monte Carlo methods, complemented by exact diagonalization calculations of the generalized Hubbard model. We analyze models of armchair hexagonal geometries nanopatterned on GaAs quantum wells. Our results reveal a distinct magnetic phase transition driven by the absence/addition of a single electron at half-filling. This form of itinerant magnetism predicted rigorously for Hubbard model remained unascertained in large scale realistic systems. We demonstrate that Coulomb scattering terms play a crucial role in stabilizing Nagaoka ferromagnetism, enabling the observation of the phase transition for system parameters near $U/t \approx 60$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.01492v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G\"okhan \"Oztarhan, Pawe{\l} Potasz, A. D. G\"u\c{c}l\"u</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Band-selective Plasmonic Polaron in Thermoelectric Semimetal Ta$_2$PdSe$_6$ with ultra-high power factor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19794</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.19794v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report the electronic structure of the thermoelectric semimetal Ta$_2$PdSe$_6$ with a large thermoelectric power factor and giant Peltier conductivity by means of angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES). The ARPES spectra reveal the coexistence of a sharp hole band with a light electron mass and a broad electron band with a relatively heavy electron mass, which originate from different quasi-one-dimensional (Q1D) chains in Ta$_2$PdSe$_6$. Moreover, the electron band around the Brillouin-zone (BZ) boundary shows a replica structure with respect to the energy originating from plasmonic polarons due to electron-plasmon interactions. The different scattering effects and interactions in each atomic chain lead to asymmetric transport lifetimes of carriers: a large Seebeck coefficient can be realized even in a semimetal. Our findings pave the way for exploring the thermoelectric materials in previously overlooked semimetals and provide a new platform for low-temperature thermoelectric physics, which has been challenging with semiconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.19794v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daiki Ootsuki, Akitoshi Nakano, Urara Maruoka, Takumi Hasegawa, Masashi Arita, Miho Kitamura, Koji Horiba, Teppei Yoshida, Ichiro Terasaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Hierarchy of Superconductivity and Topological Charge Density Wave States in Rhombohedral Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22026</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.22026v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Superconductivity and the quantum Hall effect are conventionally regarded as mutually exclusive: superconductivity is suppressed by magnetic fields, whereas the quantum Hall effect relies on them. Here we report a striking exception, where an unconventional superconducting phase is stabilized by an out-of-plane magnetic field and coexists with a re-entrant integer quantum Hall (RIQH) effect in moir\'e-less rhombohedral hexalayer graphene. The re-entrant quantum Hall state, arising from a bubble-like charge density wave (CDW), provides a natural backdrop for the emergence of superconductivity. Angle-resolved transport reveals that the field-stabilized superconducting phase occupies the same density--displacement-field regime as a stripe-ordered phase at zero field, yet only develops once the stripe is replaced by a bubble-like CDW at finite field. These findings demonstrate a decisive role of CDW order in stabilizing superconductivity in rhombohedral graphene, establishing a new paradigm for the interplay between superconductivity and quantum Hall physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.22026v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ron Q. Nguyen, Hai-Tian Wu, Erin Morissette, Naiyuan J. Zhang, Peiyu Qin, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Aaron W. Hui, Dima E. Feldman, J. I. A. Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital magnetic moments in FeCr2S4 studied by x-ray magnetic circular dichroism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14428v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We have investigated the element specific magnetic characteristics of single-crystal FeCr2S4 using x-ray absorption spectroscopy (XAS) and x-ray magnetic circular dichroism (XMCD). We have found that the Fe L2,3-edge XAS spectra do not exhibit clear multiplet structures, indicating strong hybridization between the Fe 3d and S 3p orbitals, leading to delocalized rather than localized electronic states. The Fe 3d and Cr 3d spin moments are antiferromagnetically coupled, consistent with the Goodenough-Kanamori rule. The orbital magnetic moments of Fe and Cr are determined to be -0.23 and -0.017 {\mu}B/ion, respectively. The large orbital magnetic moment of Fe is due to the d6 configuration under the relatively weak tetrahedra crystal field at the Fe site, and the delocalized Fe electrons maintain the orbital degree of freedom in spite of their itinerant nature. To understand phenomena such as the gigantic Kerr rotation, it is essential to consider not only the orbital degrees of freedom but also the role of spin-orbit coupling, which induces a finite orbital magnetic moment through t2 and e level hybridization under the tetrahedral crystal field. This finite orbital moment serves as a direct indicator of spin-orbit interaction strength and links element-specific orbital magnetism to the large Kerr rotation. On the other hand, the octahedral crystal-field splitting of the Cr 3d level is large enough to result in the quenching of the orbital moment of the Cr ion in FeCr2S4.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14428v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. K. Verma, J. Patra, V. R. Singh, Y. Nonaka, G. Shibata, K. Ishigami, A. Tanaka, K. Ohgushi, Y. Tokura, T. Koide, A. Fujimori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum phase transitions in the multiphoton Jaynes-Cummings-Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20185</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20185v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We explore quantum phase transitions in the multiphoton Jaynes-Cummings-Hubbard model (JCHM). Using the mean-field approximation, we demonstrate that the multiphoton JCHM exhibits quantum phase transitions between the Mott insulator (MI) phase, the superfluid phase, and an additional phase we refer to as the forbidden phase. The multiphoton JCHM MI phases are classified according to a conserved quantity associated with the total number of excited atoms and photons. When this conserved quantity diverges toward positive infinity, this system enters the forbidden phase. By analyzing the system, we observe MI, superfluid, and forbidden phases in both the single- and two-photon JCHMs, although the MI phases in the two-photon case are confined to subspaces with small values of the conserved quantity. In contrast, only the superfluid and forbidden phases appear in the three- and four-photon JCHMs, with no MI phase observed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20185v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/ypts-6z4p</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 112, 033709 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hiroo Azuma, William J. Munro, Kae Nemoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A superinductor in a deep sub-micron integrated circuit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13202v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Superinductors are circuit elements characterised by an intrinsic impedance in excess of the superconducting resistance quantum ($R_\text{Q}\approx6.45~$k$\Omega$), with applications from metrology and sensing to quantum computing. However, they are typically obtained using exotic materials with high density inductance such as Josephson junctions, superconducting nanowires or twisted two-dimensional materials. Here, we present a superinductor realised within a silicon integrated circuit (IC), exploiting the high kinetic inductance ($\sim 1$~nH/$\square$) of TiN thin films native to the manufacturing process (22-nm FDSOI). By interfacing the superinductor to a silicon quantum dot formed within the same IC, we demonstrate a radio-frequency single-electron transistor (rfSET), the most widely used sensor in semiconductor-based quantum computers. The integrated nature of the rfSET reduces its parasitics which, together with the high impedance, yields a sensitivity improvement of more than two orders of magnitude over the state-of-the-art, combined with a 10,000-fold area reduction. Beyond providing the basis for dense arrays of integrated and high-performance qubit sensors, the realization of high-kinetic-inductance superconducting devices integrated within modern silicon ICs opens many opportunities, including kinetic-inductance detector arrays for astronomy and the study of metamaterials and quantum simulators based on 1D and 2D resonator arrays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13202v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. H. Swift, F. Olivieri, G. Aizpurua-Iraola, J. Kirkman, G. M. Noah, M. de Kruijf, F. E. von Horstig, A. Gomez-Saiz, J. J. L. Morton, M. F. Gonzalez-Zalba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
