<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 04:00:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Ge as an ideal orbitronic platform: giant orbital Hall effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20436v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: State-of-the-art developments in magnetic devices rely on manufacturing faster, more efficient memory elements. A significant development in this direction has been the discovery of orbital torques, which employ the orbital angular momentum of Bloch electrons to switch the magnetisation of an adjacent ferromagnet, and has motivated the search for \textit{orbitronic} materials displaying strong orbital dynamics exemplified, by the orbital Hall effect (OHE). In this work we propose Ge, as an optimal orbitronic platform. We demonstrate that holes in bulk Ge exhibit a giant OHE, exceeding that of the bulk states of topological insulators, and exceeding the spin-Hall effect by four orders of magnitude. The calculation is performed within the framework of the Luttinger model and the modern theory of orbital magnetisation, while incorporating recently-discovered quantum corrections to the OHE. Our study constitutes a fundamental milestone in applying the modern theory to a system with \textit{inversion symmetry}. Moreover, we argue that bulk Ge serves as an ideal testbed for the orbital torque resulting from a charge current, since the spin- and orbital-Edelstein effects in Ge are forbidden by symmetry. Our results provide a blueprint for producing strong orbital torques in magnetic devices with Ge, guiding future experimental work in this direction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20436v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James H. Cullen, Zhanning Wang, Dimitrie Culcer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous Landau Levels in Inhomogeneous Fluxes and Emergent Supersymmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20462</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20462v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two-dimensional systems in magnetic fields host rich physics, most notably the quantum Hall effect arising from Landau level quantization. In a broad class of two-dimensional models, flat bands with topologically nontrivial band degeneracies give rise to anomalous Landau level quantization under homogeneous fields. Ascribed to the underlying quantum geometry, these are classified as singular flat bands, exhibiting unusual wavefunction localization, and anomalous quantization of Landau levels. We investigate the response of gapless singular flat bands to inhomogeneous fluxes, bridging continuum and lattice descriptions. Our analysis reveals a mechanism to controllably manipulate the anomalous Landau levels via flux inhomogeneity. We further uncover an emergent supersymmetry in the parameter space where the tower of anomalous Landau levels collapses to zero energy, rendering a lattice analog of the Aharonov-Casher theorem on degenerate zero modes in perpendicular fluxes, with wavefunction localization partly similar to Aharonov-Bohm caging. With the addition of strong correlations, these findings will have implications for realizing exotic topological and charge-ordered phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20462v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soujanya Datta, Krishanu Roychowdhury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Coherence in a Maximally Hot Hubbard Chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20498</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20498v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a detailed study of the real-time dynamics and spectral properties of the one-dimensional fermionic Hubbard model at infinite temperature. Using tensor network simulations in Liouville space, we compute the single-particle Green's function and analyze its dynamics across a broad range of interaction strengths. To complement the time-domain approach, we develop a high-resolution Chebyshev expansion method within the density matrix formalism, enabling direct access to spectral functions in the frequency domain. In the non-interacting limit, we derive exact analytical expressions for the Green's function, providing a benchmark for our numerical methods. As interactions are introduced, we observe a transition in the spectral function from a sharp peak at the free dispersion to a broadened two-band structure associated with hole and doublon excitations. These features are well captured by a Hubbard-I mean-field approximation, even at intermediate coupling. At infinite interaction strength ($U = \infty$), we exploit a determinant representation of the Green's function to access both real-time and spectral properties. In this regime, the system retains a sharp, cosine-like momentum dispersion in frequency space, while the dynamics display nontrivial light-cone spreading with sub-ballistic scaling. Our results demonstrate that strong correlations and nontrivial quantum coherence can persist even at infinite temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20498v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C\u{a}t\u{a}lin Pa\c{s}cu Moca, Ovidiu I. Patu, Bal\'azs D\'ora, Gergely Zar\'and</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hot but Coherent: Doublons at Infinite Temperature in the Hubbard chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20504</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20504v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the spectral properties and the dynamics of doublons in the one-dimensional Hubbard model at infinite temperature. Using a Chebyshev expansion approach formulated in the superfermionic representation, we compute the momentum- and frequency-resolved doublon spectral function across a wide range of interaction strengths $U$ and in the presence of an external electric field. Increasing the interaction, the spectrum gradually splits into separate bands associated with two-hole and two-particle excitations. Despite the presence of strong correlations, we find that doublons retain their coherence and undergo long-lived Bloch oscillations, as well as rich quantum walk dynamics characterized by light-cone spreadings at strong coupling, which we analyze through the time-and space-resolved Green's function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20504v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C\u{a}t\u{a}lin Pa\c{s}cu Moca, Bal\'azs D\'ora, Gergely Zar\'and</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Ferrimagnetic Ground State and Suppressed Superconductivity in Two-Dimensional HC6</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20672</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20672v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two-dimensional hydrogenated graphene (HC6) represents a promising platform for exploring emergent electronic phases. Owing to its high electronic density of states at the Fermi level, HC6 is expected to support phonon-mediated superconductivity, with a calculated critical temperature Tc of 37.4 K in the paramagnetic metallic phase. However, spin-polarized first-principles calculations reveal that HC6 stabilizes in a ferrimagnetic ground state, which is energetically favored by 0.175 eV per unit cell over the paramagnetic metallic phase. This large energy difference significantly exceeds kB T at room temperature, indicating robust magnetic order. Although the superconducting condensation energy lowers the total energy by about 7 meV, the superconducting phase remains metastable. These results highlight the dominant role of magnetism in HC6 and illustrate how a high electronic density of states can drive competing instabilities in hydrogenated two-dimensional materials, offering design principles for carbon-based magnetic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20672v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jakkapat Seeyangnok, Udomsilp Pinsook</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic antiferromagnetic half-metal and topological phases in the ferrovalley states of the sliding bilayer altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20687</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20687v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Altermagnetism is characterized by non-relativistic spin splitting and zero total magnetic moments. In this work, intrinsic antiferromagnetic half-metallic and topological phases were discovered within the ferrovalley states of sliding bilayer altermagnets. We construct the bilayer system by utilizing altermagnet monolayers with a small bandgap. The inter-layer hopping phenomenon leads to a reduction in bandgaps, and sliding engineering induces ferrovalley states. Taking the V$_2$OSSe system for example, first-principles calculations indicate that the spin-dependent inter-layer hopping in the ferrovalley state ensures a direct gap in one valley (one spin channel) and band inversion in the other valley (opposite spin channel), which is manifested as an intrinsic antiferromagnetic half-metal. The microscopic model and effective Hamiltonian employed in this research confirm the universal spin-dependent inter-layer hopping in the sliding altermagnet bilayer. Further calculations imply the existence of Chern insulator and gapless surface states in the sliding altermagnet bilayer. Adjusting the sliding direction can achieve the transition between different half-metals with conducting electrons of different spins, accompanied by the switching of gapless surface states of opposite spins. This research lays a foundation for the potential applications of intrinsic antiferromagnetic half-metals and topological phases in spintronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20687v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shihao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distinct orbital contributions to electronic and magnetic structures in La$_{4}$Ni$_{3}$O$_{10}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20727</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20727v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High-T$_c$ superconductivity has recently been discovered in Ruddlesden-Popper phase nickelates under pressure, where the low-energy electronic structure is dominated by Ni $d_{x^2 - y^2}$ and $d_{z^2}$ orbitals. However, the respective roles of these orbitals in superconductivity remain unclear. Here, by combining X-ray absorption, electron energy loss spectroscopy, and density functional theory calculations on La$_{4}$Ni$_{3}$O$_{10}$ single crystals, we identify ligand holes in the $p_{x,y}$ orbitals of planar oxygen and the $p_z$ orbitals of apical oxygen, which hybridize with the Ni $d_{x^2-y^2}$ and $d_{z^2}$ orbitals, respectively. These ligand holes enable orbital-selective O K-edge resonant inelastic X-ray scattering (RIXS) study, which reveals that $d_{x^2-y^2}$ states dominate the low-energy charge excitations and are more itinerant. We also observe a $\sim$0.1 eV bimagnon through RIXS and Raman spectroscopy, which leads to an interlayer superexchange interaction J$_z$ of $\sim$50 meV. Our results reveal distinct contributions of Ni $d_{x^2-y^2}$ and $d_{z^2}$ orbitals to the electronic and magnetic structure and provide direct experimental insights to understand the RP-phase nickelate superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20727v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shilong Zhang, Hengyuang Zhang, Zehao Dong, Jie Li, Qian Xiao, Mengwu Huo, Hsiao-Yu Huang, Di-Jing Huang, Yayu Wang, Yi Lu, Zhen Chen, Meng Wang, Yingying Peng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous Quantum Relaxation in the Infinite Temperature Hubbard Chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20759v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The self-energy encodes the fundamental lifetime of quasiparticle excitations. In one dimension, it is known to display anomalous behavior at zero temperature for interacting fermions, reflecting the breakdown of Fermi-liquid theory. Here we show that the self-energy is also anomalous in the infinite temperature Hubbard chain, where thermal fluctuations are maximal. Focusing on the second order ring diagram, we find that the imaginary part of the self-energy diverges non-perturbatively: as a power law with exponent $-1/3$ near half filling, and logarithmically away from it. These divergences imply anomalous temporal relaxation of Green's functions, confirmed by infinite temperature tensor-network simulations. Our results demonstrate that anomalous relaxation and the breakdown of perturbation theory survive even at maximal entropy, which can be observed in cold-atom experiments probing the Hubbard chain at high temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20759v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Catalin Pascu Moca, Bal\'azs D\'ora</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Luttinger surface and exchange splitting induced by ferromagnetic fluctuations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21034</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21034v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ferromagnetism in the single-orbital Hubbard model, which contains only local Coulomb repulsion and no explicit ferromagnetic exchange interactions, has been extensively studied. However, how the associated fluctuations influence the electronic properties near the transition remains a fundamental issue. Here, by applying the dynamical vertex approximation (D$\Gamma$A) to single-orbital systems with a partially flat band dispersion, we demonstrate that finite-correlation-length ferromagnetic fluctuations generate an emergent Luttinger surface and drive a Fermi surface expansion reminiscent of exchange splitting, even without magnetic order. We further derive an analytical expression that reproduces these effects, clarifying the microscopic origin for fluctuation-driven exchange splitting in correlated electron systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21034v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Motoharu Kitatani, Yusuke Nomura, Shiro Sakai, Ryotaro Arita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Preformed Cooper Pairing and the Uncondensed Normal-State Component in Phase-Fluctuating Cuprate Superconductivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21133v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a self-consistent microscopic framework beyond mean-field theory for superconductivity in cuprates. It couples fermionic quasiparticles with collective phase dynamics to treat the superconducting gap and superfluid stiffness. The phase sector explicitly incorporates both smooth bosonic Nambu-Goldstone phase fluctuations, renormalized by long-range Coulomb interactions, and topological Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless-type vortex-antivortex fluctuations. The required input is the correlated single-particle spectral function, enabling direct interfacing with Hubbard-type models. The framework provides quantitative access to key superconducting observables, including $T$-dependent gap and phase stiffness, gap-closing temperature $T_{\rm os}$, and transition temperature $T_c$, across wide ranges of doping. Using a recently proposed solvable interaction model as input, our simulations reveal several important features consistent with experimental observations in the cuprates: a $d$-wave superconducting dome in the $T$-$p$ phase diagram with a shoulder-like anomaly in the underdoped regime, a pronounced separation between $T_c$ and $T_{\rm os}$ signaling preformed Cooper pairing, a finite uncondensed normal component persisting even at $T=0$, and the onset temperature $T_{\rm on,vortex}$ of vortex signals, offering a consistent understanding of how strong correlations and phase fluctuations cooperate to shape high-$T_c$ superconductivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21133v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Yang, Y. Shi, L. Q. Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic crystals in layered materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21222</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21222v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In modern two-dimensional (2D) materials, such as graphene-based systems and atomically-thin transition-metal dichalcogenides, the interplay of strong electronic correlations, tunable moir\'e superlattices, and nontrivial band topology has given rise to rich phase diagrams and collective phenomena. Among the novel phases that have been realized, electronic crystals -- states of matter in which itinerant electrons spontaneously crystallize -- play a particularly prominent role. In this Review, we summarize the current status of electron crystallization in van der Waals heterostructures, with emphasis on the experimental platforms and measurement techniques that enable their study. We also highlight open questions and outline future directions that may elucidate more of the fascinating properties of electronic crystals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21222v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>You Zhou, Ilya Esterlis, Tomasz Smole\'nski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological nontrivial berry phase in altermagnet CrSb</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21303</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21303v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The study of topological properties in magnetic materials has long been one of the forefront research areas in condensed matter physics. CrSb, as a prototypical candidate material for altermagnetism, has attracted significant attention due to its unique magnetic properties. This system provides a novel platform for exploring the intrinsic relationship between altermagnetic order and exotic topological states. In this study, we combine systematic electrical transport experiments with first-principles calculations to investigate the possible realization mechanisms of topological semimetal states in CrSb and their manifestations in quantum transport phenomena. Our high field magneto-transport measurements reveal that the magnetoresistance of CrSb exhibits no sign of saturation up to 35 T, following a distinct power-law dependence with an exponent of 1.48. The nonlinear Hall resistivity further indicates a multiband charge transport mechanism. Under high magnetic fields, we observe pronounced Shubnikov-de Haas (SdH) quantum oscillations and discernible Zeeman-effect-induced band splitting at 1.6 K. Systematic Fermi surface and band calculations combined with Berry phase analysis confirm the nontrivial topological character of this material (with a Berry phase approaching {\pi}). These findings not only provide crucial experimental evidence for understanding the electronic structure of CrSb, but also establish an important foundation for investigating topological quantum states in altermagnets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21303v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianhua Du, Xin Peng, Yuzhi Wang, Shengnan Zhang, Yuran Sun, Chunxiang Wu, Tingyu Zhou, Le Liu, Hangdong Wang, Jinhu Yang, Bin Chen, Chuanying Xi, Zhiwei Jiao, Quansheng Wu, Minghu Fang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The influence of boundary conditions and interfacial slip on the time taken to achieve a nonequilibrium steady-state for highly confined flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20944v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the equilibration time to attain steady-state for a system of liquid molecules under boundary-driven planar Couette flow via nonequilibrium molecular dynamics (NEMD) simulation. In particular, we examine the equilibration time for the two common types of boundary driven flow: one in which both walls slide with equal and opposite velocity, and the other in which one wall is fixed and the other moves with twice the velocity. Both flows give identical steady-state strain rates, and hence flow properties, but the transient behaviour is completely different. We find that in the case of no-slip boundary conditions, the equilibration times for the counter-sliding walls flow are exactly 4 times faster than those of the single sliding wall system, and this is independent of the atomistic nature of the fluid, i.e., it is an entirely hydrodynamic feature. We also find that systems that exhibit slip have longer equilibration times in general and the ratio of equilibration times for the two types of boundary-driven flow is even more pronounced. We analyse the problem by decomposing a generic planar Couette flow into a linear sum of purely symmetric and antisymmetric flows. We find that the no-slip equilibration time is dominated by the slowest decaying eigenvalue of the solution to the Navier-Stokes equation. In the case of slip, the longest relaxation time is now dominated by the transient slip velocity response, which is longer than the no-slip response time. In the case of a high-slip system of water confined to graphene channels, the enhancement is over two orders of magnitude.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20944v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carmelo Riccardo Civello, Luca Maffioli, Joseph Johnson, Edward R. Smith, James P. Ewen, Peter J. Daivis, Daniele Dini, B. D. Todd</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Peak separation methods for inverse photoelectron spectra: Comparing second derivative, curve fitting, and deconvolution analyses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21246</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21246v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Inverse photoelectron spectroscopy (IPES) is a powerful technique for probing the unoccupied electronic states of materials. It can be regarded as the inversion process of photoelectron spectroscopy (PES), which examines the occupied states. Recently developed low-energy inverse photoelectron spectroscopy (LEIPS) can significantly advance the study of unoccupied states, owing to an improved signal-to-noise ratio and minimal sample damage compared to conventional IPES. However, the instrumental resolution remains at 0.2 eV, which is one order of magnitude lower than that of PES. Spectral broadening caused by the low instrumental resolution often results in overlapping peaks. Peak separation is therefore crucial in the analysis of LEIPS spectra. In this study, we compared three peak separation methods: second derivative, curve fitting, and deconvolution. These methods were applied to modeled and experimental LEIPS spectra of the lowest unoccupied molecular orbital-derived band of pentacene, which consists of two splitting peaks due to the two inequivalent molecules in the unit cell. We systematically and quantitatively evaluated the performance of each method in terms of analysis parameters and discussed its robustness to noise as well as its peak separation capability. This work offers a practical framework for peak separation in LEIPS, with extensions to PES and a wide range of spectroscopies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21246v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryotaro Nakazawa, Haruki Sato, Hiroyuki Yoshida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Where Non-Invertible Symmetries End: Twist Defects for Electromagnetic Duality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21279</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21279v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study novel conformal twist defects in 4d Maxwell theory, around which electric and magnetic fields are exchanged. These are codimension-2 defects living at the end of topological defects for certain non-invertible global symmetries. We determine the operator spectrum of the twist defect by solving classical electromagnetic wave equations subject to a twisted boundary condition. Using techniques from defect CFT, we show that correlation functions of these defect operators factorize into two sectors: a universal generalized free-field sector, and a chiral current sector analogous to edge modes in Chern-Simons theory. In a similar setup, we also revisit the twist fields attached to non-invertible line defects in the 2d compact boson CFT. We discuss a defect 't Hooft anomaly involving a chiral $O(2)$ symmetry, highlighting its dynamical implications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21279v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shu-Heng Shao, Siwei Zhong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of ultra-flat band in van der Waals kagome semiconductor Pd3P2(S1-xSex)8</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.11222</link>
      <description>arXiv:2111.11222v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the evolutions of structural parameters, optical properties, and electronic structures of van der Waals kagome semiconductor Pd3P2S8 with Se doping. When the doping level of Se increases, the bandgaps of Pd3P2(S1-xSex)8 single crystals decrease gradually, accompanying with the expanded unit cells. The first-principles calculations show that there is a flat band (FB) near the Fermi level in bulk Pd3P2S8. This FB mainly originates from the dz2-like orbitals of Pd atoms in the Pd kagome lattice, which has a finite interlayer electron hopping perpendicular to the PdS4 square plane. The interlayer hopping can be reinforced with the Se doping, inducing a stronger interlayer coupling via the chalcogen atoms at apical sites, which reduces the bandgap and enhances the cleavage energy. In contrast, the vanishing interlayer hopping in the two-dimensional limit results in the formation of ultra-FB in the monolayers of these compounds. The easy exfoliation and the existence of unique ultra-FB near EF make Pd3P2(S1-xSex)8 a model system to explore the exotic physics of FB in two-dimensional kagome lattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2111.11222v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.105.155115</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 105, 155115 (2022)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shaohua Yan, Ben-Chao Gong, Lin Wang, Jinzhi Wu, Qiangwei Yin, Xinyu Cao, Xiao Zhang, Xiaofeng Liu, Zhong-Yi Lu, Kai Liu, Hechang Lei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rich unconventional Hall effects in a single quasi-kagome Kondo Weyl semimetal candidate Ce$_3$TiSb$_5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04438v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is generally believed that electronic correlation, geometric frustration, and topology, \textit{individually}, can facilitate the emergence of various intriguing properties that have attracted a broad audience for both fundamental research and potential applications. Here, we report a series of unconventional Hall effects observed in a \textit{single} compound - quasi-kagome Kondo Weyl semimetal candidate Ce$_3$TiSb$_5$. In the paramagnetic phase, signature of dynamic $c$-$f$ hybridization is revealed by a reduction of anomalous Hall effect and is connected to frustration-promoted incoherent Kondo scattering. A large topological Hall effect exceeding 0.2 $\mu\Omega\cdot$cm is found at low temperatures, which should be ascribed to the non-collinear magnetic texture. In addition, a peculiar loop-shaped Hall effect with switching chirality is also seen, which is inferred to be associated with magnetic domain walls that pin history-dependent spin chirality and / or Fermi-arc surface states projected from the in-gap Weyl nodes. These exotic results place Ce$_3$TiSb$_5$ in a regime of highly-frustrated antiferromagnetic dense Kondo lattice with a nontrivial topology on an ``extended" global phase diagram, and highlight the interplay among electronic correlation, geometric frustration and topology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04438v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s43246-025-00927-8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Communications Materials 6, 206 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xiaobo He, Ying Li, Yongheng Ge, Hai Zeng, Shi-Jie Song, Jie Liu, Shuo Zou, Zhuo Wang, Yuke Li, Wenxin Ding, Jianhui Dai, Guang-Han Cao, Xiao-Xiao Zhang, Tianyou Zhai, Gang Xu, Yongkang Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resolving space-time structures of quantum impurities with a numerically exact few-body algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13706</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13706v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a numerically exact real-time evolution scheme for quantum impurities in a macroscopically large bath. The algorithm is few-body revealing, namely it identifies the electronic orbitals that can be made inactive (in a trivial product state) by a time-dependent orbital rotation. Following a quench, we show that both the number of active orbitals and their associated matrix product state bond dimensions saturate to small values, leading to an algorithm dramatically more accurate and faster than the state of the art. We are thus able to follow the dynamics for thousands of fermions, up to the long-time stationary regime, and to study subtle aspects of quantum relaxation in the spatio-temporal domain, such as the emergence of entanglement structures in the Kondo screening cloud.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13706v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuriel N\'u\~nez-Fern\'andez, Maxime Debertolis, Serge Florens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Circular dichroism in resonant photoelectron diffraction as a direct probe of sublattice magnetization in altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08380</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08380v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Altermagnets are a new class of magnetic materials that are promising for spintronics technology. Here it is shown that in altermagnets, the circular dichroism (CD) in resonant photoelectron diffraction (RPED) contains a time-reversal odd signal, which provides a direct probe of the sublattice magnetization. RPED calculations are performed for MnTe at the Mn L$_{2,3}$-edge resonance, using a combination of atomic multiplet and multiple scattering theory. A large magnetic CD is found for light helicity parallel to the N\'eel vector. This signal has the same angular distribution as the difference between the structural RPED of the two magnetic sublattices and its amplitude is approximately proportional to the X-ray magnetic CD in absorption of a single sublattice, thus providing a direct probe of the local magnetic moments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08380v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/pl1p-v5rs</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Peter Kr\"uger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic structure and transport in materials with flat bands: 2D materials and quasicrystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.06721</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.06721v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this review, we present recent works on materials whose common point is the presence of electronic bands of very low dispersion, called "flat bands", which are due to specific atomic order effects without electron interactions. These states are always indicative of some form of confinement and have consequences on the electronic properties. A first part is devoted to the cases where this confinement is due to the long-range geometry of the defect-free structure. We have thus studied periodic approximant structures of quasiperiodic Penrose and octagonal tilings, and twisted bilayers of graphene (TBG) or transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) whose rotation angle between the two layers assumes a special value, called "magic angle". In these materials, the flat bands correspond to electronic states distributed over a very large number of atoms (several hundreds or even thousands of atoms). We have shown that their electronic transport properties cannot be described by usual Bloch-Boltzmann theories, because the interband terms of the velocity operator dominate the intraband terms as far as quantum diffusion is concerned. In the case of TBG, flat bands can induce a magnetic state and other electron-electron correlation effects. The second part focuses on two-dimensional nanomaterials in the presence of local point defects that cause resonant electronic states (vacancies, adsorbed atoms or molecules). We present studies on monolayer graphene, twisted or Bernal bilayer graphene, carbon nanotubes, monolayer and multilayer black phosphorene, and monolayer TMDs. A recent result is the discovery that the selective functionalization of a Bernal bilayer graphene sublattice leads to a metallic or insulating behavior depending on the functionalized sublattice type. This result suggests that functionalization can be a key parameter to control the electronic properties of 2D materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.06721v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physe.2025.116362</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physica E 175 (2026) 116362</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Guy Trambly de Laissardi\`ere, Somepalli Venkateswarlu, Ahmed Missaoui, Ghassen Jema\"i, Khouloud Chika, Javad Vahedi, Omid Faizy Namarvar, Jean-Pierre Julien, Andreas Honecker, Laurence Magaud, Jouda Jemaa Khabthani, Didier Mayou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudogap in the lightly hole-doped triangular-lattice moir\'e Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09586</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09586v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The electronic structure of the lightly hole-doped triangular-lattice moir\'e Hubbard model is studied within cluster perturbation theory (CPT) using 13-site clusters for a fixed doping concentration $p=1/13$ varying the Coulomb parameter $U$ and the hopping phase parameter $\phi$ related to the spin-orbital interaction. We have also developed a rather simple generalized mean-field approximation (GMFA) containing the amplitude of the spin correlations as a free parameter to fit the CPT data.The evolution of the Fermi surface and the pseudogap with the parameters $\phi$ and $U$ is explained from the viewpoint of the short-range magnetic order. The geometric frustration and the additional model parameter related to the spin-orbital interaction result in a more rich physics of the pseudogap state compared to the case of a more conventional square lattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09586v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/22j6-2p89</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 125131 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>V. I. Kuz'min, M. A. Visotin, S. G. Ovchinnikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phases and phase transitions of an $S=3/2$ chain on metallic and semi-metallic surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11392v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Motivated by recent scanning tunneling microscopy experiments on chains of Co adatoms on Cu surfaces, we investigate the physics of a spin-$3/2$ Heisenberg chain with single-ion anisotropy ($D$) on metallic and semi-metallic surfaces. In the strong Kondo coupling ($J_k$) limit, a perturbative analysis maps the system onto a Haldane spin-1 chain with single-ion anisotropy, ferromagnetically coupled to the metallic surface. This Haldane state, arising from underscreening of the $S=3/2$ chain, is stable against small $D$ and characterized by topological edge modes. The nature of the $D$-driven transitions out of this state depends on the environment. Coupling to a metal (semi-metal) is a relevant (irrelevant) perturbation at the decoupled fixed point between the spin-1 chain and the two-dimensional electron gas. In the large positive $D$ limit, the system maps onto an anisotropic spin-$1/2$ Kondo system. For large negative $D$, in the Ising phase, spins are frozen. For small $J_k$, the nature of the metallic phase dominates. On a two-dimensional semi-metal, the Kondo coupling is irrelevant at the decoupled fixed point ($J_k= 0$), leading to a Kondo breakdown phase at weak coupling, irrespective of $D$. In contrast, on a two-dimensional metal, the resulting dissipative Ohmic bath is a marginally relevant perturbation, inducing antiferromagnetic ordering along the chain. In this case, $D$ drives a spin-flop transition between Ising and XY ordered phases. At $D=0$, we observe continuous transitions between the Kondo breakdown or dissipation-induced long-range ordered phases and the underscreened Haldane phase. These phase diagrams are supported by scaling arguments and sign-free auxiliary-field quantum Monte Carlo simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11392v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bimla Danu, Fakher F. Assaad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
