<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 01:28:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital dependent Coulomb drag in electron-hole bilayer graphene heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09313v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report Coulomb drag studies in an electron-hole bilayer graphene heterostructure in a magnetic field, where the orbital, spin, and valley degrees of freedom are lifted by the combined effects of exchange interaction, Zeeman energy, and vertical displacement field. Our device enables the application of a large vertical displacement field in both layers. In addition to the well-established strong Coulomb drag between Landau levels with an orbital quantum number N = 0, we observe a Coulomb drag signal between the N = 1 Landau levels under a suitable vertical displacement field. As the displacement field increases further, the Coulomb drag signal between N = 1 Landau levels weakens, and a Coulomb drag signal emerges between the N = 0 and N = 1 Landau levels. These findings suggest the important roles of the orbital index and vertical displacement field in interlayer Coulomb interactions within the quantum Hall regime of coupled bilayer systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09313v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zuocheng Zhang, Ruishi Qi, Jingxu Xie, Qize Li, Takashi Taniguchi, Kenji Watanabe, Michael F. Crommie, Feng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trigonal warping enables linear optical spectroscopy in single-valley superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09387</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09387v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In superconductors with multiple pairing channels, Bardasis-Schrieffer modes and clapping modes arise as fluctuations in channels whose angular momenta differ from that of the pair condensate. Crystal symmetries often impose selection rules which keep these modes optically dark. We show that if pairing occurs around a single Fermi surface, trigonal warping renders both of these modes, as well as the quasiparticle excitation gap, visible in the longitudinal and Hall optical responses. Our results suggest that rhombohedral graphene multilayers, which are believe to host the required ingredients, might offer an ideal setting for the study of exotic superconducting collective modes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09387v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin A. Levitan, \'Etienne Lantagne-Hurtubise</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energetically Favored One-Dimensional Moir\'e Superstructure in the Pseudo-Square Lattice GdTe3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09434</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09434v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Moir\'e engineering in layered crystals has recently gained considerable attention due to the discovery of various structural and physical phenomena, including interfacial reconstruction, superconductivity, magnetism, and distinctive optoelectronic properties. Nevertheless, most explored moir\'e systems have been limited to hexagonal lattices, thereby constraining a comprehensive understanding and technological application of moir\'e phenomena in general layered crystals. Here, we investigate GdTe3, a pseudo-tetragonal layered crystal, as a platform to explore unconventional moir\'e phenomena. GdTe3 exhibits a slight in-plane distortion correlated with the direction of charge density wave formation. Through vertical stacking of layers with different distortions-induced via a controlled strain/release process-we realize energetically favorable one-dimensional (1D) moir\'e superstructures. Using transmission electron microscopy (TEM), including high-resolution scanning TEM imaging, dark-field TEM imaging, and sample tilting experiments, we systematically examine stacking variations across the 1D moir\'e structure. Additionally, electron energy loss spectroscopy reveals modulations in electronic properties associated with the 1D moir\'e structure. Our findings expand the scope of moir\'e systems beyond conventional hexagonal twistronics, enabling exploration of moir\'e phenomena in low-symmetry van der Waals crystals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09434v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acsnano.5c09994</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ACS Nano (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jieun Yeon, Kihyun Lee, Myeongjin Jang, Tae Keun Yun, Jongho Park, Changyoung Kim, Kwanpyo Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Giant Shift Current in Electrically-Tunable Superlattice Bilayer Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09465</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09465v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent introduction of superlattice potentials has opened new avenues for engineering tunable electronic band structures featuring topologically nontrivial moir\'{e}-like bands. Here we consider optoelectronic properties of Bernal-stacked graphene subjected to a superlattice potential either electrostatically or through lattice twisting to show that it exhibits a giant shift current response that is orders of magnitude larger than existing predictions in twisted mulitlayer systems. Effects of gate voltage and the strength and phase of the superlattice potential on the shift current are delineated systematically across various topological regimes. Our study gives insight into the nature of nonlinear responses of materials and how these responses could be optimized by tuning the superlattice potential.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09465v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nabil Atlam, Swati Chaudhary, Arpit Raj, Matthew Matzelle, Barun Ghosh, Gregory A. Fiete, Arun Bansil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mechanical Force-Driven Charge Redistribution for Hydrogen Release at Ambient Conditions in Transition Metal-Intercalated Bilayer Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09501</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09501v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Transition-metal (TM) atom-functionalized nanomaterials are promising candidates for hydrogen storage due to their ability to adsorb multiple hydrogen molecules through Kubas interactions. However, achieving efficient hydrogen desorption at ambient conditions remains a critical challenge for practical use. Here, we present a novel approach to modulate the desorption temperature of hydrogen in TM-intercalated bilayer graphene (BLG) using external mechanical forces. By employing first-principles density functional theory (DFT) and thermodynamic occupancy probability calculations, we demonstrate that adjusting the interlayer distance allows for precise control over the interaction energy of H2, thereby facilitating its desorption at ambient conditions. Complete hydrogen desorption occurs when the interlayer distance is reduced below 4.7 {\AA}, 5.3 {\AA}, and 5.1 {\AA} for Sc-, Ti-, and V-intercalated BLG, respectively. Our findings suggest that external mechanical forces can effectively bring hydrogen occupancy to zero by minimizing charge transfer from the TM d-orbitals to H2 antibonding orbitals. Notably, while the total charge transferred from the TM atoms remains nearly constant at varying interlayer distances, its redistribution between the graphene layers and H2 fine-tunes the interaction strength. This approach can be extended to large interlayer distances, as supported by recent experiments on graphene oxide membranes [ACS Nano 12, 9309 (2018)]. Furthermore, recent experimental advances in noble gas and alkali metal intercalation in BLG highlight the potential of this approach to overcome the long-standing challenge of high desorption temperatures in TM-functionalized layered nanomaterials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09501v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jongdeok Kim, Vikram Mahamiya, Massimiliano Di Ventra, Hoonkyung Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Twist-angle tunable Josephson junctions in three-dimensional superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09551v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We theoretically investigate the superconducting phase and perpendicular Josephson supercurrent in twisted three-dimensional (3D) superconductors, where two layered 3D materials are stacked with a relative twist. We formulate the Bogoliubov-de Gennes Hamiltonian and develop a self-consistent method to calculate the superconducting order parameter and the resulting supercurrent. Applying this framework to a toy model with Fermi surfaces located near the Brillouin zone corners, we demonstrate a phase discontinuity at the twisted interface, indicating that a Josephson junction is formed purely by the twist. Our calculations reveal that the interface supports a finite critical current even when the Fermi surfaces of the two superconductors are completely separated, unlike in the case of a twisted normal-metal interface. We further show that the critical current can be effectively controlled by the twist angle, transitioning from a high-transparency regime at small angles to a low-transparency regime at larger angles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09551v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tenta Tani, Takuto Kawakami, Mikito Koshino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical phonons as a testing ground for spin group symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09793</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09793v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Lattice vibrations are highly sensitive to crystal symmetries and their changes across phase transitions. The latter can modify irreducible (co)representations and corresponding infrared and Raman selection rules of phonons. This concept is established for relativistic magnetic point groups, simultaneously transforming spatial and spin coordinates. However, in altermagnets described by non-relativistic spin groups with disjunct symmetry operations for both vector spaces, the phonon selection rules have remained unexplored. Here, we present a detailed study of the infrared- and Raman-active modes in the collinear antiferromagnet and altermagnet candidate Co$_2$Mo$_3$O$_8$. Comparing to ab initio calculations accurately capturing the eigenfrequencies, we identify all expected phonon modes at room temperature and deduce their selection rules using both symmetry approaches. Importantly, we observe the change of selection rules upon antiferromagnetic ordering, agreeing with the relativistic symmetry approach, while the spin group formalism predicts no changes. Therefore, optical phonons can reveal the appropriate symmetry treatment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09793v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Schilberth, M. Kond\'akor, D. Ukolov, A. Pawbake, K. Vasin, O. Ercem, L. Prodan, V. Tsurkan, A. A. Tsirlin, C. Faugeras, P. Lemmens, K. Penc, I. K\'ezsm\'arki, S. Bord\'acs, J. Deisenhofer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Doping Evolution of Nodal Electron Dynamics in Trilayer Cuprate Superconductor Bi$_2$Sr$_2$Ca$_2$Cu$_3$O$_{10+\delta}$ Revealed by Laser-Based Angle-Resolved Photoemission Spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09881</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09881v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The doping evolution of the nodal electron dynamics in the trilayer cuprate superconductor Bi$_2$Sr$_2$Ca$_2$Cu$_3$O$_{10+\delta}$ (Bi2223) is investigated using high-resolution laser-based angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES). Bi2223 single crystals with different doping levels are prepared by controlled annealing which cover the underdoped, optimally-doped and overdoped regions. The electronic phase diagram of Bi2223 is established which describes the T$_\mathrm{c}$ dependence on the sample doping level. The doping dependence of the nodal Fermi momentum for the outer (OP) and inner (IP) CuO$_2$ planes is determined. Charge distribution imbalance between the OP and IP CuO$_2$ planes is quantified, showing enhanced disparity with increasing doping. Nodal band dispersions demonstrate a prominent kink at $\sim$94$\,$meV in the IP band, attributed to the unique Cu coordination in the IP plane, while a weaker $\sim$60$\,$meV kink is observed in the OP band. The nodal Fermi velocity of both OP and IP bands is nearly constant at $\sim$1.62$\,$eV\r{A} independent of doping. These results provide important information to understand the origin of high T$_\mathrm{c}$ and superconductivity mechanism in high temperature cuprate superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09881v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1674-1056/addcc6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chinese Physics B 34, 077404 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hao Chen, Jumin Shi, Xiangyu Luo, Yinghao Li, Yiwen Chen, Chaohui Yin, Yingjie Shu, Jiuxiang Zhang, Taimin Miao, Bo Liang, Wenpei Zhu, Neng Cai, Xiaolin Ren, Chengtian Lin, Shenjin Zhang, Zhimin Wang, Fengfeng Zhang, Feng Yang, Qinjun Peng, Zuyan Xu, Guodong Liu, Hanqing Mao, Xintong Li, Lin Zhao, X. J. Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-chirality-dependent modulation of topological gap, Chern number, and valley-polarization in monolayer Kagome materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09884v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Kagome materials exhibit unique electronic properties, such as the quantum anomalous Hall effect. The control of Chern numbers is critical for quantum device manipulation, but existing research has mainly focused on collinear magnetization while neglecting chiral spin textures. Through first-principles calculations and tight-binding modeling of monolayer Cr3Se4, this study reveals spin chirality-dependent control of topological gaps, Chern numbers, and valley polarization in kagome materials. The results demonstrate that the azimuthal angle has no observable effect. For collinear magnetization, the topological bandgap decreases as the spin orientation approaches the in-plane direction. In the breathing Kagome lattice, the degeneracy between K and K' valleys is lifted, and increasing the polar angle induces successive closing and reopening of the valleys. For chiral spin textures, increasing polar angle enlarges the bandgap when chirality \k{appa} = 1, while reducing it when \k{appa} = -1. Moreover, spin chirality enables the quantum anomalous Hall state without spin-orbit coupling. Structural asymmetry and spin chirality effectively modulate the bandgap, Chern number, and valley polarization. These findings provide strategies for controlling topological states and advancing applications in quantum devices and valleytronic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09884v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenzhe Zhou, Guibo Zheng, Yating Li, Zhenzhen Wan, Aolin Li, Fangping Ouyang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strain-driven feedback tunes memory and relaxation in a Mott insulator far from equilibrium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09916</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09916v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Memory effects in metal-insulator transitions in quantum materials reveal complex physics and potential for novel technologies mimicking biological neural systems. Nonetheless, understanding of memory and nonlinearity in non-equilibrium transitions remains elusive as they can involve timescales from femtoseconds to microseconds. In this study, we extend time-resolved x-ray Bragg diffraction to the necessary high dynamic range of timescales to fully trace the pathways of far-from-equilibrium photoexcited transitions in epitaxial films of V2O3, a technologically promising prototypical Mott insulator. We find a 105 times adjustment in relaxation time: the memory of spatial and energy heterogeneity during transition causes a Kohlrausch-Williams-Watts shaped relaxation lingering over a hundred microseconds versus nanoseconds. The dramatic slowdown in the light-driven highly correlated system accompanies heterogeneous excitation barriers, as in neural systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09916v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>O. Yu. Gorobtsov, Y. Kalcheim, Z. Shao, A. Shabalin, N. Hua, D. Weinstock, R. Bouck, M. Seaberg, D. Zhu, O. G. Shpyrko, I. K. Schuller, A. Singer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Untwisted and Twisted R\'enyi Negativities: Toward a R\'enyi Proxy for Logarithmic Negativity in Fermionic Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07731</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.07731v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Entanglement entropy is a fundamental measure of quantum entanglement for pure states, but for large-scale many-body systems, R\'{e}nyi entanglement entropy is much more computationally accessible. For mixed states, logarithmic negativity (LN) serves as a widely used entanglement measure, but its direct computation is often intractable, leaving R\'{e}nyi negativity (RN) as the practical alternative. In fermionic systems, RN is further classified into untwisted and twisted types, depending on the definition of the fermionic partial transpose. However, which of these serves as the true R\'{e}nyi proxy for LN has remained unclear -- until now. In this work, we address this question by developing a robust quantum Monte Carlo (QMC) method to compute both untwisted and twisted RNs, focusing on the rank-4 twisted RN, where non-trivial behavior emerges. We identify and overcome two major challenges: the singularity of the Green's function matrix and the exponentially large variance of RN estimators. Our method is demonstrated in the Hubbard model and the spinless $t$-$V$ model, revealing critical distinctions between untwisted and twisted RNs, as well as between rank-2 and high-rank RNs. Remarkably, we find that the twisted R\'{e}nyi negativity ratio (RNR) adheres to the area law and decreases monotonically with temperature, in contrast to the untwisted RNR but consistent with prior studies of bosonic systems. This study not only establishes the twisted RNR as a more pertinent R\'{e}nyi proxy for LN in fermionic systems but also provides comprehensive technical details for the stable and efficient computation of high-rank RNs. Our work lays the foundation for future studies of mixed-state entanglement in large-scale fermionic many-body systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.07731v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fo-Hong Wang, Xiao Yan Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frequency dependence of temporal spin stiffness and short-range magnetic order in the doped two-dimensional Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20714</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20714v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study doping and temperature dependencies of temporal and spatial spin stiffnesses of the Hubbard model within the mean field approach for incommensurate magnetic order. We show that the frequency dependence of temporal spin stiffness within the considered mean-field approach is crucial to obtain small values of correlation length, comparable to those observed in cuprates. Using the obtained spin stiffnesses, we obtain the temperature and doping dependence of correlation length within the large-$N$ limit of the respective nonlinear sigma model. In agreement with the experimental data on La$_{2-x}$Sr$_x$CuO$_4$ we obtain short range magnetic order with relatively small correlation length at $0.1 \lesssim x\lesssim 0.2$, and magnetically ordered ground state in the narrow doping region $0.05\lesssim x \lesssim 0.1$. The latter state may correspond to the spin-frosen state, observed in the experimental data on La$_{2-x}$Sr$_x$CuO$_4$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20714v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/w4vc-n5l6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, L060405 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>I. A. Goremykin, A. A. Katanin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrafast Raman probe of the photoinduced superconducting to normal state transition in the cuprate Bi$_2$Sr$_2$CaCu$_2$O$_{8+\delta}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.04385v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report an ultrafast Time-Resolved Raman scattering study of the out-of-equilibrium photoinduced dynamics across the superconducting to normal state phase transition of the cuprate Bi$_2$Sr$_2$CaCu$_2$O$_{8+\delta}$. Using the polarization-resolved momentum space selectivity of Raman scattering, we track the superconducting condensate destruction and recovery dynamics with sub-picoseconds time resolution in the anti-nodal region of the Fermi surface where the superconducting gap is maximum. Leveraging ultrafast Raman thermometry, we find a significant dichotomy between the superconducting condensate and the quasiparticle temperature dynamics near the anti-nodes, which cannot be framed in terms of a single effective electron temperature. The present work demonstrates the ability of Time-Resolved Raman scattering to selectively probe out-of-equilibrium pathways of different electronic sub-degrees of freedom during a photoinduced phase transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.04385v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laur\`ene Gatuingt, Alexandr Alekhin, Niloufar Nilforoushan, Sarah Houver, Alain Sacuto, Genda Gu, Yann Gallais</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement mediated by DC current induced nonreciprocal graphene plasmonics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.10085</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.10085v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate entanglement mediated by DC current induced nonreciprocal graphene plasmon polaritons. Nonreciprocal systems are ideal for the enhancement, control, and preservation of entanglement due to the potential for unidirectional beam-like wave propagation, i.e., efficiently transporting photons from one emitter to another. Using a quantum master equation and three-dimensional Green's function analysis, we investigate a system consisting of two two-level emitters dominantly interacting via electric current induced nonreciprocal plasmonic modes of a graphene waveguide. We use concurrence as a measure of entanglement. We show that nonreciprocal graphene plasmon polaritons are a promising candidate to generate and mediate concurrence, where it is shown that there is good enhancement and control of entanglement over vacuum, which is beneficial for the broad applications of entanglement as a quantum resource. We believe our findings contribute to the development of quantum devices, enabling efficient and tunable entanglement between two-level systems, which is a central goal in quantum technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.10085v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1364/OE.473847</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jay A. Berres, S. Ali Hassani Gangaraj, George W. Hanson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defect Engineered Layer Dependent Nonlinear Optical Response in Two Dimensional Muscovite for Efficient Optical Limiting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14786v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Light-matter interactions in two-dimensional (2D) materials have gained significant interest due to their distinctive optical and electronic properties. Recently, silicates have emerged as a promising new class of 2D materials, but their nonlinear optical properties remain largely unexplored. In this study, we demonstrate layer-dependent nonlinear absorption and optical limiting capabilities of 2D muscovite using femtosecond laser excitation at 450 nm. The two-photon absorption (TPA) coefficient is highly sensitive to both the number of layers and excitation intensity, increasing markedly from (3.91+/-0.06)x10^3 cm GW^-1 in multilayer structures to (6.94+/-0.17)x10^5 cm GW^-1 in the monolayer limit at a peak intensity of 68 GW cm^-2, highlighting a strong layer-dependent enhancement in nonlinear absorption. Additionally, monolayer muscovite exhibits an optical limiting threshold of 1.46 mJ cm^-2, outperforming graphene and other 2D dichalcogenides. This enhanced TPA arises from quantum confinement and intrinsic lattice defects that facilitate nonlinear optical transitions. Density functional theory reveals that liquid-phase exfoliation disrupts potassium interlayers and induces oxygen vacancies, generating mid-gap electronic states that significantly enhance TPA. These insights open new avenues for designing low-fluence, high-efficiency optical limiters using 2D silicates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14786v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dipanwita Mitra, Guilherme S. L. Fabris, Raphael Benjamim, Mateus M. Ferrer, Marcelo Lopes Pereira Junior, Riya Sadhukhan, Dipak Kumar Goswami, Gelu Costin, Douglas S. Galv\~ao, Chandra Sekhar Tiwary, Prasanta Kumar Dattaa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
