<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 04:00:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Superdielectrics: Disorder-induced perfect screening in insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14962v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the relationship between the quantities that encode the insulating properties of matter: the ground-state quantum metric, the average localization length, and the electric susceptibility. By examining the one-dimensional Anderson insulator model and the Su-Schrieffer-Heeger chain with chiral disorder, we demonstrate that the former two measures are proportional in one-dimensional systems near criticality, and both are determined by the properties of the hybridized localized states around the Fermi energy. We employ these insights to demonstrate that the behavior of the electric susceptibility is drastically different in the bond-disordered SSH chain, with the possibility that it may diverge even when the localization length and the quantum metric remain finite. This divergence, caused by the proliferation of impurity resonances at a particular energy, leads to a novel regime that exhibits mixed characteristics of metals and insulators. We term this regime superdielectric: an insulating state characterized by a finite quantum metric and divergent static electric susceptibility, which implies perfect screening in the absence of the dc conductivity. We demonstrate that the superdielectric phase also emerges in higher-dimensional materials, such as graphene with vacancies and Kekul\'e bond distortion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14962v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ilia Komissarov, Tobias Holder, Raquel Queiroz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Superexchange: Emergent Unconventional Ferromagnetism in Thin-Film Sandwich Structures of Intrinsic Magnetic Topological Insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14993</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14993v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we investigate the nature of magnetic interactions in intrinsic magnetic topological insulator Mn(Bi1-xSbx)2Te4 (MBST in short) systems, which possesses highly-ordered ferromagnetic septuple-layers (SLs), using two types of structures: MBST(1 SL)/(Bi1-xSbx)2Te3 heterostructures and MBST(1 SL)/(Bi1-xSbx)2Te3/MBST(1 SL) sandwich structures. The out-of-plane magnetization in the sandwich structure turned out to be significantly larger than that in the heterostructure, indicating that the interlayer magnetic interaction between two MBST layers is ferromagnetic. Furthermore, the Curie temperature increased with decreasing the in-plane Mn-Mn distance in the MBST layer, which suggests the enhancement of the intralayer ferromagnetic interaction within each MBST layer. Meanwhile, in the sandwich structures with various spacer thicknesses, the Curie temperature with the spacer layer was higher than that with no spacer layer. In addition, the curve shape of anomalous Hall effects for the sandwich structure was almost unchanged by carrier-density modulation, which implies that the ferromagnetism in this system is carrier-independent. Based on the above results, magnetic behaviors in our systems cannot be explained only by the direct exchange nor superexchange interactions reported previously for MBST systems, and are instead proposed to arise from topology-related mechanisms such as the van Vleck and Bloembergen-Rowland mechanisms. This work provides a new perspective on magnetic mechanisms in MBST systems, which helps us to realize next-generation spintronic and electronic devices by flexibly controlling magnetism in intrinsic magnetic topological insulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14993v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takuya Takashiro, Ryota Akiyama, Ryotaro Minakawa, Shuji Hasegawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Magnetic Properties of RuO$_{2}$ Heterostructures Through the Ferromagnetic Layer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15004</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15004v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: RuO$_{2}$ has been proposed as the prototypical altermagnetic material. However, several reports have recently questioned its intrinsic magnetic ordering, leading to conflicting findings, especially in thin film heterostructures pointing to possible interface effects being convoluted with supposed antiferromagnetic/altermagnetic signatures. Here, extensive magnetometry measurements were performed on two independently grown thin film heterostructures of RuO$_{2}$ interfaced with either NiFe or Fe acting as the ferromagnetic layer. Below about 15 K, both samples exhibit exchange bias fields when cooled to approximately 2 K in a $+$1 T field, and a spin transitional feature is observed around 31 K. Magneto-Raman measurements on RuO$_{2}$ thin films only reveal a magnon mode when there is a NiFe layer, suggesting that RuO$_{2}$ does not intrinsically possess long range magnetic ordering.. When in contact with a ferromagnet, RuO$_2$ displays effects that could be ascribed to antiferromagnetism. However, the lack of intrinsic magnon modes points toward possible diffusion between the layers or spin disorder at the interface as seen by density functional theory (DFT) calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15004v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Frank M. Abel, Subhash Bhatt, Shelby S. Fields, Vinay Sharma, Dai Q. Ho, Daniel Wines, D. Quang To, Joseph C. Prestigiacomo, Tehseen Adel, Riccardo Torsi, Maria F. Munoz, David T. Plouff, Xinhao Wang, Brian Donovan, Don Heiman, Gregory M. Stephen, Adam L. Friedman, Garnett W. Bryant, Anderson Janotti, Michelle E. Jamer, Angela R. Hight Walker, John Q. Xiao, Steven P. Bennett</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theoretical Study of Impurity Effects on Superconductivity in UTe2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15147</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15147v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study investigates the impurity effects on UTe2 within the self-consistent Born approximation using the six-orbital f-d-p model which contains two uranium and tellurium atoms in the minimum unit cell. We analyze the dependence of superconducting transition temperature (Tc) on impurity concentration for various pairing symmetries proposed by experiments and theories. It clarifies that the decrease of Tc significantly depends on which atom sites the impurities reside. Particulalry, the analysis shows that the impurity at U-site has dominant effect on the change of Tc. Then, either the singlet state in the case of magnetic impurities or the triplet states in both non-magnetic and magnetic impurities are consistent with experiments. Thus, this indicates that elucidating the magnetic properties of impurities (i.e. magnetic or non-magnetic) is crucial for identifying the pairing symmetry of UTe2.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15147v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Koki Doi, Shingo Haruna, Mutsuki Iwamoto, Takuji Nomura, Hirono Kaneyasu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radio-Frequency Quantum Rectification in Kagome Superconductor CsV3Sb5</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15266v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rectification of electromagnetic fields into direct current (DC) is pivotal for energy harvesting, wireless charging, and next-generation communication technologies. The superconducting diode effect, which exploits the nonreciprocal transport of dissipationless superconducting currents, offers ultra-low power consumption and high rectification ratios. Combining the superconducting diode effect with the AC Josephson effect holds promise for converting radio-frequency (rf) irradiation into a quantized DC output. However, experimental realization has been hindered by challenges in achieving the necessary symmetry breaking and fabricating high-performance Josephson junctions. Here we demonstrate the quantum rectification in kagome superconductor CsV3Sb5, which hosts emergent Josephson effects and a zero-field Josephson diode. Under rf irradiation, a DC voltage emerges without applied bias, scaling linearly with frequency as V = hf/2e, where h is Planck's constant, f is the microwave frequency, and e is the electron charge. Furthermore, the rectified voltage exhibits quantized steps with increasing rf power, consistent with Shapiro step quantization. Our work establishes CsV3Sb5 as a versatile platform for wireless quantum power supplies and charging, and underscores the intertwined order parameters as a promising pathway for precise quantum matter control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15266v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Han-Xin Lou, Jing-Jing Chen, Xing-Guo Ye, Zhen-Bing Tan, An-Qi Wang, Qing Yin, Xin Liao, Jing-Zhi Fang, Xing-Yu Liu, Yi-Lin He, Zhen-Tao Zhang, Chuan Li, Zhong-Ming Wei, Xiu-Mei Ma, Dapeng Yu, Zhi-Min Liao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constrained Random Phase Approximation: the spectral method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15368</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15368v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a new constrained Random Phase Approximation (cRPA) method, termed spectral cRPA (s-cRPA), and compare it to established cRPA approaches for Scandium and Copper by varying the 3d shell filling. The s-cRPA consistently yields larger Hubbard $U$ interaction values. Applied to the realistic system CaFeO$_3$, s-cRPA produces interaction parameters significantly closer to those required within DFT+$U$ to induce the experimentally observed insulating state, overcoming the metallic behavior predicted by standard density functionals. We also address the issue of negative interaction values found in the projector cRPA method for filled d-shells, demonstrating that s-cRPA offers superior numerical stability through electron conversion. Overall, s-cRPA is more robust and effectively overcomes the known underestimation of $U$ in standard cRPA, making it a promising tool for the community. Additionally, we have enhanced our implementation with features for computing multi-center interactions to analyze spatial decay and developed a low-scaling variant with a compressed Matsubara grid to efficiently obtain full frequency-dependent interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15368v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Merzuk Kaltak, Alexander Hampel, Martin Schlipf, Indukuru Ramesh Reddy, Bongae Kim, Georg Kresse</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bending nanoribbon to induce large anisotropic magnetoconductance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15385v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: When a nanoribbon is bent under a homogeneous external magnetic field, the effective magnetic field inside becomes either homogeneous or inhomogeneous, depending on the direction of the field. This enables the selective creation of bulk, interface, and edge magnetic states in the bent structure, for a magnetic field with a strength. We establish theoretically that these tuneable states lead to a strong geometry-induced anisotropic magnetoconductance (GAMC) in perpendicularly bent nanoribbon, which can reach up to 100\%. Moreover, the GAMC can be further enhanced to 200\%, 300\%, or even higher by either further bending or tuning the bending angle. The potential of this phenomenon for practical applications is demonstrated by its stable anisotropy, which remains consistent across a wide range of Fermi energies, can be observed even at weak magnetic fields and room temperature, and occurs in various systems such as two-dimensional electron gas (2DEG) and graphene.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15385v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ponder Liu, Hao-Cheng Hung, You-Ting Huang, Jia-Cheng Li, Carmine Ortix, Ching-Hao Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Geometric Renormalization of the Hall Coefficient and Unconventional Hall Resistivity in ZrTe5</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15450</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15450v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The anomalous Hall effect (AHE), conventionally associated with time-reversal symmetry breaking in ferromagnetic materials, has recently been observed in nonmagnetic topological materials, raising questions about its origin. We unravel the unconventional Hall response in the nonmagnetic Dirac material ZrTe5, known for its massive Dirac bands and unique electronic and transport properties. Using the Kubo-Streda formula within the Landau level framework, we explore the interplay of quantum effects induced by the magnetic field (B) and disorder across the semiclassical and quantum regimes. In the semiclassical regime, the Hall resistivity remains linear in the magnetic field, but the Hall coefficient will be renormalized by the quantum geometric effects and electron-hole coherence, especially at low carrier densities where the disorder scattering dominates. In quantum limit, the Hall conductivity exhibits an unsaturating 1/B scaling. As a result, the transverse conductivity dominates transport in the ultra-quantum limit, and the Hall resistivity crosses over from B to B^{-1} dependence as the system transitions from the semiclassical regime to the quantum limit. This work elucidates the mechanisms underlying the unconventional Hall effect in ZrTe5 and provides insights into the AHE in other nonmagnetic Dirac materials as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15450v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huimin Xie, Bo Fu, Huan-Wen Wang, Wenyu Shan, Shun-Qing Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rotating Spin Wave Modes in Nanoscale M\"obius Strips</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15463</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15463v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Curved and topologically nontrivial magnetic structures offer new pathways to control spin-wave behavior beyond planar geometries. Here, we study spin-wave dynamics in M\"obius-shaped soft-magnetic nanostrips using micromagnetic simulations. By comparing single-, double-, and triple-twisted M\"obius strips to a topologically trivial bent ring, we isolate the roles of helical twist and non-orientable topology. M\"obius geometries exhibit non-degenerate mode doublets associated with counterpropagating spin waves, in contrast to the standing-wave doublets in the trivial case. This splitting arises from a twist-induced geometric (Berry) phase that breaks propagation symmetry, producing non-reciprocal dispersion relations. The M\"obius topology further imposes antisymmetric boundary conditions, resulting in half-integer wavelength quantization. Local RF excitation allows for the selective generation of spin waves with defined frequency and direction. An analytical model reproduces the dispersion behavior with excellent agreement. These results highlight how geometric and topological design can be leveraged to engineer spin-wave transport in three-dimensional magnonic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15463v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashfaque Thonikkadavan, Massimiliano d'Aquino, Riccardo Hertel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On-the-fly electrical readout of individual skyrmion dynamics by anomalous Hall effect, correlated with real-time Kerr microscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15519</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15519v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic skyrmions, topologically stabilized spin textures, are promising candidates for future memory devices and non-conventional computing applications due to their enhanced stability, non-linear interactions, and low-power manipulation capabilities. Despite their significant potential, the reliable electrical readout of individual skyrmions remains a fundamental challenge. While magnetic tunnel junctions and anomalous-Hall-effect-based techniques have demonstrated skyrmion detection capabilities, they currently fail to reliably detect single moving skyrmions as required for applications. Our approach leverages thermally activated skyrmions, where a low constant drive current simultaneously generates both skyrmion motion and the Hall voltage necessary for detection. We demonstrate the reliability of this method through real-time correlation between measured Hall voltage signals and direct Kerr microscopy imaging. Two consecutive Hall crosses allow for determining the skyrmion velocity, in accordance to Kerr microscopy videos. These advances establish a robust platform for skyrmion-based sensors, counters and unconventional computing systems that depend on precise individual skyrmion control and detection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15519v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grischa Beneke, Kilian Leutner, Nikhil Vijayan, Fabian Kammerbauer, Duc Minh Tran, Sachin Krishnia, Johannes G\"uttinger, Armin Satz, Robert Fr\"omter, Mathias Kl\"aui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NMR evidence for an antisite-induced magnetic moment on Bi in a topological insulator heterostructures MnBi2Te4/(Bi2Te3)n</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15527v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: MnBi2Te4 (MBT) is the first intrinsic magnetic topological insulator, combining a topologically protected surface metallic state and intrinsic magnetic order. A structural compatibility with the nonmagnetic Bi2Te4 (BT) parent compound gives a possibility to create MBT/BT heterostructures and manipulate their magnetic state in view of optimizing the Quantum Anomalous Hall Effect (QAHE). In this work an extensive NMR study, supported by the bulk magnetization measurements has been performed at 4.2 K on a self-organized single crystal MnBi2Te4(Bi2Te4)n heterostructure. 55Mn and 209Bi NMR signal have been recorded as a function of the out-of-plane magnetic field up to 6T, covering a spin-flop transition from the antiferromagnetic (AFM) to the canted antiferromagnetic (CAFM) configuration of the Mn layers. Structural defects were shown to contribute a small ferromagnetic component below the spin-flop field. Presence of the AFM-coupled Mn antisites has been evidenced and shown to induce an antiparallel magnetic moment on Bi atoms within the host Bi layer. Detection of the induced magnetic moment on bismuth which contributes a new ferromagnetic component is of utmost importance for understanding the magnetic interactions in the MBT/BT system. These findings have potentially important implications for engineering the QAH devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15527v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Kalvig, E. Jedryka, A. Lynnyk, P. Skupinski, K. Grasza, M. Wojcik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Taxonomy of defects in semi-dry transferred CVD graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15549</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15549v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Post-transfer in-depth morphological characterization of graphene grown by chemical vapor deposition (CVD) is of great importance to evaluate the quality and to understand the origin of defects of the transferred sheets. Herein, a semi-dry transfer technique is used to peel off millimeter-sized CVD graphene flakes from polycrystalline copper foils and transfer them onto SiO2/Si substrates. We take advantage of the unique feature of this semi-dry process: it preserves the copper substrate, enabling location-specific morphological comparisons between graphene and copper at various stages of the transfer. Thanks to a combination of morphological characterization techniques, this leads to trace and elucidate the origin of various post-transfer graphene defects (cracks, wrinkles, holes, tears). Specifically, thermally induced wrinkles are shown to evolve into nanoscale cracks, while copper surface steps lead to folds. Furthermore, we find that the macroscale topography of the copper foil also plays a critical role in defect formation. This work provides guidelines on how to correctly interpret the post-transfer morphology of graphene films on relevant substrates and how to properly assess their quality. This contributes to the optimization of both the graphene CVD growth and transfer processes for future applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15549v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.apsusc.2025.164373</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>N. Reckinger, B. Hackens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic structure of the interface between Au and WSe2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15600</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15600v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding the interface between metals and two-dimensional materials is critical for their application in electronics and for the development of metal-mediated exfoliation of large area monolayers. Studying the intricate interactions at the interface requires model systems that enable control of the roughness, purity, and crystallinity of the metal surface. Here, we investigate the layer-dependent electronic structure of WSe_2 on template-stripped gold substrates fabricated using both silicon and mica templates, giving crystallographically disordered and Au(111) ordered surfaces, respectively, and contrast these findings with ab initio predictions. We observe strong hybridization around the Brillouin zone centre at $\overline{\Gamma}$, indicating a covalent admixture in the gold-\WSe~interaction, and band shifts that suggest charge rearrangement at the Au(111) / WSe_2 interface. Core-level spectroscopy shows a single chemical environment for the interfacial WSe_2 layer on the template-stripped gold, distinct from the subsequent layers. These results reveal a mixture of van der Waals and covalent interactions, best described as a covalent-like quasi-bonding with intermediate interaction strength.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15600v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laxman Nagireddy, Samuel J. Magorrian, Matthew D. Watson, Yogal Prasad Ghimirey, Marc Walker, Cephise Cacho, Neil R. Wilson, Nicholas D. M. Hine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superpotentials, flat bands and the role of Quantum Geometry for the superfluid stiffness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15604</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15604v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the stability and enhancement of superconductivity in a system subject to a 2D periodic superpotential. This externally imposed modulation leads to a reconstructed multi-band structure with flat bands emerging in certain energy regions. When the chemical potential is tuned into one of these flat bands, the associated increase in the density of states can strongly enhance the superconducting critical temperature Tc compared to the homogeneous case while maintaining the superfluid stiffness Ds at a sizeable value. We also clarify the role of the quantum geometric effect for flat bands in such topologically trivial systems. While the overall paramagnetic interband contribution to the stiffness is negative we identify a class of certain interband scattering processes which enhance Ds and scale with the interaction, playing therefore the same role as quantum geometric effects in conventional flat band models. The enhancement of superconductivity is found to be robust against weak to moderate disorder, suggesting that the system is not overly sensitive to imperfections which is an important prerequisite for experimental realizations. Our results demonstrate that engineered superpotentials offer a compelling alternative to twist-based moire systems, providing a pathway toward tailoring superconductivity via lithographic design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15604v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Bauch, F. Lombardi, G. Seibold</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High Harmonic Spectroscopy from Lower-Order to Higher-Order Topological Insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15631v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Over the last decade, high-harmonic spectroscopy has been successfully extended to the study of ultrafast electron motion in solids, shedding light on fundamental processes such as Bloch oscillations and higher-order nonlinear phenomena. In this work, we present theoretical studies of high-harmonic spectroscopy applied to topological materials including higher-order ones, focusing on several key observables associated with high-harmonic generation - namely, helicity, circular dichroism, and ellipticity dependence. We extend current all-optical measurement approaches from lower-order topological insulators (LOTIs) to higher-order topological insulators (HOTIs), employing three distinct models: a Haldane model for Chern insulators, Kane-Mele model for topological insulators, and a breathing Kagome lattice for HOTIs. This work aims to resolve whether helicity, circular dichroism, and ellipticity dependence can reveal signatures of topological states. For the Chern insulators and topological insulators, we find that these observables can indeed capture topological phases. In contrast, for HOTIs, no clear signatures of topology emerge in the harmonic spectrum, suggesting that a more careful analysis is required to identify topological invariants in higher-order topological insulators. In particular, for the topological semimetal phase, we find a harmonic enhancement by two to three orders of magnitude in the Kagome lattice. Our study delineates the conditions under which high-harmonic spectroscopy serves as a unique tool for diagnosing topological phases, particularly for those associated with topological corner states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15631v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bryan Lorenzo, Camilo Granados, Dasol Kim, Carlos Batista, Jean Menotti, Feng Liu, Wenlong Gao, Alexis Chacon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Second Harmonic Generation by Multilayer Graphenes and its Dependence on Stacking Order and Encapsulation Environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15668</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15668v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we analyze the effects of external influences on the second harmonic generation (SHG) signal produced by multilayer graphenes. Specifically, we vary the encapsulation conditions and doping of graphenes, seeking to identify SHG "fingerprints" that are unsensitive to external perturbations. We identify characteristic features in the infrared regime that may be used as a stacking-order fingerprint for the mixed stacking tetralayer and the trilayer polytypes caused by a strong double resonance effect. Further to this, we find that the tetralayers systematically produce an SHG response that is significantly larger as compared to the trilayers. We then studied the SHG signal by the tetralayer polytypes in the terahertz regime and demonstrated the signal is highly sensitive the environmental conditions. Furthermore, we also find that accidental doping of graphene will strongly suppress the SHG signal in this regime. The above findings emphasize the need for a spectral approach to the identification of stacking order by SHG. Thus, measurements at one frequency are insufficient to confidently identify the stacking order due to the environmental sensitivities, since SHG can be readily induced with a comparable magnitude in the centrosymmetric polytypes through external symmetry-breaking.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15668v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick Johansen Sarsfield, Takaaki V. Joya, Takuto Kawakami, Mikito Koshino, Vladimir Fal'ko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classification of Magnetism and Altermagnetism in Quasicrystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15702</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15702v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Altermagnetism, an unconventional magnetic phase characterized by zero net magnetism and a spin-split electronic band, has been studied exclusively in conventional crystalline materials. In this work, we extend the theoretical framework of altermagnetism to quasicrystals (QCs), which lack translational symmetry. We classify magnetic phases in 2D QCs with $n$-fold rotational symmetry without spin-orbit coupling, by using the irreducible representation (IRRP) of the $D_n$ point group. Based on symmetry analysis, we propose the conjecture that magnetic phases corresponding to 1D non-identity IRRPs are generally altermagnetic, with the exception of those possessing parity-time symmetry. To verify our conjecture, we take the Hubbard model as an example and develop a systematic approach to determine the magnetic pattern in the QC, which effectively avoids getting trapped at local energy minima. Consequently, our tests for the Hubbard model on various QCs with different symmetries are unexceptionally consistent with our proposal. Our work highlights the QC as a platform where the altermagnetism is common among magnetic phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15702v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhi-Yan Shao, Chen Lu, Zhiming Pan, Yu-Bo Liu, Fan Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orientation dependent anomalous Hall and spin Hall currents at the junctions of altermagnets with $p$-wave magnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15723</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15723v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study charge and spin transport across a junction between an altermagnet (AM) and a $p$-wave magnet (PM) using a continuum model with boundary conditions tailored to the spin-split band structures of the two materials. Remarkably, although neither AM nor PM is spin-polarized, we find that the junction supports finite spin currents both longitudinally and transversely. We compute the longitudinal and transverse charge and spin conductivities as functions of the crystallographic orientations and the relative angle between the N\'eel vectors of AM and PM. Our results reveal that transverse charge and spin conductivities can be finite even when the longitudinal charge conductivity vanishes. For suitable parameter choices and orientation angles, the transverse conductivities are more prominent than the longitudinal ones. The origin of these effects lies in the matching and mismatching of transverse momentum modes ($k_y$) across the junction combined with the spin-dependent band splitting in AM and PM. Furthermore, while the transverse charge conductivity may cancel for certain orientations, the transverse spin conductivity remains finite due to unequal contributions of opposite $k_y$ channels. These findings highlight altermagnet/$p$-wave magnet junctions as a promising platform for tunable generation and control of transverse charge and spin currents driven purely by crystallographic orientation and spin structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15723v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sachchidanand Das, Abhiram Soori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skyrmion Lattice Order Controlled by Confinement Geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15758</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15758v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic skyrmions forming two-dimensional (2D) lattices provide a versatile platform for investigating phase transitions predicted by Kosterlitz-Thouless-Halperin-Nelson-Young (KTHNY) theory. While 2D melting in skyrmion systems has been demonstrated, achieving controlled ordering in skyrmion lattices remains challenging due to pinning effects from a non-uniform energy landscape, which often results in polycrystalline structures. Skyrmions in thin films, however, offer thermal diffusion with high tunability and can be directly imaged via Kerr microscopy, enabling real-time observation of their dynamics. To regulate lattice order in such flexible systems, we introduce geometric confinements of varying shapes. Combining Kerr microscopy experiments with Thiele model simulations, we demonstrate that confinement geometry critically influences lattice order. Specifically, hexagonal confinements commensurate with the skyrmion lattice stabilize monodomain hexagonal ordering, while incommensurate geometries induce domain formation and reduce overall order. Understanding these boundary-driven effects is essential for advancing the study of 2D phase behavior and for the design of skyrmion-based spintronic applications, ranging from memory devices to unconventional computing architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15758v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raphael Gruber, Jan Roth\"orl, Simon M. Fr\"ohlich, Maarten A. Brems, Fabian Kammerbauer, Maria-Andromachi Syskaki, Elizabeth M. Jefremovas, Sachin Krishnia, Asle Sudb{\o}, Peter Virnau, Mathias Kl\"aui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defect Anomalies, a Spin-Flux Duality, and Boson-Kondo Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14963v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that the infrared phases of certain line defects in 2+1d quantum field theories are determined by anomalies, including anomalies in the space of defect coupling constants, together with a symmetry-refined corollary of the $g$-theorem. As an example, we prove that the spin-$1/2$ impurities in the 2+1d critical $O(2)$ and $O(3)$ models (known respectively as the Halon and Boson-Kondo defects) flow to non-trivial conformal line operators in the IR, and we supply evidence that the same extends to all spin $s$. We also argue that, under particle/vortex duality, the Halon impurity is exchanged with the $\pi$-flux vortex line leading to spin-flux duality, a proposal which we test with a detailed matching of symmetries, anomalies, and phases. Finally, we write down quantum lattice Hamiltonians which can be used to test our predictions, and give an argument on the lattice in favor of spin-flux duality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14963v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zohar Komargodski, Fedor K. Popov, Brandon C. Rayhaun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revealing the Altermagnetism in Hematite via XMCD Imaging and Anomalous Hall Electrical Transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.16907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.16907v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Altermagnets are a class of magnetic materials that exhibit unconventional transport properties, such as an anomalous Hall effect, despite having compensated sublattice magnetic moments. In this study, we report fundamental experimental evidence of the altermagnetic nature of hematite ($\alpha$-\ch{Fe2O3}), combining electrical transport with advanced XPEEM imaging with linear and circular dichroism contrast. Our measurements directly visualize the N\'eel vector's coupling to the crystal orientation, confirming hematite's altermagnetic order and its symmetry-driven transport behavior. Transport measurements reveal an anisotropic AHE with a pronounced crystal orientation dependence, including a sign inversion for specific N\'eel vector alignments. Supported by first-principles theoretical calculations, we explain how the interplay between collinear spin and crystal symmetry breaking drives the observed anomalous Hall effect. These findings establish hematite as an altermagnet, paving the way for experimental identification of altermagnetic materials and their integration into spintronic technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.16907v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/adma.202505019</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Adv. Mater. 2025, e05019</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Edgar Galindez-Ruales, Rafael Gonzalez-Hernandez, Christin Schmitt, Shubhankar Das, Felix Fuhrmann, Andrew Ross, Evangelos Golias, Akashdeep Akashdeep, Laura L\"unenb\"urger, Eunchong Baek, Wanting Yang, Venkata Krishna, Rodrigo Jaeschke-Ubriego, Libor \v{S}mejkal, Jairo Sinova, Avner Rothschild, Chun-Yeol You, Gerhard Jakob, Mathias Kl\"aui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Wilson Loop Bound of Quantum Geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00100v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We define the absolute Wilson loop winding and prove that it bounds the (integrated) quantum metric from below. This Wilson loop lower bound naturally reproduces the known Chern and Euler bounds of the integrated quantum metric and provides an explicit lower bound of the integrated quantum metric due to the time-reversal protected $Z_2$ index, answering a hitherto open question. In general, the Wilson loop lower bound can be applied to any other topological invariants characterized by Wilson loop winding, such as the particle-hole $Z_2$ index. As physical consequences of the $Z_2$ bound, we show that the time-reversal $Z_2$ index bounds superfluid weight and optical conductivity from below and bounds the direct gap of a band insulator from above.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00100v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/mp2c-zzkt</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 086401 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jiabin Yu, Jonah Herzog-Arbeitman, B. Andrei Bernevig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coherent suppression and dephasing-induced reentrance of high harmonics in Dirac materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11432</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11432v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: High-harmonic generation in solids by intense laser pulses provides a fascinating platform for studying material properties and ultra-fast electron dynamics, where its coherent character is a central aspect. Using the semiconductor Bloch equations, we uncover a mechanism suppressing the high harmonic spectrum arising from the coherent superposition of intra- vs. inter-band contributions. We provide evidence for the generality of this phenomenon by extensive numerical simulations exploring the parameter space in gapped systems with both linear dispersion, such as for massive Dirac Fermions, and with quadratic dispersion, as e.g. for bilayer graphene. Moreover, we demonstrate that, upon increasing dephasing, destructive interference between intra- and inter-band contributions is lifted. This leads to reentrant behavior of suppressed high harmonics, i.e. a crossover from the characteristic spectral "shoulder" to a slowly decaying signal involving much higher harmonics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11432v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wolfgang Hogger, Alexander Riedel, Debadrito Roy, Angelika Knothe, Cosimo Gorini, Juan-Diego Urbina, Klaus Richter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$t$-$J$ model for strongly correlated two-orbital systems: Application to bilayer nickelate superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10114v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We derive a $t$-$J$ model applicable to strongly correlated two-orbital systems including bilayer nickelate superconductors. Using the Schrieffer-Wolff transformation, we exclude the doubly occupied states, which raise the onsite Coulomb energy, and derive the resulting spin interactions from the two-orbital Hubbard model. We also introduce effective interactions attributed to the interorbital Coulomb interaction. To adapt the effective model to bilayer nickelates that exhibit high-temperature superconductivity, we quantitatively evaluate the strengths of the spin interactions based on the hopping parameters in La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$. Considering the evaluated effective interactions, we propose a simplified $t$-$J$ model for bilayer nickelate superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10114v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/bsgt-sg2s</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 075143 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tatsuya Kaneko, Masataka Kakoi, Kazuhiko Kuroki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry-broken ground state and phonon mediated superconductivity in Kagome CsV$_3$Sb$_5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19686</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19686v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The newly discovered family of non-magnetic Kagome metals AV$_3$Sb$_5$ (A=K,Rb,Cs) provides a unique platform for exploring the interplay between charge density wave (CDW) order, superconductivity, non-trivial topology, and spontaneous time-reversal symmetry breaking. Although characterizing the CDW phase is essential for understanding and modeling these exotic phenomena, its nature remains unresolved. In this work, we employ first-principles free-energy calculations, accounting for both ionic kinetic energy and anharmonic effects, to resolve the atomistic phase diagram of CsV$_3$Sb$_5$ and its charge ordering structure. Our results uncover that the CDW ground state is formed by reconstructed vanadium Kagome layers in a triangular hexagonal pattern, featuring energetically degenerate different stacking orders. This accounts for the various out-of-plane modulations observed experimentally and supports the coexistence of multiple domains. The discovered symmetry-broken ground state is consistent with the absence of any electronic anisotropy in transport experiments. By combining anharmonic phonons with the calculation of electron-phonon matrix elements, we predict a superconducting critical temperature for the CDW phase in agreement with experiments, showing that superconductivity is phonon mediated. These findings not only resolve a long-standing structural puzzle, but also clarify the impact of the CDW in superconductivity, highlighting its fundamental importance in shaping the low-temperature quantum phase diagram of Kagome metals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19686v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manex Alkorta, Martin Gutierrez-Amigo, {\DH}or{\dj}e Dangi\'c, Chunyu Guo, Philip J. W. Moll, Maia G. Vergniory, Ion Errea</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
