<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 04:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A large spin-splitting altermagnet designed from the hydroxylated MBene monolayer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14174v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The development of altermagnets is fundamentally important for advancing spintronic device technology, but remains unpractical for the weak spin splitting in most cases, especially in two-dimensional materials. Based on spin group symmetry analysis and first-principles calculations, a novel hydroxyl rotation strategy in collinear antiferromagnets has been proposed to design altermagnets. This approach achieves a large chirality-reversible spin splitting exceeding $1130$ meV in $\alpha_{60}$-Mn$_2$B$_2$(OH)$_2$ monolayer. The system also exhibits intrinsic features of a node-line semimetal in the absence of spin-orbit coupling. Besides, the angles of hydroxyl groups serve as the primary order parameter, which can switch on/off the altermagnetism coupled with the ferroelastic mechanism. The corresponding magnetocrystalline anisotropy have also been modulated. Moreover, an interesting spin-related transport property with the spin-polarized conductivity of 10$^{19}$ $\Omega^{-1}m^{-1}s^{-1}$ also emerges. These findings uncover the hydroxyl rotation strategy as a versatile tool for designing altermagnetic node-line semimetals and opening new avenues for achieving exotic chemical and physical characteristics associated with large spin splitting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14174v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinyu Yang, Shan-Shan Wang, Shuai Dong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mapping Temperature Using Transmission Kikuchi Diffraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14175v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Electronic devices are engineered at increasingly smaller length scales; new metrologies to understand nanoscale thermodynamics are needed. Temperature and pressure are fundamental thermodynamic quantities whose nanoscale measurement is challenging as physical contact inevitably perturbs the system. Here we demonstrate Kikuchi diffraction thermometry (KDTh), a non-contact scanning electron microscope (SEM) technique capable of mapping nanoscale temperatures and pressures. KDTh detects local volumetric lattice changes in crystalline samples by precisely fitting Kikuchi patterns. Temperature changes are deduced using the coefficient of thermal expansion (CTE). We map lattice parameters and temperatures on Joule-heated graphite by rastering a 5.5-nm electron probe across the sample. Our parameter precision is ~0.01% and our temperature sensitivity is 2.2 K/$\sqrt{Hz}$. KDTh offers advanced sensitivity by fitting the entire Kikuchi pattern, even beyond the precision measured in transmission electron microscopy. KDTh can operate in both transmission (transmission Kikuchi diffraction, TKD) and reflection (electron backscatter diffraction, EBSD) modes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14175v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yueyun Chen, Xin Yi Ling, Jared Lodico, Tristan P. O`Neill, B. C. Regan, Matthew Mecklenburg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electric field-induced spin-valley locking in twisted bilayer buckled honeycomb materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14404</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14404v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A twisted honeycomb bilayer exhibits a moir\'e superstructure that is composed of a hexagonal arrangement of AB and BA stacked domains separated by domain boundaries. In the case of twisted bilayer graphene, the application of an electric field normal to the bilayer leads to the opening of inverted band gaps in the AB and BA stacked domains. The inverted band gaps result in the formation of a two-dimensional triangular network of counterpropagating valley protected helical domain boundary states, also referred to as the quantum valley Hall effect. Owing to spin-orbit coupling and buckling, the quantum valley Hall effect in twisted bilayer silicene and germanene is more complex than in twisted bilayer graphene. We found that there is a range of electric fields for which the spin degree of freedom is locked to the valley degree of freedom of the electrons in the quantum valley Hall states, resulting in a stronger topological protection. For electric fields smaller than the aforementioned range the twisted bilayer does not exhibit the quantum valley Hall effect, whereas for larger electric fields the spin-valley locking is lifted and the emergent quantum valley Hall states are only valley-protected.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14404v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harold J. W. Zandvliet, Pantelis Bampoulis, Cristiane Morais Smith, Lumen Eek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent Shastry-Sutherland network from square-kagome Heisenberg antiferromagnet with trimerization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14492v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the $S=1/2$ square-kagome lattice Heisenberg antiferromagnet with the trimarized modulation. In the trimerized limit, each trimer hosts the four-fold degenearte ground states characterized by the spin and chirality degrees of freedom. We find that, within the first-order perturbation theory with respect to the inter-trimer coupling, the effective Hamiltonian is the Kugel-Khomskii-type model on a Shastry-Sutherland lattice. Based on a mean-field decoupling, we propose a dimer-covering ansatz for the effective Hamiltonian; however, the validity of these states in the low-energy sector remains an open question.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14492v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomonari Mizoguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The fate of disorder in twisted bilayer graphene near the magic angle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14567</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14567v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In disordered lattices, itinerant electrons typically undergo Anderson localization due to random phase interference, which suppresses their motion. By contrast, in flat-band systems where electrons are intrinsically localized owing to their vanishing group velocity, the role of disorder remains elusive. Twisted bilayer graphene (TBG) at the magic angle $\sim 1.1^\circ$ provides a representative flat-band platform to investigate this problem. Here, we perform an atomistic tight-binding quantum transport calculation on the interplay between disorder and flat-bands in TBG devices. This non-phenomenological approach provides direct evidence that moderate disorder enhances conductance, whereas stronger disorder restores localization, revealing a disorder-driven delocalization-to-localization transport behavior. The underlying physical mechanism is understood by an effective inter-moir{\'e} tunneling strength via spectral flow analysis of a disordered TBG cylinder. Moreover, by comparing magic-angle and large-angle TBG, we demonstrate qualitatively distinct disorder responses tied to the presence of flat-bands. Our quantitative results highlight the unconventional role of disorder in flat-band moir{\'e} materials and offer insights into the observation of the fractional quantum anomalous Hall effect in disordered moir{\'e} systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14567v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhe Hou, Hailong Li, Qing Yan, Yu-Hang Li, Hua Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay of ferromagnetism, nematicity and Fermi surface nesting in kagome flat band</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14593v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent experiment on Fe-doped CoSn has uncovered a series of correlated phases upon hole doping of the kagome flat bands. Among the phases observed, a nematic phase with a six- to two-fold rotation symmetry breaking is found to prevail over a wide doping and temperature range. Motivated by these observations, we investigate the interaction-driven phases realized in a kagome model with partially filled, weakly dispersing flat bands. Density-density interactions up to second-nearest neighbors are considered. We identify a close competition between ferromagnetic and nematic phases in our self-consistent Hartree-Fock calculations: while on-site interaction favors ferromagnetism, the sizable inter-sublattice interactions stabilize nematicity over a wide doping window. Competition from translational-symmetry-breaking phases is also considered. Overall, our results show that nematicity is a generic outcome of partially filled kagome flat bands and establish a minimal framework for understanding correlated flat-band phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14593v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuman He, Wentao Jiang, Siqi Wu, Xuzhe Ying, Berthold Jack, Xi Dai, Hoi Chun Po</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bosonic Laughlin and Moore-Read states from non-Chern flat bands</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14685</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14685v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The rapid advances in the study of fractional Chern insulators (FCIs) raise a fundamental question: while initially discovered in flat Chern bands motivated by their topological equivalence to Landau levels, is single- particle band topology actually a prerequisite for these many-body topological orders emergent at fractional fillings? Here, we numerically demonstrate bosonic FCIs in two types of non-Chern flat bands in honeycomb lattices, using exact diagonalization and density matrix renormalization group calculations. In a gapless flat band with a singular band touching, we observe a Laughlin state at half filling, stabilized by onsite interactions from the hard-core limit down to arbitrarily small strength. Furthermore, we report the first example of a non- Abelian FCI in a non-Chern band system: a Moore-Read state at $\nu$ = 1 filling of the same singular flat band with hard-core bosons. Under lattice parameters that realize a gapped trivial band (C = 0) of exact flatness, we also find the Laughlin FCI of soft-core bosons in the isolated band limit where onsite interaction is much smaller than the band gap. In this case, the FCI forms as interacting bosons spontaneously avoid the peaks in quantum metric and Berry curvature, preferentially occupying Brillouin zone region with relatively uniform quantum geometry. Our work significantly expands the landscape for (non-)Abelian FCIs and broadens the understanding of their formation beyond the Chern band paradigm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14685v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongyu Lu, Wang Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electric field controlled second-order anomalous Hall effect in altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14899v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Altermagnets are a recently discovered class of compensated magnets with momentum-dependent spin splittings and unusual transport properties, even without a net magnetization. In the presence of combined four-fold rotation and time-reversal ($C_4\mathcal{T}$) symmetry, linear and also second-order, driven by a Berry curvature dipole, anomalous Hall responses are forbidden in any pure $d$-wave altermagnet. Nevertheless, here we find that the nontrivial quantum metric of the occupied Bloch states allows for an electric field induced Berry curvature dipole, which generates a strong and tunable second-order Hall current, enabling it to be switched on or off by simply adjusting the relative orientation between the symmetry-reducing dc field and the ac probe field. Specifically, we investigate the electric field induced second-order anomalous Hall response in a two-dimensional Rashba-coupled hybrid altermagnet that interpolates between $d_{x^2-y^2}$ ($B_{1g}$) and $d_{xy}$ ($B_{2g}$) altermagnet symmetry, motivated by recent proposals for mixed-symmetry states. Crucially, the nonlinear signal is highly sensitive to the underlying symmetry of the altermagnetic order at specific doping levels, offering a purely electrical method to distinguish distinct altermagnetic orders. Our results position hybrid altermagnets as a promising platform for controllable nonlinear transport and spintronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14899v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arnob Mukherjee, Biplab Sanyal, Annica M. Black-Schaffer, Ankita Bhattacharya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A universal description of Mott insulators: Characterizing quantum phases beyond broken symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14951v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using Mott insulators as a prototypical example, we demonstrate a dynamics-based characterization of quantum phases of matter through a general N-body renormalization group framework. The essential "Mott-ness" turns out to be characterized by a change of size-scaling of the effective intra- momentum repulsions between long-lived emergent "eigen-particles" that encodes the dynamics of two-body bound states in the high-energy sector. This directly offers a universal characterization at long space-time scale for the corresponding class of Mott insulators through a uniform single occupation of all momenta, and otherwise Mott metals. This universal description naturally paves the way to topological Mott insulators and is straightforward to extend to bosonic Mott systems. More generally, this demonstration exemplifies a generic paradigm of characterizing quantum phases of matter through their distinct dynamics beyond broken symmetries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14951v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matheus de Sousa, Zhiyu Fan, Wei Ku</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Localized fermions on the triangular lattice with Ising-like interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10808</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10808v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The model of localized fermions on the triangular lattice is analyzed in means of the Monte Carlo simulations in the grand canonical ensemble. The Hamiltonian of the system has a form of the extended Hubbard model (at the atomic limit) with nearest-neighbor Ising-like magnetic $J$ interactions and onsite Coulomb $U$ interactions. The model is investigated for both signs of $J$, arbitrary $U$ interaction and arbitrary chemical potential $\mu$ (or, equivalently, arbitrary particle concentration $n$). Based on the specific heat capacity and sublattice magnetization analyses, the phase diagrams of the model are determined. For ferromagnetic case ($J&lt;0$), the transition from the ordered phase (which is a standard ferromagnet and can be stable up to $k_{B}T/|J| \approx 0.61$) is found to be second-order (for sufficiently large temperatures $k_{B}T/|J| \gtrsim 0.2$) or first-order (for $-1&lt;U/|J|&lt;-0.65$ at the half-filling, i.e., $n=1$). In the case of $J&gt;0$, the ordered phase occurs in a range of $-1/2&lt;U/|J|&lt;0$ (for $n=1$), while for larger $U$ the state with short-range order is also found (also for $n \neq 1$). The ordered phase is characterized by an antiferromagnetic arrangement of magnetic moments in two sublattices forming the hexagonal lattice. The transition from this ordered phase, which is found also for $\mu \neq 0$ ($n \neq 1$) and $U/|J|&gt;-1/2$ is always second-order for any model parameters. The ordered phase for $J&gt;0$ can be stable up to $k_{B}T/|J| \approx 0.06$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10808v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/4lmb-6qqv</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review E 111 (6), 064132 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lubom\'ira Regeciov\'a (Institute of Experimental Physics Slovak Academy of Sciences, Ko\v{s}ice, Slovakia), Konrad Jerzy Kapcia (Institute of Spintronics,Quantum Information, Faculty of Physics,Astronomy, Adam Mickiewicz University in Pozna\'n, Poland)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Particle-Hole Asymmetry and Pinball Liquid in a Triangular-Lattice Extended Hubbard Model within Mean-Field Approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20719v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently, triangular lattice models have received a lot of attention since they can describe a number of strongly-correlated materials that exhibit superconductivity and various magnetic and charge orders. In this research we present an extensive analysis of the charge-ordering phenomenon of the triangular-lattice extended Hubbard model with repulsive onsite and nearest-neighbor interaction, arbitrary charge concentration, and $\sqrt{3}\times\sqrt{3}$ supercell (3-sublattice assumption). The model is solved in the ground state with the mean-field approximation which allowed to identify $8$ charge-ordered phases and a large variety of phase transitions. An exotic pinball-liquid phase was found and described. Moreover, strong particle-hole asymmetry of the phase diagram is found to play an important role for triangular lattices. The detailed analysis of band structures, unavailable for more advanced methods, such as dynamical mean-field theory, allowed us to interpret the found triangular-lattice phases and provided a great insight into the mechanisms behind the phase transitions that can also be met when correlation effects are taken into account. The complexity of the mean-field phase diagram showed the importance and usefulness of the results for the further research with correlation effects included. Together with atomic-limit approximation it can serve them as both a starting point, and a tool to interpret results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20719v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/134x-s54f</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 115155 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Aleksey Alekseev, Agnieszka Cichy, Konrad Jerzy Kapcia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Demonstration of returning Thouless pump in a Berry dipole system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08582</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08582v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Thouless pump, a cornerstone of topological physics, enables unidirectional quantized wave/particle transport via geometric Berry phase engineering in periodically driven systems. While decades of research have been dedicated to monopole-mediated pumping, mechanisms governed by higher-order singularities like Berry dipoles remain unexplored. Here, we report the experimental demonstration of a Berry-dipole-mediated returning Thouless pump (RTP) in a 1D acoustic waveguide array achieved through adiabatic encircling of a Berry dipole singularity. During this adiabatic cycle, an initial edge-localized mode first delocalizes into the bulk and eventually returns to the original edge, marking the characteristic signature of the RTP. Notably, this RTP exhibits an interesting feature of pseudospin flipping. The demonstrated RTP contrasts sharply with the well-studied monopole-governed pumps that feature unidirectional transport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08582v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qingyang Mo, Shanjun Liang, Xiangke Lan, Jie Zhu, Shuang Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantization and quantum oscillations of the sublattice charge order in Dirac insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.06681</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.06681v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report the quantization, quantum oscillations, and singular behavior of sublattice symmetry-breaking sublattice charge order (SCO) in two-dimensional Dirac insulators at charge neutrality under perpendicular magnetic fields $B$. SCO is induced by staggered sublattice potentials, such as those originating from substrates, strains, hydrogenation, and chemical doping. In small non-quantizing magnetic fields that result in less than a flux quantum threading the system, and small sublattice symmetry breaking potentials, SCO exhibits perturbative singular magnetic field dependence, $\sim |B|$, originating from hopping between neighboring sites of the same sublattice. At intermediate magnetic fields, when the cyclotron gap between the zeroth Landau level and the first Landau level, $\omega_c$, is smaller than the sublattice potential, $\omega_c\lesssim \Delta$, SCO shows $\textit{universally}$ quantized plateaus owing to discrete Landau-level degeneracy. As the magnetic flux increases by one flux quantum, one electron (per spin) is transferred from the sublattice with a higher chemical potential to the sublattice with a lower chemical potential. One electron transfer between sublattices per flux quantum results from the sublattice polarization of the zeroth Landau level in gapped Dirac materials, realizing the topological Thouless pump effect. At stronger magnetic fields, $\omega_c\gtrsim \ \Delta$, corresponding to integer quantum Hall regimes, SCO displays singularities based on the physics of quantum magneto-oscillations. Our findings suggest new ways to experimentally detect the presence of the energy gap in Dirac materials, irrespective of the gap size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.06681v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arindam Tarafdar, Tigran A. Sedrakyan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin Currents in Rashba Altermagnets: From Equilibrium to Nonlinear Regimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13890</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13890v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate equilibrium (background), linear, and nonlinear spin currents in two-dimensional Rashba spin-orbit coupled altermagnet systems, using a modified spin current operator that includes anomalous velocity from non-zero Berry curvature. The background spin current, stemming from spin-orbit coupling and modulated by the altermagnet term ($t_j$), exhibits in-plane polarization, increases linearly with Fermi energy ($\epsilon_F$), and is enhanced by both the altermagnet ($t_j$) and the Rashba parameter ($\lambda$). Linear spin current is always transverse with out-of-plane polarization and can be viewed as Spin Hall current, primarily driven by band velocity, with $t_j$ enabling a band-induced contribution (previously absent in simple Rashba systems ($t_j=0$)). This highlights altermagnet system as a promising source of spin Hall current generation. For linear spin Hall current, its band contribution's magnitude increases linearly with $\epsilon_F$, while the magnitude of anomalous component saturates at higher $\epsilon_F$. Further, the magnitude of spin Hall current is enhanced by $t_j$ but reduced by $\lambda$. Nonlinear spin currents feature both longitudinal and transverse components with in-plane polarization. Both the nonlinear longitudinal spin current from band velocity and the nonlinear transverse spin current from anomalous velocity initially decrease with $\epsilon_F$ before saturating at higher $\epsilon_F$. Importantly, $t_j$ reduces these currents while $\lambda$ enhances them. Meanwhile, the nonlinear transverse current from band velocity increases and then saturates with $\epsilon_F$, enhanced by $\lambda$ and showing non-monotonic variation with $t_j$. These findings highlight the tunability of spin current behavior through Rashba and altermagnet parameters, offering insights for spintronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13890v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/jqg2-fpk3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 155422 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Priyadarshini Kapri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterization of WSe$_2$ films using reflection Kikuchi diffraction in the scanning electron microscope and multivariate statistical analyses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22575</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.22575v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The study of thin films and 2D materials, including transition metal dichalcogenides such as WSe$_2$ offers opportunities to leverage their properties in advanced sensors, quantum technologies, and device to optimize functional performance. In this work, we characterize thin WSe$_2$ samples with variable thicknesses using scanning electron microscope (SEM)-based techniques focused on analysis of backscattered electron signal and Kikuchi diffraction patterns. These data were collected via a pixelated electron-counting direct electron detector positioned below the pole piece primarily configured for reflection Kikuchi diffraction (RKD), and a similar detector placed in the more conventional electron backscatter diffraction geometry. In addition to conventional pattern analysis for orientation microscopy, multivariate statistical methods (MSA) based on principal component analysis were applied to analyze diffraction patterns and differentiate thickness variations and crystal orientations within the thin films through data clustering. These results were compared with atomic force microscopy to validate thickness measurements. Our findings indicate that RKD combined with MSA is highly effective for characterizing 2D materials, enabling simultaneous assessment of thickness and crystallographic orientation. Systematic acceleration voltage variations in RKD experiments and comparisons with EBSD data suggest that the thickness dependency arises from inelastic scattering of diffracted electrons, which affects pattern contrast in the thin film regime. Collection and analysis of patterns obtained from monolayer, bilayer and tri-layer of WSe$_2$ are also demonstrated. This work reinforces the utility of SEM-based techniques, such as RKD, as valuable tools for the materials characterization toolkit, particularly for thin films and 2D materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.22575v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tianbi Zhang, Jakub Holzer, Tom\'a\v{s} Vystav\v{e}l, Miroslav Kol\'ibal, Est\'acio Paiva de Ara\'ujo, Chris Stephens, T. Ben Britton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A recipe for local simulation of strongly-correlated fermionic matter on quantum computers: the 2D Fermi-Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14543v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The simulation of quantum many-body systems, relevant for quantum chemistry and condensed matter physics, is one of the most promising applications of near-term quantum computers before fault-tolerance. However, since the vast majority of quantum computing technologies are built around qubits and discrete gate-based operations, the translation of the physical problem into this framework is a crucial step. This translation will often be device specific, and a suboptimal implementation will be punished by the exponential compounding of errors on real devices. The importance of an efficient mapping is already revealed for models of spinful fermions in two or three dimensions, which naturally arise when the relevant physics relates to electrons. Using the most direct and well-known mapping, the Jordan-Wigner transformation, leads to a non-local representation of local degrees of freedom, and necessities efficient decompositions of non-local unitary gates into a sequence of hardware accessible local gates. In this paper, we provide a step-by-step recipe for simulating the paradigmatic two-dimensional Fermi-Hubbard model on a quantum computer using only local operations. To provide the ingredients for such a recipe, we briefly review the plethora of different approaches that have emerged recently but focus on the Derby-Klassen compact fermion mapping in order to make our discussion concrete. We provide a detailed recipe for an end-to-end simulation including embedding on a physical device, preparing initial states such as ground states, simulation of unitary time evolution, and measurement of observables and spectral functions. We explicitly compute the resource requirements for simulating a global quantum quench and conclude by discussing the challenges and future directions for simulating strongly-correlated fermionic matter on quantum computers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14543v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.7.043018</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 7, 043018 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Arash Jafarizadeh, Frank Pollmann, Adam Gammon-Smith</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-color magneto-optical trapping of ytterbium atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24383</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.24383v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We report laser cooling and trapping of ytterbium atoms in a two-color magneto-optical trap (MOT). Benefited from both the broad singlet transition ($^1\text{S}_0\rightarrow {}^1\text{P}_1$) and the narrow intercombination transition ($^1\text{S}_0\rightarrow {}^3\text{P}_1$) of ytterbium atoms, the two-color MOT enables rapid loading and efficient cooling. We systematically investigate the shielding effect of the intercombination transition by examining the atom loading and loss rates of single-color and two-color MOTs. Our findings are general and can be extended to other alkaline earth(-like) atoms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.24383v2</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/541j-2sj9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Applied 24, 044039 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xiao Li, Yufei Wang, Ligeng Yu, Bo Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
