<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 05:00:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum geometry and linear orbital response in arbitrary $SU(2)$ representation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04164v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a unified framework to compute band-geometric quantities in multiband systems whose low-energy Hamiltonians realize arbitrary $SU(2)$ representations. Exploiting the presence of a quantization axis, we use the Wigner--Eckart theorem to identify the allowed interband matrix elements and obtain compact analytic expressions for the quantum geometric tensor, the orbital magnetic moment, and the resulting orbital transport coefficients. The formalism applies to both multifold fermions and gapped $SU(2)$ models. Its versatility is demonstrated through explicit calculations in representative $SU(3)$ and $SU(4)$ settings, where orbital Edelstein and orbital Hall responses arise naturally from the antisymmetric components of the band geometry. Our results reveal a universal link between the algebraic structure of the Hamiltonian and emergent orbitronic phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04164v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rhonald Burgos Atencia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2D Helical Twist Controls Tricritical Point in an Interacting Majorana Chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04180v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We analyze a series of interacting Majorana Fermion chains with finite range pair interactions with coupling strength $g$ that all exhibit a tri-critical point that separates an Ising critical phase from a supersymmetric gapped phase. We first notice that the interacting models exhibit an even-odd asymmetry depending on the number of sites, $\delta$, over which the interaction ranges. The even case exhibits competing order, thereby making it numerically untractable while the odd case exhibits an exactly solvable point at $g=-0.5$ where the entanglement entropy vanishes. By introducing a swirling geometrical twist, we map our 1D $\delta$-range chains to a series of 2D $\delta/2$-width models. Our new 2D models possess a unique helical boundary condition, constructed from 1D chains with the end of one connected to the start of another. We propose that the phase transition in the 1D system can be understood as a finite-system size transition in 2D. That is, the $g_c-\delta$ behavior is controlled by a 2D tri-critical universality class at $\delta\to\infty$ limit and is predicted by finite-size scaling theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04180v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hekai Zhao, Philip Phillips</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing solar cell efficiency of AlxIn1-xN/Si heterojunctions using an a-Si buffer: A study of material, interface and device properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04243v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study explores the impact of an optimized amorphous silicon (a-Si) buffer layer on AlxIn1-xN-on-Si(100) heterojunction solar cells, with Al content varying from 0% (InN) to 55%. The buffer layer improves the structural quality of the AlInN layer, as evidenced by reduced full width at half maximum values in X-ray diffraction rocking curves around the AlInN (0002) peak. Atomic force microscopy reveals that the buffer layer does not alter surface roughness. The effectiveness of the a-Si buffer is demonstrated by an enhancement of the conversion efficiency under AM1.5G illumination from 3.3 % to 3.9 % for devices with 35 % Al. Looking at the effect of the Al content in devices with the a-Si buffer, the device with 22% Al shows the best photovoltaic performance, with a conversion efficiency of 4.1 % and a VOC of 0.42 V, JSC of 15.4 mA/cm2, and FF of 63.3%. However, performance declines for Al contents above 36% due to increased resistivity and reduced carrier concentration. These findings highlight the critical role of the novel a-Si buffer layer developed by RF-sputtering and the Al content in optimizing AlInN/Si heterojunction solar cell performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04243v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.surfin.2025.107278</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>M. Sun, R. G. Cornejo, M. de la Mata, S. I. Molina, B. Damilano, S. Valdueza-Felip, F. B. Naranjo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ferroelectric Hysteresis in Superconducting Bilayers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04251v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently, coexisting ferroelectricity and superconductivity were reported in bilayer T$_{\textrm{d}}$-MoTe$_2$ and twisted bilayer graphene. Importantly, it was observed that an applied displacement field switches the superconductivity with a ferroelectric hysteresis. Such direct coupling between the ferroelectricity and superconductivity offers promising pathways for developing low-power, non-volatile memory devices. However, the coupling mechanism between the ferroelectricity and superconductivity remains poorly understood. In this work, we demonstrate that in a superconducting bilayer, the hysteretic switching of superconductivity can arise from an interlayer pairing. By deriving the Landau Ginzburg free energy expansion for the interlayer pairing, we show that along the ferroelectric hysteresis loop, the hysteretic exceeding of the critical polarization $P_{\textrm{c}}$ that destroys the interlayer pairing leads to the hysteretic switching of superconductivity. The condition to have a ferroelectric hysteretic superconducting state is established to be $P_{\textrm{r}}&lt;P_{\textrm{c}}&lt;P_{\textrm{s}}$, where $P_{\textrm{r}}$ and $P_{\textrm{s}}$ denote the remanent and saturated polarization, respectively. Crucially, our scenario of interlayer pairing yields two predictions: (1) an enhancement of the upper critical displacement field with stronger interlayer coupling and (2) a pronounced, gate-tunable interlayer crossed Andreev reflection, both of which provide clear pathways for experimental verification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04251v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanfang Li, Xin-Zhi Li, Wen-Yu He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electrical Conductivity of Copper-Graphene (Cu-Gr) Composites: The Underlying Mechanisms of Ultrahigh Conductivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04304v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Copper-graphene composite (CGC) conductors are widely considered as a potential alternative to pure copper (Cu). Yet, the effect of graphene (Gr) on the electrical conductivity of CGCs remains elusive, and their electrical performance is still controversial. This work addresses these unresolved questions by unambiguously quantifying how the electrical properties of CGCs depend on the characteristics of Gr and Cu. Gr is synthesized on Cu foils, foams, and wires by utilizing a wide range of chemical vapor deposition conditions to independently control their characteristics. Then the Gr-enhanced electrical conductivity ({\Delta}{\sigma}) is characterized for CGCs with different Cu geometries and Gr qualities. This study confirms that unprecedented electrical conductivity ({\Delta}{\sigma} = 17.1%) can be achieved only when both Gr and Cu are carefully optimized. Specifically, the study reveals three key factors: (1) {\Delta}{\sigma} is positively correlated with continuity of Gr; (2) CGCs with a continuous monolayer Gr exhibit a strong {\Delta}{\sigma}-A_s linear relation where A_s is the specific surface area of a CGC; and (3) {\Delta}{\sigma} becomes more pronounced when a Cu matrix has a curved cross-section. This work reveals the fundamental mechanisms of how Gr influences the overall electrical conductivity of CGCs and, therefore, is a crucial step toward designing and manufacturing high-performance CGC conductors for emerging applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04304v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiali Yao, Uschuas Dipta Das, Hamid Safari, Md Ashiqur Rahman Laskar, Junghoon Yeom, Umberto Celano, Wonmo Kang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local expression of fractional corner charges in obstructed atomic insulators and its application to vertex-transitive polyhedra with arbitrary genus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04325</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04325v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In obstructed atomic insulators, fractional charges appear at the corners of the crystals in the shapes of vertex-transitive polyhedra, and are given by the filling anomaly divided by the number of corners. Recent studies reveal that the filling anomaly for the cases with genus $0$ is universally given by the total charge at the Wyckoff position $1a$. In this study, we rewrite the formula in terms of the degree of sharpness of the corner, and show that the corner charge formula also holds for cases with arbitrary genus. We also extend our formula to vertex-transitive shell polyhedra, which are closed or open polyhedra without the bulk region, with all the vertices related by symmetry. Then, we show that the corner charges of such shell polyhedra are equal to the two-dimensional disclination charges of the corresponding disclinations. By identifying it with the disclination charge under the Wen-Zee action, we show that the coupling constant of the Wen-Zee action for a crystalline insulator is given by the total charge at the Wyckoff position at the disclination core.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04325v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hidetoshi Wada, Shuichi Murakami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In-plane anomalous features in the 3D quantum Hall regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04353v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Studies of the 3D quantum Hall effect (QHE) have primarily emphasized transport features that mimic the well-established 2D QHE. In this work, we show that qualitatively new features arise when an in-plane magnetic field is applied to a 3D Weyl semimetal in the quantum Hall regime. An unexpected Hall quantum oscillation, distinct from the Weyl-orbit oscillation, coexists with the QHE, along with an unquantized two-terminal magnetoresistance. Moreover, unconventional antichiral transmission enables a peculiar disorder-robust negative longitudinal resistance. Quantization tunable by the lead configuration is further found in this transport geometry. A unique type of nonlocal quantum backscattering channels underlies these phenomena. Our work demonstrates a breakdown of the topological characterization of transport even with 3D Chern numbers and reveals hidden 3D QHE transport properties. It opens a new class of transport measurements and phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04353v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/qwsp-vrm5</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Ming Lu, Xiao-Xiao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence of a two-dimensional nitrogen crystalline structure on silver surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04361</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04361v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nitrogen, the most abundant element in Earth's atmosphere, exists as a diatomic gas under standard temperature and pressure. In the two-dimensional (2D) limit, atomically thin nitrogen, termed nitrogene, has been theoretically predicted to form crystalline materials with various polymorphic configurations, exhibiting diverse chemical and physical properties. However, the synthesis of nitrogene has remained elusive due to the strong nitrogen-nitrogen triple bonds. Here, we report experimental evidence of the formation of nitrogen-based crystalline structures compatible with nitrogene on silver surfaces via ion-beam-assisted epitaxy. Through a combination of scanning tunneling microscopy, angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy, and first-principles calculations, we demonstrate that the nitrogene-like structure adopts a puckered honeycomb lattice. Notably, our calculations predict a nitrogene band gap of up to 7.5 eV, positioning it as a promising candidate for ultraviolet optoelectronic devices and high-k dielectric applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04361v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuegao Hu, Haijun Cao, Zhicheng Gao, Hui Zhou, Daiyu Geng, Dong Li, Jisong Gao, Qiaoxiao Zhao, Zhihao Cai, Peng Cheng, Lan Chen, Sheng Meng, Kehui Wu, Baojie Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coulomb drag driven electron-hole bifluidity in doped graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04602</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04602v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by the notion that a preponderance of Coulomb interactions might lead to hydrodynamics, we carry out an ab initio calculation of the charge carrier transport properties of the electron-hole plasma of doped graphene. We include both the phonon and Coulomb interactions within a momentum and band resolved Boltzmann transport formalism. We find that, under suitable conditions, the strong Coulomb drag effect induces effects like negative conductivity and joint electron-hole hydrodynamics (bifluidity) in the plasma. We also identify the exclusive electron or hole hydrodynamics. We find that there is a strong violation of the Wiedemann-Franz law in the low doped regimes. Our work elucidates the roles of the microscopic scattering mechanisms that drive these hydrodynamic phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04602v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dwaipayan Paul, Nakib H. Protik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase transitions on the dark side of the Gross-Neveu model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04626</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04626v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Gross-Neveu model in 2+1 dimensions exhibits a continuous transition from gapless Dirac semimetal to the gapped quantum anomalous Hall (QAH) insulator at a finite (attractive) coupling, at which the inversion and time-reversal symmetry become spontaneously broken, and the flavor O($M$) symmetry remains preserved. A unification of leading order parameters of 2+1 dimensional $N$ four-component Dirac fermions collects all Lorentz-singlet mass-like fermion bilinears, except the one condensing in the QAH state, into an irreducible representation of the O($M=4N$), and predicts another phase transition in the Gross-Neveu model to occur at a strong (repulsive) coupling. Here, a fermionic auxiliary-field quantum Monte Carlo algorithm is employed in order to study a lattice realization of the Gross-Neveu field theory in the repulsive regime, where the sign problem is absent. We indeed find the O($4N$) symmetry breaking transition out of Dirac semimetal to occur and to be weakly first-order for $N=2$, relevant to graphene. The size of the discontinuity and the magnitude of the critical coupling, however, both grow with $N$. Adding a finite chemical potential is found to break the symmetry and cause superconductivity. These results are in broad agreement with the predictions of the unified field theory. Our lattice model also displays an interesting exact O($2N$) symmetry, a subgroup of the low-energy O($4N$), and has the ordered ground state with the order parameter that belongs to its $N(2N-1)$-dimensional representation. Other order parameters are also examined, and a certain hierarchy among those that belong to different representations of the exact $O(2N)$ is observed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04626v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel Osiander Rein, Fakher F. Assaad, Igor F. Herbut</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hole to Electron Crossover in a (Cd,Mn)Te Quantum Well through Surface Metallization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04631v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work we look into how the contact material influences the local charge properties of a p-type CdTe-based quantum well. We study five metals deposited as 10 nm layers on the sample surface: Au, Ag, Cr, Ni and Ti. We use magneto-spectroscopy to discriminate their charge states through monitoring the Zeeman shifts at singlet-triplet transitions. Most tested metals retain the original p-type of the QW, while gold and nickel coverage flips the local doping to n-type. This is attributed to a robust bonding of these two metals to the semiconductor, efficiently passivating its surface and thus improving electron diffusion from the metal to the quantum well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04631v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amadeusz Dydnia\'nski, Mateusz Raczy\'nski, Aleksandra {\L}opion, Tomasz Kazimierczuk, Jacek Kasprzak, Karolina Ewa Po{\l}czy\'nska, Wojciech Pacuski, Piotr Kossacki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconductivity onset above 60 K in ambient-pressure nickelate films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04708v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ambient-pressure superconductivity in nickelates has been capped at an onset transition temperature (Tc) of ~40 K, a value that remains lower than the cuprate (~133 K) and iron-based (~55 K) counterparts, despite the promise shown under high pressure. Here, we report ambient-pressure superconductivity onset at ~63 K in epitaxial (La,Pr)3Ni2O7 thin films grown under compressive strain on SrLaAlO4 substrates. This Tc leap is enabled by pushing our gigantic-oxidative atomic-layer-by-layer epitaxy (GAE) method into an extreme non-equilibrium growth regime. It leverages powerful in situ oxidation to simultaneously enhance kinetics via higher temperatures and achieve full oxygenation without post-annealing. Synchrotron X-ray diffraction and scanning transmission electron microscopy confirm that this approach yields films of large-scale crystalline purity, overcoming the inherent metastability of the strained superconducting phase. These films exhibit a systematic evolution in their normal-state resistivity-temperature curve: the power-law exponent $\alpha$ evolves from Fermi-liquid-like ($\alpha$ ~2) at lower Tc to strange-metal-like ($\alpha$ ~1) in higher Tc samples, directly linking the enhanced superconductivity to non-Fermi liquid behavior. Mapping the vortex melting phase diagram by the mutual inductance technique further reveals 2D melting limit suppressed to near zero, which demonstrates significantly stronger interlayer coupling than that of cuprates. These results identify the nickelates as an anisotropic-3D high-Tc system exhibiting strange-metal behavior, presenting an alternative framework to the quasi-2D cuprate paradigm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04708v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guangdi Zhou, Heng Wang, Haoliang Huang, Yaqi Chen, Fei Peng, Wei Lv, Zihao Nie, Wei Wang, Qi-Kun Xue, Zhuoyu Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact and mean-field analysis of the role of Hubbard interactions on flux driven circular current in a quantum ring</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04736v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate circular current in both ordered and disordered Hubbard quantum rings threaded by magnetic flux, employing exact diagonalization and the Hartree-Fock mean-field approach within the tight-binding framework. The influence of on-site and extended Hubbard interactions, disorder, and electron filling on the persistent current is systematically analyzed. To construct the full many-body Hamiltonian, we introduce a linear table formalism, which, to our knowledge, has been rarely used in this context. In ordered rings, the current decreases monotonically with increasing on-site repulsion, while the impact of the extended interaction depends strongly on the filling factor. At low filling, stronger extended interaction suppresses the current, whereas near half-filling, it enhances the current up to a critical ratio, half of the on-site strength, before reducing it. Disorder significantly modifies these behaviors, notably enhancing the current at less than quarter-filling with increasing extended interaction. The localization properties of eigenstates, examined via the inverse participation ratio, further support the crucial roles of filling and the interplay between on-site and extended interactions in governing persistent current.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04736v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rahul Samanta, Santanu K. Maiti, Shreekantha Sil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of Correlated Electrons in ${\rm La_3Ni_2O_7}$ at Ambient Pressure: a Study of Double-Counting Effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04754v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We employ cluster extension of dynamical mean-field theory (CDMFT) to systematically investigate the impact of double counting corrections on the correlated electronic structure of ${\rm La_3Ni_2O_7}$ under ambient pressure. By adjusting double-counting parameters, while maintaining a fixed Fermi surface, we observe a pronounced orbital-selective density of states change: the $d_{z^2}$ orbital undergoes significant variation near the Fermi level with increasing $E_{dc}^z$, while the $d_{x^2-y^2}$ orbital remains essentially unchanged throughout the entire range. Analysis of renormalization factor show the monotonic dependence with double counting in both $d_{z^2}$ and $d_{x^2-y^2}$ orbital, and it also identifies an optimal double counting window in $d_{z^2}$ orbital aligns with experimental values. We also find the interlayer Matsubara self energy exhibits non-monotonic dependence on $E_{dc}^z$, deviating from theoretical predictions. This anomaly is attributed to the metallization of oxygen-bridged pathways, which disrupts the prerequisite for charge transfer via apical oxygen. Our results establish $E_{dc}$ as a critical control parameter for correlated electronic structure in ${\rm La_3Ni_2O_7}$ and provide a computational framework for resolving orbital-dependent correlation effects in layered materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04754v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>AAPPS Bulletin 2026</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zhong-Yi Xie, Zhihui Luo, W\'ei W\'u, Dao-Xin Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous impurity-induced charge modulations in black phosphorus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04791</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04791v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We observe anomalous charge modulations induced by ionized indium impurities on the surface of the semiconductor black phosphorus by scanning tunneling microscopy (STM). When the im- purities are switched into a negatively charged state by the STM tip, periodic charge modulations emerge around the impurity center, but strictly confined by the nanoscale impurity potential. These modulations form a distorted triangular pattern, whose periodicity remains unchanged in a wide range of positive bias. Furthermore, these local charge orders exhibit an anisotropy opposite to that expected based on the anisotropy of the Fermi surface, challenging a simple band-structure inter- pretation. Our experiment demonstrates the possibility of creating and manipulating macroscopic charge orders through impurity engineering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04791v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Byeongin Lee, Junho Bang, Sayan Banerjee, J\~oao Augusto Sobral, Young Woo Choi, Claudia Felser, Mathias S. Scheurer, Jian-Feng Ge, Doohee Cho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Edge spin galvanic effect in altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04798v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The edge spin galvanic effect (ESGE) in $d$-wave altermagnets is proposed. ESGE is a creation of an electrical current flowing along the edge of the sample, which is driven by the spin orientation of charge carriers. The ESGE current is formed owing to the altermagnetic spin splitting and the scattering of carriers by the edge of the sample. The current is sensitive to the orientation of the edge in respect to the main axes of the altermagnet. The edge spin galvanic current reverses its direction upon a reversal of the non-equilibrium spin direction or the N\'eel vector. We also propose the pure spin edge photocurrent excited by polarized radiation and formed at the edges of a sample. Its dependence on the radiation polarization and frequency is analyzed. The application of an external magnetic field converts this pure spin photocurrent into an electric current along the edge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04798v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. E. Golub</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay between Superconductivity and Altermagnetism in Disordered Materials and Heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04819</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04819v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the interplay between superconductivity and altermagnetism in disordered systems using recently derived quantum kinetic transport equations. Starting from this framework, we derive the Ginzburg-Landau free energy and identify, in addition to the conventional pair-breaking term, a coupling between the spin and the spatial variation of the superconducting order parameter. Two distinct effects emerge from this coupling. The first is a magnetoelectric effect, in which a supercurrent (i.e., a phase gradient) induces a spin texture; this contribution is quadratic in the phase gradient. The second effect arises when the magnitude, rather than the phase, of the superconducting order parameter varies in space, likewise leading to a finite magnetization. We show that these two contributions compete in the case of an Abrikosov vortex, where both the amplitude and phase of the order parameter vary spatially. The effect associated with amplitude variations also gives rise to a proximity-induced magnetization (PIM) in hybrid structures composed of a superconductor (S) and an altermagnet (AM). Using quasiclassical theory, we analyze the PIM in diffusive S/AM bilayers and S/AM/S Josephson junctions, and determine the induced magnetization profiles. In Josephson junctions, where both the PIM and the magnetoelectric effect coexist, we further predict the occurrence of $0$-$\pi$ transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04819v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rodrigo de las Heras, Tim Kokkeler, Stefan Ili\'c, Ilya V. Tokatly, F. Sebastian Bergeret</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controlling Carbon Nanostructure Synthesis in Thermal Plasma Jet: Correlation of Process Parameters, Plasma Characteristics, and Product Morphology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04880</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04880v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Thermal plasma has emerged as an effective approach for producing carbon nanostructures without the need for specific catalysts nor substrates. While efforts have focused on the effect of process parameters such as reaction pressure, input power or carbon source, the intricate role and relationship with plasma characteristics like density and temperature are often overlooked due to the complexity of the environment. This study addresses this gap by establishing a correlation between process parameters, plasma characteristics, and product morphology, essential for controlling the growth of carbon nanostructures. We explored the impact of carbon precursor type (CH4 and C2H2), hydrogen, pressure, and flow rate on nanostructure formation. Using in situ optical emission spectroscopy (OES), we mapped the distribution of both temperature and dicarbon molecule (C2) density within the plasma jet. We demonstrate that the growth of low-density nanostructures, such as carbon nanohorns (CNHs), is favoured at dilute C2 local densities and high temperatures, while denser nanostructures, such as onion-like polyhedral graphitic nanocapsules (GNCs), are favoured at higher C2 densities and lower temperatures. The carbon density can be controlled by the flow rate and the pressure, which in turn significantly influence the nanostructure morphology, evolving from graphene nanoflakes (GNFs) to GNCs as either parameter increases. Increasing the H/C ratio from 1 to 8 resulted in a morphological transition from CNHs to GNFs. During the synthesis, the plasma jet temperature surpassed 3,000 K, with crystalline growth occurring 50 to 100 mm below the nozzle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04880v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.carbon.2023.118605</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Carbon 217 (2024) 118605</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Taki Aissou, Jerome Menneveux, Fanny Casteignau, Nadi Braidy, Jocelyn Veilleux</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tuning the Electronic States of Bi2Se3 Films with Large Spin-Orbit Interaction Using Molecular Heterojunctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04922</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04922v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An electric bias can shift the Fermi level along the Dirac cone of a topological insulator and modify its charge transport, but tuning the electronic states and spin-orbit interaction (SOI) without destroying the surface topology is challenging. Here, we show that thin film Bi2Se3/n-p (p-n) molecular diodes form ordered interfaces where charge transfer and orbital re-hybridisation result in a decrease (increase) of the carrier density and improved mobility. In Bi2Se3 the spin-orbit lifetime, t_so, is 0.13 ps, which is comparable to the strongest spin-orbit materials. This lifetime drops further to 0.06 ps (0.09 ps) with the addition of p-n (n-p) molecular diodes, at the limit of measurable values. This strengthened spin-orbit interaction occurs even though molecules are made of light elements and increase the mean free path of the charge carriers by almost 50%, indicating changes to the Berry curvature and/or Rashba splitting around the hybridisation points. Raman spectroscopy gives evidence that the coupling effect may be controlled by optical irradiation, opening a pathway towards the design of heavy-light element hybrids with optically tunable quantum transport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04922v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Rogers, Craig Knox, Bryan Hickey, Lida Ansari, Farzan Gity, Timothy Moorsom, Mairi McCauley, Gilberto Teobaldi, Manuel dos Santos Dias, Hari B. Vasili, Manuel Valvidares, Mannan Ali, Gavin Burnell, Ahmet Yagmur, Satoshi Sasaki, Oscar Cespedes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tracing the horizon of tetragonal-to-monoclinic distortion in pressurized trilayer nickelate La4Ni3O10</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04975</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04975v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The crux of understanding the superconducting mechanism in pressurized Ruddlesden-Popper nickelates hinges on elucidating their structural phases. Under ambient conditions, the trilayer nickelate La4Ni3O10 stabilizes in a twinned monoclinic structure with space group P21/c. Upon heating, it undergoes a structural transition to the tetragonal I4/mmm phase at Ts ~ 1030 K, while a second transition associated with the onset of density-weave (DW) ordering emerges upon cooling below TDW ~ 135 K. Here from pressure-temperature x-ray diffraction on high quality flux-grown single crystals we unequivocally demonstrate a direct tetragonal-to-monoclinic transition with no trace of intermediate orthorhombic Bmab phase. Ab initio density-functional theory calculations as a function of pressure fully corroborate the experimental observations. The transition unfolds as a 2-fold superstructure due to the emergence of commensurate superlattice reflections and can be progressively suppressed from 1030 K down to 20 K under 14 GPa. No discernible structural distortions associated with DW ordering are detected down to 20 K at ambient pressure. This is in contrast to Raman measurements that reveal the appearance of additional phonon modes below 130 K, implying a further reduction in symmetry from monoclinic P21/c and thus indicating the presence of a third structural phase associated with the DW ordering in La4Ni3O10.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04975v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sitaram Ramakrishnan, Yingzheng Gao, Valerio Olevano, Elise Pachoud, Abdellali Hadj-Azzem, Gaston Gabarino, Olivier Perez, Alain Pautrat, Diego Valenti, Matthieu Quenot, Sebastien Pairis, Dmitry Chernyshov, Leila Noohinejad, Carsten Paulmann, Sander van Smaalen, Pierre Toulemonde, Marie-Aude Measson, Pierre Rodiere</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A meta-GGA perspective on the altermagnetism of RuO2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04995</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04995v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The metallic oxide RuO$_2$ hosts a fascinating edge case of magnetism: while nonmagnetic in ideal bulk material, density functional theory (DFT) predicts an altermagnetic ground state within the DFT$+U$ method. The magnetic state of strained or doped thin films remains controversial, but evidence for a nontrivial magnetic state is ample. Here, I study the altermagnetic ground state of RuO$_2$ on a higher rung of Jacob's ladder of density functional approximations, the meta-GGA level including the kinetic energy density and the density Laplacian. While the workhorse functional of solid-state physics is a generalized gradient approximation (GGA), the modern r$^2$SCAN-L functional has been established as a general-purpose functional which can replace GGA, while systematically improving solid-state properties without introducing spurious errors like erroneous magnetic ground states. Comparison of LSDA+U, GGA+U, and meta-GGA+U results on RuO$_2$ shows systematic enhancement of the exchange interaction, leading to a reduction of the onset value of the Hubbard $U$ parameter at different levels of density functional approximation. However, the magnetic ground state, studied at the experimental lattice constants, remains nonmagnetic with r$^2$SCAN-L. I demonstrate that altermagnetism is easily formed upon lattice expansion, hole doping, and uniaxial strain on the c-axis. The r$^2$SCAN-L calculations set conservative thresholds for distortions and doping levels for the onset of altermagnetism in a parameter-free framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04995v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Markus Meinert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Suppressing metal molecule charge transfer with a phosphorus interlayer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04999</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04999v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Porphyrins are organic molecules that exhibit excellent opto-electronics properties, making them suitable for a variety of applications. Nevertheless, their functionality strongly depends on the surface onto which they are deposited, and on the interaction between the molecules and the substrate itself, which often leads to an undesired alteration in their electronic properties. In this study, we use a phosphorus interlayer on a Cu(110) surface as a buffer layer for the electronic decoupling of Zinc-TetraPhenylPorphyrin (ZnTPP) molecules. Using a combination of complementary techniques, such as Near Edge X-ray Absorption Fine Structure (NEXAFS), X-ray and Ultraviolet Photoemission Spectroscopy (XPS, UPS) as well as Scanning Tunneling Spectroscopy (STS) techniques, it is shown how the charge transfer from the metal, responsible for quenching the ZnTPP lowest unoccupied molecular level (LUMO) levels, is effectively prevented by the presence of a phosphorus reconstruction in between.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04999v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mattia Bassotti, Luca Floreano, Luca Schio, Sergio Salaverria, Dimas G. de Oteyza, Giacomo Giorgi, Frederik Schiller, Alberto Verdini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Axionic tunneling from a topological Kondo insulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05057</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05057v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Discoveries over the past two decades have revealed the remarkable ability of quantum materials to emulate relativistic properties of the vacuum, from Dirac cones in graphene to the Weyl surface states of topological insulators. Yet the most elusive consequence of topology in quantum matter is the axionic $E\cdot B$ term in the electromagnetic response. Here we report a direct signature of axionic physics obtained through scanning tunneling microscopy (STM). Although recent STM experiments using SmB$_6$ nanowires have been interpreted as evidence for spin-polarized currents arising from topological surface states, we show that the observed spin polarization instead originates from axionic electrodynamics. Our analysis reveals a striking voltage-induced magnetization: extremely small voltages ($\sim$ 30 meV) generate tip moments of order 0.1 $\mu_B$ that reverse sign with the applied bias. The magnitude, tunability, and reversibility of this signal are consistent with an axionic $E \cdot B$ coupling, and fully account for the magnetic component of the tip density of states, ruling out static magnetism. Millivolt-scale control of spin polarization in a tunnel junction provides a new route for probing axionic electrodynamics and opens avenues for future STM and spintronics applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05057v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saikat Banerjee, Anuva Aishwarya, Fei Liu, Lin Jiao, Vidya Madhavan, Eugene J. Mele, Piers Coleman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global phase diagram of two-dimensional dirty hyperbolic Dirac liquids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05109</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05109v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Within the framework of the canonical nearest-neighbor tight-binding model for spinless fermions, a family of two-dimensional bipartite hyperbolic lattices hosts massless Diraclike excitations near half-filling with the iconic vanishing density of states (DOS) near zero energy. We show that a collection of such ballistic quasiparticles remains stable against sufficiently weak pointlike charge impurities, a feature captured by the vanishing average [$\rho_{a}(0)$] and typical [$\rho_{t}(0)$] DOS at zero energy, computed by employing the kernel polynomial method in sufficiently large $\{ 10, 3\}$ hyperbolic lattices (Schl\"afli symbol) with more than $10^8$ and $10^5$ sites, respectively, with open boundary conditions. However, at moderate disorder the system enters a metallic state via a continuous quantum phase transition where both $\rho_{a}(0)$ and $\rho_{t}(0)$ become finite. With increasing strength of disorder, ultimately an Anderson insulator sets in, where only $\rho_{t}(0) \to 0$. The resulting phase diagram for dirty Dirac fermions living on a hyperbolic space solely stems from the background negative spatial curvature, as confirmed from the vanishing $\rho_{t}(0)$ for arbitrarily weak disorder on honeycomb lattices, fostering relativistic fermions on a flatland, as the thermodynamic limit is approached.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05109v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher A. Leong, Daniel J. Salib, Bitan Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exceptionally high Verdet constant in gold nanodisc arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04608</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04608v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Magneto-optical effects in non-magnetic noble metals can be greatly enhanced by leveraging the in-plane Lorentz force at engineered plasmonic resonances. We demonstrate a 2D array of gold nanodiscs designed to host a hybrid resonance of localized plasmon and surface lattice modes. The structure exhibits a Verdet constant of 1.98e6 deg/T.m, corresponding to a Faraday rotation of -0.15 deg at a 1 T magnetic field. This Verdet constant represents a 15-fold enhancement over unpatterned gold and is highly competitive with many plasmon-enhanced diamagnetic nanostructures. These findings offer new opportunities for harnessing strong magneto-plasmonic effects in optoelectronic devices by patterning common non-magnetic metals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04608v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gajendra Mulay, Shraddha Choudhary, Ashwin A Tulapurkar, Daria O Ignatyeva, Vladimir I Belotelov, Shriganesh S Prabhu, Venu Gopal Achanta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing chiral topological states with permutation defects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04649</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04649v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The hallmark of two-dimensional chiral topological phases is the existence of anomalous gapless modes at the spatial boundary. Yet, the manifestation of this edge anomaly within the bulk ground-state wavefunction itself remains only partially understood. In this work, we introduce a family of multipartite entanglement measures that probe chirality directly from the bulk wavefunction. Our construction involves applying different permutations between replicas of the ground state wavefunction in neighboring spatial regions, creating "permutation defects" at the boundaries between these regions. We provide general arguments for the robustness of these measures and develop a field-theoretical framework to compute them systematically. While the standard topological field theory prescription misses the chiral contribution, our method correctly identifies it as the chiral conformal field theory partition function on high-genus Riemann surfaces. This feature is a consequence of the bulk-edge correspondence, which dictates that any regularization of the theory at the permutation defects must introduce gapless boundary modes. We numerically verify our results with both free-fermion and strongly-interacting chiral topological states and find excellent agreement. Our results enable the extraction of the chiral central charge and the Hall conductance using a finite number of wavefunction replicas, making these quantities accessible to Monte-Carlo numerical techniques and noisy intermediate-scale quantum devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04649v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yarden Sheffer, Ruihua Fan, Ady Stern, Erez Berg, Shinsei Ryu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fermionic neural Gibbs states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04663</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04663v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce fermionic neural Gibbs states (fNGS), a variational framework for modeling finite-temperature properties of strongly interacting fermions. fNGS starts from a reference mean-field thermofield-double state and uses neural-network transformations together with imaginary-time evolution to systematically build strong correlations. Applied to the doped Fermi-Hubbard model, a minimal lattice model capturing essential features of strong electronic correlations, fNGS accurately reproduces thermal energies over a broad range of temperatures, interaction strengths, even at large dopings, for system sizes beyond the reach of exact methods. These results demonstrate a scalable route to studying finite-temperature properties of strongly correlated fermionic systems beyond one dimension with neural-network representations of quantum states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04663v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jannes Nys, Juan Carrasquilla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comment on paper: Evidence for Dirac flat band superconductivity enabled by quantum geometry, Nature 614, 440 (2023)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06054</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.06054v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We demonstrate that an absolutely flat band retains the superconducting state at $T_c\to 0$. When $T_c&gt;0$ the flat band disappears, since it must be modified by the superconducting state. Thus, a number of the results on ultra-strong coupling superconductivity in flat band considered in the article ("Evidence for Dirac flat band superconductivity enabled by quantum geometry", Nature 614, 440 (2023)) were predicted and explained many years ago. One has to take into account that at $T_c&gt;0$ the flat band distorts, becoming tilted. As a result, the charge carriers' velocity $v_F\propto T_c$ becomes finite, rather than being extremely slow, as it is stated in the article. Thus, the statement "the charge carriers' group velocity $v_ F$ is extremely slow" is incorrect and leads the authors to the conceptional misunderstanding, confusing the reader.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.06054v5</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. R. Shaginyan, A. Z. Msezane, G. S. Japaridze</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic enhancement of conductance in fractional quantum Hall constriction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.00939</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.00939v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A disparity in the charge of quasi-particle excitations across a tunnel junction can trigger Andreev-like processes, creating an effect similar to that of a step-up transformer. We study such a junction in its strong coupling limit in the context of quantum Hall states. Specifically, for filling fractions $\nu=1$ and $1/3$, we show the DC gain in the transformer action is bounded by 3/2, irrespective of the interedge interaction range, while the AC gain is bounded by $\sqrt{3}$ and is sensitive to the range of the interaction. This setup presents a unique possibility of frequency-tunable resonances and anti-resonances across the QPC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.00939v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sampurna Karmakar, Amulya Ratnakar, Sourin Das</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shot noise in Aharonov-Bohm interferometers: Comparison of helical and conventional setups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08329</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.08329v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study tunneling transport through quantum Aharonov-Bohm (AB) interferometers and demonstrate that interference effects strongly modify shot noise of the current. We discuss in detail two simplest setups: conventional single-channel spinless interferometer and interferometer formed by helical edge states of two-dimensional topological insulator. We demonstrate that both in the conventional and the helical case the interference dramatically changes the Fano factor and its magnetic field dependence. For weak tunneling coupling, the Fano factor of both setups exhibits a periodic series of sharp AB peaks depending on the magnetic flux piercing the system. Our key finding is that the Fano factor in the helical interferometer provides information about the presence of backscattering defects violating topological protection. In particular, the amplitude of AB peaks in the helical setup is proportional to the strength of the defect in contrast to conventional setup, where peaks have finite amplitude even in the ballistic case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.08329v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. A. Niyazov, I. V. Krainov, D. N. Aristov, V. Yu. Kachorovskii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A non-magnetic mechanism of backscattering in helical edge states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04610v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study interaction-induced backscattering mechanism for helical edge states of a two-dimensional topological insulator which is tunnel-coupled to a puddle located near the edge channel. The mechanism does not involve inelastic scattering and is due to the zero-mode fluctuations in a puddle. We discuss in detail a simple model of a puddle - a cavity in the bulk of the topological insulator. Such a cavity also has helical edge states with tunneling coupling to helical states encompassing the topological insulator. We analyze effect of the edge current in the puddle. Although averaged value of this current is equal to zero, its zero-mode fluctuations act, in the presence of electron-electron interaction, similar to magnetic flux thus allowing backscattering processes, which involve tunneling through the puddle. Rectification of these fluctuations leads to a finite probability of backscattering. This effect is further enhanced due to dephasing process which is also dominated by zero-mode fluctuations. Remarkably, for temperature exceeding level spacing in the puddle, the rate of backscattering does not depend on temperature in a good agreement with recent experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04610v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1134/s0021364024603907</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JETP Letters (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>I. V. Krainov, R. A. Niyazov, D. N. Aristov, V. Yu. Kachorovskii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological dipoles of quantum skyrmions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16284v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Magnetic skyrmions are spatially localized whirls of spin moments in two dimension, featuring a nontrivial topological charge and a well-defined topological charge density. We demonstrate that the quantum dynamics of magnetic skyrmions is governed by a dipole conservation law associated with the topological charge, akin to that in fracton theories of excitations with constrained mobility. The dipole conservation law enables a natural definition of the collective coordinate to specify the skymion's position, which ultimately leads to a greatly simplified equation of motion in the form of the Thiele equation. In this formulation, the skyrmion mass, whose existence is often debated, actually vanishes. As a result, an isolated skyrmion is intrinsically pinned to be immobile and cannot move at a constant velocity. In a spin-wave theory, we show that such dynamics corresponds to a precise cancellation between a highly nontrivial motion of the quasi-classical skyrmion spin texture and a cloud of quantum fluctuations in the form of spin waves. Given this quenched kinetic energy of quantum skyrmions, we identify close analogies to the bosonic quantum Hall problem. In particular, the topological charge density is shown to obey the Girvin-MacDonald-Platzman algebra that describes neutral modes of the lowest Landau level in the fractional quantum Hall problem. Consequently, the conservation of the topological dipole suggests that magnetic skyrmion materials offer a promising platform for exploring fractonic phenomena with close analogies to fractional quantum Hall states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16284v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/sxgs-38c3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. X 15, 041037 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sopheak Sorn, J\"org Schmalian, Markus Garst</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exciton fractional Chern insulators in moir\'e heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08026</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08026v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Moir\'e materials have emerged as a powerful platform for exploring exotic quantum phases. While recent experiments have unveiled fractional Chern insulators exhibiting the fractional quantum anomalous Hall effect based on electrons or holes, the exploration of analogous many-body states with bosonic constituents remains largely uncharted. In this work, we predict the emergence of bosonic fractional Chern insulators arising from long-lived excitons in a moir\'e superlattice formed by twisted bilayer WSe$_2$ stacked on monolayer MoSe$_2$. Performing exact diagonalization on the exciton flat Chern band present in this structure, we provide compelling evidence for the existence of Abelian and non-Abelian phases at band filling $\frac{1}{2}$ and $1$, respectively, through multiple robust signatures including ground-state degeneracy, spectral flow, many-body Chern number, and particle-cut entanglement spectrum. The obtained energy gap of $\sim 10$ meV for the Abelian states suggests a remarkably high stability of this phase, which persists for a relatively wide range of twist angles and vertical electric fields. Our findings establish the presence of robust bosonic fractional Chern insulators in highly tunable and experimentally accessible moir\'e heterostructures and unveil a promising pathway for realizing non-Abelian anyons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08026v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/55zv-s9xv</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 7, L042033 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Raul Perea-Causin, Hui Liu, Emil J. Bergholtz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parity anomaly from LSM: exact valley symmetries on the lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04684</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.04684v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that the honeycomb tight-binding model hosts an exact microscopic avatar of its low-energy SU(2) valley symmetry and parity anomaly. Specifically, the SU(2) valley symmetry arises from a collection of conserved, integer quantized charge operators that obey the Onsager algebra. Along with lattice reflection and time-reversal symmetries, this Onsager symmetry has a Lieb-Schultz-Mattis (LSM) anomaly that matches the parity anomaly in the IR. Indeed, we show that any local Hamiltonian commuting with these symmetries cannot have a trivial unique gapped ground state. We study the phase diagram of the simplest symmetric model and survey various deformations, including Haldane's mass term, which preserves only the Onsager symmetry. Our results place the parity anomaly in ${2+1}$D alongside Schwinger's anomaly in ${1+1}$D and Witten's SU(2) anomaly in ${3+1}$D as 't Hooft anomalies that can arise from the Onsager symmetry on the lattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.04684v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/4x4w-pfgq</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 236501 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Salvatore D. Pace, Minho Luke Kim, Arkya Chatterjee, Shu-Heng Shao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital Quantum Simulation of the Kitaev Quantum Spin Liquid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.09156</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.09156v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The ground state of the Kitaev quantum spin liquid on a honeycomb lattice is an intriguing many-body state characterized by its topological order and massive entanglement. One of the significant issues is to prepare and manipulate the ground state as well as excited states in a quantum simulator. Here, we provide a protocol to manipulate the Kitaev quantum spin liquid via digital quantum simulation. A series of unitary gates for the protocol is explicitly constructed, showing its circuit depth is an order of O(N) with the number of qubits, N. We demonstrate the efficiency of our protocol on the IBM Heron r2 processor for N = 8 and 12. We further validate our theoretical framework through numerical simulations, confirming high-fidelity quantum state control for system sizes up to N = 450, and discuss the possible implications of these results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.09156v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/ybft-6cb4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 205123 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Seongjun Park, Eun-Gook Moon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shift current in 2D Janus Transition-Metal Dichalcogenides: the role of excitons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16067</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16067v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the shift current in two-dimensional (2D) Janus transition-metal dichalcogenides (TMDs). The shift current is evaluated using a real-time approach, where the coupling with an external field is described in terms of a dynamical Berry phase. This methodology incorporates electron-hole interactions and quasiparticle band structure renormalization through an effective Hamiltonian derived from many-body perturbation theory. We find that the shift current is strongly enhanced in correspondence with C excitons. An analysis in terms of the electron-hole pairs reveals that electron and hole are localized on different atoms, and thus, following an optical excitation, the center of the electron charge is displaced, giving rise to a significant photocurrent. Janus TMDs, with their intrinsic out-of-plane asymmetry and tunable electronic properties, are particularly appealing for next-generation optoelectronic and energy-harvesting technologies. These results highlight the role of excitons in the shift-current response of Janus TMDs and demonstrate their potential as promising building blocks for future photovoltaic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16067v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/qth8-6spb</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Materials 9, 124002 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yuncheng Mao, Ju Zhou, Myrta Gr\"uning, Claudio Attaccalite</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Residual gauge theory for quanta of surface plasmons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18280</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18280v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a gauge-theoretical framework to investigate the quanta of surface plasmons. Our formulation, based on quantum electrodynamics, highlights the importance of residual gauge symmetry. We emphasize that residual gauge symmetry, which imposes constraint equations on physical states, is fundamentally linked to Joule heating. This framework is applied to metals, semiconductors, and quantum Hall states, suggesting the presence of a latent transverse electric mode and that the quanta have the ability to maintain light-matter entanglement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18280v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ken-ichi Sasaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local classical correlations between physical electrons in Hubbard systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18709</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18709v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We demonstrate that the local nonfreeness, an unbiased measure of correlation between electrons at a single lattice site, can be computed as the mutual information between local natural spin orbitals. This leads us to prove a general result: local electron correlations in Hubbard-type models are fully classical since the local reduced density matrix is separable in the natural basis and no quantum correlations beyond entanglement are present. Finally, we compare different theoretical descriptions of magnetic and nonmagnetic states, showing that local classical correlations are drastically influenced by nonlocal processes. These results confirm the relation between local classical correlations within an open system and nonlocal entanglement, and they provide a clear path for the study of the relationship between traditional quantum resources and the nonfreeness, in terms of experimentally accessible quantities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18709v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriele Bellomia, Adriano Amaricci, Massimo Capone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Altermagnetism-induced non-collinear superconducting diode effect and unidirectional superconducting transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05543v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Current studies of non-reciprocal superconducting (SC) transport have centered on the forward-backward asymmetry of the critical current measured along a single axis. In most realizations, this diode effect is achieved via introducing ferromagnetism or applying an external magnetic field, which drives system into an effective Fulde-Ferrell (FF) state but often at the cost of severely suppressing the SC gap and thus compromising device robustness. Here we propose and theoretically demonstrate that coupling a conventional $s$-wave SC thin film to a $d$-wave altermagnet offers a more resilient alternative. The momentum-dependent spin splitting inherent to altermagnets induces a non-collinear SC-diode effect in the BCS state, with the critical-current anisotropy exhibiting a fourfold ($C_4$) symmetry. Upon entering the FF state at large splitting, this anisotropy gradually evolves into a unidirectional ($C_1$) pattern. Crucially, the FF pairing momentum locks to the discrete crystal axes, eliminating the rotational Goldstone mode and preserving a sizable SC gap without any abrupt or significant suppression. These combined features make the altermagnetic proximity an appealing platform to engineer symmetry-protected, energy-efficient and programmable SC diodes for next-generation electronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05543v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Yang, L. Q. Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relation between chiral anomaly and electric transport in $1D$ Dirac semimetal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.06063v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the interplay of chiral anomaly and dissipation in one - dimensional Dirac semimetal. For definiteness we consider the Su Schrieffer Heeger (SSH) model, which on the language of lattice field theory represents 1 D Wilson fermions. We employ the non-equilibrium Keldysh Green function formalism, and calculate the chiral imbalance and electric conductivity in the presence of energy dissipation, revealing how these observables are connected to the chiral anomaly. By systematically incorporating dissipation effects into the Keldysh framework, we demonstrate how the anomaly-induced contributions manifest in both axial charge density and electric current.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.06063v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mustafa Bohra, M. A. Zubkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic modes induced by spin and charge perturbations in Mott and Kondo insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07428v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Electronic band structures usually remain unaffected by doping via a chemical-potential shift or by increasing the temperature in conventional band insulators. In contrast, it has been shown that those of Mott and Kondo insulators can be altered by doping or by increasing the temperature: electronic modes are induced within the band gap, exhibiting momentum-shifted magnetic dispersion relations from the band edges. Here, this study demonstrates that the underlying mechanism of the remarkable strong-correlation effects can be generalized to the emergence of electronic modes caused by various spin and charge perturbations, including magnetization of spin-gapped Mott and Kondo insulators. These emergent modes can alter the band structure if a macroscopic number of spins or charges are excited by the perturbations at a given moment. The origins and dispersion relations of these emergent modes, particularly why and how the dispersion relations depend on the momentum and energy of the perturbations, are elucidated by investigating the selection rules and using the Bethe ansatz and the effective theory for weak inter-unit-cell hopping. The validity and generality of the theoretical results across different models and spatial dimensions are verified by numerical calculations for the one- and two-dimensional Hubbard models, periodic Anderson models, Kondo lattice models, and ladder and bilayer Hubbard models. This study provides crucial insights into why and how spin and charge perturbations can alter the band structure in strongly correlated insulators, thereby paving the way for band-structure engineering in strong-correlation electronics, which enables previously unexplored functionalities by exploiting the unconventional characteristics revealed in this paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07428v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/ythd-s2x8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 245110 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Masanori Kohno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dara: Automated multiple-hypothesis phase identification and refinement from powder X-ray diffraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19667v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Powder X-ray diffraction (XRD) is a foundational technique for characterizing crystalline materials. However, the reliable interpretation of XRD patterns, particularly in multiphase systems, remains a manual and expertise-demanding task. As a characterization method that only provides structural information, multiple reference phases can often be fit to a single pattern, leading to potential misinterpretation when alternative solutions are overlooked. To ease humans' efforts and address the challenge, we introduce Dara (Data-driven Automated Rietveld Analysis), a framework designed to automate the robust identification and refinement of multiple phases from powder XRD data. Dara performs an exhaustive tree search over all plausible phase combinations within a given chemical space and validates each hypothesis using a robust Rietveld refinement routine (BGMN). Key features include structural database filtering, automatic clustering of isostructural phases during tree expansion, peak-matching-based scoring to identify promising phases for refinement. When ambiguity exists, Dara generates multiple hypothesis which can then be decided between by human experts or with further characteriztion tools. By enhancing the reliability and accuracy of phase identification, Dara enables scalable analysis of realistic complex XRD patterns and provides a foundation for integration into multimodal characterization workflows, moving toward fully self-driving materials discovery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19667v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxing Fei, Matthew J. McDermott, Christopher L. Rom, Shilong Wang, Gerbrand Ceder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying Phase Transformations in Alloying Anodes via In-Situ Liquid Cell Hard X-ray Spectroscopy and Cryogenic Microscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16382</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16382v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding electrochemical phenomena at complex liquid solid interfaces requires linking real time structural dynamics with atomic scale interfacial chemistry. Here, we integrate operando synchrotron X-ray fluorescence and diffraction with high resolution cryogenic electron and ion multi model microscopy to provide a mechanistic understanding of Pt based alloying anodes across length scales. We directly observe the initial lithiation driven formation of Li2Pt and its evolution to a stable LiPt intermetallic phase during extended cycling via a solid solution type reaction mechanism. Simultaneously, the solid electrolyte interphase transitions from an unstable carbonate rich to a stable LiF dominated composition, confirmed by cryogenic scanning transmission electron microscopy and electron energy loss spectroscopy. Crucially, cryogenic atom probe tomography reveals spatially distinct compositional regimes within the alloy anode, including lithium flux limited, heterogeneous interfacial zone and a diffusion controlled, homogeneous LiPt alloy bulk. This nanoscale compositional gradient rationalises the emergent solid solution reaction mechanism and highlights how kinetic limitations and interface dynamics govern alloy formation and electrochemical stability. Our findings demonstrate a broadly applicable correlative framework bridging operando structural dynamics with near atomic resolution interfacial chemistry, advancing the rational design of durable alloy electrodes for next generation energy storage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16382v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Neil Mulcahy, Syeda Ramin Jannat, Yaqi Li, Tigran Simonian, Mariana Palos, James O. Douglas, Jessica M. Walker, Baptiste Gault, Mary P. Ryan, Michele Shelly Conroy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Twisted (co)homology of non-orientable Weyl semimetals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22303</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.22303v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The quasi-particle excitations in Weyl semimetals, known as Weyl fermions, are usually forced to emerge in charge-conjugate pairs by the Nielsen--Ninomiya theorem. When the Brillouin zone is non-orientable, this constraint is replaced by a $\mathbb{Z}_2$ charge cancellation, as a result of the chirality becoming ill-defined on such manifolds; this results in configurations with seemingly non-zero total chirality. Here, we set out to explain this behaviour from a purely topological perspective, and provide a classification of non-orientable Weyl semimetal topology in terms of exact sequences of twisted (co)homology groups. This leads to several discoveries of direct physical importance: in particular, we recover the $\mathbb{Z}_2$ charge cancellation in a coordinate-independent way, allowing meaningful limits to be set on its physical interpretation. A detailed discussion is provided on a specific Klein bottle-like topology induced by a momentum-space glide symmetry, including a full review of the insulating and semimetallic invariants of the system and a classification of the surface states on the non-orientable boundary. Beyond this, we provide a complete survey of all possible non-orientable Brillouin zones and their associated invariants, and extend our formalism into the realm of non-Hermitian topological physics and inversion-symmetric Weyl semimetals. Our work exemplifies the vast potential of fundamental mathematical descriptions to not only aid the corresponding physical intuition, but also predict novel and hitherto overlooked phenomena of great relevance throughout the physics research forefront.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.22303v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thijs Douwes, Marcus St{\aa}lhammar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wilson loop invariants and bulk-boundary correspondence in higher-order topological insulators with two anticommuting mirror symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.23471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.23471v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the higher-order bulk-boundary correspondence in a family of chiral-symmetric Bloch Hamiltonians with anticommuting mirror symmetries. These models generalize the $\pi$-flux square lattice, the prototypical topological quadrupole insulator, and include both separable and nonseparable models with extended and diagonal hopping. For separable systems, the product of subsystem chiral winding numbers correctly predicts the number of zero-energy corner states. However, this invariant fails in nonseparable models, motivating the development of new momentum-space diagnostics. We introduce gauge-independent mirror-filtered winding numbers for Wannier Hamiltonians, constructed by projecting mirror eigenstates onto the occupied subspace. Furthermore, by adapting periodicized Wilson lines from chiral Floquet theory to the case with momentum-dependent chiral operator, we define new invariants associated directly with Wannier gaps. These invariants provide a detailed characterization of Wannier band topology. Our results clarify the interplay between chiral symmetry, mirror symmetries, and Wilson loops in higher-order topological phases and point to open challenges in formulating momentum-space invariants for general nonseparable models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.23471v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suman Aich (IUB), Babak Seradjeh (IUB)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Highly Anisotropic Charge Dynamics and Spectral Weight Redistribution in the Trilayer Nickelate La$_{4}$Ni$_{3}$O$_{10}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.03806v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the $ab$-plane and $c$-axis charge dynamics of La$_{4}$Ni$_{3}$O$_{10}$ using optical spectroscopy. While a pronounced Drude profile, i.e. metallic response, is observed in the $ab$-plane optical conductivity $\sigma_{1}^{ab}(\omega)$, the $c$-axis optical spectra $\sigma_{1}^{c}(\omega)$ exhibit semiconducting behavior. The zero-frequency extrapolation of the optical conductivity $\sigma_{1}(\omega \rightarrow 0) \equiv 1/\rho_{\text{dc}}$ gives a resistivity anisotropy of $\rho_{c}/\rho_{ab} \simeq 366$ at 300~K for La$_{4}$Ni$_{3}$O$_{10}$, which is much larger than the values in iron-based superconductors but comparable to those in high-$T_{c}$ cuprates. The interband response is also highly anisotropic, showing salient orbital selectivity for light polarized in the $ab$ plane and along the $c$ axis. The interband-transition peaks in both $\sigma_{1}^{ab}(\omega)$ and $\sigma_{1}^{c}(\omega)$ are located at lower energies compared to density-functional-theory predictions, signifying considerable electronic correlations. By investigating the spectral weight transfer, we find that in the pristine phase, Coulomb correlations have a marked impact on the charge dynamics of \LNO, whereas in the density-wave state, a gap opens with the Ni-$d_{z^{2}}$ orbital being involved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.03806v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhe Liu, Jie Li, Deyuan Hu, Bingke Ji, Haoran Zhang, Jiahao Hao, Yaomin Dai, Qing Li, Mengjun Ou, Bing Xu, Yi Lu, Meng Wang, Hai-Hu Wen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Modulation of Long Range Photon Magnon Coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02732</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.02732v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Evidence of non-hermitian behavior has been recently demonstrated in cavity magnonics, including the emergence of mode level attraction and exceptional points in spectroscopic measurements. This work demonstrates experimental evidence of time-domain dynamics of magnon-photon systems that are coupled through a long-range interaction (i.e. remote coupling) exhibiting level attraction mediated by an auxiliary mode. We directly observe the temporal evolution of dissipatively coupled cavity-magnon modes, where heavily damped transmission line modes mediate the interaction. Our frequency-domain measurements confirm the predicted level attraction, while time-domain ring-down measurements reveal the characteristic signatures of dissipative coupling dynamics. Our approach offers in situ tunability over the dissipative coupling strength, including complete suppression, without requiring physical modifications to the experimental setup, providing a versatile platform for exploring tunable, non-Hermitian physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.02732v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alban Joseph, Mawgan A. Smith, Martin P. Weides, Rair Mac\^edo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polylogarithmic-Depth Quantum Algorithm for Simulating the Extended Hubbard Model on a Two-Dimensional Lattice Using the Fast Multipole Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03898</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.03898v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The extended Hubbard model on a two-dimensional lattice captures key physical phenomena, but is challenging to simulate due to the presence of long-range interactions. In this work, we present an efficient quantum algorithm for simulating the time evolution of this model. Our approach, inspired by the fast multipole method, approximates pairwise interactions by interactions between hierarchical levels of coarse-graining boxes. We discuss how to leverage recent advances in two-dimensional neutral atom quantum computing, supporting non-local operations such as long-range gates and shuttling. The resulting circuit depth for a single Trotter step scales polylogarithmically with system size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.03898v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Wang, Martina Nibbi, Maxine Luo, Isabel Nha Minh Le, Yanbin Chen, J. Ignacio Cirac, Christian B. Mendl</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
