<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 05:00:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Quasiparticle Variational Quantum Eigensolver</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16721</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16721v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a momentum-space based variational quantum eigensolver (VQE) framework for simulating quasiparticle excitations in interacting quantum many-body systems on near-term quantum devices. Leveraging translational invariance and other symmetries of the Hamiltonian, we reconstruct the momentum-resolved quasiparticle excitation spectrum through targeted simulation of low-lying excited states using VQE. We construct a translationally symmetric variational ansatz designed to evolve a free-fermion particle-hole excited state with definite momentum $q$ to an excited state of the interacting system at the same momentum, employing a fermionic fast Fourier transform (FFFT) circuit coupled to a Hamiltonian Variational Ansatz (HVA) circuit. Even though the particle number is not explicitly conserved in the variational ansatz, the correct quasiparticle state is reached by energetic optimization. We benchmark the performance of the proposed VQE implementation on the XXZ Hamiltonian, which maps onto the Tomonaga-Luttinger liquid in the fermionic representation. Our numerical results show that VQE can capture the low-lying excitation spectrum of the bosonic quasiparticle/two-spinon dispersion of this model at various interaction strengths. We estimate the renormalized velocity of the quasiparticles by calculating the slope of the dispersion near zero momentum using the VQE-optimized energies at different system sizes, and demonstrate that it closely matches theoretical results obtained from Bethe ansatz. Finally, we highlight extensions of our proposed VQE implementation to simulate quasiparticles in other interacting quantum many-body systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16721v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saavanth Velury, Yuxuan Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fabrication of A Dual Gated Mirror Symmetric Twisted Trilayer Graphene Device to Study Superconductivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16784v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Though research on graphene by itself has waned, the interest in moire materials, materials made with stacked layers of graphene with a rotational twist between the layers, has exploded in popularity. These layered devices show a key feature, flat bands. Flat bands localize electrons, which in turn leads to the expression of correlated states such as Mott insulators, superconductivity, and more. A key property of these devices is that their 2D nature allows us to tune them in situ, effectively allowing us to change the device's electronic properties. This powerful ability greatly reduces the time and money required to study superconductivity. The superconductivity in these systems seems to be similar to high-temperature superconductors such as cuprates, giving us a path towards studying high-temperature superconductivity. The fabrication of these devices is nontrivial, and thus we detail one general way to create these layered devices to give maximal tunability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16784v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmed Shaikh, Phanibhusan Singha Mahapatra, Eva Y. Andrei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reentrant Landau Levels in a Dirac topological insulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16806v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The quantum limit, where magnetic fields confine carriers to the lowest Landau level, is predicted to host exotic quantum phases arising from strengthened electronic correlations, reduced dimensionality, and increased degeneracy. We report a novel quantization regime realized in the ultra-quantum limit of the narrow-gap Dirac insulator ZrTe5, marked by anomalous magnetoresistance oscillations. These oscillations, measured in ZrTe5 single crystals down to 700 mK and up to 60 T, are distinctly non-1/B periodic and persist for magnetic fields well beyond the quantum limit. In this regime, the competition between Zeeman and cyclotron energies drives a nonlinear evolution and back-bending of Landau levels, causing low-index levels to re-cross the Fermi energy at high fields. This mechanism departs from the standard Lifshitz-Kosevich description and provides a framework to describe how the electronic structure in topological Dirac insulators evolves beyond the quantum limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16806v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Kaufmann Ribeiro, J. C. Mutch, Q. Jiang, J. P. Ayres-Sims, K. Rubi, C. A. Mizzi, E. A. Peterson, D. Bulmash, J. Singleton, N. Harrison, P. F. S. Rosa, J. -X. Zhu, J. -H. Chu, J. Larrea Jimenez, S. M. Thomas, J. C. Palmstrom</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cusped Electrical Conductivity in Spin-1 Chiral Fermion Systems Arising from Multifold Band Degeneracy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16969v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The energy-dependent electrical conductivity in spin-1 chiral fermion systems with disorder is studied using the self-consistent Born approximation. A distinct cusp-like feature appears at an energy different from the band-crossing point, arising from the multifold band-crossing structure formed by the Dirac and trivial bands. The energy position of the cusp and the corresponding value of the electrical conductivity are found to depend sensitively on both the impurity scattering strength and the curvature of the trivial band. These findings demonstrate the critical role of multifold band crossings and disorder-induced broadening of energy levels in determining the transport properties, offering theoretical insight into the unconventional conductivity behavior observed in topological semimetals hosting spin-1 chiral fermions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16969v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Risako Kikuchi, Junya Endo, Ai Yamakage</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Giant Nonlinear Photon-Drag Currents in Centrosymmetric Moir\'e Bilayers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16987</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16987v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a unified microscopic theory of nonlinear photon-drag currents, formulated within a geometric-loop framework that provides both transparent quantum-geometric interpretation and numerical tractability. In this picture, the photon-drag shift current corresponds to the dipole moment of the geometric loop, while the photon-drag injection current arises from the same loop weighted by a band velocity difference. We apply the theory to an exact continuum model of twisted bilayer graphene (TBG) with ab initio accuracy. Remarkably, an in-plane wavevector only a few times larger than that of free-space photons already produces sizable photon-drag currents in centrosymmetric TBG, comparable to photogalvanic responses in typical noncentrosymmetric two-dimensional materials. These currents are broadly tunable by twist angle, photon wavevector, and light polarization. Our results establish a quantum geometric framework for nonlinear photon-drag phenomena and highlight moir\'e bilayers as promising platforms for large, highly tunable optoelectronic responses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16987v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhuocheng Lu, Zhuang Qian, Zhichao Guo, Likun Shi, Shi Liu, Hua Wang, Kai Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pair scattering from time-modulated impurity in the Bose-Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17032</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17032v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate scattering phenomena in a one-dimensional attractive Bose-Hubbard model with a time-periodically modulated impurity. We analyze both single-particle and pair (doublon) transmission, exploring a range of interaction strengths and drive amplitudes. Our exact numerical results reveal excellent quantitative agreement with analytical predictions in the high-frequency limit. At intermediate and weak attractive interactions, we observe significant pair dissociation and the emergence of dynamically localized single-particle modes. These features are reminiscent of Floquet Bound States in the Continuum (BICs). These findings provide new avenues for engineering controllable quantum transport and localized states in ultracold atom experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17032v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Neda Ahmadi, Ameneh Sheikhan, Corinna Kollath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unconventional Geometric Phase in Twisted Junction of Cuprates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17033v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Originally introduced in optics, the Pancharatnam-Berry phase is a general concept of geometric phase defined for any two interfering polarization states. In electronic systems, however, its counterpart has long been overlooked due to the absence of electron polarization. Here, using large-scale first-principles calculations, we investigate the electronic structure of twisted bilayer Bi2Sr2CaCu2O8. We find spontaneous spin polarization and the emergence of hidden flat bands at the interface between atomic layers. Most notably, we discover an unconventional geometric phase analogous to the Pancharatnam-Berry phase in optics. This electronic geometric phase exerts opposite effects on superconducting currents of opposite chirality, enabling twisted cuprates to act as a filter for chiral superconducting current-even if the ground state itself is non-chiral.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17033v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhigang Song, Kai Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-to-mid Al content ($x\sim$ 0-0.56) Al$_x$In$_{1-x}$N layers deposited on Si(100) by radio-frequency sputtering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17039</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17039v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Radio-frequency (RF) sputtering is a low-cost technique for the deposition of large-area single-phase AlInN on silicon layers with application in photovoltaic devices. Here, the effect of the Al mole fraction x from 0 to 0.56 on the structural, morphological, electrical, and optical properties of $n$ Al$_x$In$_{1-x}$N layers deposited at 550 $^\circ$C on p-Si(100) by RF sputtering is studied. X-ray diffraction data show a wurtzite structure oriented along the c-axis in all samples, where the full width at half maximum of the rocking curve around the InN (0002) diffraction peak decreases from $\sim 9^\circ$ to $\sim 3^\circ$ while incorporating Al to the AlInN layer. The rootmean-square surface roughness, estimated from atomic force microscopy, evolves from 20 nm for InN to 1.5 nm for Al$_{0.56}$In$_{0.44}$N. Low-temperature photoluminescence spectra show a blueshift of the emission energy from 1.59 eV (779 nm) for InN to 1.82 eV (681 nm) for Al$_{0.35}$In$_{0.65}$N according to the Al content rise. Hall effect measurements of Al$_x$In$_{1-x}$N ($0&lt;x &lt;0.35$) on sapphire samples grown simultaneously point to a residual n-type carrier concentration in the 1021 cm$^{-3}$ range. The developed n-AlInN/p-Si junctions present promising material properties to explore their performance operating as solar cell devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17039v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/pssb.201900575</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>R. Blasco, S. Valdueza-Felip, D. Montero, M. Sun, J. Olea, F. B. Naranjo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A topological field-effect memristor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17090</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17090v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Overcoming the limitations of the von Neumann architecture requires new computational paradigms capable of solving complex problems efficiently. Quantum and neuromorphic computing rely on unconventional materials and device functionalities, yet achieving resilience to imperfections and reliable operation remains a major challenge. This has motivated growing interest in topological materials that provide robust and low-power operation while preserving coherence. However, integrating coherent topological transport with non-volatile memory functionality in a single reconfigurable device has remained challenging. In this work, we demonstrate a topological field-effect memristor based on inverted InAs/GaInSb/InAs trilayer quantum wells operating in the quantum spin Hall regime. The intrinsic floating-gate behavior allows one to reconfigure the transistor functionality into memristive functionality with broad electric-field tunability. Unlike other memristor implementations, one resistance state is governed entirely by dissipationless, coherent transport through helical edge channels, while the other arises from incoherent bulk conduction. By combining electrically tunable coherent and incoherent transport with memory functionality, our device realizes a prototypical topological electronic element that integrates coherent transport and adaptive memristive behavior, paving the way for hybrid quantum-neuromorphic architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17090v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manuel Meyer, Selena Barragan, Sergey Krishtopenko, Adriana Wolf, Monika Emmerling, Sebastian Schmid, Jean-Baptiste Rodriguez, Eric Tournie, Benoit Jouault, Gerald Bastard, Frederic Teppe, Victor Lopez-Richard, Ovidiu Lipan, Lukas Worschech, Sven H\"ofling, Fabian Hartmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single-Defect Spectroscopy via Random Telegraph Noise in Graphene-Contacted ReS$_2$-hBN Heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17125</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17125v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Defect spectroscopy in two-dimensional (2D) field-effect transistors (FETs) requires device architectures that suppress contact and disorder artifacts while preserving intrinsic carrier dynamics. Here, we demonstrate ReS$_2$-hBN FETs with few-layer graphene (FLG) van der Waals contacts that form nearly barrier-free interfaces, enabling intrinsic transport in ReS$_2$, an anisotropic, low-symmetry TMDC rarely exhibiting disorder-free behavior. The clean ReS$_2$-FLG platform allows direct observation of random telegraph noise (RTN) even in micron-scale channels, manifested as discrete two-level current fluctuations between 90-150 K arising from stochastic trapping at localized hBN defect sites. With increasing temperature, the RTN evolves into a 1/f spectrum as multiple traps activate. Statistical analysis of RTN amplitudes and capture-emission kinetics identifies substitutional carbon-related centers in hBN as dominant defects. These findings establish a generalizable approach for probing dielectric-origin defect dynamics in intrinsically conducting, low-symmetry 2D semiconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17125v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shubhrasish Mukherjee, Gaurab Samanta, Shubhadip Moulick, Ruta Kulkarni, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Arumugum Thamizhavel, Atindra Nath Pal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Boundary Spins in the Su-Schrieffer-Heeger-Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17173</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17173v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Studying boundary excitations provides a powerful approach to probe correlations in topological phases. We propose that localized spins near the ends of a Su-Schrieffer-Heeger-Hubbard chain embedded in an insulating environment can be detected experimentally using scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) combined with electron spin resonance (ESR). When the STM tip is in the contact regime, the tip-end-spin coupling realizes an effective Anderson impurity problem, giving rise to a Kondo peak at low bias. Spatially resolving the Kondo resonance width as the STM tip approaches the chain ends provides an indirect yet clear signature of these localized spins. To support this proposal, we use density-matrix renormalization group (DMRG) to calculate the spin gap and spin projection of end states for chains of various lengths and interaction strengths $U$ at half-filling. In the non-interacting limit ($U=0$), we derive simple analytical expressions that reproduce the numerical results for sufficiently long chains. We also discuss how the correlated phase of the isolated chain is characterized by boundary zeros in its single-particle Green's function, and briefly comment on their localization properties in relation to the boundary spins.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17173v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Armando A. Aligia, Alejandro M. Lobos, Lucila Peralta Gavensky, Claudio J. Gazza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable Kondo effect in a bilayer graphene quantum channel</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17188v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The interaction between itinerant electrons and localized spins is key to a wide range of electronic phenomena. Of particular interest is the regime where the interacting electrons exhibit both spin and valley degeneracy, resulting in SU(4) Kondo physics. However, this regime is challenging to realize in typical mesoscopic systems because it requires a strong interaction between electrons, resulting in a Kondo temperature ($T_\mathrm{K}$) significantly larger than the spin and valley splittings. Here, we present conductance measurements of a quantum point contact (QPC) in bilayer graphene (BLG). Beyond the expected quantized conductance plateaus, which reflect spin and valley degeneracy, we observe an additional subband, known as `0.7 anomaly' exhibiting signatures of Kondo physics and a $T_\mathrm{K}$ ranging from approximately 0.5 up to 2.4 K at zero magnetic field, corresponding to Kondo energies between 40 and 200 $\mu$eV. Given that the spin-orbit splitting in BLG is between 40 and 80 $\mu$eV, we argue that these results are consistent with a transition between four-fold degenerate SU(4) and two-fold degenerate spin-valley locked SU(2) Kondo effects. Furthermore, we break the valley degeneracy of the lowest subband by an out-of-plane magnetic field and show that Kondo signatures remain present, indicating a transition from SU(4) to a valley-polarized SU(2) Kondo effect, and showing the versatility of BLG QPCs for exploring many-body effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17188v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Josep Ingla-Ayn\'es, Serhii Volosheniuk, Talieh S. Ghiasi, Angelika Knothe, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Vladimir I. Fal'ko, Herre S. J. van der Zant</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ferroelectric Switchable Topological Magnon Hall Effect in Type-I Multiferroics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17189</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17189v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Electric control of magnetism at room temperature is crucial for developing next-generation, low-power spintronic devices. However, the intrinsic incompatibility between ferroelectricity and magnetism in crystal symmetry, along with the absence of strong magnetoelectric coupling mechanisms, continues to pose major challenges. In this work, we propose a general theoretical framework for magnon manipulation based on ferroelectric polarization switching in two-dimensional multiferroics. Taking monolayer multiferroics $\mbox{Ti}_{2}\mbox{F}_{3}$ as an example, our calculations demonstrate that ferroelectric switching can significantly modulate spin exchanges, thereby enabling nonvolatile and reversible electric control of the magnons. More importantly, the ferroelectric polarization reversal leads to a sign change in the Berry curvature, ensuring effective control over the valley Hall and nonlinear Hall response of magnons. This study provides a new way for realizing low-power and electrically controllable magnonic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17189v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Quanchao Du, Jinlian Lu, Xueqing Wan, Zhenlong Zhang, Zhijun Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Altermagnetic Flatband-Driven Fermi Surface Geometry for Giant Tunneling Magnetoresistance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17277v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Altermagnetism, characterized by zero net magnetization and symmetry-protected spin-split band structures, has recently emerged as a promising platform for spintronics. In altermagnetic tunnel junctions (AMTJs), the suppression of tunneling in the antiparallel configuration relies on the mismatch between spin-polarized conduction channels in momentum space. However, ideal nonoverlapping spin-polarized Fermi surfaces are rarely found in bulk altermagnets. Motivated by the critical influence of Fermi surface geometry on tunneling magnetoresistance (TMR), we investigate three experimentally synthesized altermagnets -- bulk $\mathrm{V_2Te_2O}$, $\mathrm{RbV_2Te_2O}$, and $\mathrm{KV_2Se_2O}$ -- to elucidate how flatband-driven Fermi surfaces minimize spin-channel overlap and boost AMTJ performance. Notably, $\mathrm{RbV_2Te_2O}$ and $\mathrm{KV_2Se_2O}$ host flat altermagnetic Fermi sheets, which confine spin degeneracy to minimal arc-like or nodal-like regions. Such Fermi surface geometry drastically reduces spin overlap, resulting in an unprecedented intrinsic TMR well over $10^3\%$ in the $\mathrm{KV_2Se_2O}$-based AMTJ. Incorporating an insulating barrier further enhances the TMR to $\sim10^5\%$, surpassing most conventional MTJs. These results not only establish $\mathrm{KV_2Se_2O}$ as a compelling candidate AMTJ material, but also highlight the critical role of flatband Fermi surface geometry in achieving high-performance altermagnetic-spintronic device technology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17277v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xingyue Yang, Shibo Fang, Zongmeng Yang, Pin Ho, Jing Lu, Yee Sin Ang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Building 3D superconductor-based Josephson junctions using a via transfer approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17386v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The coupling of superconductivity to unconventional materials may lead to novel quantum states and potential applications. Controlling the quality of the superconductor-normal metal interface is of crucial importance to the understanding and engineering of the superconducting proximity effect. In many cases, conventional lithography-based deposition methods introduce undesirable effects. Using the concept of via contact and dry transfer, we have constructed smooth, van der Waals-like contact between 3D superconducting NbN/Pd and graphene with low contact resistance of approximately 130 $\Omega \cdot \mu m$. Gate-tunable supercurrent, Fraunhofer pattern, and Andreev reflections are observed, the properties of which can be understood using an induced superconducting gap $\Delta$' in this planar contact geometry. We discuss potential mechanisms impacting the magnitude of $\Delta$' and suggest ways of further increasing the proximity coupling. This gentle, lithography-free contacting method can be applied to air- and damage-sensitive surfaces to engineer novel superconducting heterostructures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17386v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cequn Li, Le Yi, Kalana D. Halanayake, Jessica L. Thompson, Yingdong Guan, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Zhiqiang Mao, Danielle Reifsnyder Hickey, Morteza Kayyalha, Jun Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crystal Growth and Physical Properties of Orthorhombic Kagome Lattice Magnets $R$Fe$_6$Ge$_6$ ($R$=Y, Tb, Dy)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17398</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17398v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Kagome magnets represent a promising class of materials that exhibit intriguing electronic and magnetic properties, and they have recently garnered significant attention. While most kagome-lattice compounds are hexagonal, here we report the single-crystal growth and physical property measurements of similar compounds $R$Fe$_6$Ge$_6$ ($R$ = Y, Dy, Tb), which crystallize in an orthorhombic structure. The structure can be derived from a hexagonal prototype $R$Fe$_3$Ge$_2$ by replacing every other $R$ atom with a covalent Ge$_2$ dimer. Ordering of the latter makes the structure orthorhombic the kagome net slightly distorted, and the three Fe sites formally inequivalent. The iron and rare-earth sublattices order independently: the Fe moments order above 400 K having, with ferromagnetic Kagome planes stacked antiferromagnetically, while the rare-earth moments order below 9 K. While TbFe$_6$Ge$_6$ exhibits a single magnetic ordering transition associated with the Tb atoms, DyFe$_6$Ge$_6$ shows two distinct magnetic phase transitions, which are strongly influenced by crystal electric field effects on the Dy$^{3+}$ ions. Density functional theory (DFT) calculations show that the ferromagnetic ordering of the Fe planes is driven by a high density of states at the Fermi energy. They also reveals three dramatically different structural energy scales: $R$ and Ge$_2$ form alternating 1D chains perpendicular to the kagome planes, and violating this alternation incurs a huge energy cost. Aligning these chains is less costly, and actual 2D order of anti-aligned chains costs very little. These compounds represent a unique class of materials, offering new possibilities to investigate the interplay between the distinct crystal lattice geometry and the underlying electronic and magnetic properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17398v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhijeet Nayak, Sk Jamaluddin, Fan Wu, Emily Rapp, Resham Babu Regmi, Mohamed El Gazzah, Bence G. M\'arkus, L\'aszl\'o Forr\'o, Madhav P. Ghimire, Allen Oliver, Kateryna Foyevtsova, Igor I. Mazin, Nirmal J. Ghimire</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Momentum-Resolved Electronic Structure and Orbital Hybridization in the Layered Antiferromagnet CrPS$_4$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17403</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17403v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Chromium thiophosphate (CrPS$_4$) is a layered two-dimensional antiferromagnetic semiconductor exhibiting intriguing spintronic and magneto-optical properties, yet its electronic band structure has remained experimentally uncharacterized. Here, we employ momentum-resolved photoemission spectroscopy above and below the N\'eel temperature, complemented by density functional theory with Hubbard U corrections (DFT+U), to reveal a valence band dominated by Cr $3d$ and S $3p$ states with a ligand-to-metal charge-transfer band gap. We identify weakly hybridized t$_{2g}$ orbitals responsible for magnetic ordering and strongly hybridized e$_{g}$ orbitals that relax dipole selection rules, enabling optically active orbital transitions. These findings establish a foundational understanding of CrPS$_4$'s electronic structure, providing a benchmark for theoretical models and informing future investigations into its orbital physics and potential device applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17403v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lasse Sternemann, David Maximilian Janas, Eshan Banerjee, Richard Leven, Jonah Elias Nitschke, Marco Marino, Leon Becker, Ahmet Can Ademo\u{g}lu, Frithjof Anders, Stefan Tappertzhofen, Mirko Cinchetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Breakdown of chiral anomaly and emergent phases in Weyl semimetals under orbital magnetic fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17412v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An external orbital magnetic field applied perpendicular to the separation vector of a pair of Weyl points can couple them and induce a gap in the electronic spectrum. In this work, we investigate the gap-opening behavior in the presence of a lattice, revealing rich phenomenology absent in the continuum picture. Specifically, we address the emergence of layered Chern insulating states, examining how the anisotropy of the Weyl cone dispersion influences the sequence of phase transitions, and establishing connections to the continuum limit. We analyze the evolution of surface Fermi-arc states across these regimes, highlighting their distinct behaviors during the gap-opening transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17412v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Faruk Abdulla, Anna Keselman, Daniel Podolsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flat band surface state superconductivity in thick rhombohedral graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17423</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17423v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rhombohedral multilayer graphene has recently emerged as a rich platform for studying correlation driven magnetic, topological and superconducting states. While most experimental efforts have focused on devices with N$\leq 9$ layers, the electronic structure of thick rhombohedral graphene features flat-band surface states even in the infinite layer limit. Here, we use layer resolved capacitance measurements to directly detect these surface states for $N\approx 13$ layer rhombohedral graphene devices. Using electronic transport and local magnetometry, we find that the surface states host a variety of ferromagnetic phases, including both valley imbalanced quarter metals and broad regimes of density in which the system spontaneously spin polarizes. We observe several superconducting states localized to a single surface state. These superconductors appear on the unpolarized side of the density-tuned spin transitions, and show strong violations of the Pauli limit consistent with a dominant attractive interaction in the spin-triplet, valley-singlet pairing channel. In contrast to previous studies of rhombohedral multilayers, however, we find that superconductivity can persist to zero displacement field where the system is inversion symmetric. Energetic considerations suggest that superconductivity in this regime is described by the existence of two independent surface superconductors coupled via tunneling through the insulating single crystal graphite bulk.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17423v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi Guo, Owen I. Sheekey, Trevor Arp, Kry\v{s}tof Kol\'a\v{r}, Thibault Charpentier, Ludwig Holleis, Ben Foutty, Aidan Keough, Maya Kang-Chou, Martin E. Huber, Takashi Taniguchi, Kenji Watanabe, Cyprian Lewandowski, Andrea F. Young</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Origin of large topological Hall effect in the EuCd$_2$Sb$_2$ antiferromagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17445v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the origin of large topological Hall effect in the single-crystalline EuCd$_2$Sb$_2$, which orders antiferromagnetically at the N\'eel temperature $T_{\rm N}=7.4$ K. Measurements of magnetoresistance and Hall resistivity disclose anomalies that evolve with temperature and magnetic field, closely tracking the magnetization process. Analysis of these data identifies three possible mechanisms responsible for the enhanced Berry curvature driving the observed topological Hall effect. Below and above $T_{\rm N}$, Weyl states are the main sources of large momentum-space Berry curvature, though their formation mechanisms differ in these two temperature ranges. Below $T_{\rm N}$, breaking of $C_{3}$ symmetry generates Dirac points that split into Weyl nodes in applied magnetic field, whereas above $T_{\rm N}$, strong spin fluctuations can induce Weyl states. The third contribution, which occurs below $T_{\rm N}$, arises from scalar spin chirality developing within antiferromagnetic domain walls, which generates a real-space Berry curvature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17445v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Faheem Gul, Orest Pavlosiuk, Tetiana Romanova, Dariusz Kaczorowski, Piotr Wi\'sniewski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frustration driven magnetic correlations in the spin-$5/2$ triangular lattice antiferromagnet RbFe(HPO$_{3}$)$_{2}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17480</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17480v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A detailed study of the structural and magnetic properties of a spin-$5/2$ triangular lattice antiferromagnet RbFe(HPO$_{3}$)$_{2}$ is presented using x-ray diffraction, magnetization, heat capacity, and $^{31}$P nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) experiments on a polycrystalline sample. The crystal structure features an equilateral triangular lattice of Fe$^{3+}$ ions. The thermodynamic measurements reveal the onset of a magnetic long-range order at $T_{\rm N1} \simeq 7.8$ K in zero-field, followed by another low temperature field induced ordering at $T_{\rm N2}$ in higher fields. The transition at $T_{\rm N1}$ is further confirmed from the NMR spin lattice relaxation measurements. The value of the frustration ratio ($f \simeq 7$) implies moderate spin frustration in the compound. The $^{31}$P NMR spectra exhibit two distinct spectral lines corresponding to two inequivalent phosphorus sites (P1 and P2), consistent with the crystal structure. The P1 site is strongly coupled with an isotropic hyperfine coupling of $A_{\rm hf}^{\rm iso} = 0.55(2)$ T/$\mu_{\rm B}$ while the P2 site is weakly coupled with $A_{\rm hf}^{\rm iso} = 0.25(3)$ T/$\mu_{\rm B}$ with the Fe$^{3+}$ ions. The magnetic susceptibility and NMR shift data are described well assuming a spin-$5/2$ isotropic triangular lattice antiferromagnetic model with an average exchange coupling of $J/k_{\rm B} = 2.8(2)$ K. Below $T_{\rm N1}$, the spectra evolve into a nearly rectangular powder pattern, indicating a commensurate antiferromagnetic type order. The $^{31}$P spin-lattice relaxation rate well below $T_{\rm N1}$ follows a $T^3$ temperature dependence, implying a two-magnon Raman scattering mechanism in the ordered state. Three well-defined phase regimes are clearly ascertained in the $H-T$ phase diagram, reflecting a weak magnetic anisotropy in the compound.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17480v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Nagpal, Sebin J. Sebastian, Surya P. Patra, S. Shibash, Q. -P. Ding, Y. Furukawa, R. Nath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient prediction of topological superlattice bands with spin-orbit coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17483</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17483v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a symmetry indicator framework to efficiently predict the topology of superlattice-induced minibands with spin-orbit coupling. Our algorithm requires input only from the parent material before the superlattice is applied. The simplification arises by assuming a perturbatively weak superlattice potential; however, our results extend beyond the perturbative regime as long as the superlattice-induced gaps remain open. We first consider a time-reversal- and inversion-symmetric system subject to a weak superlattice potential and derive a compact formula for the $\mathbb{Z}_2$ invariant of the lowest miniband. We then extend to time-reversal breaking systems and compute the Chern number. We apply our theory to selected transition metal dichalcogenides, HgTe/CdTe quantum wells, and thin films of three-dimensional topological insulators and Dirac semimetals. We find topological superlattice bands can arise even from non-topological materials, broadening the pool of candidates for realizing topological flat bands. Our theory predicts which geometry and periodicity of superlattice will yield topological bands for a given material, providing a clear guiding principle for designing topological superlattice heterostructures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17483v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Nabil Y. Lhachemi, Valentin Cr\'epel, Jennifer Cano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractional Chern insulator edges: crystalline effects and optical measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17494</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17494v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Edge states of chiral topologically ordered phases are commonly described by chiral Luttinger liquids, effective theories that are exact only in the hydrodynamic limit. Motivated by recent bulk observations of fractional Chern insulators (FCIs) in two-dimensional materials and by synthetic realizations in ultracold atoms, we revisit this framework and quantify deviations from the hydrodynamic limit due to lattice effects. Using a combination of analytical arguments and numerical simulations, we disentangle universal from nonuniversal edge properties. We outline experimental probes in excitonic FCIs and in ultracold atom systems, and in particular propose time-resolved edge spectroscopy to directly access the predicted exponents and velocities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17494v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan-Qi Wang, Johannes Motruk, Andrey Grankin, Mohammad Hafezi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aspects of quantum geometry in photonic time crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17317v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a geometric description of quantum light in photonic time crystals on the SU(1,1) coherent-state manifold. In a projective picture, the evolution of each mode appears as a M\"obius isometry on the Poincar\'e disk, where topologies of trajectories distinguish stable, unstable, and critical regimes. The geometric phase is related to the hyperbolic area enclosed by cyclic paths in the complex projective Hilbert space. This framework offers an intuitive view of stability and topology in quantum photonic time crystals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17317v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karthik Subramaniam Eswaran, Ali Emami Kopaei, Krzysztof Sacha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Spin Transfer in WTe2/Fe3GeTe2 van der Waals Heterostructure Enabled by Direct Interlayer p-Orbital Hybridization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02966</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02966v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent experiments have demonstrated efficient spin transfer across layers in the van der Waals heterostructure composed of WTe2 and Fe3GeTe2, signaling a potential breakthrough in developing all-van der Waals spin-orbit torque devices. However, the reasons behind the unusually high interlayer spin transparency observed, despite the weak van der Waals interactions between layers, remain unclear. In this study, we employ density functional theory and the non-equilibrium Green's function method to explore this phenomenon. We find that the efficient cross-layer spin transfer arises from direct hybridization of p-orbitals between tellurium atoms at the interface. This interlayer orbital hybridization lowers the electronic potential barrier and significantly modifies the spin-polarized electronic structure of Fe3GeTe2. Consequently, an effective channel for spin-polarized transport is established between WTe2 and Fe3GeTe2, leading to high interlayer spin transparency. Combining this enhanced spin transparency with the large spin Hall angle of WTe2 explains the high spin-orbit torque efficiency observed experimentally. Furthermore, we predict that applying a gate voltage can further increase this efficiency. Our findings offer a pathway for designing high-performance, all-van der Waals spin-orbit torque devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02966v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. L. Ning, M. Q. Dong, X. Zhang, J. S. Huang, B. Liu, Zhi-Xin Guo, Y. Dong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of Topological Hall Effect in Synthetic Antiferromagnetic Skyrmion System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15012</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.15012v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Synthetic antiferromagnetic (SAF) skyrmions have emerged as promising candidates for next-generation high-speed and highly integrated spintronic devices, owing to their exceptional properties such as high driving velocity, nanoscale dimensions, and the absence of the skyrmion Hall effect. In this work, we report the observation of the topological Hall effect in both compensated and non-compensated synthetic antiferromagnetic skyrmion systems based on [Pt/Co/Ru]2 bilayers. The antiferromagnetic skyrmions are demonstrated to be robust in these synthetic antiferromagnets under zero-field. Our first principal calculations and micromagnetic simulations demonstrate that the formation of the antiferromagnetic skyrmions are due to nonuniformity of RKKY coupling associated with the proximity effect induced magnetic moments in the Pt and Ru layers. The skyrmions in the Pt and Ru layers adjacent to the Co layers lead to the observed topological Hall effect. This work not only provides insight into the effect of the magnetic proximity effect and RKKY coupling to the SAF skyrmions, but also an effective detection method for the SAF skyrmion systems, thereby laying a foundation for the practical application of antiferromagnetic skyrmions in spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.15012v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinbao Geng, Guanqi Li, Zhongxiang Zhang, Wenjing Hu, Wenjing Zhong, Xiaoming Xiong, Yongbing Xu, Zhendong Chen, Junlin Wang, Xiangyu Zheng, Jing Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher Chern bands in helical homotrilayer transition metal dichalcogenides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17819</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17819v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose helically twisted homotrilayer transition metal dichalcogenides as a platform for realizing correlated topological phases of matter with higher and tunable Chern numbers. We show that a clear separation of scales emerges for small twist angles, allowing us to derive a low-energy continuum model that captures the physics within moir\'e-scale domains. We identify regimes of twist angle and displacement field for which the highest-lying hole band is isolated from other bands and is topological with $K$-valley Chern number $C=-2$. We demonstrate that varying the displacement field can induce a transition from $C=-2$ to $C=-1$, as well as from a topologically trivial band to a $C=-1$ band. We derive an effective tight-binding description for a high-symmetry stacking domain which is valid for a wide range of twist angles, and we show that the $C=-2$ band can remain stable at filling fraction $\nu=-1$ in the presence of interactions in Hartree-Fock calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17819v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/6jf2-7mst</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 205122 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jungho Daniel Choi, Nicol\'as Morales-Dur\'an, Yves H. Kwan, Andrew J. Millis, Nicolas Regnault, Daniele Guerci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exchange tensors, generalized RKKY interactions, and magnetization dynamics in heterostructures of ferromagnets and topological insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03572v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive theoretical analysis of magnetic heterostructures composed of ferromagnetic (FM) layers interfaced with three-dimensional topological insulators (TIs). Integrating out the topological surface states and computing the spin determinant to second order in spins, we derive the effective generalized Ruderman-Kittel-Kasuya-Yosida (RKKY) exchange interactions mediated by topological surface states. These interactions inherently incorporate spin-momentum locking and anisotropic spin susceptibilities stemming from the Dirac-like dispersion of the TI surface electrons. The analysis reveals that the interplay between the spin-orbit coupling intrinsic to the TI and the magnetization in the FM layer induces highly nonlocal and retarded, chiral, and Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya (DM)-like contributions to the effective spin Hamiltonian. Furthermore, the spin dynamics is studied through a derivation of the LLG equation for this problem. The induced interactions renormalize many of the FM's intrinsic properties, but a new term in the LLG equation is induced that is related to the rate of change of the magnetization's curl, which is relevant to skyrmion dynamics. The magnon dispersion exhibits modifications due to the TI-mediated interactions, including a softened inertial spin-wave mode and tunable magnon gaps, sensitive to a tunable chemical potential and interfacial exchange coupling strength. The results also apply to finite temperatures. They elucidate topologically induced magnetic phenomena and pave the way for engineering exotic spin textures, such as skyrmions and chiral domain walls, in TI-FM hybrid systems with tunable interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03572v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Svingen Johnsen, Asle Sudb\o</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ferroelectricity-driven altermagnetism in two-dimensional van der Waals multiferroics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00712v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Altermagnets (AMs) are a recently identified class of unconventional collinear compensated antiferromagnets that exhibit momentum-dependent spin splitting despite having zero net magnetization. This unconventional magnetic order gives rise to a range of phenomena, including the anomalous Hall effect, chiral magnons, and nonlinear photocurrents. Here, using spin space group (SSG) symmetry analysis and first-principles calculations, we demonstrate an efficient strategy to control altermagnetism in two-dimensional multiferroics through ferroelectric polarization and interlayer sliding. For material realization, we find that monolayer and bilayer FeCuP2S6 exhibit finite spin splitting when ferroelectric sublattices are connected by nonsymmorphic screw-axis operations rather than pure translation or inversion symmetry. Interlayer sliding further enables reversible switching or suppression of spin splitting through modifications of the SSG. Our calculations further reveal that the anomalous Hall response serves as a direct probe of these spin-split states. These findings establish two-dimensional van der Waals multiferroics as promising platforms for realizing electrically controllable altermagnetism and advancing next-generation spintronic and magnetoelectric technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00712v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bo Zhao, Fu Li, Wei Ren, Hao Wang, Hongbin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moir\'e-induced gapped phases in twisted nodal superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15708v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We demonstrate the emergence of gapped phases driven by the moir\'{e} superlattice that trivialize the topological states in twisted nodal superconductors. The effect arises from umklapp tunneling between non-adjacent Dirac points in momentum space close to specific twist angles or chemical potentials, determined by the Fermi surface geometry. We confirm the robustness of the non-topological phase against interactions with self-consistent calculations and show that this gap competes with the previously predicted topological gapped phases, leading to topological phase transitions. These transitions were overlooked in prior literature, signifying the necessity of modifying the phase diagrams of topological phases exhibited in twisted nodal superconductors with and without an interlayer current. We also estimate the relevant twist angles and discuss experimental signatures, focusing on twisted Bi$_2$Sr$_2$CaCu$_2$O$_{8+x}$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15708v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin P. Lucht, J. H. Pixley, Pavel A. Volkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
