<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 05:00:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Anisotropic scattering rates in strain-tuned Sr$_2$RuO$_4$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09024</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.09024v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by recent angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) experiments, we analyze the temperature, frequency, and momentum dependence of the single-particle scattering rate in a model of the $\gamma$-band of Sr$_2$RuO$_4$ under strain, with particular emphasis on the behavior near the Lifshitz transition where the Fermi energy crosses a single Van Hove point. While the scattering rate is only moderately anisotropic at zero strain, we find that it becomes strongly anisotropic at the Lifshitz point. At the lowest energies, we recover the expected universal behavior: the scattering rate varies (ignoring logarithmic corrections) as $\tau^{-1}\sim \omega $ at the Van Hove point and as $\tau^{-1}\sim \omega^{3/2}$ away from it. At higher energies, however, corrections of order $\omega^2$ become important in both regimes. We show that the experimentally observed behavior $\tau^{-1} \sim \omega^{\alpha}$ with $\alpha \approx 1.4(2)$ at the Van Hove point can be quantitatively explained by a superposition of linear and quadratic contributions to the scattering rate, which are comparable in magnitude at the intermediate energies probed by experiment, rather than in terms of a new universal power law. We further predict a distinctive anisotropy, strain dependence, and a non-monotonic frequency dependence of the scattering rate at a Lifshitz transition, all of which may be directly tested in experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.09024v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ben Currie, David T. S. Perkins, Evgeny Kozik, Joseph J. Betouras, J\"org Schmalian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital magnetization from parallel transport of Bloch states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09051</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.09051v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum geometric formulations of linear and nonlinear responses can be constructed from a single building block in the form of a gauge-invariant interband transition operator. Here, we identify a second building block for quantum geometry: a band-resolved adiabatic connection operator that captures the noncommutativity between band projectors and their momentum derivatives. The band-resolved adiabatic connection operator, first introduced in the theory of adiabatic driving, serves as a generalized angular momentum within the state manifold of single bands, and we employ it to reformulate expressions for the band-resolved orbital magnetic moment. This form provides a complementary geometric interpretation alongside the multiband separation between energetic- and quantum-state properties by the two-state Berry curvature. Our formalism allows us to present formulas valid for both nondegenerate and degenerate bands, thereby removing the limitations of the common Bloch-state formula. We illustrate our theory by calculating a large orbital magnetization emerging without spin-orbit coupling in a spin-compensated, noncoplanar anomalous Hall magnet with degenerate bands.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.09051v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johannes Mitscherling, Jan Priessnitz, Libor \v{S}mejkal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of ubiquitous charge correlations and hidden quantum critical point in hole-doped kagome superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09256</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.09256v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The interplay between superconductivity and charge-density wave (CDW) order, and its evolution with carrier density, is central to the physics of many quantum materials, notably high-$T_c$ cuprates and kagome metals. Hole-doped kagome compounds exhibit puzzling double-dome superconductivity and, as chemical substitution inevitably introduces quenched disorder, their properties remain poorly understood. Here, by leveraging the sensitivity of nuclear quadrupole resonance to local and static orderings, we uncover new features, primarily the incipient and fragmented CDW phases, in the charge landscape of CsV$_3$Sb$_{5-x}$Sn$_x$. Static CDW puddles are observed well above the transition temperature, a hallmark of pinning by defects. Their doping and temperature evolution indicate that, in the absence of disorder, the inverse Star-of-David $\pi$-shifted (ISD-$\pi$) CDW order would vanish near $x=0.12$, between the two superconducting domes. This critical doping represents a hidden quantum critical point. Nevertheless, the ISD-$\pi$ pattern persists well beyond previous reports, although its volume fraction is progressively reduced up to the critical doping at which it saturates. We establish that carrier doping promotes fragmentation of the ISD-$\pi$ order, whereas randomness preserves the ISD-$\pi$ patches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.09256v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ilija K. Nikolov, Giuseppe Allodi, Adrien Rosuel, Ginevra Corsale, Anshu Kataria, Pietro Bonf\`a, Roberto De Renzi, Andrea Capa Salinas, Stephen D. Wilson, Marc-Henri Julien, Samuele Sanna, Vesna F. Mitrovi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bulk superconductivity in the kagome metal YRu3B2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.09314v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Materials with a kagome sublattice have been heavily studied recently for their exotic electronic band structure, structural frustration, high-temperature charge order transitions, and unconventional electron-phonon coupling. In LaRu3Si2, it was proposed that electronic flat bands conspire with the characteristic phonon spectrum of the kagome lattice to drive enhanced superconductivity at Tc = 7 K. Here, we report bulk superconductivity in the structural analogue YRu3B2, which hosts a structurally pristine kagome lattice. We observe a superconducting transition at Tc = 0.7 K through magnetization, resistivity, and heat-capacity measurements in this novel kagome metal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.09314v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tobi Gaggl, Ryo Misawa, Markus Kriener, Yuki Tanaka, Rinsuke Yamada, Max Hirschberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-dimensionality-induced tunable ferromagnetism in SrRuO$_3$ ultrathin films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09320</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.09320v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum materials near electronic or magnetic phase boundaries exhibit enhanced tunability, as their emergent properties become highly sensitive to external perturbations. Here, we demonstrate precise control of ferromagnetism in a SrRuO$_3$ ultrathin film, where a high density of states (DOS), arising from low-dimensional quantum states, places the system at the crossover between a non-magnetic and bulk ferromagnetic state. Using spin- and angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (SRPES/ARPES), transport measurements, and theoretical calculations, we systematically tune the Fermi level via electron doping across the high-DOS point. We directly visualize the spin-split band structure and reveal its influence on both magnetic and transport properties. Our findings provide compelling evidence that magnetism can be engineered through DOS control at a phase crossover, establishing a pathway for the rational design of tunable quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.09320v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinyoung Kim, Minjae Kim, Donghan Kim, Sungsoo Hahn, Younsik Kim, Minsoo Kim, Byungmin Sohn, Changyoung Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Translating Chirality into Multidirectional Motion through Broadband Chiroptical MXenes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.09326v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The integration of chirality into functional materials enables control of light-matter interactions beyond binary illumination (on/off). Conventional photoactuators rely on binary modulation, limiting them to unidirectional motion. In contrast, we introduce a ternary optical logic paradigm where actuation direction is encoded by the handedness of circularly polarized light (CPL). Here, we establish a chiral Ti$_{3}$C$_{2}$T$_{x}$ MXene platform bridging molecular chirality and mechanical actuation. Phenylalanine enantiomers are covalently anchored onto MXene nanoflakes via chiral nanopainting. The 2D confinement forces ligands into vertically aligned supramolecular networks. Interlayer-spacing analysis and simulations corroborate that such supramolecular networks unlock exceptionally broadband circular dichroism from the ultraviolet to the near-infrared. This supramolecular chirality synergizes with MXene's plasmonic properties to drive handedness-dependent photothermal conversion, with a 30\% differential temperature rise between matched and mismatched CPL. Embedding this chiral MXene into thermoresponsive hydrogels realizes, to the best of our knowledge, the first CPL-driven soft actuator that implements LCP/RCP/off as a ternary input to program multidirectional deformation based on a photothermal mechanism. This molecular-to-macroscopic translation demonstrates a new paradigm for chirality-encoded soft robotics and adaptive photonics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.09326v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wookjin Jung, Dongkyu Lee, Yonghee Lee, Ki Hyun Park, Jihyeon Yeom</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry-driven giant magneto-optical Kerr effects in altermagnet hematite</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09451</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.09451v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Altermagnets have attracted tremendous interest for revealing intriguing physics and promising spintronics applications. In contrast to conventional antiferromagnets, altermagnets break both PT and Tt symmetries, and simultaneously exhibit spin-split band structures with a vanishing net magnetization. To quantify insulating altermagnets without conduction electron, we propose to use magneto-optical Kerr effect (MOKE) to identify the altermagnetic fingerprints. In particular, we demonstrate not only the giant MOKE responses, but also their connection with the orientations of Neel vectors at room temperature in altermagnet hematite alpha-Fe_2O_3. Specifically, under the Neel vector along the [1-100] axis, we find a giant polar Kerr rotation angle 93.4 mdeg in the (11-20) plane, which is allowed by the magnetic space group C2'/c'. Under the Neel vector along the [11-20] axis, we find a longitudinal Kerr angle 9.6 mdeg in the (0001) plane, which is allowed by the magnetic space group C2/c. Further, we show that such pronounced MOKE effects directly enable an optical imaging of altermagnetic domains, together with their reversible domain wall (DW) motion. Our studies not only suggest MOKE can be used to identify altermagnet candidates, but also signify the feasibility of exploring altermagnetic optical and DW spintronics, which could largely expand the current research paradigm of altermagnetism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.09451v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaxin Luo, Xiaodong Zhou, Jinxuan Liang, Ledong Wang, Qiuyun Zhou, Yong Jiang, Wenhong Wang, Yugui Yao, Luyi Yang, Wanjun Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single-crystal growth, structural characterization, and physical properties of a decorated square-kagome antiferromagnet KCu$_7$TeO$_4$(SO$_4$)$_5$Cl</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.09584v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The square-kagome lattice, composed of two-dimensional corner-sharing triangles, provides a novel platform for studying frustrated magnetism. However, material realizations of the square-kagome lattice remain scarce. Here, we report the single-crystal growth, structural characterization, magnetic and electric properties of KCu$_7$TeO$_4$(SO$_4$)$_5$Cl, a nabokoite-type compound featuring a distorted and decorated square-kagome lattice. Weak anomalies near 4 K are observed in both magnetization and specific heat, indicating the onset of a magnetic transition.The formation of a long-range antiferromagnetic state below 4.5 K is further confirmed by $^{35}$Cl nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) measurements. Magnetic susceptibility data reveal nearly isotropic Curie-Weiss temperatures ($\sim-145$ K) and $g$-factors ($\sim2.4$) for both in-plane and out-of-plane magnetic fields. Moreover, we observe two successive ferroelectric transitions at $T_\mathrm{FE1}\sim30$ K and $T_\mathrm{FE2}\sim27$ K, driven by inversion-symmetry breaking, most likely associated with distortions in the Cu2O$_4$Cl$_1$ pyramids and the adjacent SO$_4$ tetrahedra. These results suggest that a three-dimensional model incorporating interlayer couplings via decorating sites is essential for capturing the magnetic and electric behaviors in KCu$_7$TeO$_4$(SO$_4$)$_5$Cl.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.09584v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingjing Jing, Andreas Eich, Yiqiu Liu, Lunhua He, Aifeng Wang, Yisheng Chai, Young Sun, Yi Cui, Weiqiang Yu, Xinrun Mi, Michael Merz, Mingquan He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconductivity and geometric superfluid weight of a tunable flat band system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09901</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.09901v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study superconductivity and superfluid weight of the two-dimensional $\alpha$-$\mathcal{T}_3$ lattice with on-site asymmetries, hosting an isolated quasi-flat band with tunable bandwidth via a parameter $\alpha$. Within a mean-field approximation of the attractive Hubbard model, we obtain the superconducting order parameters on the three inequivalent sublattices and show their strong dependence on $\alpha$, interaction strength, and electron filling. At quasi-flat band filling, a superconducting gap opens and grows power-law fast with interaction strength, instead of the usual slow exponential growth, due to diverging density of states. We calculate the superfluid weight from linear response theory and study its band dispersion and geometric contributions. While the conventional part proportional to band derivatives is suppressed in the quasi-flat band regime, the contribution dominated by the quantum metric grows linearly for small interaction strength. We further demonstrate how tuning $\alpha$ enhances the quantum metric and thus the geometric superfluid weight especially near half-filling, while increasing on-site asymmetries increases the conventional contribution by broadening the quasi-flat band. We obtain the Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless transition temperature and demonstrate its strong dependence and enhancement with the parameter $\alpha$. Our results establish a tunable flat band system, the $\alpha$-$\mathcal{T}_3$ lattice model, as a candidate for tunable quantum geometry and superfluid weight and as a prototype of related behavior in tunable quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.09901v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. A. Mojarro, Sergio E. Ulloa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Connecting single-layer $t$-$J$ to Kondo lattice models: Exploration with cold atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09926</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.09926v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Kondo effect, a hallmark of many-body physics, emerges from the antiferromagnetic coupling between localized spins and conduction fermions, leading to a correlated many-body singlet state. Here we propose to use the mixed-dimensional (mixD) bilayer Hubbard geometry as a platform to study Kondo lattice physics with current ultracold atom experiments. At experimentally feasible temperatures, we predict that key features of the Kondo effect can be observed, including formation of the Kondo cloud around a single impurity and the competition of singlet formation with Ruderman-Kittel-Kasuya-Yosida (RKKY) interactions for multiple impurities, summarized in the Doniach phase diagram. Moreover, we show that the mixD platform provides a natural bridge between the Doniach phase diagram of the Kondo lattice model, relevant to heavy-fermion materials, and the phase diagram of cuprate superconductors as described by a single-layer Zhang-Rice type $t$-$J$ model: It is possible to continuously tune between the two regimes by changing the interlayer Kondo coupling. Our findings demonstrate that the direct connection between high-temperature superconductivity and heavy-fermion physics can be experimentally studied using currently available quantum simulation platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.09926v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hannah Lange, Eugene Demler, Jan von Delft, Annabelle Bohrdt, Fabian Grusdt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Absence of transport altermagnetic spin-splitting effect in RuO2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07985</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.07985v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Altermagnets, which exhibit the advantages of both antiferromagnets and ferromagnets, have attracted significant attention recently. Among them, ruthenium dioxide (RuO2), a prototypical altermagnet candidate, is under intensive debate on its magnetic order and altermagnetic characters. In this work, we provide a comprehensive study of the spin-to-charge conversion in epitaxial RuO2 thin films with various orientations and fabrication methods. By utilizing thermal spin injections from a ferrimagnetic insulator, we unambiguously reveal a negative spin Hall angle for RuO2, which is opposite to all the previous reports using ferromagnetic metals. Most importantly, we observe robust anisotropic spin-to-charge conversion in RuO2, with voltage ratios of 30% for the (100)- and (110)-orientations and 40% for the (101)-orientations. The ratio remains consistent across RuO2 films fabricated by sputtering, pulsed laser deposition, and molecular-beam epitaxy. These results conclusively show a robust and anisotropic spin Hall effect in RuO2 with the absence of altermagnetic spin-splitting contributions. Our study provides crucial insights and advances the understanding of spin-to-charge conversions in emerging materials with low crystal symmetries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.07985v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Chun Wang, Zhe-Yu Shen, Chia-Hsi Lin, Wei-Chih Hsu, You-Sheng Chen, Yi-Ying Chin, Akhilesh Kr. Singh, Wei-Li Lee, Chien-Te Chen, Ssu-Yen Huang, Danru Qu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Monte Carlo Simulation of Bipolaron Superconductivity in Extended Hubbard--Holstein models on Face-Centered-Cubic and Body-Centered-Cubic Lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17398</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17398v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate superlight pairing of bipolarons driven by electron-phonon interactions (EPIs) in face-center-cubic (FCC) and body-center-cubic (BCC) lattices using a continuous-time path-integral quantum Monte Carlo (QMC) algorithm. The EPIs are of the Holstein and extended Holstein types, and a Hubbard interaction is also included. Effects of adiabaticity are calculated. The number of phonons associated with the bipolaron, inverse mass, and radius are calculated and used to construct a phase diagram for bipolaron pairing (identifying the regions of pairing into intersite bipolarons and onsite bipolarons). From the inverse mass we determine that for the extended interaction, there is a region of light pairing associated with intersite bipolarons formed in both BCC and FCC lattices. Intersite bipolarons in the extended model at intermediate phonon frequency and large Coulomb repulsion become superlight due to first order hopping effects. We estimate the transition temperature, determining that intersite bipolarons are associated with regions of high transition temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17398v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. D. Adebanjo, J. P. Hague, P. E. Kornilovitch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical signatures and control of time-reversal breaking in twisted nodal superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.22495v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent observations of time-reversal breaking superconductivity at twisted cuprate interfaces motivate the development of new approaches to better characterize this emergent phenomenon. Here we study the dynamical properties of the order parameters at the twisted unconventional superconductor interfaces. We reveal the emergence of a soft collective mode (Josephson plasmon) at the time-reversal breaking transition, which can be tuned by temperature, twist angle or magnetic field. Furthermore, nonlinear dynamical responses contain direct signatures of both the transition and the broken symmetry itself. In particular, we show that the generation of a second harmonic voltage under alternating current driving is a necessary and sufficient signature of time-reversal symmetry breaking. Finally, we demonstrate that strong nonlinear driving induces dynamical phase transitions between phases with and without spontaneous symmetry breaking, introducing a tool for their out-of-equilibrium control. We discuss the signatures of our predictions in AC current-driven experiments on twisted Bi$_2$Sr$_2$CaCu$_2$O$_{8+x}$ interfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.22495v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jefferson Tang, Pavel A. Volkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anisotropic spin fluctuations in the triangular Kondo lattice compound CePtAl$_4$Ge$_2$ probed by site-selective $^{27}$Al NMR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03007</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03007v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A site-selective $^{27}$Al nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) study is carried out on the Kondo lattice compound CePtAl$_4$Ge$_2$, which crystallizes in a rhombohedral lattice with quasi-two-dimensional Ce layers forming a triangular lattice network. Two inequivalent Al sites, Al(1) and Al(2), are unambiguously assigned by comparing measured nuclear quadrupole parameters with electric field gradients obtained from electronic structure calculations. Knight shift analysis yields distinct hyperfine coupling constants, revealing that they arise predominantly from RKKY-type transferred hyperfine fields through conduction electrons. Spin-lattice relaxation measurements reveal pronounced anisotropic spin fluctuations, and comparison of the relaxation rates between the two Al sites clarifies the momentum-space structure of these fluctuations. At low magnetic fields, $(T_1T)^{-1}$ is strongly enhanced on cooling toward the N\'eel temperature, indicating the growth of in-plane antiferromagnetic correlations in the paramagnetic state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03007v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/bd5f-n2yg</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 235102 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>H. Sakai, S. Shin, S. Kambe, Y. Tokunaga, H. Harima, E. Pomjakushina, T. Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
