<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 01:39:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Spin Glass Dynamics on Complex Hardware Topologies: A Bond-Correlated Percolation Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24867</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24867v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding how frustration and disorder shape relaxation in complex systems is a central problem in statistical physics and quantum annealing. Spin-glass models provide a natural framework to explore this connection, as their energy landscapes are governed by competing interactions and constrained topologies. We investigate the non-exponential relaxation behavior of spin glasses on network architectures relevant to quantum annealing hardware -- such as finite size Chimera, Pegasus, and Zephyr graphs -- where embedding constraints and finite connectivity strongly modulate the distribution of barriers and metastable states. This slow relaxation arises from the combined effects of frustration and disorder, which persist even beyond the conventional spin-glass transition. Within the Fortuin-Kasteleyn-Coniglio-Klein (FKCK) cluster formalism, the appearance of unfrustrated cluster regions gives rise to multiple relaxation scales, as distinct domains follow different dynamical pathways across a rugged energy landscape. This framework enables a more comprehensive characterization of spin-glass energy landscapes and offers valuable insight into how topological constraints and disorder jointly govern relaxation dynamics, providing quantitative benchmarks for evaluating the performance and limitations of quantum annealing architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24867v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Viviana G\'omez, Gabriel T\'ellez, Fernando J. G\'omez-Ruiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Molecular simulations of Perovskites CsXI3 (X = Pb,Sn) Using Machine-Learning Interatomic Potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24874</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24874v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cesium based halide perovskites, such as CsPbI3 and CsSnI3, have emerged as exceptional candidates for next generation photovoltaic and optoelectronic technologies, but their practical application is limited by temperature dependent phase transitions and structural instabilities. Here, we develop machine learning interatomic potentials within the LATTE framework to simulate these materials with near experimental accuracy at a fraction of the computational cost compared to previous computational studies. Our molecular dynamics simulations based on the trained MLIPs reproduce energies and forces across multiple phases, enabling large scale simulations that capture cubic tetragonal orthorhombic transitions, lattice parameters, and octahedral tilting with unprecedented resolution. We find that Pb based perovskites exhibit larger octahedral tilts and higher phase transition temperatures than Sn based analogues, reflecting stronger bonding and enhanced structural stability, whereas Sn based perovskites display reduced tilts and lower barriers, suggesting tunability through compositional or interface engineering. Beyond these systems, our work demonstrates that MLIPs can bridge first principles accuracy with simulation efficiency, providing a robust framework for exploring phase stability, anharmonicity, and rational design in next generation halide perovskites.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24874v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Atefe Ebrahimi, Franco Pellegrini, Stefano De Gironcoli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergence of Chimeras States in One-dimensional Ising model with Long-Range Diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24903</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24903v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we examine the conditions for the emergence of chimera-like states in Ising systems. We study an Ising chain with periodic boundaries in contact with a thermal bath at temperature T, that induces stochastic changes in spin variables. To capture the non-locality needed for chimera formation, we introduce a model setup with non-local diffusion of spin values through the whole system. More precisely, diffusion is modeled through spin-exchange interactions between units up to a distance R, using Kawasaki dynamics. This setup mimics, e.g., neural media, as the brain, in the presence of electrical (diffusive) interactions. We explored the influence of such non-local dynamics on the emergence of complex spatiotemporal synchronization patterns of activity. Depending on system parameters we report here for the first time chimera-like states in the Ising model, characterized by relatively stable moving domains of spins with different local magnetization. We analyzed the system at T=0, both analytically and via simulations and computed the system's phase diagram, revealing rich behavior: regions with only chimeras, coexistence of chimeras and stable domains, and metastable chimeras that decay into uniform stable domains. This study offers fundamental insights into how coherent and incoherent synchronization patterns can arise in complex networked systems as it is, e.g., the brain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24903v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alejandro de Haro Garc\'ia, Joaqu\'in J. Torres</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of vector rogue waves in repulsive three-component atomic mixtures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24917</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24917v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report the experimental observation of vector extensions of Peregrine solitons in highly particle-imbalanced, pairwise immiscible three-component repulsive Bose-Einstein condensates (BECs). The possibility of an effectively attractive character of the minority components is established by constructing a generalized reduction scheme for an imbalanced N-component setup with arbitrary interaction signs. These components may suffer intra- and inter-component modulation instability, which along with the presence of an attractive potential well induces the dynamical formation of highly reproducible vector rogue waves. Exploiting different Rb hyperfine states, it is possible to flexibly tune the effective interactions stimulating the realization of a plethora of vector rogue waves, including single and double Peregrine-like wave peaks. The experimental findings are in quantitative agreement with suitable three-dimensional mean-field simulations, while quasi-one-dimensional analysis of the non-polynomial Schr\"odinger model provides additional insights into the rogue wave characteristics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24917v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. A. Bougas, G. C. Katsimiga, S. Mossman, P. Engels, P. G. Kevrekidis, S. I. Mistakidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stabilisation of hBN/SiC Heterostructures with Vacancies and Transition-Metal Atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24952</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24952v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: When two-dimensional atomic layers of different materials are brought into close proximity to form van der Waals (vdW) heterostructures, interactions between adjacent layers significantly influence their physicochemical properties. These effects seem particularly pronounced when the interface exhibits local order and near-perfect structural alignment, leading to the emergence of Moir\'e patterns. Using quantum mechanical density functional theory calculations, we propose a prototypical bilayer heterostructure composed of hexagonal boron nitride (hBN) and silicon carbide (SiC), characterized by a lattice mismatch of 18.77\% between their primitive unit cells. We find that the removal of boron atoms from specific lattice sites can convert the interlayer interaction from weak vdW coupling to robust localized silicon-nitrogen covalent bonding. Motivated by this, we study the binding of transition-metal adatoms and formulate design guidelines to enhance surface reactivity, thereby enabling the controlled isolation of single-metal atoms. Our machine-learning-assisted molecular dynamics simulations confirm both dynamical stability and metal anchoring feasibility at finite temperatures. Our results suggest the hBN/SiC heterostructure as a versatile platform for atomically precise transition-metal functionalization, having potential for next-generation catalytic energy-conversion technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24952v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arsalan Hashemi, Nima Ghafari Cherati, Sadegh Ghaderzadeh, Yanzhou Wang, Mahdi Ghorbani-Asl, Tapio Ala-Nissila</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magneto-optical spectroscopy based on pump-probe strobe light</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24964</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24964v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate a pump-probe strobe light spectroscopy for sensitive detection of magneto-optical dynamics in the context of hybrid magnonics. The technique uses a combinatorial microwave-optical pump-probe scheme, leveraging both the high-energy resolution of microwaves and the high-efficiency detection using optical photons. In contrast to conventional stroboscopy using a continuous-wave light, we apply microwave and optical pulses with varying pulse widths, and demonstrate magnetooptical detection of magnetization dynamics in Y3Fe5O12 films. The detected magneto-optical signals strongly depend on the characteristics of both the microwave and the optical pulses as well as their relative time delays. We show that good magneto-optical sensitivity and coherent stroboscopic character are maintained even at a microwave pump pulse of 1.5 ns and an optical probe pulse of 80 ps, under a 7 megahertz clock rate, corresponding to a pump-probe footprint of ~1% in one detection cycle. Our results show that time-dependent strobe light measurement of magnetization dynamics can be achieved in the gigahertz frequency range under a pump-probe detection scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24964v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shihao Zhou, Yujie Zhu, Chunli Tang, Rui Sun, Junming Wu, Yuzan Xiong, Ingrid E. Russell, Yi Li, Dali Sun, Frank Tsui, Binbin Yang, Valentine Novosad, Jia-Mian Hu, Wencan Jin, Wei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical excitations and disorder in two-dimensional topological insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25009v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Topological phases of matter have garnered significant interest over the past two decades for two main reasons: their identification, via topological invariants, relies on the quantum geometry of the Bloch states, bringing attention to an aspect of electronic band structure overlooked up to their discovery. Secondly, these classes of materials present electronic states with unusual properties, leading to exotic phenomena and making them relevant for potential applications. In this thesis we explore both fundamental and technological aspects of the first discovered topological phase: the topological insulator. To this end, we consider different models of topological insulators with a particular emphasis on Bismuth compounds, evaluating their viability for photovoltaic applications, and separately, the impact of structural disorder on their properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25009v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alejandro Jos\'e Ur\'ia-\'Alvarez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite-Temperature Study of the Hubbard Model via Enhanced Exponential Tensor Renormalization Group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25022v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The two-dimensional (2D) Hubbard model has long attracted interest for its rich phase diagram and its relevance to high-$T_c$ superconductivity. However, reliable finite-temperature studies remain challenging due to the exponential complexity of many-body interactions. Here, we introduce an enhanced $1\text{s}^+$ eXponential Tensor Renormalization Group algorithm that enables efficient finite-temperature simulations of the 2D Hubbard model. By exploring an expanded space, our approach achieves two-site update accuracy at the computational cost of a one-site update, and delivers up to 50% acceleration for Hubbard-like systems, which enables simulations down to $T\!\approx\!0.004t$. This advance permits a direct investigation of superconducting order over a wide temperature range and facilitates a comparison with zero-temperature infinite Projected Entangled Pair State simulations. Finally, we compile a comprehensive dataset of snapshots spanning the relevant region of the phase diagram, providing a valuable reference for Artificial Intelligence-driven analyses of the Hubbard model and a comparison with cold-atom experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25022v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Changkai Zhang, Jan von Delft</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Dynamical Duality of Quantum Particles in One Dimension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25056</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25056v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove a generalized dynamical duality for identical particles in one dimension (1D). Namely, 1D systems with arbitrary statistics -- including bosons, fermions and anyons -- approach the same momentum distribution after long-time expansion from a trap, provided they share the same scattering length for short-range interactions. This momentum distribution is uniquely given by the rapidities, or quasi-momenta, of the initial trapped state. Our results can be readily detected in quasi-1D ultracold gases with tunable s- and p-wave interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25056v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Chen, Xiaoling Cui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phonon dynamics and chiral modes in the two-dimensional square-octagon lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25071v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Chiral phonons, originally identified in two-dimensional hexagonal lattices and later extended to kagome, square, and other lattices, have been extensively studied as manifestations of broken inversion and time-reversal symmetries in vibrational dynamics. In this work, we investigate the vibrational dynamics of the two-dimensional square-octagon lattice using a spring-mass model with central-force interactions. The model incorporates mass contrast and variable coupling strengths among nearest, next-nearest, and third-nearest neighbors. From the dynamical matrix, we obtain the phonon dispersion relations and identify tunable phononic band gaps governed by both mass and spring-constant ratios. The angular dependence of phase and group velocities is analyzed to reveal the pronounced anisotropy inherent to this lattice geometry. We also examine the distinctive features of the square-octagon geometry, including flat-band anomalies in the density of states and anisotropic sound propagation induced by longer-range couplings. In addition, we explore the emergence of chiral phonons by introducing a time reversal symmetry-breaking term in the dynamical matrix, and to elucidate their optical signatures, we construct a minimal model to study infrared circular dichroism arising from chiral phonon modes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25071v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ravi Kiran, A. Taraphder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Universal Scaling Law for $T_c$ in Unconventional Superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25082v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding the pairing mechanism of unconventional superconductors remains a core challenge in condensed matter physics, particularly the ongoing debate over whether the related effects caused by electron-electron interactions unify various unconventional superconductors (UcSs). To address this challenge, it is necessary to establish a universal quantitative relationship for the superconducting transition temperature ($T_c$), which can be directly obtained from experiments and correlated with microscopic parameters of different material systems. In this work, we establish a relation: $N_{\text{CP}}\cdot k_{B}T_{c}^\star = \alpha\cdot U $, where $\alpha = 1/(16\pi)$ is a universal constant, $k_B$ is the Boltzmann constant, $T_{c}^\star$ is the maximal $T_{c}$, $U$ is the on-site Coulomb interaction, and $N_{\text{CP}}$($\propto(\xi_0/a)^D$) quantifies the spatial extent of Cooper pairs ($\xi_0$) relative to lattice parameter ($a$) in $D$ dimensions. The validity of this scaling relationship is empirically demonstrated, across a four order-of-magnitude $T_c^\star$ range (0.08--133 K), by database from 173 different compounds spanning 13 different UcS families in over 500 experiments. The fact that the unified relationship is satisfied by different materials of different UcS families reveals that they may share superconducting mechanisms. In addition, the scaling relationship indicates the existence of a maximum $T_{c}^\star$ determined by the minimum $N_{\text{CP}}$, providing a benchmark for theoretical and experimental exploration of high-temperature superconductivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25082v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Way Wang, Zhongshui Ma, Hai-qing Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single-Shot All-Optical Switching in CoFeB/MgO Magnetic Tunnel Junctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25102</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25102v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate single shot al optical switching (AOS) in rare earth free CoFeB/MgO magnetic tunnel junctions (MTJs), a material system widely adopted in spin transfer torque magnetic random access memory (STT MRAM). By tuning the capping layer thickness, we show that precise heat control enables deterministic magnetization reversal from parallel (P) to antiparallel (AP) state. Furthermore, we detect magnetization reversal in a micro scale MTJ device via the tunnel magnetoresistance (TMR) effect. Our findings suggest that ultrafast spin transport or dipolar interactions or a combination of both may play essential roles in the switching process. This work represents a significant step toward integrating AOS with MTJ technology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25102v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junta Igarashi, S\'ebastien Geiskopf, Takanobu Shinoda, Butsurin Jinnai, Yann Le Guen, Julius Hohlfeld, Shunsuke Fukami, Hideo Ohno, Jon Gorchon, St\'ephane Mangin, Michel Hehn, Gr\'egory Malinowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contactless cavity sensing of superfluid stiffness in atomically thin 4Hb-TaS$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25124</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25124v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The exceptional tunability of two-dimensional van der Waals materials offers unique opportunities for exploring novel superconducting phases. However, in such systems, the measurement of superfluid phase stiffness, a fundamental property of a superconductor, is challenging because of the mesoscopic sample size. Here, we introduce a contact-free technique for probing the electrodynamic response, and thereby the phase stiffness, of atomically thin superconductors using on-chip superconducting microwave resonators. We demonstrate this technique on 4Hb-TaS$_2$, a van der Waals superconductor whose gap structure under broken mirror symmetry is under debate. In our cleanest few-layer device, we observe a superconducting critical temperature comparable to that of the bulk. The temperature evolution of the phase stiffness features nodeless behavior in the presence of broken mirror symmetry, inconsistent with the scenario of nodal surface superconductivity. With minimal fabrication requirements, our technique enables microwave measurements across wide ranges of two-dimensional superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25124v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Trevor Chistolini, Ha-Leem Kim, Qiyu Wang, Su-Di Chen, Luke Pritchard Cairns, Ryan Patrick Day, Collin Sanborn, Hyunseong Kim, Zahra Pedramrazi, Ruishi Qi, Takashi Taniguchi, Kenji Watanabe, James G. Analytis, David I. Santiago, Irfan Siddiqi, Feng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exotic Acoustic-Edge and Thermal Scaling in Disordered Hyperuniform Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25136v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a first-principles theory for the vibrational density of states (VDOS) and thermal properties of network materials built on stationary correlated disordered point configurations. For scalar (mass--spring) models whose dynamical matrix is a distance-weighted graph Laplacian, we prove that the limiting spectral measure is the pushforward of Lebesgue measure by a Fourier symbol that depends only on the edge kernel \(f\) and the two-point statistics \(g_2\) (equivalently the structure factor \(S\)). For hyperuniform systems with small-$k$ scaling \(S(k)\sim k^\alpha\) and compensated kernels, {the VDOS exhibits an algebraic \emph{pseudogap} at low frequency, \(g(\omega)\sim \omega^{\,2d/\beta-1}\) with \(\beta=\min\{4,\alpha+2\}\), which implies a low-temperature specific heat \(C(T)\sim T^{\,2d/\beta}\) and a heat-kernel decay \(Z(t)\sim t^{-d/\beta}\), defining a spectral dimension \(d_s=2d/\beta\).} This hyperuniformity-induced algebraic edge depletion could enable novel wave manipulation and low-temperature applications. Generalization to vector mechanical models and implications on material design are also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25136v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Jiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polar core vortex dynamics in disc-trapped homogeneous spin-1 Bose-Einstein condensates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25139</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25139v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the dynamics of polar core vortices in the easy plane phase of an atomic spin-1 Bose-Einstein condensate confined in a two-dimensional disc potential. A single vortex moves radially outward due to its interaction with background flows that arise from boundary effects. Pairs of opposite sign vortices, which tend to attract, move either radially inward or outward, depending on their strength of attraction relative to boundary effects. Pairs of same sign vortices repel. Spiral vortex dynamics are obtained for same-sign pairs in the presence of a finite axial magnetization. We quantify the dynamics for a range of realistic experimental parameters, finding that the vortex dynamics are accelerated with increasing quadratic Zeeman energy, consistent with existing studies in planar systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25139v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Edmonds, Lewis A. Williamson, Matthew J. Davis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Geometric Pathway for Tuning Ferroelectric Properties via Polar State Reconfiguration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25142</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25142v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report the discovery of a geometric pathway for tuning ferroelectric properties through thermally driven reconfiguration between coexisting polar states in Li-substituted NaNbO3. Using first-principles density functional theory calculation and 7Li solid-state nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy measurement, we reveal that Li substitution creates two distinct polar configurations whose transformation under annealing enhances the Curie temperature and induces piezoelectric hardening. Our findings establish a geometrically-driven polar state reconfiguration mechanism, providing a general design principle for ferroics whereby macroscopic functional properties can be engineered via lattice geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25142v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao-Cheng Thong, Bo Wu, Fan Hu, Pedro B. Groszewicz, Chen-Bo-Wen Li, Jun Chen, Mao-Hua Zhang, Dragan Damjanovic, Ben Xu, Ke Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monte Carlo study on critical exponents of the classical Heisenberg model in ferromagnetic icosahedral quasicrystal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25169</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25169v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quasicrystals (QCs) lack three-dimensional periodicity of atomic arrangement but possess long-range structural order, which are distinct from periodic crystals and random systems. Here, we show how the ferromagnetic (FM) order arises in the icosahedral QC (i-QC) on the basis of the Monte Carlo simulation of the Heisenberg model on the Yb lattice of Cd$_{5.7}$Yb composed of regular icosahedrons. By finite-size scaling of the Monte Carlo data, we identified the critical exponents of the magnetization, magnetic susceptibility, and spin correlation length, $\beta=0.508(30)$, $\gamma=1.361(59)$, and $\nu=0.792(17)$, respectively. We confirmed that our data satisfy the hyperscaling relation and estimated the other critical exponents $\alpha=-0.376(51)$, $\delta=3.68(23)$, and $\eta=0.282(65)$. These results show a new universality class inherent in the i-QC, which is different from those in periodic magnets and spin glasses. In the i-QC, each Yb site at vertices of the regular icosahedrons is classified into 8 classes with respect to the coordination numbers of the nearest-neighbor and next-nearest-neighbor bonds. We revealed the FM-transition mechanism by showing that the difference in the local environment of each site is governed by cooperative evolution of spin correlations upon cooling, giving rise to the critical phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25169v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/4zb8-2zjq</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 7 (2025) 043113</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shinji Watanabe, Tsunetomo Yamada, Hiroyuki Takakura, Nobuhisa Fujita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear and isotropic magnetoresistance of Co$_{1-x}$Fe$_x$Si at x=0.2; 0.4; 0.65</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25194v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We studied the magnetoresistance (MR) of well-characterized samples of Co$_{1-x}$Fe$_x$Si at x=0.2, 0.4, and 0.65 at temperatures between 1.8 and 100~K and magnetic fields of 9~T. The quasilinear dependence of MR on the magnetic field at low temperatures and the practically isotropic properties of MR in these compounds are tentatively attributed to the specifics of Weyl electron spectra and general disorder of the materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25194v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. E. Petrova, S. Yu. Gavrilkin, V. A. Stepanov, S. S. Khasanov, Dirk Mensel, S. M. Stishov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-Gap Hf-HfOx-Hf Josephson Junctions for meV-Scale Particle Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25203</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25203v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Superconducting qubits have motivated the exploration of Josephson-junction technologies beyond quantum computing, with emerging applications in low-energy photon and phonon detection for astrophysics and dark matter searches. Achieving sensitivity at the THz (meV) scale requires materials with smaller superconducting gaps than those of conventional aluminum or niobium-based devices. Here, we report the fabrication and characterization of hafnium (Hf)-based Josephson junctions (Hf-HfOx-Hf), demonstrating Hf as a promising low-Tc material platform for ultra-low threshold single THz photon and single-phonon detection. Structural and chemical analyses reveal crystalline films and well-defined oxide barriers, while electrical transport measurements at both room and cryogenic temperatures exhibit clear Josephson behavior, enabling extraction of key junction parameters such as critical current, superconducting gap and normal-state resistance. This work presents the first comprehensive study of Hf-based junctions and their potential for next-generation superconducting detectors and qubit architectures leveraging low superconducting gap energies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25203v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Y. Balaji, M. Surendran, X. Li, A. Kemelbay, A. Gashi, C. Salemi, A. Suzuki, S. Aloni, A. Tynes Hammack, A. Schwartzberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strain Engineering of Correlated Charge-Ordered Phases in 1T-TaS2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25265</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25265v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Strain engineering is a powerful strategy for controlling the structural and electronic properties of two-dimensional materials, particularly in systems hosting charge density wave (CDW) order. In this work, we apply uniaxial tensile and compressive strain to thin 1T-TaS2 flakes using a flexible, device-compatible platform, and systematically investigate the strain-dependent behavior of the nearly commensurate (NC) to incommensurate (IC) CDW phase transition. This transition is driven by Joule heating at room temperature. Electrical transport measurements reveal that both the switching threshold voltage and the resistance of the NC-CDW phase exhibit clear, reversible strain dependence. Furthermore, we identify a quadratic dependence between the strain-induced resistance change and the threshold voltage, confirming that piezoresistive modulation governs the strain-tunability of the phase transition. We demonstrate a room-temperature, electrically-readout strain and displacement sensor with threshold-like response in a programmable window. These results highlight the potential of 1T-TaS2 for on-chip sensing of strain and displacement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25265v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.nanolett.5c04101</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Rafael Luque Merino, Felix Carrascoso, Eudomar Henr\'iquez-Guerra, M. Reyes Calvo, Riccardo Frisenda, Andres Castellanos-Gomez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Immobile and mobile excitations of three-spin interactions on the diamond chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25349v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a solvable one-dimensional spin-1/2 model on the diamond chain featuring three-spin interactions, which displays both, mobile excitations driving a second-order phase transition between an ordered and a $\mathbb{Z}_2$-symmetry broken phase, as well as non-trivial fully immobile excitations. The model is motivated by the physics of fracton excitations, which only possess mobility in a reduced dimension compared to the full model. We provide an exact mapping of this model to an arbitrary number of independent transverse-field Ising chain segments with open boundary conditions. The number and lengths of these segments correspond directly to the number of immobile excitations and their respective distances from one another. Furthermore, we demonstrate that multiple immobile excitations exhibit Casimir-like forces between them, resulting in a non-trivial spectrum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25349v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Bayer, M. Vieweg, K. P. Schmidt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement-enhanced correlation propagation in the one-dimensional SU($N$) Fermi-Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25358</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25358v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the dynamics of correlation propagation in the one-dimensional Fermi-Hubbard model with SU($N$) symmetry when the replusive-interaction strength is quenched from a large value, at which the ground state is a Mott-insulator with $1/N$ filling, to an intermediate value. From approximate analytical insights based on a simple model that captures the essential physics of the doublon excitations, we show that entanglement in the initial state leads to collective enhancement of the propagation velocity $v_{\text{SU}(N)}$ when $N&gt;2$, becoming equal to the velocity of the Bose-Hubbard model in the large-$N$ limit. These results are supported by numerical calculations of the density-density correlation in the quench dynamics for $N=2,3,4,$ and $6$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25358v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mathias Mikkelsen, Ippei Danshita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of Planar Slits in Multilayer Graphite Crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25399</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25399v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using a two-dimensional coarse-grained chain model, planar slits in multilayer graphite crystals are simulated. It is shown that when covering a linear cavity on the flat surface of a graphite crystal with a multilayer graphene sheet, an open (unfilled slit) can form only if the cavity width does not exceed a critical value L_o (for width L&gt;L_o, only a closed state of the slit is formed, with the cavity space filled by the covering sheet). The critical width of the open slit L_o increases monotonically with the number of layers K in the covering sheet. For a single-layer cavity, there is a finite critical value of its width L_o&lt;3nm, while for two- and three-layer cavities, the maximum width of the open slit increases infinitely with increasing K as a power function K^\alpha with exponent 0&lt;\alpha&lt;1. Inside the crystal, two- and three-layer slits can have stable open states at any width. For a slit with width L&gt;7.6nm, a stationary closed state is also possible, in which its lower and upper surfaces adhere to each other. Simulation of thermal oscillations showed that open states of two-layer slits with width L&lt;15nm are always stable against thermal oscillations, while wider slits at T&gt;400K transition from the open to the closed state. Open states of three-layer slits are always stable against thermal oscillations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25399v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander V. Savin, Artem P. Klinov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Microscopic Nature of Orbital Disorder in LaMnO$_{3}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25414v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a revised atomistic picture of the order-disorder transition in the archetypal orbital-ordered perovskite material, LaMnO$_{3}$. Our study uses machine-learning-driven molecular-dynamics simulations which describe the temperature evolution of pair distribution functions in close agreement with experiment. We find the orbital-disordered phase in LaMnO$_{3}$ to comprise a mixture of differing structural distortions with and without inversion symmetry, implying a mixture of different orbital arrangements. These distortions are highly dynamic with an estimated lifetime of $\sim 40$ fs at 1,000 K, and their fluctuations converge with the timescales of conventional thermal motion in the high-$T$ phase - indicating that the electronic instability responsible for static Jahn-Teller distortions at low temperature instead drives phonon anharmonicity at high temperatures. Beyond LaMnO$_{3}$, our work opens an avenue for studying a wider range of correlated materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25414v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bodoo Batnaran, Andrew L. Goodwin, Michael A. Hayward, Volker L. Deringer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of interlayer Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction on the shape and dynamics of magnetic twin-skyrmions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25415v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic skyrmions have been proposed as promising candidates for storing information due to their high stability and easy manipulation by spin-polarized currents. Here, we study how these properties are influenced by the interlayer Dzyaloshinskii--Moriya interaction (IL-DMI), which stabilizes twin-skyrmions in magnetic bilayers. We find that the spin configuration of the twin-skyrmion adapts to the direction of the IL-DMI by elongating or changing the helicities in the two layers. Driving the skyrmions by spin-polarized currents in the current-perpendicular-to-plane configuration, we observe significant changes either in the skyrmion velocity or in the skyrmion Hall angle depending on the current polarization. These findings unravel further prospects for skyrmion manipulation enabled by the IL-DMI.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25415v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tim Matthies, Levente R\'ozsa, Roland Wiesendanger, Elena Y. Vedmedenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schr\"odinger-invariance in non-equilibrium critical dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25429v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The scaling functions of single-time and two-time correlators in systems undergoing non-equilibrium critical dynamics with dynamical exponent ${z}=2$ are predicted from a new time-dependent non-equilibrium representation of the Schr\"odinger algebra. These explicit predictions are tested and confirmed in the ageing of several exactly solvable models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25429v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Malte Henkel, Stoimen Stoimenov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite-Temperature Ferroelectric Phase Transitions from Machine-Learned Force Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25439</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25439v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Simulating finite temperature phase transitions from first-principles is computationally challenging. Recently, molecular dynamics (MD) simulations using machine-learned force fields (MLFFs) have opened a new avenue for finite-temperature calculations with near-first-principles accuracy. Here we use MLFFs, generated using on-the-fly training, to investigate structural phase transitions in four of the most well-studied ferroelectric oxides; BaTiO$_3$, PbTiO$_3$, LiNbO$_3$ and BiFeO$_3$. Only using the 0 K ground state structure as input for the training, the resulting MLFFs can qualitatively predict all the main structural phases and phase transitions, while the quantitative results are sensitive to the choice of exchange correlation functional with PBEsol found to be more robust than LDA and r$^2$SCAN. MD simulations also reproduce the experimentally observed order-disorder character of Ti displacements in BaTiO$_3$, the abrupt first order transitions of BiFeO$_3$ and PbTiO$_3$, and the mixed order-disorder and displacive character of the ferroelectric transition in LiNbO$_3$. Finally, we discuss the potential and limitations of using MLFFs for simulating ferroelectric phase transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25439v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kristoffer Eggestad, Ida C. Skogvoll, {\O}ystein Gullbrekken, Benjamin A. D. Williamson, Sverre M. Selbach</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strongly nonlinear Bernstein modes in graphene reveal plasmon-enhanced near-field magnetoabsorption</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25443v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Bernstein modes -- hybrid magnetoplasmon excitations arising from the coupling between cyclotron motion and collective oscillations in two-dimensional electron systems -- offer direct access to non-local electrodynamics. These modes can exhibit rich nonlinear behavior akin to strong-coupling phenomena in cavity quantum electrodynamics, but reaching nonlinear regime has remained experimentally challenging. Here we report the observation of nonlinear Bernstein modes in graphene using terahertz excitation with near-field enhancement from embedded metallic contacts. Photoresistance spectroscopy reveals sharp resonances at Bc/2 and Bc/3 that saturate at radiation intensities nearly an order of magnitude lower than the cyclotron resonance. We ascribe this to strong local heating of the electron gas due to resonant excitation of high-amplitude Bernstein magnetoplasmons, associated with a combination of the field-concentration effect of the near field and plasmonic amplification that is resonantly enhanced in the region of Bernstein gaps. Polarization-resolved measurements further confirm the near-field origin: Bernstein resonances are insensitive to circular helicity but strongly depend on the angle of linear polarization, in sharp contrast to the cyclotron resonance response. Our results establish graphene as a platform for nonlinear magnetoplasmonics, opening opportunities for strong-field manipulation of collective electron dynamics, out-of-equilibrium electron transport, and solid-state analogues of cavity quantum electrodynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25443v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. Yahniuk, I. A. Dmitriev, A. L. Shilov, E. M\"onch, M. Marocko, J. Eroms, D. Weiss, P. Sadovyi, B. Sadovyi, I. Grzegory, W. Knap, J. Gumenjuk-Sichevska, J. Wunderlich, D. A. Bandurin, S. D. Ganichev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strongly enhanced lifetime of higher-order bimerons and antibimerons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25478v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic bimerons, similar to skyrmions, are topologically nontrivial spin textures characterized by topological charge $Q$. Most studies so far have focused on low-$Q$ solitons ($|Q| \leq 1$), such as skyrmions, bimerons, and vortices. Here, we present the first calculations of the lifetimes of high-$Q$ bimerons and demonstrate that they are fundamentally more stable than high-$Q$ skyrmions over a wide range of temperature. To obtain realistic results, our chosen system is an experimentally feasible van der Waals interface, Fe$_3$GeTe$_2$/Cr$_2$Ge$_2$Te$_6$. We show that the lifetimes of high-$Q$ (anti)bimerons can exceed the lifetime of those with $|Q|=1$ by 3 orders of magnitude. Remarkably, this trend remains valid even when extrapolated to room temperature (RT), as the lifetimes are dominated by entropy rather than energy barriers. This contrasts with high-$Q$ skyrmions, whose lifetimes fall with $|Q|$ near RT. We attribute this fundamental difference between skyrmions and bimerons to their distinct magnetic texture symmetries, which lead to different entropy-dominated lifetimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25478v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shiwei Zhu, Moritz A. Goerzen, Changsheng Song, Stefan Heinze, Dongzhe Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of entanglement fluctuations and quantum Mpemba effect in the $\nu=1$ QSSEP model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25519</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25519v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the out-of-equilibrium dynamics of entanglement fluctuations in the $\nu=1$ Quantum Symmetric Simple Exclusion Process, a free-fermion chain with hopping amplitudes that are stochastic in time but homogeneous in space. Previous work showed that the average entanglement growth after a quantum quench can be explained in terms of pairs of entangled quasiparticles performing random walks, leading to diffusive entanglement spreading. By incorporating the noise-induced statistical correlations between the quasiparticles, we extend this description to the full-time probability distribution of the entanglement entropy. Our generalized quasiparticle picture allows us to compute the average time evolution of a generic function of the reduced density matrix of a subsystem. We also apply our result to the entanglement asymmetry. This allows us to investigate the restoration of particle-number symmetry in the dynamics from initial states with no well-defined particle number, and the emergence of the quantum Mpemba effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25519v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Angelo Russotto, Filiberto Ares, Pasquale Calabrese, Vincenzo Alba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Maximum Quantum Work at Criticality: Stirling Engines and Fibonacci-Lucas Degeneracies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25533</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25533v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many-body effects and quantum criticality play a central role in determining the performance of quantum thermal machines. Although operating near a quantum critical point (QCP) is known to enhance engine performance, the precise thermodynamic conditions required to attain the Carnot efficiency limit remain unsettled. Here, we derive the exact conditions for a quantum Stirling engine to achieve Carnot efficiency when a QCP drives its working medium. In the low-temperature regime, where only the ground-state manifold is populated, the net work output is given by $ W = k_B \delta \ln (g_{\text{crit}}/g_0) $ with $ \delta = T_H - T_L $, which directly yields the Carnot efficiency $ \eta_C = 1 - T_L/T_H $, independent of microscopic details. Notably, whereas ideal Stirling cycles attain Carnot efficiency only with a perfect regenerator, here no regenerator is required because, at low temperatures, the thermal population remains confined to the degenerate ground state; this represents a clear quantum advantage over engines with classical working substances. We validate this universal result by recovering known behaviors in various quantum systems, including spin chains with Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interactions and magnetic anisotropies. Applying the framework to the one-dimensional antiferromagnetic Ising model, we predict non-extensive scaling of the work output governed by Fibonacci and Lucas numbers for open chains and closed rings, respectively, which converges to classical extensivity in the thermodynamic limit. This analysis establishes a general and robust foundation for designing quantum thermal machines that reach the Carnot bound while delivering finite work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25533v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bastian Castorene, Martin HvE Groves, Francisco J. Pe\~na, Eugenio E. Vogel, Patricio Vargas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chirality-Induced Spin Currents in a Fermi Gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25537v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We observe and model spin currents arising from chirality and effective spin-exchange interactions in a weakly interacting $^6$Li Fermi gas. Chirality is introduced by a static displacement between the center of the trapped atoms and the center of an applied magnetic bowl, which produces spatially varying spin rotation. Spin-selective spin current is observed via oscillations in the centers of mass of the spin-up and spin-down components, which appear to bounce off of or pass through one another, depending on the relative size of the chirality and s-wave spin scattering interactions. We show that this behavior obeys a driven oscillator equation with an effective spin-dependent driving force.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25537v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Camen A. Royse, J. E. Thomas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Spin Liquids Stabilized by Disorder in Non-Kramers Pyrochlores</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25539v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study investigates the emergence of quantum spin liquid phases in pyrochlore oxides with non-Kramers ions, driven by structural randomness that effectively acts as a transverse field, introducing quantum fluctuations on top of the spin ice manifold. This is contrary to the naive expectation that disorder favors phases with short-range entanglement by adjusting the spins with their local environment. Given this unusual situation, it is essential to assess the stability of the spin-liquid phase with respect to the disorder. To perform this study, a minimal model for disordered quantum spin ice, the transverse-field Ising model, is analyzed using a formulation of gauge mean-field theory (GMFT) directly in real space. This approach allows the inclusion of disorder effects exactly and provides access to non-perturbative effects. The analysis shows that the quantum spin ice remains remarkably stable with respect to disorder up to the transition to the polarized phase at high fields, indicating that it can occur in real materials. Moreover, the Griffiths region of enhanced disorder-induced fluctuations appears tiny and restricted to the immediate vicinity of this transition due to the uniqueness of the low-energy excitations of the problem. For most of the phase diagram, an average description of the disorder captures the physical behavior well, indicating that the inhomogeneous quantum spin ice behaves closely to its homogeneous counterpart.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25539v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcus V. Marinho, Eric C. Andrade</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coupling between vibration and Luttinger liquid in mechanical nanowires</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25608</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25608v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The vibration of the mechanical nanowire coupled to photons via photon pressure and coupled to charges via the capacity has been widely explored in experiments in the past decades. This system is electrically neutral, thus its coupling to the other degrees of freedom is always challenging. Here, we show that the vibration can slightly change the nanowire length and the associated Fermi velocity, which leads to coupling between vibration and Luttinger liquid. We consider the transverse and longitudinal vibrations of the nanowires, showing that the transverse vibration is much more significant than the longitudinal vibration, which can be measured through the sizable frequency shift. We predict an instability of the vibration induced by this coupling when the frequency becomes negative at a critical temperature for the transverse vibrations in nanowires with low Fermi energy, which can be reached by tuning the chemical potential and magnetic field. The time-dependent oscillation of the conductance, which directly measures the Luttinger parameter, can provide evidence for this coupling. Our theory offers a new mechanism for exploring the coupling between the vibration and the electronic excitations, which may lead to intriguing applications in cooling and controlling the mechanical oscillators with currents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25608v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zeyu Rao, Yue-Xin Huang, Guang-Can Guo, Ming Gong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin Seebeck Effect in Correlated Antiferromagnetic V2O3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25637</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25637v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The spin Seebeck effect is useful for probing the spin correlations and magnetic order in magnetic insulators. Here, we report a strong longitudinal spin Seebeck effect (LSSE) in antiferromagnetic V2O3 thin films. The LSSE response at cryogenic temperatures increases as a function of the external magnetic field until it approaches saturation. The response at given power and field exhibits a non-monotonic temperature dependence, with a pronounced peak that shifts toward higher temperatures as the field increases. Furthermore, the magnitude of the LSSE signal decreases consistently with increasing thickness, implying that the bulk SSE dominates any interfacial contribution. This negative correlation between the SSE and the thickness implies that the magnon energy relaxation length in V2O3 is shorter than the thickness of our thinnest film, 50 nm, consistent with the strong spin-lattice coupling in this material.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25637v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Renjie Luo, Tanner J. Legvold, Gage Eichman, Henry Navarro, Ali C. Basaran, Erbin Qiu, Ivan K. Schuller, Douglas Natelson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using Crossed Andreev Reflection to Split Electrons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25641v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mesoscopic systems possess shot noise in their currents due to the quantization of the conducting quasiparticles. Measurements of this shot noise are useful to study phenomena that do not manifest themselves in standard conductance or resistance measurements, such as the statistics of the conducting quasiparticles or quantum entanglement via Bell tests. The corresponding particle statistics can be determined via two particle quantum interference experiments, such as the Hong-Ou-Mandel effect which demonstrates a bunching effect for bosons or an anti-bunching effect in fermions. In superconducting proximity junctions, electrons incident on a superconductor can induce holes via crossed Andreev reflection (CAR) in spatially separated normal metal leads, where the resulting hole currents have nontrivial partition noise due to the four terminal configuration. These nonlocally generated currents, using a superconductor as a mesoscopic beam splitter, enable fabrication of mesoscopic analogs to quantum optics interferometers using metallic and superconducting films with multiport geometries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25641v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Austin Marga, Venkat Chandrasekhar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-dependent anisotropic electron-phonon coupling in KTaO$_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25655</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25655v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: KTaO$_3$ (KTO) is an incipient ferroelectric, characterized by a softening of the lowest transverse optical (TO) mode with decreasing temperature. Cooper pairing in the recently discovered KTO-based heterostructures has been proposed to be mediated by the soft TO mode. Here we study the electron coupling to the zone-center odd-parity modes of bulk KTO by means of relativistic Density Functional Perturbation Theory (DFPT). The coupling to the soft TO mode is by far the largest, with comparable contributions from both intraband and interband processes. Remarkably, we find that for this mode, spin-non-conserving matrix elements are particularly relevant. We develop a three-band microscopic model with spin-orbit coupled $t_{2g}$ orbitals that reproduces the main features of the ab initio results. For the highest energy band, the coupling can be understood as a "dynamical" isotropic Rashba effect. In contrast, for the two lowest bands, the Rashba-like coupling becomes strongly anisotropic. The DFPT protocol implemented here enables the calculation of the full electron-phonon coupling matrix projected onto any mode of interest, and it is easily applicable to other systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25655v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giulia Venditti, Francesco Macheda, Paolo Barone, Jos\'e Lorenzana, Maria N. Gastiasoro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast high-fidelity baseband reset of a latched state for quantum dot qubit readout</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25703</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25703v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A common method for reading out the state of a spin qubit is by latching one logical qubit state, either $|1\rangle$ or $|0\rangle$, onto a different, metastable charge state. Such a latched state can provide a superior charge sensing signal for qubit readout, and it can have a lifetime chosen to be long enough that the charge sensed readout can be high fidelity. However, the passive reset out of latched states is inherently long, which is not desirable. In this work, we demonstrate an on-demand, high fidelity (&gt; 99%) re-initialization of a quantum dot qubit out of a latched readout state. The method is simple to apply as it involves a single baseband voltage pulse to a specific region in the quantum dot stability diagram where the relaxation time from the latched state to the ground state is over 50 times faster. We describe the mechanism for the reset process as well as the boundaries for the optimal reset region in the qubit gate voltage space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25703v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Piotr Marciniec, M. A. Wolfe, Tyler Kovach, J. Reily, Sanghyeok Park, Jared Benson, Mark Friesen, Benjamin D. Woods, Matthew J. Curry, Nathaniel C. Bishop, J. Corrigan, M. A. Eriksson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dual quantum locking: Dynamic coupling of hydrogen and water sublattices in hydrogen filled ice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25707</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25707v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hydrogen hydrates (HH) are a unique class of materials composed of hydrogen molecules confined within crystalline water frameworks. Among their multiple phases, the filled ice structures, particularly the cubic C2 phase, exhibit exceptionally strong host-guest interactions due to ultra-short H2-H2O distances and a 1:1 stoichiometry leading to two interpenetrated identical diamond-like sublattices, one comprised of water molecules, the other of hydrogen molecules. At high pressures, nuclear quantum effects involving both hydrogen molecules and the water lattice become dominant, giving rise to a dual-lattice quantum system. In this work, we explore the sequence of pressure- and temperature-driven phase transitions in HH, focusing on the interplay between molecular rotation, orientational ordering, lattice symmetry breaking and hydrogen bond symmetrization. Using a combination of computational modeling based on classical and path-integral molecular dynamics,
  quantum embedding, and high pressure experiments, including Raman spectroscopy and synchrotron X-ray diffraction at low temperatures and high pressures, we identify signatures of quantum-induced ordering and structural transformations in the C2 phase. Our findings reveal that orientational ordering in HH occurs at much lower pressures than in solid hydrogen, by inducing structural changes in the water network and enhancing the coupling of water and hydrogen dynamics. This work provides new insights into the quantum behavior of hydrogen under extreme mechanochemical confinement and establishes hydrogen-filled ices as a promising platform for the design of hydrogen-rich quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25707v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Loan Renaud, Tomasz Poreba, Simone Di Cataldo, Alasdair Nicholls, L\'eon Andriambariarijaona, Maria Rescigno, Richard Gaal, Michele Casula, A. Marco Saitta, Livia Eleonora Bove</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ETH-monotonicity in two-dimensional systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25711</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25711v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a recently discovered property of many-body quantum chaotic systems called ETH-monotonicity in two-dimensional systems. Our new results further support ETH-monotonicity in these higher dimensional systems. We show that the flattening rate of the $f$-function is directly proportional to the number of degrees of freedom in the system, so as $L^2$ where $L$ is the linear size of the system, and in general, expected to be $L^d$ where $d$ is the spatial dimension of the system. We also show that the flattening rate is directly proportional to the particle (or hole) number for systems of same spatial size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25711v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nilakash Sorokhaibam, Anjan Daimari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic emittance properties of an Fe-doped Beta-Ga2O3(010) photocathode: Ultracold electron emission at 300K and the polaron self-energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25722v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Measurements of the spectral emission properties of an iron-doped Beta-Ga2O3(010) photocathode at 300K reveal the presence of ultracold electron emission with a 6meV mean transverse energy (MTE) in the 3.5-4.4eV photon energy range (282-354nm). This extreme sub-thermal photoemission signal is consistent with direct emission of electrons photoexcited from the Fe dopant states into the low effective mass and positive electron affinity primary conduction band, and it is superimposed on a stronger signal with a larger MTE associated with an (optical)phonon-mediated momentum resonant Franck-Condon (FC) emission process from a thermally populated and negative electron affinity upper conduction band. For photon energies above 4.5eV, a transition from a long to a short transport regime is forced by an absorption depth reduction to below 100nm and both MTE signals exhibit spectral trends consistent with phonon-mediated FC emission if the polaron formation self-energy is included in the initial photoexcited electron thermalization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25722v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louis A. Angeloni, Ir-Jene Shan, J. H. Leach, W. Andreas Schroeder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Random Matrix Behavior of a Fermionic Quantum Gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25735</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25735v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The pursuit of universal governing principles is a foundational endeavor in physics, driving breakthroughs from thermodynamics to general relativity and quantum mechanics. In 1951, Wigner introduced the concept of a statistical description of energy levels of heavy atoms, which led to the rise of Random Matrix Theory (RMT) in physics. The theory successfully captured spectral properties across a wide range of atomic systems, circumventing the complexities of quantum many-body interactions. Rooted in the fundamental principles of stochasticity and symmetry, RMT has since found applications and revealed universal laws in diverse physical contexts, from quantum field theory to disordered systems and wireless communications. A particularly compelling application arises in describing the mathematical structure of the many-body wavefunction of non-interacting Fermi gases, which underpins a complex spatial organization driven by Pauli's exclusion principle. However, experimental validation of the counting statistics predicted in such systems has remained elusive. Here, we probe at the single-atom level ultracold atomic Fermi gases made of two interacting spin states, obtaining direct access to their counting statistics in situ. Our measurements show that, while the system is strongly attractive, each spin-component is extremely well described by RMT predictions based on Fredholm determinants. Our results constitutes the first experimental validation of the Fermi-sphere point process through the lens of RMT, and establishes its relevance for strongly-interacting systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25735v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maxime Dixmerias, Giuseppe Del Vecchio Del Vecchio, Cyprien Daix, Joris Verstraten, Tim de Jongh, Bruno Peaudecerf, Pierre Le Doussal, Gr\'egory Schehr, Tarik Yefsah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatially Inhomogeneous Triplet Pairing Order and Josephson Diode Effect Induced by Frustrated Spin Textures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25756v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate that frustrated spin textures can generate anisotropic Josephson couplings between $d$-vectors that can stabilize spatially varying pairing orders in spin triplet superconductors. These couplings depend on the relative orientation of $d$-vectors, analogous to Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya and $\Gamma$-type interactions in magnetism, leading to an effective "pliability" of the pairing order that competes with superfluid stiffness. Such couplings cannot originate from spin-orbit coupling; rather, they can arise, for example, when itinerant electrons are coupled to a local exchange field composed of frustrated spin moments. Using a $T$-matrix expansion, we show that coupling to a local exchange field leads to an effective tunneling of itinerant electrons that is dependent on the underlying spin configurations at the barrier between superconducting grains. Furthermore, Josephson tunneling through frustrated spin textures can produce a Josephson diode effect. The diode effect originates either from nonvanishing spin chirality in the barrier, or from antisymmetric Josephson coupling between noncollinear $d$-vectors, both of which break inversion and time-reversal symmetries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25756v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grayson R. Frazier, Yi Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconductivity in overdoped cuprates can be understood from a BCS perspective!</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25767</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25767v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We summarize key experimental studies of the low energy properties of overdoped cuprate high temperature superconductors and conclude that a theoretical understanding of the "essential physics" is achievable in terms of a conventional Fermi-liquid treatment of the normal state, and a BCS mean-field treatment of the (d-wave) superconducting state. For this perspective to be consistent, it is necessary to posit that there is a crossover from a strongly correlated underdoped regime (where a different theoretical perspective is necessary) to the more weakly correlated overdoped regime. It is also necessary to argue that the various observed features of the overdoped materials that are inconsistent with this perspective can be attributed to the expected effects of the intrinsic disorder associated with most of the materials being solid state solutions (alloys). As a test of this idea, we make a series of falsifiable predictions concerning the expected behavior of "ideal" (disorder free) overdoped cuprates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25767v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. J. Ramshaw, Steven A. Kivelson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Peierls Instability in Hexagonal Lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24230v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate a conventional tight-binding model for graphene, where distortion of the honeycomb lattice is allowed, but penalized by a quadratic energy. We prove that the optimal 3-periodic lattice configuration has Kekul\'e O-type symmetry, and that for a sufficiently small elasticity parameter, the minimizer is not translation-invariant. Conversely, we prove that for a large elasticity parameter the translation-invariant configuration is the unique minimizer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24230v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Gontier, Thaddeus Roussign\'e, \'Eric S\'er\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Build Anomalous (3+1)d Topological Quantum Field Theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24834v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a systematic framework for constructing (3+1)-dimensional topological quantum field theories (TQFTs) that realize specified anomalies of finite symmetries, as encountered in gauge theories with fermions or fermionic lattice systems. Our approach generalizes the Wang-Wen-Witten symmetry-extension construction to the fermionic setting, building on two recent advances in the study of fermionic TQFTs and related homotopy theory. The first is the categorical classification of anomalous TQFTs in (3+1)d. The second, which we develop further in a planned sequel to this paper, is a hastened Adams spectral sequence for computing supercohomology groups, closely paralleling techniques from cobordism theory. By integrating supercohomology and cobordism methods within the recently developed categorical framework of fusion 2-categories, we provide a concrete and systematic route to constructing fermionic TQFTs with specified anomalies, thereby establishing a conceptual bridge between anomaly realization, cobordism, and higher-categorical structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24834v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arun Debray, Weicheng Ye, Matthew Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pairing-induced phase transition in the non-reciprocal Kitaev chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24851v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Investigating the robustness of non-reciprocity in the presence of competing interactions is central to understanding non-reciprocal quantum matter. In this work, we use reservoir engineering to induce non-reciprocal hopping and pairing in the fermionic Kitaev chain, and reveal the emergence of a pairing-induced phase transition. The two phases appear in the spectrum of the non-Hermitian Kitaev Hamiltonian describing the dynamics of correlations, separated by an exceptional point. In the non-reciprocal phase, dynamics are characterized by directionality and slow relaxation, and the steady state supports non-reciprocal density and spatial correlations. At strong pairing, we uncover an unexpected density wave phase, featuring short relaxation times, a modulation in particle occupation and strikingly different correlation spreading depending on pairing non-reciprocity. Our work highlights the non-trivial breakdown of non-reciprocity due to superconducting pairing and invites experimental investigation of non-reciprocal fermionic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24851v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pietro Brighi, Andreas Nunnenkamp</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extracting Spectral Diffusion in Two-Dimensional Coherent Spectra via the Projection Slice Theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24865v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A robust and streamlined method is presented for efficiently extracting spectral diffusion from two-dimensional coherent spectra by employing the projection-slice theorem. The method is based on the optical Bloch equations for a single resonance that include a Frequency-Frequency Correlation Function (FFCF) in the time domain. Through the projection slice theorem (PST), analytical formulation of the diagonal and cross-diagonal projections of time-domain two-dimensional spectra are calculated that include the FFCF for arbitrary inhomogeneity. The time-domain projections are Fourier transformed to provide frequency domain slices that can be fit to slices of experimental spectra. Experimental data is used to validate our lineshape analysis and confirm the need for the inclusion of the FFCF for quantum wells that experience spectral diffusion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24865v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cesar Perez, Steven Cundiff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NLIE formulations for the generalized Gibbs ensemble in the sine-Gordon model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25344</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25344v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we propose two sets of nonlinear integral equations (NLIE) for describing the thermodynamics in the sine-Gordon model, when higher Lorentz spin conserved charges are also coupled to the Gibbs ensemble. We call them NLIE I and II. The derivation of the equations, is based on T-Q relations given by the equivalent thermodynamic Bethe ansatz (TBA) formulation of the problem in the repulsive regime. Though the equations are derived in the repulsive regime at discrete values of the coupling constant, a straightforward analytical continuation ensures their validity within the whole repulsive regime of the theory. For the NLIE I formulation, appropriate analytical continuation makes the penetration into the attractive regime also possible. However, the magnitude of this penetration is restricted by the spin of the largest spin conserved charge contained in the Gibbs ensemble. Within their range of validity, these NLIE formulations provide efficient theoretical frameworks for computing expectation values of conserved charge densities, their associated currents, and vertex operators and their descendants, with respect to the generalized Gibbs ensemble.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25344v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arpad Hegedus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Second-order Stark shifts exceeding 10$\,$GHz in electrically contacted SiV$^-$ centers in diamond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25543v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Negatively charged silicon vacancy centers (SiV$^-$) in diamond exhibit excellent spin coherence and optical properties, making them promising candidates for quantum technologies. However, the strain-induced inhomogeneous distribution of optical transition frequencies poses a challenge for scalability. We demonstrate electrical tuning of the SiV$^-$ center zero-phonon lines using in-plane contacts to apply moderate electric fields up to 45$\,$MV/m. The second-order Stark shift exceeds 10$\,$GHz, which is of the same order of magnitude as the 15$\,$GHz inhomogeneous distribution of SiV$^-$ observed in emitters embedded in optical nanostructures such as photonic crystal nanocavities. Analysis of individual SiV$^-$ centers shows significant variation in polarizabilities between defects indicating that the polarizability strongly depends on local parameters like strain. The observed polarizabilities are 3-25 times larger than those of tin vacancy centers, which we attribute to valence band resonances that delocalize the $e_u$ wavefunctions. Photoluminescence excitation measurements reveal that optical linewidths increase moderately with applied electric field strength. Our results demonstrate that large electrical Stark shifts can overcome the inhomogeneous distribution of transition frequencies, representing a significant step toward scalable SiV$^-$-based quantum technologies such as quantum repeaters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25543v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manuel Rieger, Nori N. Chavira Leal, Rubek Poudel, Tobias Waldmann, Lina M. Todenhagen, Stefan Kresta, Viviana Villafane, Martin S. Brandt, Kai M\"uller, Jonathan J. Finley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>N\'eel proximity effect at antiferromagnet/superconductor interfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.03962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.03962v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Spin-splitting induced in a conventional superconductor weakens superconductivity by destroying spin-singlet and creating spin-triplet Cooper pairs. We demonstrate theoretically that such an effect is also caused by an adjacent compensated antiferromagnet, which yields no net spin-splitting. We find that the antiferromagnet produces N\'eel triplet Cooper pairs, whose pairing amplitude oscillates rapidly in space similar to the antiferromagnet's spin. The emergence of these unconventional Cooper pairs reduces the singlet pairs' amplitude, thereby lowering the superconducting critical temperature. We develop a quasiclassical Green's functions description of the system employing a two-sublattice framework. It successfully captures the rapid oscillations in the Cooper pairs' amplitude at the lattice spacing scale as well as their smooth variation on the larger coherence length scale. Employing the theoretical framework thus developed, we investigate this N\'eel proximity effect in a superconductor/antiferromagnet bilayer as a function of interfacial exchange, disorder, and chemical potential, finding rich physics. Our findings also offer insights into experiments which have found a larger than expected suppression of superconductivity by an adjacent antiferromagnet.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.03962v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.106.144512</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 106, 144512 (2022)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>G. A. Bobkov, I. V. Bobkova, A. M. Bobkov, Akashdeep Kamra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic field-temperature competition and quantum criticality in a strange metal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.11914</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.11914v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Strange metals defy the quasiparticle description of conventional metals, exhibiting a linear in temperature ($T$-linear) resistivity in a broad temperature range. It has become increasingly clear that, together with $T$-linear resistivity, strange metals exhibit a characteristic response in strong magnetic fields, which might point to the quantum critical origin of the strange metal behavior. To explore the effects of strong magnetic fields on the dynamics of quantum fluctuations in a strange metal, here we report the thermodynamic study of electronic density of states on the Fermi surface in CeCoIn$_5$. Using ultrafast nanocalorimeters, we access the electronic density of states at low temperatures and high magnetic fields through two independent thermodynamic probes -- the nuclear spin-lattice relaxation rate and the electronic specific heat -- measured simultaneously on the same crystal. Both thermodynamic probes exhibit magnetic field and temperature competition, characteristic of quantum criticality, indicating that magnetic field acts as a cutoff for the dynamics of quantum critical fluctuations in CeCoIn$_5$. However, at low temperatures and high magnetic fields, the electronic specific heat and the nuclear spin-lattice relaxation rate cannot be understood solely in terms of a critical enhancement of the electronic density of states at the Fermi surface. This indicates that quantum criticality in CeCoIn$_5$ involves both local and itinerant fluctuating critical modes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.11914v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Khansili, A. Bangura, R. D. McDonald, B. J. Ramshaw, A. Rydh, A. Shekhter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Andreev bound states at nonmagnetic impurities in superconductor/antiferromagnet heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.02512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.02512v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Andreev bound states can occur at single impurities in superconductors if the impurities suppress superconductivity for a given system. In particular, well-known Yu-Shiba-Rusinov states occur at magnetic impurities in conventional s-wave superconductors. Here we demonstrate that nonmagnetic impurities in S/AF heterostructures with conventional intraband s-wave pairing also produce Andreev bound states. Analogously to the Yu-Shiba-Rusinov bound states the bound states in S/AF bilayers are spin split, but the spin of a particular bound state is determined by the sublattice to which the impurity belongs. The standard decay of the bound state LDOS is superimposed by atomic oscillations related to the staggered character of the exchange field in the host material and by another oscillating pattern produced by finite-momentum Neel triplet pairing generated at the impurity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.02512v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.214508</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 109, 214508 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>G. A. Bobkov, I. V. Bobkova, A. M. Bobkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical demonstration of Abelian fractional statistics of composite fermions in the spherical geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14880</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14880v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Fractional quantum Hall (FQH) fluids host quasiparticle excitations that carry a fraction of the electronic charge. Moreover, in contrast to bosons and fermions that carry exchange statistics of $0$ and $\pi$ respectively, these quasiparticles of FQH fluids, when braided around one another, can accumulate a Berry phase, which is a fractional multiple of $\pi$. Deploying the spherical geometry, we numerically demonstrate that composite fermion particle (CFP) excitations in the Jain FQH states carry Abelian fractional statistics. Previously, the exchange statistics of CFPs were studied in the disk geometry, where the statistics get obscured due to a shift in the phase arising from the addition of another CFP, making its determination cumbersome without prior knowledge of the shift. We show that on the sphere this technical issue can be circumvented and the statistics of CFPs can be obtained more transparently. The ideas we present can be extended to determine the statistics of quasiparticles arising in certain non-Abelian partonic FQH states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14880v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.045148</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 045148 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Koyena Bose, Ajit C. Balram</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disordered Parity Anomalous Semimetal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11270v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The parity anomalous semimetal is a topological state of matter characterized by its semi-metallic nature and a quantum Hall conductance of one-half $e^{2}/h$ ($e$ is the elementary charge and $h$ is the Planck constant). Here we investigate the topological phase transition driven by disorder in a semi-magnetic structure of topological insulator, and narrow-gap weak topological insulator film. We demonstrate that strong disorder not only leads to a topological transition from the parity anomalous semimetal to a diffusive metal with non-quantized anomalous Hall conductance, but also induces the topological phase in a trivial insulating phase. Our calculations of the local density of states provide clear picture for the formation of a single gapless Dirac fermion, which emerges as the disorder strength increases. The half quantized Hall effect is attributed to the existence of the gapless Dirac cone. Our findings of disorder-induced parity anomalous semimetal and diffusive metal significantly advance our understanding of the disorder-driven topological phase transition in magnetic topological insulators, opening up new avenues for further exploration in the field of quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11270v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shi-Hao Bi, Bo Fu, Shun-Qing Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Fermi-Liquid Transport Phenomena in Infinite-Layer Nickelates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.01412v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently discovered superconducting infinite-layer nickelates $R$NiO$_2$ ($R$=Nd, La, Pr) attract increasing attention due to their similarities to cuprates. Both $R$NiO$_2$ and YBCO cuprates exhibit the non-Fermi-liquid transport behavior, characterized by resistivity proportional to temperature near the quantum critical point of the charge or spin density wave. In this study, we analyze the resistivity of infinite-layer nickelate Nd$_{0.85}$Sr$_{0.15}$NiO$_2$ based on a three-dimensional tight-binding model within the framework of the quasi-particle picture by applying linear response theory. We take account of the self-energy by the fluctuation-exchange approximation for the Ni orbital and the T-matrix approximation for an impurity effect on the Nd orbitals. We find that (i) the $T$-linear resistivity at low temperatures is derived from the spin fluctuations, and (ii) a negative and $T$-linear Seebeck coefficient is obtained. Therefore, NdNiO$_2$ behaves as a quasi-two-dimensional electron system, similar to CeCoIn$_5$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.01412v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shinichi Hiragami, Seiichiro Onari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proof of the absence of nontrivial local conserved quantities in the spin-1 bilinear-biquadratic chain and its anisotropic extensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.04945</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.04945v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We provide a complete classification of the integrability and nonintegrability of the spin-1 bilinear-biquadratic model with a uniaxial anisotropic field, which includes the Heisenberg model and the Affleck-Kennedy-Lieb-Tasaki model. It is rigorously shown that, within this class, the only integrable systems are those that have been solved by the Bethe ansatz method, and that all other systems are nonintegrable, in the sense that they do not have nontrivial local conserved quantities. Here, "nontrivial" excludes quantities like the Hamiltonian or the total magnetization, and "local" refers to sums of operators that act only on sites within a finite distance. This result establishes the nonintegrability of the Affleck-Kennedy-Lieb-Tasaki model and, consequently, demonstrates that the quantum many-body scars observed in this model emerge independently of any conservation laws of local quantities. Furthermore, we extend the proof of nonintegrability to more general spin-1 models that encompass anisotropic extensions of the bilinear-biquadratic Hamiltonian, and completely classify the integrability of generic Hamiltonians that possess translational symmetry, $U(1)$ symmetry, time-reversal symmetry, and spin-flip symmetry. Our result accomplishes a breakthrough in nonintegrability proofs by expanding their scope to spin-1 systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.04945v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akihiro Hokkyo, Mizuki Yamaguchi, Yuuya Chiba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cluster spin glass correlations and dynamics in Zn$_{0.5}$Mn$_{0.5}$Te</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16130</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16130v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a magnetometry, muon spin relaxation ($\mu$SR), and neutron scattering study of the insulating face-centered-cubic spin glass Zn$_{0.5}$Mn$_{0.5}$Te. The magnetometry and $\mu$SR results confirm a spin freezing transition around $T_f \approx 23$ K, with the spin fluctuation rate decreasing gradually and somewhat inhomogeneously through the sample volume as the temperature decreases toward $T_f$. Characteristic spin correlation times well above $T_f$ are on the order of 10$^{-10}$ s, in line with expectations for a cluster spin glass. Using magnetic pair distribution function (mPDF) analysis and reverse Monte Carlo (RMC) modeling of the magnetic diffuse neutron scattering data, we show that the spin-glass ground state consists of clusters of spins exhibiting short-range-ordered type-III antiferromagnetic correlations, with a locally ordered moment of 3.1(1) $\mu_{\mathrm{B}}$ between nearest-neighbor spins. The type-III correlations decay exponentially as a function of spin separation distance with a correlation length of approximately 5 \AA. The diffuse magnetic scattering and corresponding mPDF show no significant changes across $T_f$, indicating that the dynamically fluctuating short-range spin correlations in the paramagnetic state retain the same basic type-III configuration; the only change apparent from the neutron scattering data is a gradual reduction of the correlation length and locally ordered moment with increasing temperature. Taken together, these results paint a unique and detailed picture of the local magnetic structure and dynamics in Zn$_{0.5}$Mn$_{0.5}$Te and show that this material is best described as a cluster spin glass. In addition, this work showcases a statistical method for extracting diffuse scattering signals from neutron powder diffraction data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16130v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/qv69-dv54</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 144440 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sabrina R. Hatt, Camille Shaw, Emma Zappala, Raju Baral, Stuart Calder, Gerald D. Morris, Brenden R. Ortiz, Karine Chesnel, Benjamin A. Frandsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Grassmann manifolds in topological systems via quantum distance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20046</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20046v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum states defined over a parameter space form a Grassmann manifold. To capture the geometry of the associated gauge structure, gauge-invariant quantities are essential. We employ the projector of a multilevel system to quantify the quantum distance between states. Using the multidimensional scaling method, we transform the quantum distance into a reconstructed manifold embedded in Euclidean space. This approach is demonstrated with examples of topological systems, showcasing their topological features within these manifolds. Our method provides a comprehensive view of the manifold, rather than focusing on local properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20046v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shin-Ming Huang, Dimitrios Giataganas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning the Renyi entropy of multiple disjoint intervals in transverse-field quantum Ising models with restricted Boltzmann machine</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20444</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20444v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Renyi entropy with multiple disjoint intervals are computed from the improved swapping operations by two methods: one is from the direct diagonalization of the Hamiltonian and the other one is from the state-of-the-art machine learning method with neural networks. We use the paradigmatic transverse-field Ising model in one-dimension to demonstrate the strategy of the improved swapping operation. In particular, we study the second Renyi entropy with two, three and four disjoint intervals. We find that the results from the above two methods match each other very well within errors, which indicates that the machine learning method is applicable for calculating the Renyi entropy with multiple disjoint intervals. Moreover, as the magnetic field increases, the Renyi entropy grows as well until the system arrives at the critical point of the phase transition. However, as the magnetic field exceeds the critical value, the Renyi entropy will decrease since the system enters the paramagnetic phase. Overall, these results match the theoretical predictions very well and demonstrate the high accuracy of the machine learning methods with neural networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20444v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Han-Qing Shi, Hai-Qing Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature dependent energy gap for Yu-Shiba-Rusinov states at the quantum phase transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04196v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Motivated by recent experiments, which allow for fine tuning of the effective magnetic interaction between the impurity and the superconductor, we investigate the regime around the quantum phase transition where the system's ground state changes from a weakly coupled free spin to a screened spin regime. At this transition we find that the Yu-Shiba-Rusinov (YSR) states remain at finite energies at low temperatures, thereby generating a gap in the spectrum, which is inconsistent with predictions of the original YSR theory. We investigate various gap-generating scenarios and determine that the local suppression of the order parameter, only captured by self-consistent calculations, generates the gap.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04196v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/k8qc-3cs6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 134505 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Theiler, Christian R. Ast, Annica M. Black-Schaffer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic phase diagram of multiferroic and magnetocaloric TmFeO$_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17291v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Neutron diffraction experiments of TmFeO$_3$ single crystals were performed in the external magnetic fields. The field along $c$-axis increases temperature of spin-reorientation transition TSR from phase ${\Gamma}4$ to ${\Gamma}2$. Application of the field along $b$-axis led to the decrease of TSR and to the formation of new phases. Based on the temperature and field dependence of the Bragg reflection intensity, the configuration of magnetically induced phases was proposed. The magneto-structural effects were observed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17291v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. I. Tkachenko, P. Fabrykiewicz, A. K. Ovsianikov, M. Meven, O. V. Usmanov, I. A. Zobkalo, K. A. Shaykhutdinov, K. Yu. Terentjev, S. V. Semenov, E. Ressouche, K. Beauvois</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interaction induced Anderson transition in a kicked one dimensional Bose gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02565v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the Lieb-Liniger model of one-dimensional bosons subjected to periodic kicks. In both the non-interacting and strongly interacting limits, the system undergoes dynamical localization, leading to energy saturation at long times. However, for finite interactions, we reveal an interaction-driven transition from an insulating to a metallic phase at a critical kicking strength, provided the number of particles is three or more. Using the Bethe Ansatz solution of the Lieb-Liniger gas, we establish a formal correspondence between its dynamical evolution and an Anderson model in $N$ spatial dimensions, where $N$ is the number of particles. This theoretical prediction is supported by extensive numerical simulations for three particles, complemented by finite-time scaling analysis, demonstrating that this transition belongs to the orthogonal Anderson universality class.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02565v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/dyxq-qkmd</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 173403 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hazel Olsen, Pierre Devillard, Gianni Aupetit-Diallo, Patrizia Vignolo, Mathias Albert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Many-body localization and particle multioccupancy in the disordered Bose-Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03712v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the potential influence of the particle multi-occupations on the stability of many-body localization in the disordered Bose-Hubbard model. Within the higher-energy section of the dynamical phase diagram, we find that there is no apparent finite-size boundary drift between the thermal phase and the many-body localized regime. We substantiate this observation by introducing the Van Vleck perturbation theory into the field of many-body localization. The appropriateness of this method rests largely on the peculiar Hilbert-space structure enabled by the particles' Bose statistics. The situation is reversed in the lower-energy section of the dynamical phase diagram, where the significant finite-size boundary drift pushes the putative many-body localized regime up to the greater disorder strengths. We utilize the algebraic projection method to make a connection linking the disordered Bose-Hubbard model in the lower-energy section to an intricate disordered spin chain model. This issue of the finite-size drift could hence be analogous to what happens in the disordered Heisenberg chain. Both trends might be traced back to the particles' intrinsic or emergent single-occupancy constraint like the spin-$1/2$, hard-core boson, or spinless fermion degrees of freedom.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03712v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/q5l5-517x</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 134205(2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jie Chen, Chun Chen, Xiaoqun Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin Texture Control and Magnetic Gap Engineering in a Ferromagnetic Insulator-Topological Insulator Sandwiched Heterostructure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10979</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10979v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum materials combining magnetism and topological fermions are a key platform for low-energy electronics, spintronics, and quantum phases that break time-reversal symmetry (TRS), such as the quantum anomalous Hall effect (QAHE). Coupling a topological insulator to a magnetic material allows proximity magnetization with the potential to achieve these phases at elevated temperatures. One potential architecture for realizing QAHE at elevated temperature is a heterostructure comprising two single-septuple layers (1SL) of MnBi2Te4 (a 2D ferromagnetic insulator) with four-quintuple layer (4QL) Bi2Te3 in the middle. However, the origin of this gap has not yet been explicitly determined, as there are other non-magnetic mechanisms that have been shown to produce bandgaps in similar systems. Here, through spin- and angle-resolved photoemission, the magnetic nature of the gap opening is investigated to demonstrates direct control of the spin state via small magnetic fields and confirm the magnetic origin of the gap through spin splitting and broken TRS. Furthermore, the hallmark chiral spin texture of non-magnetic topological insulators is preserved away from the {\Gamma}-point, despite the large 72+/-10 meV exchange gap at the Dirac point. The robust magnetic gap and controllable spin texture hold significant promise for future technologies requiring both magnetic properties and topological protection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10979v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad T. H. Bhuiyan, Qile Li, James Blyth, Ji-Eun Lee, Jonathan Denlinger, Jaime S\'anchez-Barriga, Alexander Fedorov, Anton Tadich, Emile Reinks, Sung-Kwan Mo, Alexei Fedorov, Oliver J. Clark, Mark T. Edmonds</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three-body Physics in the Impurity Limit of 39K Bose-Einstein Condensates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13129</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13129v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Loss spectroscopy is a key tool for investigating systems where important system parameters are linked to intrinsic resonant loss processes. We investigate loss processes of impurity atoms embedded in a medium of a Bose-Einstein Condensate close to a Feshbach resonance. In this case, three-body loss processes occur faster than the measurement duration, impeding a direct time-resolved measurement. Here, we discuss how an even faster two-body loss process can be used to probe the system. The time-dependent number of atoms in the medium is reconstructed from such measurements, allowing for the extraction of the three-body loss rate coefficient $L_3$ and its scaling with scattering length. Moreover, the medium atom number is reconstructed from spectroscopic loss measurements. This allows for a comparison of the medium densities based on both the extracted loss rates and the spectroscopically reconstructed atom number. Finally, the number of lost medium atoms per loss event is evaluated and found to exceed 2 at strong interactions, which is attributed to secondary collisions in the medium. These investigations establish the use of a fast loss mechanism as a new tool in the field and provide quantitative measurements of three-body losses at large interaction strengths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13129v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/54hb-ksqx</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 111, 063314 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>A. M. Morgen, S. S. Balling, M. T. Str{\o}e, T. G. Skov, M. R. Skou, A. G. Volosniev, J. J. Arlt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fragility of local moments against hybridization with flat bands</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14326v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Kondo screening of a localized magnetic moment crucially depends on the spectral properties of the electronic bath to which it is coupled. Unlike textbook examples, realistic systems as well as dynamical mean-field theory of correlated lattice models force us to explicitly consider sharp features in the hybridization function near the Fermi energy. A case currently under the spotlight is twisted bilayer graphene, where the hybridization function of the heavy-fermion-like bands to the itinerant ones displays a divergence. We clarify how this impacts the screening mechanisms by means of a toy model with a tunable $\delta$-peak in the hybridization function, superimposed to a regular part. Our analysis unveils an unexpectedly big impact on the Kondo screening already for a parametrically small weight of the flat band in the bath.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14326v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Max Fischer, Arianna Poli, Lorenzo Crippa, Dumitru C\u{a}lug\u{a}ru, Sergio Ciuchi, Matthias Vojta, Alessandro Toschi, Giorgio Sangiovanni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental Investigation of a Bipartite Quench in a 1D Bose gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.05839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.05839v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Long wavelength dynamics of 1D Bose gases with repulsive contact interactions can be captured by Generalized HydroDynamics (GHD) which predicts the evolution of the local rapidity distribution. The latter corresponds to the momentum distribution of quasiparticles, which have infinite lifetime owing to the integrability of the system. Here we experimentally investigate the dynamics for an initial situation that is the junction of two semi-infinite systems in different stationary states, a protocol referred to as `bipartite quench' protocol. More precisely we realise the particular case where one half of the system is the vacuum state. We show that the evolution of the boundary density profile exhibits ballistic dynamics obeying the Euler hydrodynamic scaling. The boundary profiles are similar to the ones predicted with zero-temperature GHD in the quasi-BEC regime, with deviations due to non-zero entropy effects. We show that this protocol, provided the boundary profile is measured with infinite precision, permits to reconstruct the rapidity distribution of the initial state. For our data, we extract the initial rapidity distribution by fitting the boundary profile and we use a 3-parameter ansatz that goes beyond the thermal assumption. Finally, we investigate the local rapidity distribution inside the boundary profile, which, according to GHD, presents, on one side, features of zero-entropy states. The measured distribution shows the asymmetry predicted by GHD, although unelucidated deviations remain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.05839v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L\'ea Dubois, Guillaume Th\'em\`eze, J\'er\^ome Dubail, Isabelle Bouchoule</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature dependence of coercivity for isolated Ni nanowires unraveled by high-sensitivity micromagnetometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13675</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13675v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Magnetic nanowires are critical components in fields such as data storage and spintronics, where precise control of their magnetic properties is essential for device optimization. In particular, the behavior of isolated nanowires is often different from that of an ensemble, offering an opportunity to explore the role that dipolar and magnetoelastic interactions play in the latter system. Unfortunately, the comparison between a collection of nanowires and single ones is often poorly characterized, as measuring individual nanowires with weak magnetic signals is a challenging task. In this work, we employ a highly-sensitive micromechanical torsional oscillator to measure the magnetic response of few individual Ni nanowires with 72 +/- 5 nm average diameter, fabricated by electrodeposition in anodic aluminum oxide templates as an array and subsequently released from this membrane. When comparing the magnetic properties as a function of temperature between single nanowires and the array, we show that coercivity values of individual nanowires are at least twice as large as for the array in the range 5 K - 200 K. Also, we characterize the differences in the hysteresis loops, which are more squared for isolated nanowires, with a high magnetic remanence close to 80 % of the saturation value. Our results highlight the crucial role of dipolar and mechanical interactions in modifying the magnetic behavior of nanowires arrays, providing valuable insights for the design and application of nanowires-based magnetic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13675v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/dcf2-7rsc</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 134452 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Evelyn A. Escudero Bruna, Federico Rom\'a, Fernando Meneses, Paula. G. Bercoff, Moira I. Dolz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neuralized Fermionic Tensor Networks for Quantum Many-Body Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08329</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08329v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We describe a class of neuralized fermionic tensor network states (NN-fTNS) that introduce non-linearity into fermionic tensor networks through configuration-dependent neural network transformations of the local tensors. The construction uses the fTNS algebra to implement a natural fermionic sign structure and is compatible with standard tensor network algorithms, but gains enhanced expressivity through the neural network parametrization. Using the 1D and 2D Fermi-Hubbard models as benchmarks, we demonstrate that NN-fTNS achieve order of magnitude improvements in the ground-state energy compared to pure fTNS with the same bond dimension, and can be systematically improved through both the tensor network bond dimension and the neural network parametrization. Compared to existing fermionic neural quantum states (NQS) based on Slater determinants and Pfaffians, NN-fTNS offer a physically motivated alternative fermionic structure. Furthermore, compared to such states, NN-fTNS naturally exhibit improved computational scaling and we demonstrate a construction that achieves linear scaling with the lattice size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08329v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Si-Jing Du, Ao Chen, Garnet Kin-Lic Chan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Expansion dynamics of strongly correlated lattice bosons: A selfconsistent density-matrix approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09397</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09397v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the spatio-temporal dynamics of interacting bosons on a two-dimensional Hubbard lattice in the strongly interacting regime, taking into account the dynamics of condensate amplitude as well as the direct transport of non-condensed fluctuations. To that end we develop a selfconsistent density-matrix approach which goes beyond the standard Gutzwiller mean-field theory. Starting from the Liouville-von-Neumann equation we derive a quantum master equation for the time evolution of the system's local density matrix at each lattice site, with a dynamical bath that represents the rest of the system. We apply this method to the expansion dynamics of an initially prepared cloud of interacting bosons in an optical lattice. We observe a ballistic expansion of the condensate, as expected, followed by slow, diffusive transport of the normal bosons. We discuss, in particular, the robustness of the Mott insulator phase as well as its melting due to incoherent transport. The method should be applicable to various models of lattice bosons in the strongly correlated regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09397v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/bzvn-sp2h</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 112, 043322 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Julian Schwingel, Michael Turaev, Johann Kroha, Sayak Ray</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The effect of dephasing and spin-lattice relaxation during the switching processes in quantum antiferromagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00430</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00430v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The control of antiferromagnetic order can pave the way to large storage capacity as well as fast manipulation of stored data. Here achieving a steady-state of sublattice magnetization after switching is crucial to prevent loss of stored data. The present theoretical approach aims to obtain instantaneous stable states of the order after reorienting the N\'eel vector in open quantum antiferromagnets using time-dependent Schwinger boson mean-field theory. The Lindblad formalism is employed to couple the system to the environment. The quantum theoretical approach comprises differences in the effects of dephasing, originating from destructive interference of different wave vectors, and spin-lattice relaxation. We show that the spin-lattice relaxation results in an exponentially fast convergence to the steady-state after full ultrafast switching.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00430v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.21468/SciPostPhys.19.4.117.</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>SciPost Phys. 19, 117 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Asliddin Khudoyberdiev, G\"otz S. Uhrig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An accurate DFT-1/2 approach for shallow defect states: Efficient calculation of donor binding energies in silicon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14738v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Accurate prediction of shallow-donor electron binding energies is critical for device modeling, dopant activation, and donor-based quantum technologies. Traditional beyond-DFT approaches (e.g., hybrid functionals, GW) are prohibitively expensive for the large supercells needed to capture the extended, hydrogenic wavefunctions, while semi-local DFT underestimates band gaps and suffers from delocalization errors. We present a simple, practical protocol for shallow donors based on the DFT-1/2 approximate quasiparticle correction that maintains the computational cost of standard DFT and enables supercells up to thousands of atoms. This approach provides a straightforward and reproducible workflow that delivers reliable donor binding energies with minimal computational overhead. Applied to group-V donors in Si, Si:X (X= P, As, Sb, Bi), the method yields binding energies in close agreement with experiment. We found that, for Si:Bi, it is essential to include spin-orbit coupling to achieve near-experimental values with a difference of only $\sim$ 4 meV. For arsenic, the method yields excellent agreement with experiment, with a difference of only ~0.3 meV. For antimony, the results match experiment to within ~5 meV, and for phosphorus, the deviation is within ~8 meV. Beyond its high accuracy, DFT-1/2 offers a significant practical advantage, providing a straightforward, reproducible, and transferable workflow that is less demanding than hybrid functional approaches while remaining fully generalizable to other shallow impurities in semiconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14738v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua Claes, Bart Partoens, Dirk Lamoen, Marcelo Marques, Lara K. Teles</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric Effects on Tunneling in Driven Quantum Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03674</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03674v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We review quantum tunneling provoked by external field driving, focusing on the role of geometric effects. The discussion begins with an overview of tunneling phenomena, including the Landau-Zener model and the Schwinger effect, both of which are essential frameworks to describe the generation of elementary excitation of the system. We also refer to the relation between the modern theory of polarization and the geometry of the system, and introduce the shift vector via adiabatic perturbation theory. Then we introduce the twisted Landau-Zener model and shown how the shift vector modulates tunneling probability, followed by several illustrative applications of this model. We also explain the Keldysh crossover, which is the crossover from a quantum tunneling regime to photon absorption regime in driven systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03674v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.7566/JPSJ.94.111003</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. 94, 111003 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shintaro Takayoshi, Takashi Oka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crystal-Field--Driven Magnetoelectricity in the Triangular Quantum Magnet CeMgAl$_{11}$O$_{19}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.08746v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report dielectric and magnetoelectric studies of single-crystalline \ce{CeMgAl11O19}, a Kramers triangular magnet embedded in a polarizable hexaaluminate lattice. In zero magnetic field, the permittivity $\varepsilon'(T)$ follows the Barrett law of a quantum paraelectric down to 25 K, below which a broad minimum develops near 3 K without evidence of static ferroelectric or magnetic order. Application of magnetic fields up to \SI{9}{\tesla} shifts this minimum to higher temperatures and broadens it, evidencing a tunable magnetoelectric response.The magnetoelectric coupling was characterized using results from magnetization measurements. The anomaly temperature $T^*$, extracted from the local minimum of $\varepsilon'(T)$, exhibits a linear dependence on the squared magnetization $M^2$, consistent with the biquadratic magnetoelectric coupling allowed in centrosymmetric systems. This magnetoelectric effect, mediated by spin-orbit-entangled Kramers doublets interacting with a frustrated antipolar liquid, establishes \ce{CeMgAl11O19} as a prototype for exploring quantum magnetoelectricity in frustrated systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.08746v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sonu Kumar (Charles University, Faculty of Mathematics and Physics, Department of Condensed Matter Physics, Prague, Czech Republic, Adam Mickiewicz University, Faculty of Physics and Astronomy, Department of Experimental Physics of Condensed Phase, Pozna\'n, Poland), Ga\"el Bastien (Charles University, Faculty of Mathematics and Physics, Department of Condensed Matter Physics, Prague, Czech Republic), Maxim Savinov (Institute of Physics, Czech Academy of Sciences, Prague, Czech Republic), Petr Proschek (Charles University, Faculty of Mathematics and Physics, Department of Condensed Matter Physics, Prague, Czech Republic), Adam Eli\'a\v{s} (Charles University, Faculty of Mathematics and Physics, Department of Condensed Matter Physics, Prague, Czech Republic), Karol Za{\l}\k{e}ski (Adam Mickiewicz University, NanoBioMedical Centre, Pozna\'n, Poland), Ma{\l}gorzata \'Sliwi\'nska-Bartkowiak (Adam Mickiewicz University, Faculty of Physics and Astronomy, Department of Experimental Physics of Condensed Phase, Pozna\'n, Poland), Ross H. Colman (Charles University, Faculty of Mathematics and Physics, Department of Condensed Matter Physics, Prague, Czech Republic), Stanislav Kamba (Institute of Physics, Czech Academy of Sciences, Prague, Czech Republic)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ab-initio calculation of magnetic exchange interactions using the spin-spiral method in VASP: Self-consistent versus magnetic force theorem approaches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11603v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present an ab initio investigation of magnetic exchange interactions using the spin-spiral method implemented in the VASP code, with a comparative analysis of the self-consistent (SC) and magnetic force theorem (MFT) approaches. Using representative 3d ferromagnets (Fe, Co, Ni) and Mn-based full Heusler compounds, we compute magnon dispersion relations directly from spin-spiral total energies and extract real-space Heisenberg exchange parameters via Fourier transformation. Curie temperatures are subsequently estimated within both the mean-field and random-phase approximations. The SC spin-spiral calculations yield exchange parameters and magnon spectra in excellent agreement with previous theoretical data, confirming their quantitative reliability across different classes of magnetic systems. In contrast, the MFT approach exhibits systematic quantitative deviations: it overestimates spin-spiral energies and exchange couplings in high-moment systems such as bcc Fe and the Mn-based Heuslers, while underestimating them in low-moment fcc Ni. The magnitude of these discrepancies increases strongly with magnetic moment size, exceeding several hundred percent in the high-moment compounds. These findings underscore the decisive role of self-consistency in accurately determining magnetic exchange parameters and provide practical guidance for future first-principles studies of spin interactions and excitations using the spin-spiral technique.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11603v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Umit Dogan Daglum, Maria Stamenova, Ersoy Sasioglu, Stefano Sanvito</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Yamaji effect in models of underdoped cuprates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13943</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13943v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent angle-dependent magnetoresistance measurements in underdoped cuprates have revealed compelling evidence for small hole pockets in the pseudogap regime, including observation of the Yamaji effect in HgBa$_2$CuO$_{4+\delta}$ (Chan et al., Nature Physics 10.1038/s41567-025-03032-2 (2025)). A key distinction between theories is their predicted Fermi volumes, measured as fractions of the square lattice Brillouin zone: $p/4$ per pocket for spin density wave (SDW) versus $p/8$ for fractionalized Fermi liquid (FL*), where $p$ is the hole doping. We calculate the $c$-axis magnetoresistance $\rho_{zz}(\theta, \phi)$ within the semiclassical Boltzmann formalism for both states, and using the ancilla layer model (ALM) for FL* in a single-band Hamiltonian. The results from the $\text{FL}^*$ phase show good consistency with current experimental data. Conversely, the results for the SDW phase are highly sensitive to the ordering momentum along the $z$-direction. An ordering vector of $Q = (\pi, \pi, \pi)$ yields predictions that starkly disagree with the experiment. The only possibility for agreement within the SDW scenario is to assume an ordering momentum of $Q = (\pi, \pi, 0)$. However, even in this specific case, the SDW scenario predicts a marginally smaller Yamaji angle at $\phi=0$ than the FL* theory, and a second Yamaji peak near in-plane angle $\phi = 45^\circ$, which was not observed in the experiment. In reality, the N\'eel ordering vector is likely uncorrelated between adjacent layers, so that there is no coherent interlayer transport of hole-pocket quasiparticles in the SDW scenario, and consequently no Yamaji effect. Our results support the FL* interpretation of Fermi arcs in the pseudogap phase, and establish Yamaji angle measurements as a discriminatory tool between theoretical models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13943v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jing-Yu Zhao, Shubhayu Chatterjee, Subir Sachdev, Ya-Hui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of Majorana Fermions on a Quantum Computer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20034</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20034v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The study of quasiparticle dynamics is central to understanding non-equilibrium phenomena in quantum many-body systems. Direct simulation of such dynamics on quantum hardware has been limited by circuit depth and noise constraints. In this work, we use a recently developed constant-depth circuit algorithm to examine the real-time evolution of site-resolved magnetization in a transverse-field Ising chain on noisy intermediate-scale quantum devices. By representing each spin as a pair of Majorana fermions, we identify two distinct dynamical regimes governed by the relative strength of spin interaction. Furthermore, we show how local impurities can serve as probes of Majorana modes, acting as dynamical barriers in the weak coupling regime. These results demonstrate that constant-depth quantum circuits provide a viable route for studying quasiparticle propagation and for probing Majorana signatures on currently available quantum processors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20034v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxiao Hang, Rosa Di Felice, Aiichiro Nakano, Stephan Haas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear optical quantum theory of demagnetization in L1$_0$ FePt and FePd</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22972v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is now well established that a laser pulse can demagnetize a
  ferromagnet. However, for a long time, it has not had an analytic
  theory because it falls into neither nonlinear optics (NLO) nor
  magnetism. Here we attempt to fill this gap by developing a
  nonlinear optical theory centered on the spin moment, instead of
  the more popular susceptibility. We first employ group theory to
  pin down the lowest order of the nonzero spin moment in a
  centrosymmetric system to be the second order, where the
  second-order density matrix contains four terms of sum frequency
  generation (SFG) and four terms of difference frequency generation
  (DFG). By tracing over the product of the density matrix and the
  spin matrix, we are now able to compute the light-induced spin
  moment. We apply our theory to FePt and FePd, two most popular
  magnetic recording materials with identical crystal and electronic
  structures. We find that the theory can clearly distinguish the
  difference between those two similar systems. Specifically, we
  show that FePt has a stronger light-induced spin moment than FePd,
  in agreement with our real-time ultrafast demagnetization
  simulation and the experimental results. Among all the possible
  NLO processes, DFGs produce the largest spin moment change, a
  manifestation of optical rectification. Our research lays a solid
  theoretical foundation for femtomagnetism, so the light-induced spin moment reduction can now be computed and compared among
  different systems, without time-consuming real-time calculations,
  representing a significant step forward.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22972v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. P. Zhang, Y. H. Bai, Thomas F. George</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum simulation of the phase transition of the massive Thirring model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.00803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.00803v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent advancements in quantum computing technology have enabled the study of fermionic systems at finite temperature via quantum simulations. This presents a novel approach to investigating the chiral phase transition in such systems. Among these, the quantum minimally entangled typical thermal states~(QMETTS) algorithm has recently attracted considerable interest. The massive Thirring model, which exhibits a variety of phenomena at low temperatures, includes both a chiral phase transition and a topologically non-trivial ground state. It therefore raises the intriguing question of whether its phase transition can be studied using a quantum simulation approach. In this study, the chiral phase transition of the massive Thirring model and its dual topological phase transition are studied using the QMETTS algorithm. Numerical results are obtained on a classical computer simulating circuit-based quantum computations. The results show that QMETTS is able to accurately reproduce the phase transition and thermodynamic properties of the massive Thirring model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.00803v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP09(2025)120</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of High Energy Physics volume 2025, Article number: 120 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jia-Qi Gong, Ji-Chong Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact analysis of AC sensors based on Floquet time crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22731</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22731v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We discuss the behavior of general Floquet Time Crystals (FTCs), including prethermal ones, in closed systems acting as AC sensors. We provide an analytical treatment of their quantum Fisher information (QFI) dynamics, which characterizes the ultimate sensor accuracy. By tuning the direction and frequency of the AC field, we show how to induce transitions resonantly between macroscopic paired cat states in the FTC sensor. This allows for robust Heisenberg scaling precision (QFI $\sim N^2 t^2$) for exponentially long times in the system size. The QFI dynamics exhibit, moreover, a characteristic step-like structure in time due to the eventual dephasing along the cat subspaces. The behavior is discussed for various initial sensor preparations, including ground states and low- and high-correlated states. Furthermore, we examine the performance of the sensor along the FTC phase transition; with the QFI capturing its critical exponents. Our findings are presented for both linear and nonlinear response regimes and illustrated for a specific FTC based on the long-range interacting LMG model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22731v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei Tsypilnikov, Matheus Fibger, Fernando Iemini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collective many-body dynamics in a solid-state quantum sensor controlled through nanoscale magnetic gradients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.11920</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.11920v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Coherent collective dynamics of strongly interacting qubits are a central resource in quantum information science, with applications from quantum computing and simulation to metrology. While electronic spins interact strongly via dipolar couplings in dense solid-state ensembles, imperfections and positional disorder pose major obstacles to coherent correlated behavior, limiting their usefulness. Here, we realize collective many-body dynamics by combining time-dependent magnetic field gradients with global coherent control of dense electron spin ensembles in diamond. We control and probe the dynamics of nanometer-scale spin spirals, and, by exploiting Hamiltonian engineering that enhances the microscopic symmetry of the interactions, we observe a disorder-resilient collective spin evolution. Our results establish a pathway to interaction-enhanced quantum metrology and nanoscale imaging of materials and biological systems under ambient conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.11920v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Piotr Put, Nathaniel T. Leitao, Haoyang Gao, Christina Spaegele, Oksana Makarova, Lillian B. Hughes Wyatt, Andrew C. Maccabe, Matthew Mammen, Bartholomeus Machielse, Hengyun Zhou, Szymon Pustelny, Ania C. Bleszynski Jayich, Federico Capasso, Leigh S. Martin, Hongkun Park, Mikhail D. Lukin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulating the interplay of dipolar and quadrupolar interactions in NMR by spin dynamic mean-field theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17720v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The simulation of nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) experiments is a notoriously difficult task, if many spins participate in the dynamics. The recently established dynamic mean-field theory for high-temperature spin systems (spinDMFT) represents an efficient yet accurate method to deal with this scenario. SpinDMFT reduces a complex lattice system to a time-dependent single-site problem, which can be solved numerically with small computational effort. Since the approach retains local quantum degrees of freedom, a quadrupolar term can be exactly incorporated. This allows us to study the interplay of dipolar and quadrupolar interactions for any parameter range, i.e., without the need for a perturbative treatment. We highlight the relevance of local quantum effects by a comparison with the classical analogue system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17720v3</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timo Gr\"a{\ss}er, G\"otz S. Uhrig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum-group-invariant $D^{(2)}_{n+1}$ models: Bethe ansatz and finite-size spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00610v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider the quantum integrable spin chain models associated with the Jimbo R-matrix based on the quantum affine algebra $D^{(2)}_{n+1}$, subject to quantum-group-invariant boundary conditions parameterized by two discrete variables $p=0,\dots, n$ and $\varepsilon = 0, 1$. We develop the analytical Bethe ansatz for the previously unexplored case $\varepsilon = 1$ with any $n$, and use it to investigate the effects of different boundary conditions on the finite-size spectrum of the quantum spin chain based on the rank-$2$ algebra $D^{(2)}_3$. Previous work on this model with periodic boundary conditions has shown that it is critical for the range of anisotropy parameters $0&lt;\gamma&lt;\pi/4$, where its scaling limit is described by a non-compact CFT with continuous degrees of freedom related to two copies of the 2D black hole sigma model. The scaling limit of the model with quantum-group-invariant boundary conditions depends on the parameter $\varepsilon$: similarly as in the rank-$1$ $D^{(2)}_2$ chain, we find that the symmetry of the lattice model is spontaneously broken, and the spectrum of conformal weights has both discrete and continuous components, for $\varepsilon=1$. For $p=1$, the latter coincides with that of the $D^{(2)}_2$ chain, which should correspond to a non-compact brane related to one black hole CFT in the presence of boundaries. For $\varepsilon=0$, the spectrum of conformal weights is purely discrete.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00610v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Holger Frahm, Sascha Gehrmann, Rafael I. Nepomechie, Ana L. Retore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distinct Types of Parent Hamiltonians for Quantum States: Insights from the $W$ State as a Quantum Many-Body Scar</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24713</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24713v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The construction of parent Hamiltonians that possess a given state as their ground state is a well-studied problem. In this work, we generalize this notion by considering simple quantum states and examining the local Hamiltonians that have these states as exact eigenstates. These states often correspond to Quantum Many-Body Scars (QMBS) of their respective parent Hamiltonians. Motivated by earlier works on Hamiltonians with QMBS, in this work we formalize the differences between three distinct types of parent Hamiltonians, which differ in their decompositions into strictly local terms with the same eigenstates. We illustrate this classification using the $W$ state as the primary example, for which we rigorously derive the complete set of local parent Hamiltonians, which also allows us to establish general results such as the existence of asymptotic QMBS, and distinct dynamical signatures associated with the different parent Hamiltonian types. Finally, we derive more general results on the parent Hamiltonian types that allow us to obtain some immediate results for simple quantum states such as product states, where only a single type exists, and for short-range-entangled states, for which we identify constraints on the admissible types. Altogether, our work opens the door to classifying the rich structures and dynamical properties of parent Hamiltonians that arise from the interplay between locality and QMBS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24713v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Gioia, Sanjay Moudgalya, Olexei I. Motrunich</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
