<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 05:00:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>External-field-induced transition from altermagnetic metal to fully-compensated ferrimagnetic metal in monolayer $\mathrm{Cr_2O}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05352</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05352v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Altermagnets and fully-compensated ferrimagnets are two canonical classes of zero-net-moment magnets. An altermagnetic (AM) half-metal cannot exist due to its AM spin splitting, while a fully-compensated ferrimagnetic (FC-FIM) metal seems impossible to realize because both spin channels remain gapless. Here, we propose that an FC-FIM metal can be realized by breaking the rotational or mirror symmetry that links two spin-opposite magnetic atoms in an AM metal. We further demonstrate that charge-carrier doping is fundamentally unable to generate a net magnetic moment in an altermagnet, whereas such a net moment can be readily induced in a fully-compensated ferrimagnet. We use the AM monolayer $\mathrm{Cr_2O}$ as a concrete example to validate our proposal. Either electric field or uniaxial strain can break the $S_{4z}$ symmetry of $\mathrm{Cr_2O}$, thereby inducing a transition from an AM metal to an FC-FIM metal. Uniaxial strain plus carrier doping creates a net moment in an altermagnet, and the so-called piezomagnetism is essentially a strain-driven switch from altermagnetism to fully-compensated ferrimagnetism. By analogy, we advance the concept of electromagnetism: an electric field drives the transition from altermagnetism to fully-compensated ferrimagnetism, and subsequent charge-carrier doping stabilizes a net magnetization. Our work provides a roadmap for further exploring the connection and distinction between altermagnet and fully-compensated ferrimagnet, and confirms the feasibility of FC-FIM metal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05352v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>San-Dong Guo, Qiqi Luo, Shi-Hao Zhang, Peng Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interaction-Induced Breakdown of Anderson Localization: Thermodynamic Segregation disguised as the Skin Effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05393</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05393v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the interplay between strong disorder and repulsive interactions in the one-dimensional Fermi-Hubbard model under open boundary conditions. While uncorrelated disorder is widely accepted to localize all single-particle eigenstates, a phenomenon typically reinforced by interactions in the Many-Body Localization (MBL) regime, we report a counter-intuitive breakdown of this paradigm. We demonstrate that strong repulsive interactions can overcome disorder-induced localization, driving the system into a macroscopically segregated phase where spin species accumulate at opposite boundaries. Although this boundary accumulation phenomenologically mimics the Non-Hermitian Skin Effect (NHSE) observed in non-reciprocal systems, our comprehensive analysis reveals a fundamentally different origin. By performing a rigorous control experiment in the Hermitian limit, we prove that the segregation persists without non-reciprocity, identifying many-body energy minimization as the primary driver. This "interaction-induced segregation" manifests as a sharp thermodynamic crossover, characterized by a divergent energy susceptibility, challenging the conventional understanding of disorder-interaction competition in open quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05393v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Tozar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum geometry and $X$-wave magnets with $X=p,d,f,g,i$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05477</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05477v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum geometry is a differential geometry based on quantum mechanics. It is related to various transport and optical properties in condensed matter physics. The Zeeman quantum geometry is a generalization of quantum geometry including the spin degrees of freedom. It is related to electromagnetic cross responses. Quantum geometry is generalized to non-Hermitian systems and density matrices. Especially, the latter is quantum information geometry, where the quantum Fisher information naturally arises as quantum metric. We apply these results to the $X$-wave magnets, which include $d$-wave, $g$-wave and $i$-wave altermagnets as well as $p$-wave and $f$-wave magnets. They have universal physics for anomalous Hall conductivity, tunneling magneto-resistance and planar Hall effect. We obtain various analytic formulas based on the two-band Hamiltonian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05477v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Motohiko Ezawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prussian Blue and Prussian Blue Analogs as Emerging Memristive Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05607v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Prussian blue analogues (PBAs) and related organic materials are promising platforms for next-generation memory and energy-storage technologies due to their redox activity, ionic mobility, and compatibility with low-cost and scalable fabrication. Electrodeposited Prussian Blue (PB) and Prussian White (PW) thin films show robust resistive switching with ON/OFF ratios from one to three orders of magnitude in both bipolar and unipolar modes. Structural and spectroscopic analyses reveal homogeneous films with well-defined grain boundaries and ionic pathways that enable filamentary conduction. Current-voltage measurements, impedance spectroscopy, and quantum transport modeling indicate switching mechanisms governed by ohmic or space-charge-limited conduction, driven by potassium-ion migration and reversible redox processes. PB-based devices also exhibit conductance quantization with discrete steps at integer and half-integer multiples of G0, consistent with ballistic electron transport through atomic-scale channels. Complementary studies on perylene-based liquid crystals and FeHCF on graphene oxide highlight the versatility of PBAs for memory and supercapacitor applications. Together, these results demonstrate the multifunctionality and scalability of PBAs for future ReRAM, neuromorphic computing, multilevel memory, cryptographic hardware, and high-performance energy-storage devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05607v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. B. Avila</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Suppression of stripe-ordered structural phases in monolayer IrTe$_2$ by a gold substrate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05616</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05616v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Metal-assisted exfoliation of two-dimensional (2D) materials has emerged as an efficient route to isolating large-area monolayer crystals, yet the influence of the supporting metal substrate on their intrinsic properties remains poorly understood. Here, we demonstrate successful gold-assisted exfoliation of monolayer IrTe$_2$ up to the millimeter scale. Angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES), combined with first-principles calculations, reveals that the low-energy electronic structure closely resembles that of a freestanding monolayer 1T-IrTe$_2$. We find that quasi-covalent hybridization together with substrate-induced strain leads to only modest modifications of the electronic bands. Although strain contributes to phase stability, it is essentially hybridization that drives the stabilization of the 1T-phase of the monolayer IrTe$_2$ by suppressing stripe-ordered phase transitions. These results establish gold-assisted exfoliation as a robust route to prepare a large-area monolayer IrTe$_2$ and highlight the role of metal-substrate interaction in engineering 2D materials with tailored structural phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05616v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kati Asikainen, Fr\'ed\'eric Chassot, Baptiste Hildebrand, Aymen Mahmoudi, Joel Morf, Mahault Berset, Pascal Turban, Matti Alatalo, S. Assa Aravindh, Marko Huttula, KeYuan Ma, Fabian O. von Rohr, Jean-Christophe Le Breton, Thomas Jaouen, Claude Monney</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Size-effects on shift-current in layered CuInP$_2$S$_6$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05796</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05796v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two-dimensional ferroelectrics have recently emerged as a promising avenue for next-generation optoelectronic and photovoltaic devices. Due to the intrinsic absence of inversion symmetry, 2D ferroelectrics exhibit bulk photovoltaic effect (BPVE), which relies on hot, non-thermalized photo-excited carriers to generate a photo-induced current with enhanced performances thanks to efficient charge separation mechanisms. The absence of a required p-n junction architecture makes these materials particularly attractive for nanoscale energy harvesting. Recent studies have reported enhanced BPVE in nanometer-thick CuInP$_2$S$_6$ ferroelectric embedded between two graphene wafers, driven by relatively strong polarization and reduced dimensionality. Short circuit photocurrent density values have been observed to reach up to mA/cm$^2$. In this paper, we demonstrate that the shift-current mechanism alone cannot fully account for these high conductivity values, suggesting that additional mechanisms may play a significant role. Furthermore, our work confirms the existence of a strong size effect, which drastically reduces the shift-conductivity response in the bulk limit, in agreement with experimental observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05796v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Delodovici, Brahim Dkhil, Charles Paillard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microscopic theory of the inverse spin galvanic effect in anisotropic Rashba models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05799</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05799v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Rashba spin-orbit coupling (SOC) is a well-known mechanism for the spin-charge interconversion via the inverse and direct spin galvanic effects. The lack of a full inversion symmetry allows the coupling of the charge current and spin density. In this paper we investigate this phenomenon when the in-plane rotational symmetry is lowered to the $C_{2v}$ and $C_{3v}$ symmetry groups, whereby the electron spectrum becomes anisotropic. We find that in the $C_{2v}$ case, depending on the ratio between the Rashba SOC strengths along the principal axes, the non-equilibrium spin density deviates notably from the $90^o$ degrees rotation, with respect to the applied electric field, familiar in the isotropic case. In the $C_{3v}$ case, when a warping cubic-in-momentum term is present, whereas the standard $90^o$ degrees rotation of the spin density remains, the spin-charge interconversion depends on the intensity of the warping itself. The microscopic theory takes into account disorder including vertex corrections, both via the diagrammatic implementation of the Kubo formula and via the quantum kinetic theory. We show that vertex corrections are crucial to capture the details of the inverse spin galvanic effect in contrast to previous treatments based on the constant broadening approximation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05799v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Veneri, Francesco Quintavalle, Thierry Valet, Roberto Raimondi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncovering surface states of the Dirac semimetal BaMg2Bi2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05886</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05886v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: BaMg2Bi2 is a Dirac semimetal characterized by a simple Dirac cone crossing the Fermi level at the center of the Brillouin zone, protected by C3 rotational symmetry. Together with its Sr-based analogue SrMg2Bi2, it has been proposed as a promising candidate for a chemically driven topological switch: while SrMg2Bi2 is an insulator, BaMg2Bi2 exhibits non-trivial topological features. A detailed understanding of its electronic structure is essential to elucidate its electronic and transport properties. Previous photoemission studies confirmed the Dirac nature of BaMg2Bi2, but were limited to high photon energies, which hindered direct comparison with density functional theory calculations (DFT), due to reduced resolution and higher-frequency matrix-element modulation in that regime. In this work, we combine high-resolution angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) and DFT calculations to get full insight on the valence band states, providing a comprehensive picture of the low-energy electronic structure. Our measurements reveal the presence of previously unobserved surface states. We found that they are topologically trivial, but they unlock a more comprehensive understanding of the material's behavior, reconciling previous discrepancies between experiment and theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05886v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. De Vita, J. Bakkelund, H. \'Swi\k{a}tek, M. J. Winiarski, S. Malick, C. V. B. Nielsen, F. Bertran, A. J. H. Jones, P. Majchrzak, F. Miletto Granozio, J. A. Miwa, R. Ernstorfer, T. Pincelli, T. Klimczuk, C. Bigi, F. Mazzola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay of Rashba and Dresselhaus Spin-Orbit Couplings on the Stability of Topological FFLO Phases in 1D Fermi Gases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05901</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05901v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the stabilization of topological Fulde-Ferrell-Larkin-Ovchinnikov (FFLO) phases, with a specific emphasis on the intraband FFLO phase, in a one-dimensional (1D) Fermi gas subjected to an external magnetic field. This research highlights the crucial role of the interplay between Rashba spin-orbit coupling (RSOC) and Dresselhaus spin-orbit coupling (DSOC). Employing a Fermi-Hubbard model alongside the density matrix renormalization group (DMRG) method, we examine the combined effects of RSOC and DSOC on these exotic superfluid phases, taking into account attractive fermionic interactions. Our principal finding reveals that while RSOC primarily stabilizes conventional zero-momentum pairing, DSOC performs a distinct and crucial role in selectively stabilizing the intraband FFLO phase. This stabilization is achieved by enhancing spin polarization within a single helicity band and suppressing interband coherence, thereby facilitating the formation of finite-momentum FFLO pairs within the same band and resulting in the emergence of a topologically nontrivial superfluid. This targeted control of intraband FFLO pairing paves the way for new strategies in the manipulation of superfluid phases in spin-orbit coupled systems and offers essential insights for experimental realizations in ultracold atomic gases, with implications for topological quantum computing and Majorana fermions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05901v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hamid Mosadeq, Mohammad-Hossein Zare, Reza Asgari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimal two band model and experimental proposals to distinguish pairing mechanisms of the high-T$_c$ superconductor La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05956</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05956v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The discovery of high-T$_c$ superconductivity in La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ has opened the door to a new route to high temperature superconductivity, distinct from that in cuprates and iron-based materials. Yet, despite intense recent activity, we lack experimentally testable protocols for distinguishing between different pairing scenarios. In this Letter, we construct a minimal two-band model that reproduces the Fermi-surface topology observed in recent ARPES measurements and DFT calculations, and we analyze superconductivity arising from two distinct pairing mechanisms. We show that these mechanisms yield sharply different responses to an applied perpendicular electric field. Thus, La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ offers the unique opportunity to cleanly distinguish between different pairing scenarios. Finally, we propose three concrete experimental proposals designed to distinguish these scenarios and thereby identify the pairing mechanism most relevant to the real material.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05956v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zheng-Duo Fan, Ashvin Vishwanath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase transitions on the dark side of the Gross-Neveu model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04626</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04626v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Gross-Neveu model in 2+1 dimensions exhibits a continuous transition from gapless Dirac semimetal to the gapped quantum anomalous Hall (QAH) insulator at a finite (attractive) coupling, at which the inversion and time-reversal symmetry become spontaneously broken, and the flavor O($M$) symmetry remains preserved. A unification of leading order parameters of 2+1 dimensional $N$ four-component Dirac fermions collects all Lorentz-singlet mass-like fermion bilinears, except the one condensing in the QAH state, into an irreducible representation of the O($M=4N$), and predicts another phase transition in the Gross-Neveu model to occur at a strong (repulsive) coupling. Here, a fermionic auxiliary-field quantum Monte Carlo algorithm is employed in order to study a lattice realization of the Gross-Neveu field theory in the repulsive regime, where the sign problem is absent. We indeed find the O($4N$) symmetry breaking transition out of Dirac semimetal to occur and to be weakly first-order for $N=2$, relevant to graphene. The size of the discontinuity and the magnitude of the critical coupling, however, both grow with $N$. Adding a finite chemical potential is found to break the symmetry and cause superconductivity. These results are in broad agreement with the predictions of the unified field theory. Our lattice model also displays an interesting exact O($2N$) symmetry, a subgroup of the low-energy O($4N$), and has the ordered ground state with the order parameter that belongs to its $N(2N-1)$-dimensional representation. Other order parameters are also examined, and a certain hierarchy among those that belong to different representations of the exact $O(2N)$ is observed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04626v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel Osiander Rein, Fakher F. Assaad, Igor F. Herbut</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Instantaneous response and quantum geometry of insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07052</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07052v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the time-dependent Quantum Geometric Tensor (tQGT) as a comprehensive tool for capturing the geometric character of insulators observable within linear response. We show that tQGT describes the zero-point motion of bound electrons and acts as a generating function for generalized sum rules of electronic conductivity. It therefore enables a systematic framework for computing the instantaneous response of insulators, including optical mass, orbital angular momentum, and dielectric constant. This construction guarantees a consistent approximation across these quantities upon restricting the number of occupied and unoccupied states in a low-energy description of an infinite quantum system. We outline how quantum geometry can be generated in periodic systems by lattice interference and examine spectral weight transfer from small frequencies to high frequencies by creating geometrically frustrated flat bands.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07052v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1073/pnas.2405837122</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Nishchhal Verma, Raquel Queiroz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electrically Tunable Spin Exchange Splitting in Graphene Hybrid Heterostructure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08908v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Graphene, with spin and valley degrees of freedom, fosters unexpected physical and chemical properties for the realization of next-generation quantum devices. However, the spin symmetry of graphene is rather robustly protected, hampering manipulation of the spin degrees of freedom for the application of spintronic devices such as electric gate tunable spin filters. We demonstrate that a hybrid heterostructure composed of graphene and LaCoO3 epitaxial thin film exhibits an electrically tunable spin exchange splitting. The large and adjustable spin exchange splitting of 155.9 - 306.5 meV was obtained by the characteristic shifts in both the spin symmetry broken quantum Hall states and the Shubnikov-de-Haas oscillations. Strong hybridization induced charge transfer across the hybrid heterointerface has been identified for the observed spin exchange splitting. The substantial and facile controllability of the spin exchange splitting provides an opportunity for spintronics applications with the electrically-tunable spin polarization in hybrid heterostructures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08908v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/adfm.202311287</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Adv. Funct. Mater. 34, 2311287 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Dongwon Shin, Hyeonbeom Kim, Sung Ju Hong, Sehwan Song, Yeongju Choi, Youngkuk Kim, Sungkyun Park, Dongseok Suh, Woo Seok Choi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Family of multilayer graphene superconductors with tunable chirality: Momentum-space vortices nucleated by a ring of Berry curvature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21616</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21616v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent experiments in rhombohedrally-stacked multilayer graphene heterostructures have reported signatures of chiral superconductivity, emerging from a spin and valley-polarized normal state with broken time-reversal symmetry and an associated anomalous Hall effect. These findings bring into focus the role of the electronic Bloch wavefunction and the quantum geometric tensor in determining the superconducting pairing channel. In this work, we examine superconducting instabilities of a model of $N$-layer rhombohedral graphene that possesses an enhanced Berry curvature distribution on an extended ring in momentum space $-$ that we dub the 'Berry ring of fire' $-$ in the presence of an isotropic attractive interaction with a parametrically controlled spatial range. We determine that local interactions favor a $N$-fold winding in the order parameter phase for odd-$N$ layered systems, with even-$N$ layers requiring a spatially extended attraction range to achieve pairing. For generic interaction lengths, we discover a family of chiral superconductors and, remarkably, momentum-space vortices nucleated on the Berry ring of fire. The existence of these vortices can be traced to a momentum-space flux quantization condition involving the Berry curvature, with the phase winding dictated by a combination of the Berry flux and a 'statistical flux' to enforce Fermi-Dirac statistics. Such an order parameter structure allows for the possibility of in-situ tuning between various chiral superconducting phases through changes in the electron density or the displacement field. We discuss ways in which these predictions can be experimentally tested and potentially exploited in future devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21616v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/pgqh-wm5v</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 214505 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Adarsh S. Patri, Marcel Franz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Short-wavelength mesophases in the ground states of core-softened particles in two-dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07240</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07240v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We describe the formation of short-wavelength mesophases in a two-dimensional core-softened particle system. By proposing a series of specific ansatz for each relevant phase, we performed a variational analysis to obtain the ground-state phase diagram. Our results reveal a variety of cluster lattice phases with distinct cluster orientations, alongside traditional two-dimensional Bravais lattices such as square, triangular, oblique, and rectangular structures, as well as other non-Bravais arrangements including honeycomb and kagome phases. We characterize in detail the ground-state phase transitions and identify coexistence regions between competing phases, capturing both first-order and continuous transitions. In addition, we highlight the crucial role of the competing length scales introduced by the hard-core repulsion in shaping the rich landscape of mesophases, emphasizing the interplay between intra-cluster structure and inter-cluster organization. Finally, our analytical results are confronted with extensive molecular dynamics simulations, which interestingly show the existence of decagonal and dodecagonal quasicrystalline phases in regions of the phase diagram that exhibit a high degree of frustration. This study provides a systematic framework that could support future investigations of classical thermal melting behavior or quantum phase transitions in similar cluster-forming systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07240v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R\^omulo Cenci, Lucas Nicolao, Alejandro Mendoza-Coto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large anisotropic magnetoresistance in $\alpha$-MnTe induced by strain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.16738v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: $\alpha\textrm{-MnTe}$ is a p-type semiconducting altermagnet with a N\'eel temperature near $300\thinspace\textrm{K}$. Due to the altermagnetic nature, $\mathcal{PT}$ symmetry is broken, and Kramers degeneracy is lifted in the valence band maxima along the $\Gamma\textrm{-K}$ line and the A point. However, the energy difference is found to be small, and any small shift in the spectrum can dramatically change the linear-response transport properties. Here we show that a strain modulating the [0001] axis of the unit cell by $\sim\pm0.5\%$ can significantly change the transport signature by switching the thermal window between the two regions of the valence band. When the $\Gamma\textrm{-K}$ line is dominating, the planar Hall effect and the anisotropic magnetoresistance can be enhanced by an order of magnitude, with the maximum up to $\sim70\%$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.16738v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bao-Feng Chen, Jie-Xiang Yu, Gen Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytical approach to the magneto-fluorescence of triplet excitons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.03261v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The fluorescence of triplet excitons and color-centers is strongly dependent on magnetic field that mixes the zero field spin eigenstates that determine the radiative recombination rates back into the singlet ground state through spin-orbit coupling. For films of molecules, and polycrystalline color-centers samples an average over molecular orientations has to be performed to model the magneto-fluorescence lineshapes. This limits our analytical understanding of the lineshapes and complicates the analysis of the fluorescence dependence on magnetic field. Here, we present a framework that allows to average over triplet molecular orientations analytically. Our approach provides very accurate numerical routines computing precisely the averages matrix elements that appear in magneto-fluorescence and semi-analytical approximations that can be used to model experimental traces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.03261v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan Sun, A. D. Chepelianskii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Axionic tunneling from a topological Kondo insulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05057</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05057v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Discoveries over the past two decades have revealed the remarkable ability of quantum materials to emulate relativistic properties of the vacuum, from Dirac cones in graphene to the Weyl surface states of topological insulators. Yet the most elusive consequence of topology in quantum matter is the axionic $E\cdot B$ term in the electromagnetic response. Here we report a direct signature of axionic physics obtained through scanning tunneling microscopy (STM). Although recent STM experiments using SmB$_6$ nanowires have been interpreted as evidence for spin-polarized currents arising from topological surface states, we show that the observed spin polarization instead originates from axionic electrodynamics. Our analysis reveals a striking voltage-induced magnetization: extremely small voltages ($\sim$ 30 meV) generate tip moments of order 0.1 $\mu_B$ that reverse sign with the applied bias. The magnitude, tunability, and reversibility of this signal are consistent with an axionic $E \cdot B$ coupling, and fully account for the magnetic component of the tip density of states, ruling out static magnetism. Millivolt-scale control of spin polarization in a tunnel junction provides a new route for probing axionic electrodynamics and opens avenues for future STM and spintronics applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05057v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saikat Banerjee, Anuva Aishwarya, Fei Liu, Lin Jiao, Vidya Madhavan, Eugene J. Mele, Piers Coleman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
