<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 04:00:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Strain-tunability of the multipolar Berry curvature in altermagnet MnTe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21481</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21481v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The anomalous Hall effect describes the generation of a transverse voltage by a longitudinal current even in the absence of an external magnetic field. While typically observed in ferromagnets, it has also been predicted to arise in altermagnets, materials characterized by rotational symmetries that enable broken time reversal symmetry despite compensated collinear magnetic ordering. These symmetries enforce band (anti)crossings that can generate significant contributions to the Berry curvature that drives the anomalous Hall effect. This Berry curvature is predicted to exhibit a characteristic multipolar order, resulting in a symmetry-enforced distribution at or near net compensation which is highly sensitive to perturbations that distort this balance. However, exploring the predicted multipolar Berry curvature of altermagnets and its reversible manipulation remains challenging. Here, we demonstrate evidence for the multipolar nature of the altermagnetic Berry curvature in MnTe by tuning the anomalous Hall effect via uniaxial stress. Upon straining, the magnitude of the anomalous Hall conductivity changes and, at a critical strain of 0.14%, the sign is reversed. Symmetry analysis and density functional theory calculations reveal that this tunability is a direct consequence of the altermagnetic multipolar Berry curvature. Our results provide insight into the role of crystal and magnetic symmetries in the realization of higher-order Berry curvature distributions and their unique tunability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21481v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shane Smolenski, Ning Mao, Dechen Zhang, Yucheng Guo, A. K. M. Ashiquzzaman Shawon, Mingyu Xu, Eoghan Downey, Trisha Musall, Ming Yi, Weiwei Xie, Chris Jozwiak, Aaron Bostwick, Nobumichi Tamura, Eli Rotenberg, Lu Li, Kai Sun, Yang Zhang, Na Hyun Jo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anisotropy of the chiral, semiconducting phase LaRhC$_{2}$: a handedness resolved study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21510</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21510v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Chirality in quantum materials is a topic of significant importance due to its profound effects on the electronic, magnetic, and optical properties of these systems. However, it is non-trivial to decouple the behavior of two enantiomorphs within the same material -- perhaps explaining why the influence of chirality on electrical properties has remained largely unexplored. In this work, we examine the electrical conductivity, magnetoresistance, and thermal expansion coefficient of LaRhC$_{2}$ -- a compound with a chiral crystal structure (tetragonal symmetry, space groups $\textit{P}$4$_{1}$ or $\textit{P}$4$_{3}$). The identification of a suitable monochiral domain was achieved via electron backscatter diffraction, which simultaneously determines crystallographic orientation and handedness. Both enantiomorphs are confirmed by single-crystal X-ray diffraction on monochiral specimens. The analysis of electrical resistivity was made possible through the single-domain extraction of enantiopure specimens from a polycrystalline sample using focused ion beam techniques. We establish that LaRhC$_{2}$ is a semiconductor with band gaps of approximately 20 meV and 33 meV parallel and perpendicular to the fourfold screw axis of the crystal structure, respectively -- consistent with band structure calculations. A significant anisotropy is also observed in the thermal expansion, electrical resistivity as well as angular-dependent magnetoresistance parallel and perpendicular o [001] crystallographic directions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21510v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Volodymyr Levytskyi, Ulrich Burkhardt, Markus K\"onig, Christoph Hennig, Eteri Svanidze, Yuri Grin, Roman Gumeniuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-accuracy low-noise electrical measurements in a closed-cycle pulse-tube cryostat</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21525</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21525v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A shift of paradigm to obtain (sub-)Kelvin environment is currently on-going with the democratization of cryogen-free cryocoolers, boosted by their easy-to-use and continuous operation without the need of liquid helium whose cost and scarcity globally increase. Thanks to their large sample space and cooling power, they can host a superconducting magnet and are an adapted platform for quantum technologies, material science, low temperature detectors and even medical fields. The drawback is that this type of system is inherently based on gas compression that induces a certain level of vibrations and electromagnetic perturbations, which can potentially prevent the determination of low amplitude signals or spoil their stability. In this paper we demonstrate that pulse-tube based cryocoolers can be used for electrical precision measurements, using a commercial cryomagnetic system combined with our home-made a coaxial cryoprobe. In particular, parts-per-billion level of measurement uncertainties in resistance determination, based on quantum Hall resistance standards, is achievable at the level of state-of-the-art measurements involving conventional cryostats based on liquid helium. We performed an extensive characterization of the cryomagnetic system to determine the level of vibrations and electromagnetic perturbations, and revealed that although the magnetic field has a drastic effect on the noise level, only marginal interplays on the measurement are observed as long as the working frequencies of the instrumentation are not in the vicinity of the ones of the perturbations. The set of characterization measurements presented here are easily implementable in laboratories, which can help to determine the vibrations and electromagnetic pollution generated by any cryocooler.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21525v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mathieu Taupin, Kamel Dougdag, Djamel Ziane, Francois Couedo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real Space Imaging of Spin Scattering in Chirality-Induced Spin Selectivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21558v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The interaction between electron spin and molecular chirality plays a fundamental role in quantum phenomena, with significant implications for spintronics and quantum computing. The chirality-induced spin selectivity (CISS) effect, where chiral materials preferentially transmit electrons of a particular spin, has sparked intense interest and debate regarding its underlying mechanism. Despite extensive research, the spatial distribution of spin polarization in chiral systems, the key evidence to reveal the spin scattering mechanism in CISS, has remained experimentally elusive particularly due to complications arising from spin-orbit coupling in metal electrodes typically used in such studies. Here we show, through reflective magnetic circular dichroism measurements on chiral tellurium nanowires with graphene electrodes, that current-induced spin polarization exhibits identical signs in both the nanowire and electrodes, distinct from the presumed spin filter scenario. The observed spin polarization scales linearly with current amplitude, aligns parallel to the current direction, reverses with chirality or current flow, and demonstrates spin relaxation lengths of several micrometers into graphene. Our findings provide the first direct visualization of spatial spin distribution in chiral devices. This work establishes a new paradigm for investigating spin-dependent phenomena in chiral materials and opens avenues for developing chirality-based spintronic and quantum devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21558v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jaehyun Lee, Sang-hyuk Lee, Uiseok Jeong, Daryll J. C. Dalayoan, Soobeom Shin, Hu Young Jeong, Hosub Jin, Binghai Yan, Noejung Park, Seon Namgung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pathways from a chiral superconductor to a composite Fermi liquid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21591</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21591v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent experiments have reported chiral time-reversal broken superconductivity in $n$-layer rhombohedral graphene for $n = 4,5, 6$. Introducing a moir\'e potential by alignement with a hexagonal boron nitride substrate suppresses the superconductivity but leads instead to various fractional quantum anomalous Hall phenomena. Motivated by these observations, we consider the fate of the phase transition between (a chiral) Landau Fermi liquid (LFL) metal and a Composite Fermi Liquid (CFL) metal in the presence of attractive interactions. These are parent states, respectively, for the superconductor and the fractional quantum Hall states. For weak attractive interactions, the LFL is usually unstable to superconductivity while the CFL is stable. This raises the possibility of a direct continuous phase transition between the chiral superconductor and the CFL. However, we show that generically the LFL close to the transition to the CFL is stable against superconductivity. Thus the evolution between the CFL and chiral superconductor goes through an intermediate stable LFL phase for weak attractive interactions. With stronger interactions, the evolution can instead go through a non-Abelian paired quantum Hall state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21591v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunchao Zhang, Leyna Shackleton, T. Senthil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strain-Induced Antiferromagnetic-to-Altermagnetic Phase Transition and Topology in $(\mathrm{CrO}_2)_1/(\mathrm{TaO}_2)_2$ Superlattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21741</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21741v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Topological aspects in altermagnets have come into focus recently, and tuning the antiferromagnetic (AFM) state into an altermagnetic phase remains an active frontier. We realize both within a rutile superlattice here in this paper. With first principles calculation, we show that a uniaxial strain of only 0.5$\%$ along the c axis converts the $(\mathrm{CrO}_2)_1/(\mathrm{TaO}_2)_2$ rutile superlattice from a trivial antiferromagnet into an altermagnet with topology accompanied by a weak SOC. The strain opens a spin-dependent band splitting of $\sim 1.1 eV$ and, despite the weak SOC together with in-plane magnetic moment orientation, generates an intrinsic anomalous Hall conductivity of order $10^3 S/cm$, comparable magnitude to that in ferromagnetic Weyl semimetals. Tiny SOC here with in-plane \(\text{N\'eel}\) orientation gaps out the Weyl nodal rings, giving rise to 16 Weyl points in the superlattice. Thus, we point out a simple route toward strain and field tunable, low-dissipation altermagnetic electronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21741v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wanfei Shan, Qun Yang, Prineha Narang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hexagonal boron nitride/bilayer graphene moir\'e superlattices in the Dirac-material family: energy-band engineering and carrier doping by dual gating</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21759v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We review the fabrication and transport characterization of hexagonal boron nitride (hBN)/Bernal bilayer graphene (BLG) moir\'e superlattices. Due to the moir\'e effect, the hBN/BLG moir\'e superlattices exhibit an energy gap at the charge neutrality point (CNP) even in the absence of a perpendicular electric field. In BLG, the application of a perpendicular electric field tunes the energy gap at the CNP, which contrasts with single-layer graphene and is similar to the family of rhombohedral multilayer graphene. The hBN/BLG moir\'e superlattice is associated with non-trivial energy-band topology and a narrow energy band featuring a van Hove singularity. By employing a dual-gated device structure where both the perpendicular displacement field and the carrier density are individually controllable, systematic engineering of the energy-band structure can be achieved. The data presented here demonstrate the universality and diversity in the physics of hBN/BLG moir\'e superlattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21759v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-648X/ae05a5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys.: Condens. Matter 37 393001 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Takuya Iwasaki, Yoshifumi Morita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-energy photoexcitation inside the Mott gap in doped Hubbard and t-J ladders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21813</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21813v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate changes in the optical conductivity of doped Mott insulators by tuning ultrashort pump pulses to target either the Drude or low-energy absorption regions. Using a hole-doped two-leg Hubbard ladder and a four-leg t-J ladders, we calculate the optical conductivity after pump by employing the time-dependent density matrix renormalization group. We find that a monocycle electric field pulse tuned to the Drude absorption reduces the Drude weight, accompanied by a slight enhancement in the mid-infrared (mid-IR) spectral weight. However, this enhancement diminishes as the pulse intensity increases. In contrast, a pump pulse tuned to the mid-IR absorption only affects the Drude weight. This behavior arises because the mid-IR absorption originates from magnetic excitations that do not couple directly to photons. These predictions can be tested experimentally by applying ultrashort low-energy pump pulses to cuprate materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21813v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sumal Chandra, Kazuya Shinjo, Shigetoshi Sota, Seiji Yunoki, Takami Tohyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ab initio study of magnetoresistance effect in $\mathrm{Mn_{3}Sn}/\mathrm{MgO}/\mathrm{Mn_{3}Sn}$ antiferromagnetic tunnel junction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21877</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21877v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The antiferromagnets with the time-reversal symmetry broken magnetic structures possess a finite spin splitting in the momentum space, and may contribute to a realization of a finite tunnel magnetoresistance (TMR) effect even with magnets with zero net spin polarization. In this paper, we study the TMR effect with the noncollinear antiferromagnet $\mathrm{Mn_{3}Sn}$ whose inverse $120^{\circ}$ antiferromagnetic order breaks the time-reversal symmetry. In particular, we employ the representative barrier material $\mathrm{MgO}$ as the tunnel insulator, and calculate the TMR effect in the $\mathrm{Mn_{3}Sn}(01\bar{1}0)/\mathrm{MgO}(110)/\mathrm{Mn_{3}Sn}$ magnetic tunnel junctions (MTJs), which has an optimal geometry for the spin-orbit torque switching of the magnetic configurations. We show that a finite TMR ratio reaching $\gtrsim 1000\%$ appears in the $\mathrm{Mn_{3}Sn}/\mathrm{MgO}/\mathrm{Mn_{3}Sn}$ MTJs, which is due to the spin splitting properties of $\mathrm{Mn_{3}Sn}$ in the momentum space combined with the screening effect of $\mathrm{MgO}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21877v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katsuhiro Tanaka, Yuta Toga, Susumu Minami, Satoru Nakatsuji, Takuya Nomoto, Takashi Koretsune, Ryotaro Arita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Seamless: Unexpected Defective Merging in Single-Orientation Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21908v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Single-orientation stitching of graphene has emerged as the predominant method for growth of large-area, high-quality graphene films. Particularly noteworthy is graphene grown on single-crystalline Cu(111)/sapphire substrates, which exhibits exceptionally planar oriented stitching due to the atomically smooth substrate, facilitating the formation of continuous, high-quality graphene monolayer. These single-orientation stitches have conventionally been regarded as seamless with negligible defect concentrations. In this report, we present experimental observations regarding graphene grown on single-crystalline Cu(111)/sapphire substrates. Among the graphene flakes with single-orientation, our findings reveal two major merging behaviors: one producing the expected seamless stitching, and another unexpectedly generating structural defects that create nanoscale pathways permitting water permeation. Notably, we identify a unique merging structure--overlapped junction, in which the edge of one graphene flake overlaps and lies atop the edge of another flake, rather than forming a continuous atomic stitch. This discovery challenges the conventional anticipation of single-orientation stitched graphene films as seamless single crystalline film, while offers unique perspective for graphene applications in molecular sieving, selective filtration membranes, and protective coatings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21908v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhien Wang, Jiangtao Wang, Diego Exposito, Andrey Krayev, Shih-Ming He, Xudong Zheng, Zachariah Hennighausen, Ivan Brihuega, Se-Young Jeong, Jing Kong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Challenges and opportunities in proximity-driven exciton-spin engineering in van der Waals heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21956</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21956v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: van der Waals heterostructures consisting of transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) and two-dimensional (2D) magnets offer a versatile platform to study the coexistence and transformation of different excitons. By focusing on TMD WSe$_2$ and 2D magnetic CrI$_3$, as a bilayer WSe$_2$/CrI$_3$ and a trilayer CrI$_3$/WSe$_2$/CrI$_3$, we provide their description using a parameter-free, high-fidelity many-body perturbation theory. This ab initio approach allows us to elucidate the character of magnetic Frenkel excitons in CrI3 and how the nonmagnetic Wannier-Mott excitons in WSe2 are modified by the proximity of CrI3. We reveal novel proximity-induced interlayer excitons in these heterostructures. In contrast to the sensitivity of proximity-induced modifications of excitons in WSe$_2$, which depend on the interfacial details, the interlayer magnetic excitons are remarkably robust and are present across the different stacking configurations between WSe$_2$ and CrI$_3$, simplifying their experimental demonstration. These findings suggest unexplored opportunities for information transduction using magnetic excitons and integrating photonics, electronics, and spintronics in proximitized materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21956v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mushir Thodika, Dimitar Pashov, Igor Zutic, Mark van Schilfgaarde, Swagata Acharya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electric-field effect on spin diffusion length in solids: An \textit{ab initio} study beyond the drift-diffusion model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21962v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently, we developed an \textit{ab initio} approach of spin diffusion length (l_{s}) in solids [Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 046705 (2025)], based on a linearized density-matrix master equation with quantum treatment of electron scattering processes. In this work, we extend the method to include the drift term due to an electric field along a periodic direction, implemented efficiently using a Wannier-representation-based covariant derivative. We employ this approach to investigate the electric-field effect on l_{s} of monolayer WSe_{2}, bulk GaAs, bulk GaN, and graphene-h-BN heterostructure. Our results show that l_{s} can be significantly enhanced or suppressed by a moderate downstream or upstream field respectively. Although the widely-used drift-diffusion model performs well for WSe_{2} and GaAs, it can introduce large errors of the electric-field-induced changes of l_{s} in both GaN and graphene-h-BN. Thus, to accurately capture the influence of electric fields on l_{s} in realistic materials, it is necessary to go beyond the drift-diffusion model and adopt a microscopic \textit{ab initio} methodology. Moreover, in graphene-h-BN, we find that the field-induced change of l_{s} is not only governed by the drift term in the master equation, but is also significantly affected by the electric-field modification of the equilibrium density matrix away from Fermi-Dirac distribution function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21962v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junqing Xu, Weiwei Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predictor-corrector method based on dynamic mode decomposition for tensor-train nonequilibrium Green's function calculations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22177</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22177v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The nonequilibrium Green's function (NEGF) formalism is a powerful tool to study the nonequilibrium dynamics of correlated lattice systems, but its applicability to realistic system sizes and long timescales is limited by unfavorable memory scaling. While compressed representations, such as the recently introduced quantics tensor train (QTT) format, alleviate the memory bottleneck, the efficiency of QTT-NEGF calculations is hindered by poor initializations and slow or unstable convergence of globally updated self-consistent iterations. Here, we introduce a predictor-corrector solver for QTT-NEGF simulations that combines dynamic mode decomposition (DMD) extrapolation with the recently proposed causality-preserving block-time-stepping updates. The DMD predictor supplies accurate initial guesses that reduce the iteration count of the calculation, while the block-time-stepping correction ensures stable convergence even for long propagation intervals. Applying this method to the Hubbard model on a $32\times 32$ lattice within the nonequilibrium $GW$ approximation, we demonstrate stable propagation up to times of $t_\mathrm{max}=512$ inverse hoppings, surpassing the capabilities of both matrix-based implementations and previous QTT solvers. Our contribution is twofold. (i) We integrate tensor dynamic mode decomposition with the QTT representation, which establishes a general framework that is not limited to NEGFs. (ii) We demonstrate its practical benefits in NEGF simulations, where it enables stable and efficient access to unprecedented timescales at high momentum resolution, thereby advancing controlled studies of long-time dynamics and nonequilibrium steady states in correlated lattice systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22177v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maksymilian \'Sroda, Ken Inayoshi, Michael Sch\"uler, Hiroshi Shinaoka, Philipp Werner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Features of the Electronic and Charge States of Monovalent-Doped Manganite Films Probed by Magnetic Circular Dichroism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22231</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22231v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic circular dichroism (MCD) spectroscopy in the range of 1.2 - 3.7 eV was studied for La1-xKxMnO3 (x = 0.05 - 0.18) epitaxial films over a wide temperature range. The thin films were grown using a two-step procedure: deposition of LaxMnO3-{\delta} and potassium K+ incorporation into the films via isopiestic annealing. The temperature behavior of the MCD effect in different spectral regions was analyzed alongside the temperature dependences of magnetization, resistivity, and magnetoresistance of the films. It was found that the MCD signal is sensitive not only to the magnetic but also to the charge sublattice of the material. Accordingly, a correlation between the magneto-optical and magnetoresistive responses of the system was identified. These findings underscore the high information content of MCD spectroscopy for investigating the magnetic and magnetotransport properties of strongly correlated magnetic oxides. The ground and excited electronic states in the La1-xKxMnO3 films were identified, and the obtained data were compared with magneto-optical data for divalent - doped and lanthanum-deficient manganite films. Good agreement was observed, indicating the universality of the electronic structure and the shared mechanisms underlying the observed effects in such materials. These results broaden the understanding of the band structure in manganites and provide a solid foundation for its theoretical description.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22231v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jallcom.2025.181990</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Alloys and Compounds Volume 1036, 20 July 2025, 181990</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yulia E. Samoshkina, Dmitriy A. Petrov, Dmitry S. Neznakhin, Igor E. Korsakov, Andrei V. Telegin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuum theory for topological phase transitions in exciton systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22274</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22274v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An effective continuum theory is constructed for the topological phase transition of excitons in quasi-two-dimensional systems. These topological excitons crucially determine the optoelectronic properties, because of their larger binding energies in 2D as well as their topologically enhanced exciton transport. The core idea of this letter is, that the essential physics determining the topological invariants across the phase transition is localized near $N$-fold band-crossing points (BCPs) in the interaction-induced exciton band structure. The construction of the continuum theory around these BCPs needs only the information of exciton states that build up these BCPs at both $\mathbf{Q}=0$ and finite $\mathbf{Q}$ points, and not the numerically challenging solution of the Bethe-Salpeter equation over the full exciton Brillouin zone. This theory applies to systems with and without spin conservation. Our theory is illustrated in two specific examples: the transition metal dichalcogenide twisted bilayer systems and the Bernevig-Hughes-Zhang (BHZ) model. These results offer a promising route toward studying complex systems, such as the room-temperature quantum spin Hall system Bismuthene (Bi/SiC) and other twisted bilayer systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22274v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaochan Cai, Armando Consiglio, Domenico Di Sante, Ronny Thomale, Werner Hanke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-organization mechanism in Bridgman-grown MnBi2Te4/(Bi2Te3)n: influence on layer sequence and magnetic properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22303</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22303v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The growth of high-quality magnetic topological insulator crystals by the Bridgman method remains challenging due to thermodynamic limitations inherent to this technique. Nevertheless, this approach continues to provide bulk materials with significantly reduced free carrier concentrations compared to epitaxial methods. Here, we investigate the Inverted Vertical Bridgman growth of MnBi2Te4/(Bi2Te3)n crystals, with particular emphasis on the structural ordering of MnBi2Te4 septuple layers within the Bi2Te3 quintuple-layer matrix and its influence on magnetic properties. Through a detailed analysis of growth dynamics, we identify four distinct stages, including a turbulent flow regime promoting pure MnBi2Te4 phase, rapid MnTe precipitation reducing Mn content in the melt, a stationary growth phase supporting ordered stacking of septuple and quintuple layers, and a final stage marked by flow cessation and defect formation. We demonstrate that septuple layer spacing is inversely correlated with MnTe supersaturation due to the diffusion-limited incorporation in stationary growth phase. Magnetic characterization reveals antiferromagnetic ordering in pure MnBi2Te4 phase and in MnBi2Te4/(Bi2Te3)n heterostructure, with ferromagnetism emerging for wider septuple layer spacing. We determine critical temperatures for observed antiferromagnetic and ferromagnetic phase transitions and magnetic anisotropy constants for ferromagnetic samples. Our findings highlight key growth parameters governing magnetic and structural quality, offering a pathway to scalable synthesis of layered topological insulators with tunable magnetic properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22303v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pawe{\l} Skupi\'nski, Kamil Sobczak, Katarzyna Gas, Anna Reszka, Yadhu K. Edathumkandy, Jakub Majewski, Krzysztof Grasza, Maciej Sawicki, Agnieszka Wo{\l}o\'s</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Competing $s$-wave pairing in overdoped $t$-$J$ model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22473</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22473v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The $d$-wave pairing symmetry has long been considered a defining feature of high-temperature superconductivity in cuprates. In this work, we reveal that $s$-wave pairing states exhibit variational energies comparable to the $d$-wave state in a square $t$-$J$ model, particularly at high doping levels ($\delta\gtrsim 15\%$) by using the state-of-the-art tensor network simulation. This surprising result suggests that $s$-wave pairing may play an important role in the cuprate phase diagram, especially for the overdoped region. Our findings provide a potential resolution to discrepancies in recent Josephson tunneling experiments on twisted bilayer cuprates and offer new insights into the evolution of pairing symmetry with doping.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22473v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wayne Zheng, Tao Cheng, Zheng-Yuan Yue, Fu-Chun Zhang, Wei-Qiang Chen, Zheng-Cheng Gu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limitations of detecting structural changes and time-reversal symmetry breaking in scanning tunneling microscopy experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22634v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The family of kagome superconductors $A$V$_3$Sb$_5$ ($A$=K, Cs, Rb) is an exciting playground for investigating various density waves, unusual superconductivity and a surprising time-reversal symmetry breaking despite the absence of spin magnetism. The origin of time-reversal symmetry breaking has been of particular interest, and conflicting results have been intensely debated. Scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) provided crucial evidence by the observation that apparent chirality associated with the 2 $\times$ 2 charge density wave (CDW) may be modified by the direction of magnetic field, a phenomenon observed in select sample areas in some experiments, but not others. Related to this, Xing et al. investigated the effects of magnetic and electric fields on the 2 $\times$ 2 CDW state and the lattice structure of kagome superconductor RbV$_3$Sb$_5$. They report a $\sim$ 1% change in the in-plane lattice constants, concomitant with the CDW intensities modification, controlled by the field direction. This was interpreted as a rare case of piezomagnetism. Here we show how the apparent magnetic field induced lattice and CDW intensity change is a consequence of two independent experimental artifacts: reconfiguration of atoms at the STM tip apex that alter the amplitudes of CDW modulations, and piezo creep, hysteresis, and thermal drift that artificially distort STM topographs. We find no evidence supporting that magnetic field leads to intrinsic changes in the sample, which challenges reported piezomagnetism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22634v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher Candelora, Ilija Zeljkovic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to image single isolated atoms by using coherent low-energy electrons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22586</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22586v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Coherent low-energy electrons have been demonstrated as a practical tool for imaging individual macromolecules and two-dimensional (2D) crystals. Low-energy electrons exhibit unique properties: low radiation damage to biological molecules and high sensitivity to the local potentials. In this study, we outline the conditions at which single isolated charge-free atoms can be imaged by low-energy electron holography. A single atom produces an interference pattern consisting of concentric fringes of finite diameter and of very weak intensity. The diffraction angle theta, determined as the first minimum of the concentric rings interference pattern, exhibits similar dependency on the source-to-sample distance zs as sin(theta) ~ 0.3/sqrt(zs) for electrons of different energies (50, 100 and 200 eV) and scattered off different elements (Li, C, and Cs). The results are compared to the recently reported experimental holograms of alkali atoms intercalated into bilayer graphene and adsorbed on top of graphene.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22586v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1515/mim-2025-0018/html</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Methods in Microscopy, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tatiana Latychevskaia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamic, magnetic and transport properties of the repulsive Hubbard model on the kagome lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.01048</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.01048v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Over the past decades, magnetic frustration has been under intense debate due to its unusual properties. For instance, frustration in the kagome lattice suppresses long range spin correlations and it is expected to be a candidate for a spin liquid system. Therefore, with the advent of experiments with ultra-cold atoms, the interest for frustrated geometries has increased. Given this, in the present work we investigate the repulsive Hubbard model on the kagome lattice by unbiased quantum Monte Carlo simulations. We examine its thermodynamic properties, as well as the magnetic and transport response of the system at finite temperatures and different values of the repulsive interaction. From these results, we discuss the possible occurrence of adiabatic cooling, a quite important feature in ultra-cold systems, and the presence of a metal-to-insulator transition at a finite interaction strength. Our findings may guide future experiments in ultra-cold fermionic atoms on the kagome lattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.01048v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.107.035134</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 107, 035134 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Andressa R. Medeiros-Silva, Natanael C. Costa, Thereza Paiva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry- and energy-resolved entanglement dynamics in a disordered Bose-Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.14825</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.14825v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Using numerical quantum quenches with the integration of both symmetry and energy resolutions, we comprehensively study the dynamics of symmetry-resolved entanglement in a disordered Bose-Hubbard (dBH) model, concentrating on the two types of inhomogeneous initial states to target the lower- and higher-energy sections of its dynamical phase diagram. (i) Motivated by the recent experiment [A. Lukin et al., Science 364, 256 (2019)] which focused on the lower-energy dynamic behaviors of the dBH chain, we first show that, at low energies, for a thermalizing state, although the second law of thermodynamics prohibits the decrease of the total entropy over time, for part of the channel-resolved entropies, a long-term entropic reduction may arise at weak disorder. (ii) A companion channel-resolved analysis at strong disorder further hints that the priorly observed double-log growth of the number entropy might not directly indicate the breakdown of MBL in spin or fermion chains, providing a refreshing perspective on this major controversy in the community. (iii) From time-evolving the line-shape low-energy product state, we subsequently reveal an abrupt formation of a novel "entropy imbalance pattern" across the different symmetry channels. Intriguingly, this imbalance melts in the strong-disorder limit. We conjecture that the melting of the entropic pattern, together with the freezing of a concurrent particle-density wave, embodies a dual trait inherent to MBL. (iv) Specifically, we find a cluster MBL regime, unique to the Bose statistics, emerging from the higher-energy section. This cluster MBL regime realizable even at weak disorder appears not suffer from the finite-size drift and is distinguished by its absence of the hallmark of MBL - the unbounded growth of the entanglement entropy. Our theoretical predictions are by and large testable via the present experimental facilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.14825v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/88sq-cm27</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 094201(2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jie Chen, Chun Chen, Xiaoqun Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-consistent tight-binding calculations with extended Hubbard interactions in rhombohedral multilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00530</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00530v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the mean-field broken symmetry phases of charge neutral multilayer rhombohedral graphene within tight-binding approximations including self-consistent extended Hubbard interactions. We used on-site and inter-site Hubbard interactions obtained from a newly developed first-principles calculation method. Our calculations for systems up to eight layers give rise to electron-hole asymmetries, band flatness, band gaps, and layer anti-ferromagnetic ground states in keeping with available experiments. By including the intersite Hubbard interactions up to the next-nearest neighboring sites, the band gaps are shown to open when the number of layers is larger than three, while the trilayer system maintains its metallic nature with two low energy density of state peaks near the Fermi energy whose separation increases with the range of inter-site Hubbard parameters. Within our framework, the calculated band gaps reflect mean-field ground states with extended Hubbard interactions, in closer agreement with experimental estimates. The tight-binding formulation further enables efficient treatment of large rhombohedral chiral systems, including twisted multilayer graphene.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00530v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongkyu Lee, Wooil Yang, Young-Woo Son, Jeil Jung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nanoscale defects as probes of time reversal symmetry breaking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14648</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14648v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Nanoscale defects such as Nitrogen Vacancy (NV) centers can serve as sensitive and non-invasive probes of electromagnetic fields and fluctuations from materials, which in turn can be used to characterize these systems. Here we specifically discuss how NV centers can probe time-reversal symmetry breaking (TRSB) phenomena in low-dimensional conductors. We argue that the difference in relaxation rates $\Gamma_{\pm \hat{z}}$ of NV centers starting from $m = \pm 1$ spin states to the ground state with $m = 0$ directly probes TRSB. The effect arises from the difference in the fluctuation spectrum of left and right-polarized electromagnetic fields emanating from such materials. In the quantum Hall setting, the NV center experiences (nearly zero) large additional contribution to its relaxation due to the presence of the material when its magnetic dipole (anti-) aligns with the external field. More generally, the difference in the relaxation rates is sensitive to the imaginary part of the wave-vector dependent Hall conductivity. We argue that this can be used to determine the Hall viscosity, which can potentially distinguish candidate fractional quantum Hall states and be used to infer the pairing angular momentum in TRSB superconductors. For the latter, we consider specifically the case of TRSB in stacked twisted Bismuth strontium calcium copper oxide (BSCCO) flakes, which have recently been investigated experimentally and are suggested to exhibit TRSB. We show that the average relaxation rate $\left[\Gamma_{+\hat{z}} + \Gamma_{-\hat{z}}\right]$ near such a system exhibits a Hebel-Slichter like enhancement below $T_c$. The difference $\Gamma_{+\hat{z}} - \Gamma_{-\hat{z}}$ also inherits this peak but is only non-zero for $T &lt; T_c$ and only in a chiral d-wave superconductor. We provide concrete estimates for observing this effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14648v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suman Jyoti De, Tami Pereg-Barnea, Kartiek Agarwal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-dopant origin of competing stripe and pair formation in Hubbard and $t$-$J$ models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.18131v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding the physics of the two-dimensional Hubbard model is widely believed to be a key step in achieving a full understanding of high-$T_\mathrm{c}$ cuprate superconductors. In recent years, progress has been made by large-scale numerical simulations at finite doping and, on the other hand, by microscopic theories able to capture the physics of individual charge carriers. In this work, we study single pairs of dopants in a cylindrical system using the density-matrix renormalization group algorithm. We identify two coexisting charge configurations that couple to the spin environment in different ways: A tightly bound configuration featuring (next-)nearest-neighbor pairs and a stripe-like configuration of dopants on opposite sides of the cylinder, accompanied by a spin domain wall. Thus, we establish that the interplay between stripe order and uniform pairing, central to the models' phases at finite doping, has its origin at the single-pair level. By interpolating between the Hubbard and the related $t$-$J$ model, we are able to quantitatively understand discrepancies in the pairing properties of the two models through the three-site hopping term usually omitted from the $t$-$J$ Hamiltonian. This term is closely related to a next-nearest-neighbor tunneling $t'$, which we observe to upset the balance between the competing stripe and pair states on the two-dopant level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.18131v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/dpfl-12st</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. X 15, 031074 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tizian Blatz, Ulrich Schollw\"ock, Fabian Grusdt, Annabelle Bohrdt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of a non-reciprocal skyrmion Hall effect of hybrid chiral skyrmion tubes in synthetic antiferromagnetic multilayers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19698</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19698v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A hybrid chiral skyrmion tube is a well-known example of a 3D topological spin texture, exhibiting an intriguing chirality transition along the thickness direction. This transition progresses from left-handed to right-handed N\'eel-type chirality, passing through a Bloch-type intermediate state. Such an exotic spin configuration potentially exhibits distinctly different dynamics from that of the common skyrmion tube that exhibits a homogeneous chirality; yet these dynamics have not been ascertained so far. Here we reveal the distinct features of current-induced dynamics that result from the hybrid chiral skyrmion tube structure in synthetic antiferromagnetic (SyAFM) multilayers. Strikingly, the SyAFM hybrid chiral skyrmion tubes exhibit a non-reciprocal skyrmion Hall effect in the flow regime. The non-reciprocity can even be tuned by the degree of magnetic compensation in the SyAFM systems. Our theoretical modeling qualitatively corroborates that the non-reciprocity stems from the dynamic oscillation of skyrmion helicity during its current-induced motion. The findings highlight the critical role of the internal degrees of freedom of these complex skyrmion tubes for their current-induced dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19698v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41467-025-63759-7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature Communications 16, 8285 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Takaaki Dohi, Mona Bhukta, Fabian Kammerbauer, Venkata Krishna Bharadwaj, Ricardo Zarzuela, Aakanksha Sud, Maria-Andromachi Syskaki, Duc Minh Tran, Sebastian Wintz, Markus Weigand, Simone Finizio, J\"org Raabe, Robert Fr\"omter, Jairo Sinova, Mathias Kl\"aui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Peierls substitution for Wannier obstructions: response to disorder and interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09709</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.09709v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the interplay between quantum geometry, interactions, and external fields in complex band systems. When Wannier obstructions preclude a description based solely on atomic-like orbitals, this complicates the prediction of electromagnetic responses particularly in the presence of disorder and interactions. In this work, we introduce a generalized Peierls substitution framework based on Lagrange multipliers to enforce the constraints of the Wannier obstruction in the band of interest. Thus we obtain effective descriptions of interactions and disorder in the presence of non-trivial quantum geometry of that band. We apply our approach to examples including the diamagnetic response in flat-band superconductors and delocalization effects in flat-band metals caused by interactions and disorder.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.09709v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/xkxw-1134</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Shuai A. Chen, Roderich Moessner, Tai Kai Ng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissecting intervalley coupling mechanisms in monolayer transition metal dichalcogenides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.16665v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Monolayer (1L) transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) provide a unique opportunity to control the valley degree of freedom of optically excited charge carriers due to the spin-valley locking effect. Despite extensive studies of the valley-contrasting physics, stimulated by perspective valleytronic applications, a unified picture of competing intervalley coupling processes in 1L-TMDs is lacking. Here, we apply broadband helicity-resolved transient absorption to explore exciton valley polarization dynamics in 1L-WSe${}_2$. By combining experimental results with microscopic simulations, we dissect individual intervalley coupling mechanisms and reveal the crucial role of phonon-assisted scattering in the fast decay of the A exciton circular dichroism and the formation of the dichroism of opposite polarity for the B exciton. We further provide a consistent description of the valley depolarization driven by the combined action of Coulomb scattering processes and indicate the presence of efficient single spin-flip mechanisms. Our study brings us closer to a complete understanding of exciton dynamics in TMDs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.16665v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleg Dogadov, Henry Mittenzwey, Micol Bertolotti, Nicholas Olsen, Thomas Deckert, Chiara Trovatello, Xiaoyang Zhu, Daniele Brida, Giulio Cerullo, Andreas Knorr, Stefano Dal Conte</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supersonic flow and hydraulic jump in an electronic de Laval nozzle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.16321v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In very clean solid-state systems, where carrier-carrier interactions dominate over any other scattering mechanisms, the flow of electrons can be described within a hydrodynamic framework. In these cases, analogues of viscous fluid phenomena have been experimentally observed. However, experimental studies of electron hydrodynamics have so far been limited to the low velocity, linear response regime. At velocities approaching the speed of sound, the electronic fluid is expected to exhibit compressible behaviour where nonlinear effects and discontinuities such as shocks and choked flow have long been predicted. This compressible regime remains unexplored in electronic systems, despite its promise of strongly nonlinear flow phenomena. Here, we demonstrate compressible electron flow in bilayer graphene through an electronic de Laval nozzle, a structure that accelerates charge carriers past the electronic speed of sound, until they slow down suddenly in a shock. Discontinuities in transport measurements and local flattening of potential in Kelvin probe measurements are consistent with a viscous electron shock front and the presence of supersonic electron flow, and are not consistent with Ohmic or ballistic flow. Breaking the sound barrier in electron liquids opens the door for novel, intrinsically nonlinear electronic devices beyond the paradigm of incompressible flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.16321v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johannes Geurs, Tatiana A. Webb, Yinjie Guo, Itai Keren, Jack H. Farrell, Jikai Xu, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Dmitri N. Basov, James Hone, Andrew Lucas, Abhay Pasupathy, Cory R. Dean</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4D-QENS Analysis of Correlated Ionic Conduction in SrCl$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20312</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20312v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Methods of elucidating the mechanisms of fast-ion conduction in solid-state materials are pivotal for advancements in energy technologies such as batteries, fuel cells, sensors, and supercapacitors. In this study, we examine the ionic conduction pathways in single crystal SrCl$_2$, which is a fast-ion conductor above 900~K, using four-dimensional Quasi-Elastic Neutron Scattering (4D-QENS). We explore both coherent and incoherent neutron scattering at temperatures above the transition temperature into the superionic phase to explore the correlated motion of hopping anions. Refinements of the incoherent QENS yield residence times and jump probabilities between lattice sites in good agreement with previous studies, confirming that ionic hopping along nearest-neighbor directions is the most probable conduction pathway. However, the coherent QENS reveals evidence of de Gennes narrowing, indicating the importance of ionic correlations in the conduction mechanism. This highlights the need for improvements both in the theory of ionic transport in fluorite compounds and the modeling of coherent 4D-QENS in single crystals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20312v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jared Coles, Omar Chmaissem, Matthew Krogstad, Daniel M. Pajerowski, Feng Ye, Duck Young Chung, Mercouri G. Kanatzidis, Stephan Rosenkranz, Raymond Osborn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
