<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 01:29:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Nonadiabatic Wave-Packet Dynamics: Nonadiabatic Metric, Quantum Geometry, and Analogue Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00166</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00166v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a unified theory for the nonadiabatic wave-packet dynamics of Bloch electrons subject to slowly varying spatial and temporal perturbations. Extending the conventional wave-packet ansatz to include interband contributions, we derive equations for the interband coefficients using the time-dependent variational principle, referred to as the wave-packet coefficient equation. Solving these equations and integrating out interband contributions yields the leading-order nonadiabatic corrections to the wave-packet Lagrangian. These corrections appear in three forms: (i) a nonadiabatic metric in real and momentum space, which we identify with the energy-gap-renormalized quantum metric, (ii) modified Berry connections associated with the motion of the wave-packet center, and (iii) an energy correction arising from spatial and temporal variations of the Hamiltonian. This metric reformulates the wave-packet dynamics as geodesic motion in phase space, enabling an analogue-gravity perspective in condensed matter systems. As an application, we analyze one-dimensional Dirac electron systems under a slowly varying exchange field $\bm{m}$. Our results demonstrate that variations in the magnitude of $\bm{m}$ are important to nonadiabatic dynamics, in sharp contrast to the adiabatic regime where directional variations of $\bm{m}$ are crucial.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00166v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yafei Ren, M. E. Sanchez Barrero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Mott quantum criticality in a modified periodic Anderson model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00225v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mott quantum criticality is a central theme in correlated electron physics, observed in systems featuring both continuous zero-temperature transitions and those with finite-temperature critical endpoints. Within dynamical mean-field theory (DMFT), the paradigmatic single-band Hubbard model (SBHM) displays such criticality only above a finite-temperature endpoint. In contrast, the modified periodic Anderson model (MPAM) is a rare example known to host a surface of genuinely continuous Mott quantum critical points (QCPs) at zero temperature. Using DMFT with the numerical renormalization group as an impurity solver, we investigate the finite-temperature, real-frequency properties of the MPAM. Our central finding is the emergence of quantum critical scaling in the electrical resistivity, with critical exponents $z_{\text{met}} = 0.76$ and $z_{\text{ins}} = 0.66$ on the metallic and insulating sides, respectively. These values fall within the range reported for the SBHM, suggesting that both transitions are governed by a common universality class. We further substantiate the presence of local quantum criticality by demonstrating robust $\omega/T$ scaling in single- and two-particle correlation functions. Finally, we identify novel transport signatures in the optical conductivity, where the distinct evolution of two isosbestic points serves as a unique fingerprint of the QCP. These results establish the MPAM as a canonical model for investigating genuine Mott quantum criticality and support the existence of a universal framework for this fundamental phenomenon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00225v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sujan K. K., N. S. Vidhyadhiraja</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disorder-Induced Damping of Spin Excitations in Cr-Doped BaFe$_2$As$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00242</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00242v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Partial chemical substitution inevitably introduces disorder. In doped Hund's metals, such as the iron-based superconductors, effects like charge doping and chemical pressure are often considered dominant. Here, we investigate spin excitations in Ba(Fe$_{1-x}$Cr$_x$)$_2$As$_{2}$ (CrBFA) by high-resolution Resonant inelastic X-ray scattering (RIXS) for samples with $x = 0, 0.035,$ and $ 0.085$. In CrBFA, Cr acts as a hole dopant, but also introduces localized spins that compete with Fe-derived magnetic excitations. We found that the Fe-derived magnetic excitations are softened primarily by damping, becoming overdamped for $x = 0.085$. At this doping level, complementary angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy measurements (ARPES) show the absence of electronic structure reconstruction effects such as the nematic band splitting. We propose a localized spin model that explicitly incorporates substitutional disorder and Cr local moments, successfully reproducing our key observations. These results reveal a case where disorder dominates over charge doping in the case of a correlated Hund's metal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00242v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marli R. Cantarino, Rafael M. P. Teixeira, R. Pakuszewski, Wagner R. da Silva Neto, Juliana G. de Abrantes, Mirian Garcia-Fernandez, P. G. Pagliuso, C. Adriano, Claude Monney, Thorsten Schmitt, Eric C. Andrade, Fernando A. Garcia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strange diffusivity of incoherent metal in half-filled two-dimensional Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00281</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00281v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study charge transport across the metal-insulator crossover in the half-filled two-dimensional Hubbard model, with particular emphasis on precision control. The dynamic current-current correlation function is obtained directly in the thermodynamic limit, and the optical conductivity is extracted using numerical analytic continuation. To achieve this, we develop a multiscale approach: the non-perturbative low-frequency behavior is computed using the unbiased diagrammatic Monte Carlo technique, while the high-frequency physics is captured via a self-consistent (semi-)analytic diagrammatic theory. We found that across a broad temperature range where the DC resistivity displays anomalous scaling, $\sim T^\alpha$ with $0&lt;\alpha\lesssim 1$, the Nernst-Einstein relation implies the diffusion constant with the characteristic $\sim 1/\sqrt{T}$ "strange metal" behavior. It was also revealed that the insulating regime is entered through a peculiar non-Fermi liquid state-which we call a Pseudogap Metal-characterized by insulating charge compressibility coexisting with metallic transport. Diagrammatically, the high-temperature incoherent transport is captured by the dressed polarization bubble, whereas near the metal-insulator crossover, the effective interaction vertex between opposite-spin particles is responsible for transferring the Drude weight to a high-frequency continuum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00281v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Youngmin Eom, Igor S. Tupitsyn, Nikolay V. Prokof'ev, Boris Svistunov, Evgeny Kozik, Aaram J. Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Role of lattice structure and breaking of antiferromagnetic spin order in enhancement of ferromagnetic, electronic, and magneto-electric properties in Fe$_{2-x}$Sc$_x$O$_3$ system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00382</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00382v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The strategy of breaking AFM ground state of alpha-Fe2O3 by doping non-magnetic Sc3+ (3d0) ions at the Fe3+ (3d5) sites has been used to understand modified lattice-structure, magnetic spin order, and charge-spin coupling in Fe$_{2-x}$Sc$_x$O$_3$  system ($x =$ 0.2, 0.5, 1.0). The material has been stabilized in single-phased (rhombohedral $\alpha$-Fe$_2$O$_3$) or mix-phased (rhombohedral alpha-Fe$_2$O$_3$ and cubic Sc$_2$O$_3$-types) structures by varying the Sc content and heat treatment temperature. Neutron diffraction confirmed magnetic moment approximately 2.75-4.68 Bohr-magneton per Fe site and spin reorientation from in-plane to out of plane direction below the Morin transition approximately 260 K. The material showed magnetic coercivity (0.2 to 6 kOe). The electrical properties transformed from insulating state (conductivity 10-14-10-10 S/cm and polarization 0.5-2 micro-C/cm$^2$) to high conductive state (conductivity approximately 10-10 -10-7 S/cm and polarization greater than 2 micro-C/cm$^2$) above Morin transition. The material at 300 K produced the maximum current density 20-95 micro-A/cm$^2$, ferroelectric polarization 2.7-15.6 micro-C/cm$^2$, ME voltage up to 5 mV with coupling coefficient 0.53 mV/Oe/cm and huge negative magnetoconductance up to 90%. The results in the present hematite based canted ferromagnetic materials are expected to be useful for applying in low power spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00382v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. N. Bhowmik, Bipin Kumar Parida, Amit Kumar, P. D. Babu, S. M. Yusuf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of nodal-line superconductivity in chiral crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00416</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00416v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Chiral crystals, whose key feature is the structural handedness, host exotic quantum phenomena driven by the interplay of band topology, spin-orbit coupling (SOC), and electronic correlations. Due to the limited availability of suitable chiral-crystal materials, their unconventional superconductivity (SC) remains largely unexplored. Here, we report the discovery of unconventional SC in the La(Rh,Ir)Si family of materials by combining muon-spin spectroscopy, band-structure calculations, and perturbation theory. This family, characterized by a double-helix chiral structure, hosts exotic multifold fermions that are absent in other topological chiral crystals. While LaRhSi behaves as a fully-gapped superconductor, the substitution of 4$d$-Rh by 5$d$-Ir significantly enhances the SOC and leads to the emergence of topological nodal-line SC in LaIrSi. The developed model shows that the nodal-line SC arises from an isotropic SOC with a specific strength. Such an exotic mechanism expands our conventional understanding of material candidates for unconventional SC, which typically rely on a significantly anisotropic SOC to promote the triplet pairing. Our work establishes a new type of phase diagram, which provides a comprehensive roadmap for identifying and engineering unconventional SC in chiral crystals. Furthermore, it calls for renewed investigations of unconventional SC in other widely studied superconductors with a chiral structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00416v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/adma.202511385</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Tian Shang, Jianzhou Zhao, Lun-Hui Hu, Weikang Wu, Keqi Xia, Mukkattu O. Ajeesh, Michael Nicklas, Yang Xu, Qingfeng Zhan, Dariusz J. Gawryluk, Ming Shi, Toni Shiroka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shot noise as a probe for Andreev reflection in graphene-based heterojunctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00486</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00486v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Shot noise emerges due to the discrete nature of charge transport and provides direct access to the underlying microscopic transport mechanisms governing current flow in mesoscopic conductors. In this work, we demonstrate that quantum shot noise offers a direct and robust fingerprint of Andreev reflection, distinguishing between retro and specular processes in graphene-superconductor, graphene-superconductor-graphene, and superconductor-graphene-superconductor junctions. At the graphene-superconductor interface, exact reflection amplitudes obtained from full wavefunction matching within the Bogoliubov-de Gennes formalism capture retro and specular regimes. The associated Fano factor exhibits distinct Fermi-level-dependent signatures, with retro Andreev reflection suppressing and specular Andreev reflection enhancing the shot noise. Extensions to graphene-superconductor-graphene and superconductor-graphene-superconductor configurations reveal how the transmission spectrum and, consequently, the noise profile are modified in the presence of multiple interfaces, coherent quasiparticle interference, and superconducting phase variations. Our findings establish shot noise spectroscopy as a potent and experimentally viable probe for differentiating Andreev reflection types in graphene-based quantum devices, providing complementary insights beyond conventional conductance measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00486v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shahrukh Salim, Poornima Shakya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic dynamics in NiTiO3 honeycomb antiferromagnet using neutron scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00513</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00513v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ilmenite NiTiO3 consists of a buckled honeycomb lattice, with the Ni spins aligned ferromagnetically in-plane and antiferromagnetically out-of-plane. Using neutron spectroscopy, the magnetic structure and the dynamics were investigated as a function of temperature. Dispersive acoustic bands and nearly dispersionless optical bands at ~3.7 meV are described by a highly anisotropy Heisenberg model with stronger antiferromagnetic (AFM) out-of-plane, weaker ferromagnetic (FM) in-plane interactions and an anisotropy gap of 0.95 meV. The order parameter yields a critical exponent between the Heisenberg and two-dimensional Ising models, consistent with highly anisotropic Heisenberg systems. The frustration parameter ~ 2 supports a weakly frustrated system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00513v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Srimal Rathnayaka, Luke Daemen, Tao Hong, Songxue Chi, Stuart Calder, John A. Schneeloch, Yongqiang Cheng, Bing Li, Despina Louca</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theory of Emergent Trionic Order in One-Dimensional Bose-Fermi Mixtures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00523</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00523v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a one-dimensional (1D) lattice mixture of hard-core bosons and spinless fermions with attractive interspecies interaction and correlated fermion pair hopping. Using Schrieffer-Wolff (SW) transformation and bosonization, we derive an effective low-energy theory that reveals a density-induced resonance mechanism. When the filling ratio satisfies $\rho_{c0}:\rho_{b0} = 2:1$, a non-oscillatory cosine term emerges in the bosonized theory. This term favors the formation of trions, i.e., bound states of two fermions and one boson. By performing a renormalization-group (RG) analysis, we identify a phase transition from a gapless two-component Luttinger liquid to a partially gapped trionic phase, where trionic correlations exhibit dominant quasi-long-range order. Our findings provide a microscopic understanding of composite superfluidity and offer experimentally relevant signatures for Bose-Fermi mixtures in 1D lattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00523v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan-Guang Yue, Qi Song, Jie Lou, Yan Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic frictional effects near metal surfaces with strong correlations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00682</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00682v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The electronic friction-Langevin dynamics (EF-LD) offers a simplified framework for describing nonadiabatic effects at metal surfaces, particularly in electrochemical and molecular electronic applications. We investigate the electronic friction behavior for the Hubbard-Holstein model using density matrix renormalization group (DMRG) theory. We show that electron-electron interactions lead to the formation of two energy levels in the impurity, resulting in two peaks in the electronic friction at the resonances of electron attachment or detachment with the metal's Fermi level. We further benchmark our results against mean field theory (MFT) and exact diagonalization (ED). The results calculated by ED and DMRG show strong agreement at high temperatures, suggesting the results from DMRG are reliable; however, at low temperatures, ED exhibits significant deviations relative to DMRG due to the finite-size limitations inherent in ED calculations. MFT completely fails to recover Fermi resonance in electronic friction. Moreover, we investigate the dynamics of the electronic friction using EF-LD. Simulations reveal differences between the electronic population and kinetic energy dynamics predicted by MFT and DMRG approaches, suggesting that MFT approach is unreliable for nonadiabatic dynamics of strongly correlated systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00682v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunhao Liu, Wenjie Dou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay of energy and charge transfer in WSe2/CrSBr heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00810</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00810v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Van der Waals heterostructures (vdWHs) composed of transition-metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) and layered magnetic semiconductors offer great opportunities to manipulate exciton and valley properties of TMDs. Here, we present magneto-photoluminescence (PL) studies in a WSe2 monolayer (ML) on a CrSBr crystal, an anisotropic layered antiferromagnetic semiconductor. Our results reveal unique behavior of each of the ML-WSe2 PL peaks under magnetic field that is distinct from the pristine case. An intriguing feature is the clear enhancement of the PL intensity that we observe each time the external magnetic field tunes the energy of an exciton in CrSBr into resonance with one of the optical states of WSe2. This result suggests a magnetic field-controlled resonant energy transfer (RET) beyond other effects reported in similar structures. Our work provides deep insight on the importance of different mechanisms into magnetic vdWHs and underscores its great potential for light harvesting and emission enhancement of two-dimensional materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00810v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.nanolett.5c03150</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nano Lett. 2025, XXXX, XXX, XXX-XXX</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e Roberto de Toledo, Caique Serati de Brito, Barbara L. T. Rosa, Alisson R. Cadore, C\'esar Ricardo Rabahi, Paulo E. Faria Junior, Ana Carolina Ferreira de Brito, Talieh S. Ghiasi, Josep Ingla-Ayn\'es, Christian Sch\"uller, Herre S. J. van der Zant, Stephan Reitzenstein, Ingrid D. Barcelos, Florian Dirnberger, Yara Galv\~ao Gobato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum action of the Josephson dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00902</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00902v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the beyond-mean-field Josephson dynamics of the relative phase between two coupled macroscopic quantum systems. Using a covariant background field method, we derive the one-loop only-phase quantum effective action and the corresponding equation of motion for the quantum average of the phase. These analytical results are benchmarked against the exact quantum dynamics of the two-site Bose-Hubbard model, demonstrating a relevant improvement over the standard mean-field predictions across a wide range of interaction strengths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00902v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cesare Vianello, Sofia Salvatore, Luca Salasnich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase Diagram and Spectral Function of the Two-Dimensional Disordered Bose-Hubbard Model: A Real-Space Dynamical Mean-Field Theory Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01230v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We numerically investigate the two-dimensional Bose-Hubbard model with local onsite disorder, where the competition between disorder and short-range interactions leads to the emergence of a Bose glass (BG) phase between the Mott insulator (MI) and superfluid (SF) phases. In order to analyze the inhomogeneous system we employ real-space bosonic dynamical mean-field theory and perform an ensemble average over disorder realizations. To distinguish the MI from the BG phase, we compare the Edwards-Anderson order parameter and the compressibility with the energy gap condition. To identify the insulator to SF transition, we apply a percolation analysis to the condensate order parameter. In qualitative accordance with the theorem of inclusions we always find an intermediate BG phase between the SF and MI. However, the quantitative comparison indicates significant deviations between the MI to BG phase boundary expected in the thermodynamic limit and the one obtained for a finite system size. Analyzing the spectral function in the strong-coupling regime reveals evidence for analytically predicted damped localized modes in the dispersion relation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01230v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bastian Schindler, Renan da Silva Souza, Walter Hofstetter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Spin Hall effect on planar Archimedean lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01465</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01465v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Archimedean lattices constitute a unique family of two-dimensional tilings formed from regular polygons arranged with uniform vertex configurations. While the kagome lattice has been extensively studied and the snub square lattice has served as a quasicrystal approximant, the broader family remains comparatively unexplored in the context of electronic and topological properties. In this work, we present a systematic tight-binding study of all eight pure Archimedean lattices, incorporating both $s$ and $p$ orbitals. We analyze their band structures, investigate topological edge states arising from unconventional nanoribbon geometries, and evaluate $\mathbb{Z}_2$ invariants as well as intrinsic spin Hall conductivities using the Kubo formalism. Our results reveal that several Archimedean lattices, such as the truncated hexagonal and truncated trihexagonal lattices, host nearly dispersionless flat bands extending across the Brillouin zone, which remain robust even in the presence of next-nearest-neighbor hopping and strong spin-orbit coupling. In particular, the truncated trihexagonal lattice supports topologically protected, highly spin-polarized edge states across multiple ribbon geometries. These states are stable against defects and spin-flip scattering, and they give rise to sizable spin Hall currents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01465v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. V. Duc Pham, Nicki F. Hinsche, Ingrid Mertig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric phases on graphene from Atiyah-Singer index theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01574v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the emergence of geometric phases in graphene-based nanostructures through the lens of the Atiyah-Singer index theorem. By modeling low-energy quasiparticles in curved graphene geometries as Dirac fermions, we demonstrate that topological defects arising from the insertion of pentagonal or heptagonal carbon rings generate effective gauge fields that induce quantized Berry phases. We derive a compact expression for the geometric phase in terms of the genus and number of open boundaries of the structure, providing a topological classification of zero-energy modes. This framework enables a deeper understanding of quantum holonomies in graphene and their potential application in holonomic quantum computation. Our approach bridges discrete lattice models with continuum index theory, yielding insights that are both physically intuitive and experimentally accessible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01574v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Dantas, A. Carvalho, G. Garcia, C. Furtado</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Computation of the Electronic Structure of Some Prototype Solids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01648</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01648v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Over the last decade, researchers have been working to improve a crucial aspect of quantum computing to predict Hamiltonian energy of solids. Quantum algorithms such as Variational Quantum Eigensolver (VQE) and Variational Quantum Deflation (VQD) have been used to study the molecular systems. However, there is growing interest in adapting and applying these methods to periodic solid-state materials. In this work, we have integrated first-principles density functional theory with VQE and VQD algorithms and utilizing the Wannier Tight-Binding Hamiltonian (WTBH) method to predict the electronic characteristics of solids. We demonstrate that VQE and VQD algorithms can be used to accurately predict electronic characteristics in a variety of multi-component prototype solid-state materials such as-Silicon (semiconductor), Gold (metallic), Boron Nitrile (insulator), Graphene (semi-metal). Efficient SU2 performs well among all the predefined ansatz used in the study. COBYLA is the fastest optimizer among the classical optimizers with minimum number of iterations for convergence. Results of noise models help to understand the band structure when calculated on real quantum hardware. As quantum hardware advances, our method stands as a prototype for future quantum simulations of materials pushing us closer to autonomous quantum discovery engines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01648v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naman Khandelwal, Nidhi Verma, Pooja Jamdagni, Ashok Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct spatiotemporal imaging of a long-lived bulk photovoltaic effect in $BiFeO_{3}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01729</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01729v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The bulk photovoltaic effect (BPVE), a manifestation of broken centrosymmetry, has attracted interest as a probe of the symmetry and quantum geometry of materials, and for use in novel optoelectronic devices. Despite its bulk nature, the BPVE is typically measured with interfaces and metal contacts, raising concerns as to whether the observed signals are genuinely of bulk origin. Here, we use a contactless pump-probe microscopy method to observe the space- and time-resolved dynamics of photoexcited carriers in single-crystal, monodomain $BiFeO_{3}$. We observe asymmetric transport of carriers along the polar axis, confirming the intrinsic bulk and symmetry-driven nature of BPVE. This asymmetric transport persists for several nanoseconds after photoexcitation, which cannot be explained by the shift or phonon ballistic current BPVE mechanisms. Monte Carlo simulations show that asymmetric momentum scattering by defects under non-equilibrium conditions explains the long-lived carrier drift, while first principles calculations confirm that oxygen vacancies have an asymmetric electronic state that can cause such asymmetric scattering. Our findings highlight the critical role of defects in long-lived photoresponses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01729v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saptam Ganguly, Sebin Varghese, Aaron M. Schankler, Xianfei Xu, Kazuki Morita, Michel Viret, Andrew M. Rappe, Gustau Catalan, Klaas-Jan Tielrooij</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative and bond-traceable resonant X-ray optical tensors of organic molecules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01734v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: X-ray scattering at the carbon absorption edge is uniquely sensitive to local molecular bond identity and orientation in organic nanostructures, encoded as a function of photon energy and polarization. However, quantitative analysis is precluded due to the lack of accurate optical models with bond and orientation specificity. We generate such a model through an algorithm that parameterizes and refines density functional theory calculations with angle-resolved absorbance spectroscopy measurements. The resulting optical tensor is shown to reproduce data from samples with domains of different orientation and crystalline packing, enabling label-free orientation analyses of individual chemical moieties within molecular nanostructures using resonant X-rays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01734v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor Murcia, Obaid Alqahtani, Harlan Heilman, Brian A. Collins</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Concise Review of Recently Synthesized 2D Carbon Allotropes: Amorphous Carbon, Graphynes, Biphenylene and Fullerene Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01877</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01877v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2D) carbon allotropes have received considerable attention due to their unique properties and potential applications in several fields, including electronics, catalysis, energy storage, and sensing. Following the experimental realization of graphene, numerous other 2D carbon structures have been proposed and, in some cases, successfully synthesized. This work presents a concise review of the recently experimentally realized 2D carbon allotropes, including graphynes, biphenylene-based networks, fullerene networks, and monolayer amorphous carbon. For each class, we discuss structural characteristics, theoretical predictions, and synthesis methods, with emphasis on the interplay between theory and experiment. We also highlight instances where experimental studies overlooked relevant theoretical contributions. Finally, we identify theoretically predicted structures that remain unexplored experimentally, suggesting opportunities for synthesis-driven investigations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01877v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ricardo Paupitz, Alexandre F. Fonseca, Mizraim Bessa, Guilherme S. L. Fabris, William F. da Cunha, Leonardo D. Machado, Marcelo L. Pereira Junior, Luiz A. Ribeiro Junior Douglas S. Galv\~ao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic nonlinear valley Nernst effect in the strained bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01961v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We theoretically analyze the nonlinear valley Nernst effect (NVNE) as the second-order response of temperature gradient through the semiclassical framework of electron dynamics up to second order. Our study shows that an intrinsic nonlinear pure valley current can be generated vertically to the applied temperature in the materials with both inversion and time-reversal symmetries. This intrinsic NVNE has a quantum origin from the quantum metric and shows independence from the relaxation time. It's found that the local largest symmetry near the valleys for the nonvanishing intrinsic NVNE is a single mirror symmetry in two-dimensional systems. We theoretically investigate the intrinsic NVNE in the uniaxially strained gapless bilayer graphene and find the intrinsic NVNE can emerge when applying the temperature gradient vertically to the direction of strain. Interestingly, a transition from the compressive strain to the tensile one results in the sign reversal of the intrinsic NVNE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01961v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ying-Li Wu, Jia-Liang Wan, Xiao-Qin Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extremely Large and Angle-Dependent Magnetoresistance in Kagome Dirac Semimetal RFe$_6$Sn$_6$ (R=Ho, Dy)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02010v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report on the electronic, magnetic, and magneto-transport properties of Fe-based kagome Dirac system, RFe$_6$Sn$_6$ (R = Ho, Dy). Magnetic properties study reveals an antiferromagnetic order with N$\acute{e}$el temperature of $T_N \approx$ 570 K. Additionally, a weak ferromagnetic order emerge at low temperatures. Magnetotransport measurements demonstrate an extremely large magnetoresistance (XMR) reaching as high as $3\times 10^{3} \%$ for HoFe$_6$Sn$_6$ and $ 1\times 10^{3} \%$ for DyFe$_6$Sn$_6$ when measured at 2 K with 9 T of magnetic field. The semi-classical two-band model fitting of the Hall conductivity reveals nearly perfect electron-hole compensation and high carrier mobility, which leads to XMR behaviour in these system. Further, we identify large magnetoresistance anisotropy for the magnetic fields applied in different crystallographic orientations. In addition, considerable modification in the angle-dependent magnetoresistance (ADMR) pattern has been noticed between 2 and 50 K, indicating temperature-dependent changes in the Fermi surface topology of these systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02010v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Susanta Ghosh, Achintya Low, Nayana Devaraj, Susmita Changdar, Awadhesh Narayan, Setti Thirupathaiah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Domain Wall Engineering in Graphene-Based Josephson Junctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02082v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent progress has enabled the controlled fabrication of domain walls (DWs) in graphene, which host topological kink states. Meanwhile, reliable techniques for constructing graphene-based Joseph- son junctions have been established. While the experimental prerequisites for combining DWs with Josephson junctions are now available, this direction remains largely unexplored. In this work, we theoretically investigate transport properties in graphene-based Josephson junctions mediated by topological kink states and propose three DW engineering strategies. (i) DW number engineering uncovers a continuous evolution of critical current interference pattern from Aharonov-Bohm oscil- lation to Fraunhofer diffraction with increasing DW number, reproducing experimental observations [Barrier et al., Nature 628, 741 (2024)] and suggesting enhanced sensitivity for magnetometry ap- plications. (ii) DW symmetry engineering demonstrates that an asymmetric configuration of DWs under magnetic field yields an ideal Josephson diode characterized by pronounced nonreciprocal transport. (iii) DW geometry engineering reveals that intersecting DWs enable controllable super- current splitting with ratios among leads tunable through the intersection angle, magnetic field, and superconducting phase difference. Our findings elucidate the rich physics of DW-based Josephson junctions and establish a versatile platform for next-generation quantum devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02082v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xia'an Du, Junjie Qi, Hua Jiang, X. C. Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three prerequisites for high-temperature superconductivity in t-PtBi$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02178</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02178v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Although the generic mechanism behind high-temperature superconductivity remains notoriously elusive, a set of favorable conditions for its occurrence in a given material has emerged: (i) the electronic structure should have a very high density of states near the Fermi level; (ii) electrons need to be susceptible to a sizable interaction with another degree of freedom to ensure pairing themselves; (iii) the ability to fine-tune some of the system properties significantly helps maximising the critical temperature. Here, by means of high-resolution ARPES, we show that all three criteria are remarkably fulfilled in trigonal platinum bismuthide (t-PtBi$_2$). Specifically, this happens on its surface, which hosts topological surface states known as Fermi arcs. Our findings pave the way for the stabilisation and optimisation of high-temperature superconductivity in this topological material.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02178v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrii Kuibarov, Susmita Changdar, Riccardo Vocaturo, Oleksandr Suvorov, Alexander Fedorov, Rui Lou, Maxim Krivenkov, Luminita Harnagea, Sabine Wurmehl, Jeroen van den Brink, Bernd B\"uchner, Sergey Borisenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diamagnetic Meissner response of odd-frequency superconducting pairing from quantum geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02243v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the role of quantum geometry in the Meissner response for odd-frequency superconducting pairs in multiband systems. Odd-frequency pairing is traditionally associated with a paramagnetic Meissner response, which raises questions about the stability of the superconducting phase, especially in multiband systems where odd-frequency pairing is ubiquitous. Using analytical calculations in a general two-band, we show that the quantum geometric contribution to the Meissner response from odd-frequency pairs is always diamagnetic for its interband processes, while intraband processes always yield a paramagnetic response. With odd-frequency pairing itself generated by interband pairing, an overall diamagnetic response may often be anticipated. We confirm these results with numerical calculations of models with both flat and dispersive bands. In flat band systems, where geometric effects dominate, the diamagnetic odd-frequency response can even exceed the even-frequency contribution, making odd-frequency pairs the primary source of the diamagnetic Meissner response. In a dispersive two-band system with finite quantum geometry, we similarly find a robust diamagnetic contribution from odd-frequency pairing, even when the total response turns paramagnetic due to even-frequency contributions. These results establish that quantum geometry stabilizes odd-frequency superconductivity and also identify flat-band materials as candidates for realizing odd-frequency superconductivity with a diamagnetic Meissner effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02243v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ankita Bhattacharya, Annica M. Black-Schaffer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intricacies of Frustrated Magnetism in the Kondo Metal YbAgGe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02252</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02252v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The combination of localized magnetic moments, their frustration and interaction with itinerant electrons is a key challenge of condensed matter physics. Frustrated magnetic interactions promote degenerate ground states with enhanced fluctuations, a topic that is predominantly studied in magnetic insulators. The coupling between itinerant and localized electrons in metals add complexity to the problem, and presently formulated only for extreme cases in which the itinerant electrons mediate exchange between localized spins (RKKY interaction) or suppress the formation of magnetic moments (Kondo screening). Here, we report an in-depth experimental study of the distorted Kagome metal YbAgGe, unravelling the open questions of how frustration, localized magnetism and itinerant electrons are intertwined in frustrated Kondo metals. We find that coupled itinerant and localized electrons give rise to dynamic magnetic correlations below T* ~ 20 K. At lower temperature, frustrated magnetic interactions establish anisotropic magnetic short-range correlations that culminate into antiferromagnetic long-range order below TN = 0.68 K with a significantly reduced modulated magnetic moment. We show that local moment Hamiltonians can yield limited understanding of the microscopic behaviour in frustrated metals, and prompt the extension of more sophisticated model Hamiltonians incorporating itinerant effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02252v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. G. Mazzone, C. B. Larsen, B. Ueland, X. Boraley, D. M. Pajerowski, Y. Skourski, J. Taylor, B. Fak, S. L. Bud'ko, R. McQueeney, P. C. Canfield, O. Zaharko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic structure factor of quantum hard rods from exact form-factors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02314v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the quantum hard-rods model and obtain compact analytical expressions for density form factors, and a semi-analytical treatment for dynamic and static structure factors calculations, greatly reducing computational complexity. We identify conditions under which these form factors vanish and analyze real-space correlations, confirming the model's Tomonaga-Luttinger liquid behavior. The results reveal universal features of low energy physics of gapless quantum fluid and relation to Luttinger liquid theory, providing precise benchmarks for numerical simulations. This work establishes quantum hard rods as an important testbed for theories of strongly correlated one-dimensional systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02314v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stanis{\l}aw Kiedrzy\'nski, Emilia Witkowska, Mi{\l}osz Panfil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>All-optical band structure reconstruction and onset of Landau quantization of Dirac fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02362v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The nature of relativistic electrons in solids depends on the precise shape of the underlying band structure. Prominently, symmetry-related mechanisms, such as the breaking of time reversal symmetry in topological insulators, can lead to the emergence of band gaps on small energy scales. It is, thus, important to quantify potential gaps of the Dirac cone with meV precision. Yet established band structure measurements are often challenged by their strict surface sensitivity or limited energy resolution. In this work, we use broadband, time-resolved THz magneto-spectroscopy to access the band structure of Dirac electrons in a buried HgTe quantum well by contact-free, all-optical measurements. Optical doping allows us to control the Fermi level without applying any electrical gate voltages. The background-free measurement of the cyclotron resonance of the Dirac system over 2.5 optical octaves, a broad range of magnetic field strengths, and different Fermi energies allows us to reconstruct the band structure near the Dirac point with sub-meV precision, and to observe a crossover of Landau quantization from a quasi-classical to the relativistic regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02362v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Josef Riepl (Department of Physics, University of Regensburg, Regensburg, Germany), Marc Aichner (Department of Physics, University of Regensburg, Regensburg, Germany, LSI, CNRS, CEA/DRF/IRAMIS, Ecole Polytechnique, Institut Polytechnique de Paris, Palaiseau, France), Nikolai N. Mikhailov (A.V. Rzhanov Institute of Semiconductor Physics, Novosibirsk, Russia), Sergei A. Dvoretsky (A.V. Rzhanov Institute of Semiconductor Physics, Novosibirsk, Russia), Grigory V. Budkin (A. F. Ioffe Insitute, Saint Petersburg, Russia), Sergey D. Ganichev (Department of Physics, University of Regensburg, Regensburg, Germany), Christoph Lange (Department of Physics, TU Dortmund University, Dortmund, Germany), Joshua Mornhinweg (Department of Physics, University of Regensburg, Regensburg, Germany, Harvard John A. Paulson School of Engineering and Applied Sciences, Cambridge, MA, USA), Rupert Huber (Department of Physics, University of Regensburg, Regensburg, Germany)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental electronic structure of the mineral superconductor covellite CuS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02468v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Covellite (CuS) is the first known natural mineral superconductor. Despite its simple chemical formula, covellite exhibits a rich crystal structure at the origin of several remarkable properties. The ionic arrangement in CuS crystals leads to a mixed valence of Cu and a second-order structural transition at 55 K. Despite the abundance of structural studies and theoretical reports on its electronic structure, there are scarce references on its experimental band structure. By means of Angle Resolved PhotoEmission Spectroscopy (ARPES), we have probed the experimental electronic structure of covellite. We compare our results with the predictions of density-functional theory (DFT) calculations. Our experimental data are in remarkable agreement with the calculations, revealing subtle fingerprints of the structural phase transition, and confirming the quasi-2D nature of the electronic structure of CuS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02468v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/st9q-frph</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review B 112, 115103 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alexandre Antezak, Takemi Kato, Pedro Rezende Gon\c{c}alves, Franck Fortuna, Marcin Rosmus, Natalia Olszowska, Andr\'es Felipe Santander-Syro, Emmanouil Frantzeskakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced Terahertz Thermoelectricity via Engineered van Hove Singularities and Nernst Effect in Moir\'e Superlattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02548</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02548v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Thermoelectric materials, long explored for energy harvesting and thermal sensing, convert heat directly into electrical signals. Extending their application to the terahertz (THz) frequency range opens opportunities for low-noise, bias-free THz detection, yet conventional thermoelectrics lack the sensitivity required for practical devices. Thermoelectric coefficients can be strongly enhanced near van Hove singularities (VHS), though these are usually difficult to access in conventional materials. Here we show that moir\'e band engineering unlocks these singularities for THz optoelectronics. Using 2D moir\'e structures as a model system, we observe strong enhancement of the THz photothermoelectric response in monolayer and bilayer graphene superlattices when the Fermi level is tuned to band singularities. Applying a relatively small magnetic field further boosts the response through the THz-driven Nernst effect, a transverse thermoelectric current driven by the THz-induced temperature gradient. Our results establish moir\'e superlattices as a versatile platform for THz thermoelectricity and highlight engineered band structures as a route to high-performance THz optoelectronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02548v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Elesin, A. L. Shilov, S. Jana, I. Mazurenko, P. A. Pantaleon, M. Kashchenko, N. Krivovichev, V. Dremov, I. Gayduchenko, G. Goltsman, T. Taniguchi, K. Watanabe, Y. Wang, E. I. Titova, D. A. Svintsov, K. S. Novoselov, D. A. Bandurin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interaction-limited conductivity of twisted bilayer graphene revealed by giant terahertz photoresistance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02552</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02552v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Identifying the microscopic processes that limit conductivity is essential for understanding correlated and quantum-critical states in quantum materials. In twisted bilayer graphene (TBG) and other twist-controlled materials, the temperature dependence of metallic resistivity follows power-law scaling, with the exponent spanning a broad range, rendering standard transport measurements insufficient to unambiguously identify the dominant scattering processes and giving rise to competing interpretations ranging from phonon-limited transport and umklapp scattering to strange metallicity and heavy fermion renormalization. Here, we use terahertz (THz) excitation to selectively raise the electron temperature in TBG while keeping the lattice cold, enabling a direct separation of electron-electron and electron-phonon contributions to resistivity. We observe a giant THz photoresistance, reaching up to 70% in magic-angle devices, demonstrating that electronic interactions dominate transport even in regimes previously attributed to phonons, including the linear-in-temperature resistivity near the magic angle. Away from the magic angle, we observe coexisting photoresistance and robust quadratic-in-temperature resistivity at extremely low carrier densities where standard electron-electron scattering mechanisms (umklapp and Baber inter-band scattering) are kinematically forbidden. Our analysis identifies the breakdown of Galilean invariance in the Dirac-type dispersion as a possible origin of the interaction-limited conductivity, arising from inter-valley electron-electron collisions. Beyond twisted bilayer graphene, our approach establishes THz-driven hot-electron transport as a general framework for disentangling scattering mechanisms in low-density quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02552v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. L. Shilov, M. Kravtsov, J. Covey, M. A. Kashchenko, O. Popova, X. Zhou, I. Yahniuk, T. Taniguchi, K. Watanabe, A. I. Berdyugin, Y. Wang, S. D. Ganichev, V. Perebeinos, D. A. Svintsov, A. Principi, K. S. Novoselov, D. L. Maslov, D. A. Bandurin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum States in Twisted Tubes with Linear Cross-Section Variation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00432</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00432v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the quantum dynamics of a particle confined in a twisted tube with a linearly varying cross section. By relating a general linear transformation matrix to the system's Hamiltonian, we use an extended thin-layer method to derive an effective Hamiltonian for tangential motion under mild and general linear transformations. Explicit forms are provided for three fundamental transformations: rotation, scaling, and shearing. Rotation introduces a gauge field coupled to angular momentum, while scaling and shearing produce geometric potentials that lift degeneracies in non-circular cross sections. In square cross sections, these transformations cause energy splittings among formerly degenerate states, whereas circular cross sections retain degeneracy. Through an example combining rotation and squeezing, we analyze state evolution and compute the quantum geometric tensor to quantify geometric response. Our results demonstrate how geometric transformations can tailor quantum states and suggest that circular waveguides are more robust against mode mixing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00432v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guo-Hua Liang, Ai-Guo Mei, Men-Yun Lai, Shu-Sheng Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Breakdown of the Kirchhoff's law of thermal radiation by a spatiotemporally modulated nonreciprocal metasurface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00463</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00463v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Kirchhoff's law of thermal radiation, which dictates that the emissivity of a surface equals its absorptivity under thermal equilibrium, which dictates that the emissivity of a surface equals its absorptivity under thermal equilibrium, fundamentally limits the efficiency of photonic systems by enforcing reciprocal energy exchange between source and detector. Breaking this reciprocity is particularly important for advancing photonic devices for energy conversion, radiative cooling, and mid-infrared sensing and imaging. Driven by the growing need for photonic platforms to overcome reciprocity constraints, we present the first demonstration of spatiotemporally modulated nonreciprocal metasurfaces operating at mid-infrared frequencies suitable for the violation of the Kirchhoff's law at room temperature. We fabricate a graphene-based integrated photonic structure and experimentally demonstrate nonreciprocal reflection from a metasurface modulated at gigahertz frequencies. We develop a theoretical framework to relate nonreciprocal scattering under spatiotemporal modulation with unequal absorptivity and emissivity for violation of the spectral directional Kirchhoff's law. Our experiment and theory imply effective decoupling of absorption and emission channels by breaking time-reversal symmetry at thermal wavelengths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00463v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anatoly Efimov, Chun-Chieh Chang, Simo Pajovic, Wilton J. M. Kort-Kamp, Dongsung Kim, Hou-Tong Chen, Diego A. R. Dalvit, Abul K. Azad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Band Geometry Induced Third-Harmonic Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00776v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Third-harmonic generation (THG) is a key nonlinear optical process for ultrafast imaging, terahertz (THz) signal generation, and symmetry-sensitive probes, often dominating in centrosymmetric materials where lower-order responses vanish. Yet, the role of band geometry, Fermi surface effects, and disorder in enabling large and tunable THG remains poorly understood. Here, we develop a finite-frequency quantum kinetic theory of THG based on the density matrix formalism, deriving the third-harmonic conductivity tensor. Our framework isolates five distinct band-geometric contributions to interband and intraband processes, separates Fermi sea from Fermi surface terms, and incorporates disorder effects phenomenologically. We further provide a complete symmetry classification of THG for all 122 magnetic point groups. Applying the theory to the spin-split altermagnet RuO$_2$, we trace its THG response to specific geometric terms. These results establish a predictive foundation for designing materials with enhanced and tunable THG in the finite-frequency regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00776v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sanjay Sarkar, Debottam Mandal, Amit Agarwal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase-Sensitive Measurements on a Fermi-Hubbard Quantum Processor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01637</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01637v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fermionic quantum processors are a promising platform for quantum simulation of correlated fermionic matter. In this work, we study a hardware-efficient protocol for measuring complex expectation values of the time-evolution operator, commonly referred to as Loschmidt echoes, with fermions in an optical superlattice. We analyze the algorithm for the Fermi-Hubbard model at half-filling as well as at finite doping. The method relies on global quench dynamics and short imaginary time evolution, the latter being realized by architecture-tailored pulse sequences starting from a product state of plaquettes. Our numerical results show that complex Loschmidt echoes can be efficiently obtained for large many-body states over a broad spectral range. This allows one to measure spectral properties of the Fermi-Hubbard model, such as the local density of states, and paves the way for the study of finite-temperature properties in current fermionic quantum simulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01637v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto R. Cavallar, Luis Escalera-Moreno, Titus Franz, Timon Hilker, J. Ignacio Cirac, Philipp M. Preiss, Benjamin F. Schiffer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for a Superfluid-to-solid Transition of Bilayer Excitons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.16995</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.16995v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: One of the most spectacular properties associated with Bose-Einstein condensation (BEC) is superfluidity in which the system exhibits zero viscosity and flows without dissipation. The superfluid phase has been observed in wide ranging Bosonic systems spanning naturally occurring quantum fluids, such as liquid helium, to engineered platforms such as bilayer excitons and cold atom systems. Theoretical works have proposed that interactions could drive the BEC ground state into another exotic phase that simultaneously exhibits properties of both a crystalline solid and a superfluid - termed a supersolid. Identifying a material system, however, that hosts the predicted BEC solid phase, driven purely by interactions and without imposing an external lattice potential, has remained elusive. Here we report observation of a superfluid to insulator transition in the layer-imbalanced regime of bilayer magneto-excitons. Mapping the transport behavior of the bilayer condensate as a function of density and temperature, suggests that the insulating phase is an ordered state of dilute excitons, stabilized by dipole interactions. The insulator melts into a recovered superfluid upon increasing the temperature, which could indicate that the low temperature solid is also a quantum coherent phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.16995v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yihang Zeng, Dihao Sun, Naiyuan J. Zhang, Ron Q. Nguyen, Qianhui Shi, A. Okounkova, K. Watanabe, T. Taniguchi, J. Hone, C. R. Dean, J. I. A. Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of anisotropic dispersive dark exciton dynamics in CrSBr</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06372</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06372v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Many-body excitons in CrSBr are attracting intense interest in view of their highly anisotropic magneto-optical coupling and their potential for novel optical interfaces within spintronic and magnonic devices. Characterizing the orbital character and propagation of these electronic excitations is crucial for understanding and controlling their behavior; however, this information is challenging to access. Ultra-high resolution resonant inelastic x-ray scattering is a momentum-resolved technique that can address these crucial questions. We present measurements collected at the Cr $L_3$-edge which show a rich spectrum of excitations with a variety of spin-orbital characters. While most of these excitations appear to be localized, the dispersion of the lowest energy dark exciton indicates that it is able to propagate along both the $a$ and $b$ directions within the planes of the crystal. This two-dimensional character is surprising as it contrasts with electrical conductivity and the behavior of the bright exciton, both of which are strongly one-dimensional. The discovery of this propagating dark exciton highlights an unusual coexistence of one- and two-dimensional electronic behaviors in CrSBr.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06372v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Sears, B. Zager, W. He, C. A. Occhialini, Y. Shen, M. Lajer, J. W. Villanova, T. Berlijn, F. Yakhou-Harris, N. B. Brookes, D. G. Chica, X. Roy, E. Baldini, J. Pelliciari, V. Bisogni, S. Johnston, M. Mitrano, M. P. M. Dean</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum geometry and local moment swapover in correlated graphene heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03700</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03700v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Graphene-based multilayer systems serve as versatile platforms for exploring the interplay between electron correlation and topology, thanks to distinctive low-energy bands marked by significant quantum metric and Berry curvature from graphene's Dirac bands. Here, we investigate Mott physics and local spin moments in Dirac bands hybridized with a flat band of localized orbitals in functionalized graphene. Via hybridization control, a topological transition is realized between two symmetry-distinct site-selective Mott states featuring local moments in different Wyckoff positions, with a geometrically enforced metallic state emerging in between. We find that this geometrically controlled local moment ``swapover'' and associated metal-insulator physics may be realized through proximity coupling of epitaxial graphene on SiC(0001) with group IV intercalants, where the Mott state faces geometrical obstruction in the large-hybridization limit. Our work shows that chemically functionalized graphene provides a correlated electron platform, very similar to the topological heavy fermions in graphene moir\'e systems but at significantly enhanced characteristic energy scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03700v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niklas Witt, Siheon Ryee, Lennart Klebl, Jennifer Cano, Giorgio Sangiovanni, Tim O. Wehling</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Friedel oscillations in a two-dimensional electron gas and monolayer graphene with a non-Coulomb impurity potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01835</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01835v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study Friedel oscillations in a two-dimensional non-interacting electron gas and in a monolayer graphene in the presence of a single impurity. The potential generated by the impurity is modeled using a non-Coulomb interaction ($\sim r^{-\eta}$). The charge carrier density deviation as a function of distance from the impurity is calculated within the linear response theory. Our results show that, in both a two-dimensional non-interacting electron gas and graphene, the phase of charge carrier density oscillations remains unaffected by the parameter $\eta$, which characterizes the non-Coulomb nature of the interaction, at large distances from the impurity. The parameter $\eta$ influences only the amplitude of the oscillations in this regime. The results for an impurity modeled by Coulomb-like potential ($\eta = 1$) are recovered in both cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01835v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physe.2025.116328</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physica E 173, 116328 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Levente M\'ath\'e, Ioan Grosu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Floquet M\"obius topological insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.01401v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: M\"obius topological insulators have dispersive edge bands with M\"obius twists in momentum space, which are protected by the combination of chiral and $Z_2$-projective translational symmetries. In this work, we reveal a unique type of M\"obius topological insulator, whose edge bands could twist around the quasienergy $\pi$ of a periodically driven system and are thus of Floquet origin. By applying time-periodic quenches to an experimentally realized M\"obius insulator model, we obtain interconnected M\"obius edge bands around zero and $\pi$ quasienergies, which can coexist with a gapped or gapless bulk. These M\"obius bands are topologically characterized by a pair of generalized winding numbers, which are integer-quantized due to an emergent chiral symmetry at a high-symmetry point in momentum space. Numerical investigations of the quasienergy and entanglement spectra provide consistent evidence for the presence of such M\"obius topological phases. A protocol based on the adiabatic switching of edge-band populations is further introduced to dynamically characterize the topology of Floquet M\"obius edge bands. Our findings thus extend the scope of M\"obius topological phases to nonequilibrium settings and unveil a unique class of M\"obius-twisted topological edge states without static counterparts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.01401v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Longwen Zhou, Fan Zhang, Jiaxin Pan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Precise quantum-geometric electronic properties from first principles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23652</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.23652v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The calculation of quantum-geometric properties of Bloch electrons -- Berry curvature, quantum metric, orbital magnetic moment and effective mass -- was implemented in a pseudopotential plane-wave code. The starting point was the first derivative of the periodic part of the wavefunction psi_k with respect to the wavevector k. This was evaluated with perturbation theory by solving a Sternheimer equation. Comparison of effective masses obtained from perturbation theory for silicon and gallium arsenide with carefully-converged numerical second derivatives of band energies confirms the high precision of the method. Calculations of quantum-geometric quantities for gapped graphene were performed by adding a bespoke symmetry-breaking potential to first-principles graphene. As the two bands near the opened gap are reasonably isolated, the results could be compared with those obtained from an analytical two-band model, allowing to assess the strengths and limitations of such widely-used models. The final application was trigonal tellurium, where quantum-geometric quantities flip sign with chirality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.23652v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e Lu\'is Martins, Carlos Loia Reis, Ivo Souza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature Dependent Mechanical and Structural Properties of Uniaxially Strained Planar Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14709</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14709v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Using molecular dynamics simulations in a planar graphene sheet, we investigate the temperature dependence of its mechanical behavior under uniaxial tensile stress applied either along the armchair or the zigzag direction. Stress-strain curves are calculated for different temperatures and the corresponding dependence of various elastic parameters, like the Young modulus, the third-order elastic modulus, the tensile strength and failure strain, is presented. Fracture stress and strain, as well as the Young modulus, decrease almost linearly with temperature. The distributions of bond lengths and bond angles at different strains and temperatures are also discussed and approximate analytical expressions are presented. The latter describe accurately the numerically obtained distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14709v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>San\'e Erasmus, Charalampos Skokos, George Kalosakas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microscopic Theory of Light-Induced Coherent Phonons Mediated by Quantum Geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03257v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Light-induced coherent phonons provide a powerful platform for ultrafast control of material properties. However, the microscopic theory and quantum geometric nature of this phenomenon remain underexplored. Here, we develop a fully quantum-mechanical framework based on Feynman diagrams to systematically describe the generation of coherent phonons by light. We identify a dominant second-order, double-resonant process in noncentrosymmetric semiconductors that efficiently couples light to both electronic and phononic excitations. Crucially, we uncover the quantum geometric origin, encoded in the electron-phonon coupling (EPC) shift vector and the EPC quantum geometric tensor. Applying our theory to ferroelectric BaTiO$_3$ and SnSe, we demonstrate the potential for light-induced modulation of ferroelectric polarization driven by coherent phonons. This work provides fundamental insights for designing efficient optical control strategies for both coherent phonons and ferroelectric polarization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03257v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaming Hu, Zhichao Guo, Wenbin Li, Hua Wang, Kai Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constrained Random Phase Approximation: the spectral method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15368</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15368v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a new constrained Random Phase Approximation (cRPA) method, termed spectral cRPA (s-cRPA), and compare it to established cRPA approaches for Scandium and Copper by varying the 3d shell filling. The s-cRPA consistently yields larger Hubbard $U$ interaction values. Applied to the realistic system CaFeO$_3$, s-cRPA produces interaction parameters significantly closer to those required within DFT+$U$ to induce the experimentally observed insulating state, overcoming the metallic behavior predicted by standard density functionals. We also address the issue of negative interaction values found in the projector cRPA method for filled d-shells, demonstrating that s-cRPA offers superior numerical stability through electron conversion. Overall, s-cRPA is more robust and effectively overcomes the known underestimation of $U$ in standard cRPA, making it a promising tool for the community. Additionally, we have enhanced our implementation with features for computing multi-center interactions to analyze spatial decay and developed a low-scaling variant with a compressed Matsubara grid to efficiently obtain full frequency-dependent interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15368v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Merzuk Kaltak, Alexander Hampel, Martin Schlipf, Indukuru Ramesh Reddy, Bongjae Kim, Georg Kresse</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observable criterion for collective entanglement in Boson-lattice system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.05477</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.05477v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: An optical lattice with cold trapped atoms represents a quantum system of fundamental importance as it enables the study of quantum many-body system in a controllable way. It is thus necessary to develop theoretical and experimental tools to explore quantum correlation in such systems to advance our understanding of many-body physics. While previous works have identified some profound aspects of quantum entanglement using e.g. entanglement entropy, there exists a critical demand to have an experimentally accessible tool to investigate many-body quantum entanglement in a broad context. We present an entanglement criterion characterizing collective entanglement in Boson lattice systems and enabling experimental observation readily. On applying our approach to the extended Bose-Hubbard model, we show that our criterion witnesses phase transitions such as Mott insulator--superfluid and Mott insulator--charge density wave transitions. Remarkably, it also makes it possible to detect multipartite entanglement among boson lattice sites in a rigorous sense. Our criterion can be experimentally tested via Raman scattering or time-of-flight methods, which are within the reach of current technology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.05477v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mehmet Emre Tasgin, Hyunchul Nha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single-atom imaging of ${}^{173}$Yb in optical tweezers loaded by a five-beam magneto-optical trap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07371v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We report on the trapping and imaging of individual ytterbium atoms in arrays of optical tweezers, loaded from a magneto-optical trap (MOT) formed by only five beams in an orthogonal configuration. In our five-beam MOT, operating on the narrow ${}^1$S${}_0 \rightarrow {}^3$P${}_1$ intercombination transition, gravity balances the radiation pressure of a single upward-directed beam. This approach enables efficient trapping and cooling of the most common ytterbium isotopes (${}^{171}$Yb, ${}^{173}$Yb and ${}^{174}$Yb) to $\lesssim 20\,\mu$K at densities $\sim 10^{11}$ atoms/cm$^3$ within less than one second. This configuration allows for significantly reducing the complexity of the optical setup, potentially benefiting any ytterbium-atom based quantum science platform leveraging single-atom microscopy, from quantum processors to novel optical clocks. We then demonstrate the first single-atom-resolved imaging of the fermionic, large-spin isotope ${}^{173}$Yb ($I=5/2$), employing a two-color imaging scheme that does not rely on magic-wavelength trapping. We achieve a high single-atom detection fidelity of $99.96(1)\%$ and a large survival probability of $98.5(2)\%$, despite large differential light shifts affecting all nuclear spin sublevels of the excited ${}^3$P${}_1$ state involved in the cooling transition. The demonstrated capabilities will play a key role in future quantum simulations and computing applications with ${}^{173}$Yb arrays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07371v2</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/2058-9565/adf7cf</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Quantum Sci. Technol. 10, 045019 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Omar Abdel Karim, Alessandro Muzi Falconi, Riccardo Panza, Wenliang Liu, Francesco Scazza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
