<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 01:45:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent Network of Josephson Junctions in a Kagome Superconductor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09777</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09777v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Materials with a Kagome lattice are intensely studied because they host novel, exotic states that combine strong correlations and electronic topology. The AV3Sb5 (A = K, Rb, Cs) group, in particular, is of major interest due to its combination of charge density waves, unconventional superconductivity, and indications of time-reversal symmetry breaking and electronic nematicity. Recently, critical current oscillations in an external magnetic field were observed in an unstructured flake of CsV3Sb5 at low current densities. In this work, we unequivocally show that the origin of these oscillations is a network of Josephson junctions intrinsic to the flake that emerges below its critical temperature. Under radio-frequency radiation, we observe perfectly quantized, integer Shapiro steps. The sensitivity of the step height to the contact placement indicates a rich and complex network of junctions. By performing interference studies along multiple field directions, we demonstrate that the observed interference effects are a result of geometrically small junctions and filamentary supercurrent flow. Upon microstructuring the flake, prominent features of the interference pattern are fully preserved, illustrating the localized nature of these flakes and their stability to thermal cycles. These results pave the way for determining the exact nature of superconductivity in the AV3Sb5 family.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09777v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tycho J. Blom, Matthijs Rog, Marieke Altena, Andrea Capa Salinas, Stephen D. Wilson, Chuan Li, Kaveh Lahabi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relationship among Structural, Disordered, Magnetism and Band Topology in MnSb2Te4(Sb2Te3)n Family</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09973</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09973v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Interplay between topology and magnetism induces various exotic quantum phenomena, with magnetic topological insulators (MTIs) serving as a prominent example due to their ability to host the quantum anomalous Hall effect (QAHE). However, the realization of QAHE at higher temperature approaching magnetic-transition-temperature remains a significant challenge, primarily due to the scarcity of suitable material platforms and limited understanding of the intricate relationships between band topology, magnetism, and defects. Here, we report a comprehensive investigation of MnSb2Te4(Sb2Te3)n (n = 0 - 5) single crystals, including the discovery of novel MnSb8Te13 pure phase. Experimental measurements confirm that MnSb8Te13 exhibits ferromagnetism and features topologically nontrivial electronic structures, characterized by a Dirac point located further from the conduction band and a possible larger bulk gap compared to MnBi2Te4(Bi2Te3)n (n = 0 - 3). Moreover, we systematically analyze the relationship between structure, magnetism, topology, and disorder within Mn(Sb, Bi)2Te4((Sb, Bi)2Te3)n family. Present work will shed light on the exploration of potential platforms capable of achieving QAHE near magnetic transition temperature, offering new directions for advancing topological quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09973v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.jpclett.5c02250</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. Chem. Lett. 16, 9507-9516 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ming Xi, Yuchong Zhang, Wenju Zhou, Famin Chen, Donghan Jia, Huiyang Gou, Tian Qian, Hechang Lei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Roles of Electrically Excited Magnons in Unidirectional Magnetoresistance of Metallic Magnetic Bilayers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10309</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10309v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Unidirectional magnetoresistance (UMR) in metallic bilayers arises from nonlinear spin-charge transport mediated by broken time-reversal and inversion symmetries, yet the role of magnons remains unsettled. We develop a theoretical framework that incorporates coupled electron-magnon dynamics, revealing cross diffusion and spin-angular-momentum transfer between the two subsystems, which renormalize the characteristic electron and magnon spin-diffusion lengths. We show that nonequilibrium magnons, indirectly excited by the electric field, can suppress UMR by absorbing spin angular momentum from conduction electrons. We also analyze the magnetic-field, thickness, and temperature dependencies and identify distinct features that constitute experimental fingerprints of magnonic contributions to UMR in metallic bilayers, providing qualitative to semiquantitative guidance for elucidating the underlying physical mechanisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10309v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shashank Gupta, Steven S. -L. Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atomic-Scale Origins of Oxidation Resistance in Amorphous Boron Nitride</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10326v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Amorphous boron nitride (\textrm{$\alpha$}-BN) is a promising ultrathin barrier for nanoelectronics, yet the atomistic mechanisms governing its chemical stability remain poorly understood. Here, we investigate the structure-property relationship that dictates the oxidation of \textrm{$\alpha$}-BN using a combination of machine-learning molecular dynamics simulations and angle-resolved X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy. The simulations reveal that the film structure, controlled by synthesis conditions, is the critical factor determining oxidation resistance. Dense, chemically ordered networks with a high fraction of B-N bonds effectively resist oxidation by confining it to the surface, whereas porous, defect-rich structures with abundant homonuclear B-B and N-N bonds permit oxygen penetration and undergo extensive bulk degradation. These computational findings are consistent with experimental trends observed in \textrm{$\alpha$}-BN films grown by chemical vapour deposition. XPS analysis shows that a film grown at a higher temperature develops a more ordered structure with a B/N ratio nearer to stoichiometric and exhibits superior resistance to surface oxidation compared to its more defective, lower-temperature counterpart. Together, these results demonstrate that the oxidation resistance of \textrm{$\alpha$}-BN is a tunable property directly linked to its atomic-scale morphology, providing a clear framework for engineering chemically robust dielectric barriers for future nanoelectronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10326v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Onurcan Kaya (Catalan Institute of Nanoscience and Nanotechnology, Department of Electronic Engineering, Universitat Aut\`onoma de Barcelona), Qiushi Deng (School of Engineering, The Australian National University, Canberra, Australia), Thomas Souvignet (Universit\'e Claude Bernard Lyon 1, CNRS, LMI UMR 5615, Villeurbanne, France), Catherine Marichy (Universit\'e Claude Bernard Lyon 1, CNRS, LMI UMR 5615, Villeurbanne, France), Catherine Journet (Universit\'e Claude Bernard Lyon 1, CNRS, LMI UMR 5615, Villeurbanne, France), Ivan Cole (School of Engineering, The Australian National University, Canberra, Australia), Stephan Roche (Catalan Institute of Nanoscience and Nanotechnology, ICREA, Barcelona, Spain)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ferromagnetic Resonance Spectroscopy on the Kagome Magnet MgMn$_6$Sn$_6$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10356</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10356v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: MgMn$_6$Sn$_6$ is the itinerant ferromagnet on the kagome lattice with high ordering temperature featuring complex electronic properties due to the nontrivial topological electronic band structure, where the spin-orbit coupling (SOC) plays a crucial role. Here, we report a detailed ferromagnetic resonance (FMR) spectroscopic study of MgMn$_6$Sn$_6$ aimed to elucidate and quantify the intrinsic magnetocrystalline anisotropy that is responsible for the alignment of the Mn magnetic moments in the kagome plane. By analyzing the frequency, magnetic field, and temperature dependences of the FMR modes, we have quantified the magnetocrystalline anisotropy energy density that reaches the value of approximately $ 3.5\cdot 10^6$ erg/cm$^3$ at $T = 3$ K and reduces to about $1\cdot 10^6$ erg/cm$^3$ at $T = 300$ K. The revealed significantly strong magnetic anisotropy suggests a sizable contribution of the orbital magnetic moment to the spin magnetic moment of Mn, supporting the scenario of the essential role of SOC for the nontrivial electronic properties of MgMn$_6$Sn$_6$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10356v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00723-025-01806-8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Applied Magnetic Resonance, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Riju Pal, Kakan Deb, Nitesh Kumar, Bernd B\"uchner, Alexey Alfonsov, Vladislav Kataev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controllable Domain Wall Memories with Magnetic Topological Insulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10369</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10369v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Domain wall memories have undergone several changes over the years for faster shift, read, and write operations; however, fundamental issues persist due to creating pinning sites topographically along the nanowire. The deformity in notches creates non-uniform pinning strength, leading to multiple faults during shift operation. This study proposes a novel approach to address these challenges and gain greater control over domain manipulation for advanced applications in Boolean and non-Boolean paradigms. Utilizing the magnetic topological insulator (MTI) can create pinning sites without potentially faulty topographical notches made through complex lithography. Moreover, applying an external current enables precise control over the pinning potentials at these sites. Micromagnetic simulations validate the effectiveness of MTI-based pinning sites, showcasing their potential for future applications. Our approach introduces an alternative method for creating pinning sites by cross-architecture of ferromagnetic nanowires and MTI nanobars, inducing exchange interaction at their intersection points. This method offers simplicity of fabrication and enables control over the pinning strength by external current.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10369v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arifa Hoque, Sanjukta Bhanja</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resolving the Structural Duality of Graphene Grain Boundaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10491</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10491v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Grain boundaries (GBs) are ubiquitous in large-scale graphene samples, playing a crucial role in their overall performance. Due to their complexity, they are usually investigated as model structures, under the assumption of a fully relaxed interface. Here, we present cantilever-based non-contact atomic force microscopy (ncAFM) as a suitable technique to resolve, atom by atom, the complete structure of these linear defects. Our experimental findings reveal a richer scenario than expected, with the coexistence of energetically stable and metastable graphene GBs. Although both GBs are structurally composed of pentagonal and heptagonal like rings, they can be differentiated by the irregular geometric shapes present in the metastable boundaries. Theoretical modeling and simulated ncAFM images, accounting for the experimental data, show that metastable GBs form under compressive uniaxial strain and exhibit vertical corrugation, whereas stable GBs remain in a fully relaxed, flat configuration. By locally introducing energy with the AFM tip, we show the possibility to manipulate the metastable GBs, driving them toward their minimum energy configuration. Notably, our high-resolution ncAFM images reveal a clear dichotomy: while the structural distortions of metastable grain boundaries are confined to just a few atoms, their impact on graphene's properties extends over significantly larger length scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10491v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haojie Guo, Emiliano Ventura-Mac\'ias, Mariano D. Jim\'enez-S\'anchez, Nicoleta Nicoara, Pierre Mallet, Jean-Yves Veuillen, Vincent T. Renard, Antonio J. Mart\'inez-Galera, Pablo Pou, Julio G\'omez-Herrero, Rub\'en P\'erez, Iv\'an Brihuega</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time domain braiding of anyons revealed through a nonequilibrium fluctuation dissipation theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10525</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10525v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We derive a novel fluctuation--dissipation theorem (FDT) valid for nonequilibrium initial states that imprint the braiding of anyons in the time domain. The derivation is carried out within the Unifying Nonequilibrium Perturbative Theory (UNEPT), which applies to both standard reservoir geometries and configurations with one or two quantum point contacts (QPCs) injecting dilute anyonic fluxes. Based on this FDT, we propose complementary methods to determine the time-domain braiding phase. The first method relates the DC backscattering noise to the integral of the current with respect to DC drives, while the second connects the AC current phase shift to the DC noise. The latter provides a particularly robust probe of the statistical angle $\theta$, offering an intrinsic calibration and cancelling certain nonuniversal renormalization effects. Specializing to a thermalized Tomonaga--Luttinger liquid (TLL), we further show that in the quantum regime the phase shift enables a direct determination of the scaling dimension $\delta$ when $\delta &gt; 1/2$. These results define experimentally accessible schemes to extract either $\theta$ or $\delta$ in minimal single-QPC setups, without relying on interferometry or cross-correlation measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10525v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ines Safi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supercurrent interference and its transfer in a kagome superconductor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10543v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Superconductivity represents a macroscopic quantum state notable for its rich manifestations of electronic coherence and collective behavior. Kagome materials AV3Sb5 (A= K, Cs, Rb) possess cascade intertwined quantum phases including superconductivity, symmetry-breaking charge orders, nematic orders and topological states, making them attractive materials for exploring exotic superconducting states. However, the superconducting properties and the Cooper pairing behaviors have not been fully explored and understood. In this work, by studying both the magnetoresistance and critical current behaviors in KV3Sb5 ring and pristine flakes, we reveal the charge 2e paring in KV3Sb5 although anomalous oscillations with smaller periodicity were observed, and report the intrinsic superconducting phase coherence in KV3Sb5 flakes. The former is demonstrated by the careful verification of the Little-Parks oscillations in differential resistance colormaps, and the latter indicates the existence of superconducting domains in KV3Sb5. Moreover, we observed a special phenomenon: the transfer of supercurrent interference patterns between the superconducting ring and the superconducting flake, which demonstrates the global critical current effect of the superconducting phase coherence. These findings provide new insights into the Cooper pairing behaviors in KV3Sb5 and highlight the importance of global effect of superconducting phase coherence in the understanding of the superconducting behaviors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10543v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Heng Wu, Houssam el Mrabet Haje, Michiel Dubbelman, Brenden R. Ortiz, Stephen D. Wilson, Mazhar N. Ali, Yaojia Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrable Model of a Superconductor with non-Fermi liquid and Mott Phases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10684</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10684v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present and analyze an exactly solvable interacting fermionic pairing model, which features interactions that entangle states at momenta $\mathbf{k}$ and $-\mathbf{k}$. These interactions give rise to novel correlated ground states, leading to a rich phase diagram that includes superconducting, multiple metallic, and Mott-insulating phases. At finite interaction strengths, we observe the emergence of multiple many-body Fermi surfaces, which violate Luttinger's theorem and challenge the conventional Landau-Fermi liquid paradigm. A distinguishing feature of our model is that it remains quantum integrable, even with the addition of pairing interactions of various symmetries, setting it apart from the Hatsugai-Kohmoto model. Our results provide an analytically tractable framework for studying strong correlation effects that give rise to fractionalized excitations and unconventional superconductivity, offering valuable insights into a broad class of integrable many-body systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10684v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Santhosh M, Jorge Dukelsky, Gerardo Ortiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emerging Ferroelectric Domains: Stacking and Rotational Landscape of MoS2 Moire Bilayers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10831v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The structures and properties of moire patterns in twisted bilayers of two-dimensional (2D) materials are known to depend sensitively on twist angle, yet their dependence on stacking order remains comparatively underexplored. In this study, we use molecular dynamics simulations to systematically investigate the combined effects of stacking order and rotation in MoS2 bilayers. Beginning from five well-established high-symmetry bilayer stackings, we apply twist angles between 1 and 120 to the top layer, revealing a variety of relaxed moire structures. Our results show that the initial stacking significantly influences the moire domain configurations that emerge at a given twist angle. While all five stacking orders are metastable without twist, they form two moire-equivalent classes- AA/AB and AA',A'B,AB', i.e., for a given twist angle, structures within each class relax to the same moire configuration. Specifically, initial AA and AB stackings give rise to triangular ferroelectric domains near 0+/-3, while AA', A'B, and AB' stackings produce triangular ferroelectric domains near 60+/-3. At precisely 60 and 120 twists, the bilayers relax to into pure high-symmetry stackings, highlighting the rotational relationships between these configurations and explaining the shift of 60 in the ferroelectric rotational range. These findings demonstrate the critical role of stacking order in governing the rich moire landscapes accessible in twistronic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10831v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anikeya Aditya, Ayu Irie, Nabankur Dasgupta, Rajiv K. Kalia, Aiichiro Nakano, Priya Vashishta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Field-Enhanced Graphene Superconductivity with Record Pauli-Limit Violation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10873v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spin-polarized superconductors offer a rare platform for studying electronic correlations, but few candidate systems have been experimentally confirmed to date. Here, we report the observation of a spin-polarized superconducting state, denoted SC5, in WSe2-proximitized rhombohedral trilayer graphene. At in-plane magnetic field B|| = 0 T, SC5 has a critical temperature of 68 mK and an out-of-plane critical magnetic field of only 12 mT. Surprisingly, these values are significantly enhanced as B|| increases, and the superconductivity persists to B|| = 8.8 T. This value corresponds to a record-high Pauli-limit violation ratio of at least 80 among all superconductors, while the true critical field is beyond the limit of our instrument. We conclude that SC5 experiences a canting crossover from Ising-type to spin-polarized superconductor with increased B||.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10873v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jixiang Yang, Omid Sharifi Sedeh, Chiho Yoon, Shenyong Ye, Henok Weldeyesus, Armel Cotten, Tonghang Han, Zhengguang Lu, Zach Hadjri, Junseok Seo, Lihan Shi, Emily Aitken, Prayoga P Liong, Zhenghan Wu, Mingchi Xu, Christian Scheller, Mingyang Zheng, Rasul Gazizulin, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Dominique Laroque, Mingda Li, Fan Zhang, Dominik M. Zumb\"uhl, Long Ju</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-dimensional flat-bands in Moire-diamonds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10908v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The discovery of flat-bands in magic-angle twisted bilayer graphene has underscored the potential of moire engineering for correlated states, but such phases are notoriously difficult to realize and highly fragile against perturbations. Here, we propose an alternative route to flat-bands by introducing sp3 hybridization in twisted graphite. Instead of relying on fine-tuned magic angles, our approach identifies flat-band states at relatively large twist angles with short moire periods. In this regime, sp3-induced reconstructions generate electronic states that, once formed, are locked by substantial energy barriers, rendering them robust against external perturbations. Using twisted graphite as a prototype, we uncover a series moire-diamond that host two-dimensional flat conduction of valence bands, where carriers are localized within specific momentum planes but remain dispersive along orthogonal directions. The emergence of dimensional flat-bands opens a new platform for flat-band-driven correlated physics and suggests opportunities for designing quantum materials with highly directional electronic functionalities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10908v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yalan Wei, Shifang Li, Yuke Song, Chaoyu He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase-sensitive evidence for 2x2 pair density wave in a kagome superconductor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10958</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10958v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The pair-density-wave (PDW) exhibits periodic amplitude and sign modulations of the superconducting order parameter. Such a pairing state has been proposed to be sensitive to nonmagnetic scattering. In this work, we observe the nonmagnetic PDW-breaking effect in a kagome superconductor, using scanning tunneling microscopy. We observe 2x2 PDW induced by the coupling between charge order and superconductivity. The global PDW is substantially suppressed upon doping the kagome lattice with dilute isovalent nonmagnetic impurities, whereas the charge order and uniform superconductivity remain robust. Spatial correlation analysis further confirms that PDW is distinctly suppressed near dopants. We attribute the PDW suppression to a nonmagnetic PDW breaking effect, arising from phase sign modulation of PDW in the kagome d-orbital hosting Bogoliubov Fermi states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10958v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao-Yu Yan, Guowei Liu, Hanbin Deng, Xitong Xu, Haiyang Ma, Hailang Qin, Jun-Yi Zhang, Yuanyuan Zhao, Haitian Zhao, Zhe Qu, Yigui Zhong, Kozo Okazaki, Xiquan Zheng, Yingying Peng, Zurab Guguchia, X. X. Wu, Qianghua Wang, X-H Fan, Wei Song, M-W Gao, Hendrik Hohmann, Matteo Durrnagel, Ronny Thomale, Jia-Xin Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local-Antisymmetric Flat Band and Coexisting Correlated stripe charge orders in WSe2-Modulated Twisted Bilayer Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11088v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Insulating, atomically flat transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) like WSe2 are ideal substrates for probing intrinsic graphene properties. Conventionally, their influence on graphene's band structure is assumed negligible, particularly when small moire patterns form. Combining scanning tunneling microscopy/spectroscopy and theoretical analysis, we reveal that the atomic registry in graphene/WSe2 heterostructures profoundly modulates the electronic structure of magic-angle twisted bilayer graphene (MATBG). At special graphene/WSe2 twist angles, an incommensurate moire superlattice hosts three distinct atomic stacking configurations (A, B, X types). These induce position-dependent potentials that asymmetrically shift MATBG's flat bands, transforming them from hole-side to electron-side asymmetric within a single AA-stacked region. This symmetry breaking enables the unprecedented coexistence of orthogonal stripe charge orders in the correlated regime-a phenomenon previously considered mutually exclusive due to Coulomb repulsion. This band modulation arises from the synergistic effects of the graphene/WSe2 interfacial atomic registry and heterostrain within the MATBG, exhibiting multi-field tunability. Our work establishes interfacial atomic registry as a critical, previously overlooked tuning parameter for flat-band physics, opening avenues to engineer correlated quantum states in van der Waals heterostructures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11088v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chi Zhang, Shihao Zhang, Mengmeng Zhang, Lin He, Qi Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spinon band flattening by its emergent gauge field in quantum kagome ice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11134v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fractional excitations provide a key to identifying sought-after topological quantum spin liquid states in realistic materials. Their single-particle dynamics already presents a challenging many-body problem on account of the coupling to their emergent gauge field. Here, we study the spinon excitations of kagome ice, realized at the $2/3$ magnetization plateau of spin ice, by combining up-to-$63$-site exact diagonalization with an analytical state graph mapping. We find a macroscopically degenerate mode in the spinon spectrum. It originates from the destructive interference due to the interaction with surrounding gauge fields, a form of many-body caging. We explicitly construct, and count, the concomitant many-body wave functions. Finally, we discuss the possible role of these flat modes in the magnetization process of kagome antiferromagnets, in particular with regard to the asymmetric termination of the kagome ice magnetisation plateau.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11134v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masafumi Udagawa, Roderich Moessner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonequilibrium spin-splitter effect in altermagnet superconductor hybrids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11355</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11355v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the nonequilibrium spin-splitter effect in superconducting altermagnets and superconductor altermagnet hybrids by computing the alternating spin current and edge the spin density in the presence of an alternating electric field. We show that while in the normal state the effect is not sensitive to the field frequency, in the superconducting state, there is a strong effect for frequencies on the scale of $\Delta_0$ or lower. We contrast the effect to the spin accumulation induced by the spin-Hall effect, by showing that for the altermagnet spin-splitter effect the out-of-phase spin density does not diverge in the adiabatic limit. This difference is attributed to the absence of any equilibrium spin-splitter effect in altermagnets. In fact, the out-of-phase component vanishes below the gap excitation frequency $2\Delta_0$, because below this frequency the absence of dissipation and the behavior of the system under time-reversal directly determine the relative phase between the charge current, spin current, and spin accumulation. The nonequilibrium effect can be tuned by external parameters like temperature. In fact, it has a nonmonotonic temperature dependence, taking its largest value for temperatures around $0.8T_{c}$. The value at this temperature can be significantly larger than the normal state spin density or the low temperature spin density. Thus, besides using the nonequilibrium spin-splitter effect to identify altermagnets, its tunability makes it also suitable for applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11355v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tim Kokkeler, Tero T. Heikkil\"a, F. Sebastian Bergeret</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deterministic Switching in Altermagnets via Asymmetric Sublattice Spin Current</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11362v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate a deterministic switching mechanism in collinear altermagnets driven by asymmetric sublattice spin currents. Unlike conventional antiferromagnets, where combined parity-time-reversal symmetry enforces purely staggered sublattice spin torques, altermagnets host symmetry-protected nonrelativistic spin splitting that produces unequal torques on the two sublattices. Using doped FeSb$_2$ as a representative $d$-wave altermagnet, our Landau--Lifshitz--Gilbert simulations show that these torques enable magnetic-field-free and deterministic 180$^\circ$ N\'eel vector reversal over picosecond timescale. The mechanism is generic to even-parity altermagnets and remains effective even in centrosymmetric, weak spin-orbit coupled systems, where the N\'eel spin-orbit torque mechanism fails. Our results establish an experimentally accessible mechanism for switching of altermagnetic order, opening pathways for realizing ultrafast, low-power altermagnet spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11362v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sayan Sarkar, Sunit Das, Amit Agarwal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Host-atom-driven transformation of a honeycomb oxide into a dodecagonal quasicrystal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11426</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11426v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dodecagonal oxide quasicrystals (OQCs) have so far been limited to a few elemental systems, with no general formation mechanism established. Here, we demonstrate a versatile approach to OQC formation via a host-atom-induced transformation of a metal-oxide honeycomb (HC) network. Adsorption of Ba, Sr, or Eu onto the HC layer triggers its reorganization into a dodecagonal tiling, as revealed by low-energy electron diffraction and scanning tunneling microscopy. Full conversion occurs when 73% of the honeycomb rings are occupied. Kelvin probe and UV photoelectron spectroscopy show a linear decrease in work function with increasing host coverage, followed by a sharp increase upon quasicrystal formation due to reduced host dipoles. This transformation mechanism enables the fabrication of structurally precise OQCs, including a new Eu-Ti-O phase that extends the field to lanthanide quasicrystals, forming a 2D grid of localized magnetic moments. The method offers a general route to explore lattice-matched substrates for epitaxial growth and may be adapted to other 2D honeycomb materials - such as graphene, hexagonal ice, and silica - paving the way for engineered aperiodic systems beyond transition metal oxides.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11426v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Haller, Julia Hewelt, V. Y. M. Rajesh Chirala, Loi Vinh Tran, Ankur Bhide, Muriel Wegner, Stefan F\"orster, Wolf Widdra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flux confinement-deconfinement transition of dimer-loop models on three-dimensional bipartite lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11607v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by recent work that mapped the low-temperature properties of a class of frustrated spin $S=1$ kagome antiferromagnets with competing exchange and single-ion anisotropies to the fully-packed limit (with each vertex touched by exactly one dimer or nontrivial loop) of a system of dimers and nontrivial (length $s &gt; 2$) loops on the honeycomb lattice, we study this fully-packed dimer-loop model on the three-dimensional bipartite cubic and diamond lattices as a function of $w$, the relative fugacity of dimers. We find that the $w \rightarrow 0$ O($1$) loop-model limit is separated from the $w \rightarrow \infty$ dimer limit by a geometric phase transition at a nonzero finite critical fugacity $w_c$: The $w&gt;w_c$ phase has short loops with an exponentially decaying loop-size distribution, while the $w&lt;w_c$ phase is dominated by large loops whose loop-size distribution is governed by universal properties of the critical O($1$) loop soup. This transition separates two {\em distinct} Coulomb liquid phases of the system: Both phases admit a description in terms of a fluctuating divergence-free polarization field $P_{\mu}(\mathbf{r})$ on links of the lattice and are characterized by dipolar correlations at long distances. The transition at $w_c$ is a flux confinement-deconfinement transition. Equivalently, and independent of boundary conditions, half-integer test charges $q=\pm 1/2$ are confined for $w&gt;w_c$, but become deconfined in the small-$w$ phase. Although both phases are unstable to a nonzero fugacity for the charge $\pm 1/2$ excitations, the destruction of the $w &gt;w_c$ Coulomb liquid is characterized by an interesting slow crossover, since test charges with $q=\pm 1/2$ are confined in this phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11607v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Souvik Kundu, Kedar Damle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spinon Mediation of Witness-Spin Dynamics and Ground State in Herbertsmithite</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11678v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The kagome lattice of spin-1/2 Cu atoms in herbertsmithite (ZnCu3(OH)6Cl2) may sustain a quantum spin liquid (QSL) state with spinon quasiparticles. Each kagome plane is separated from its homologues by a layer of spinless Zn atoms. Providentially, however, some spin-1/2 Cu atoms substitute randomly onto these inter-kagome Zn sites. We reconceptualize these 'impurity' atoms as quantum 'witness-spins', an exceptional new interrogative of the conjectured Z2-gauge-symmetric QSL state. Thus we introduce spin-noise spectroscopy to explore herbertsmithite witness-spin dynamics for QSL studies. It reveals the existence, slowing and intensification of spin noise, prefatory to a sharp transition at T* {\approx} 260 mK. Below T* the spin-noise power spectral density S_M({\omega},T) {\propto} {\omega}^{-{\alpha}(T)} stabilizes at {\alpha} {\approx} 1; the spin noise variance {\sigma}_M^2(T) diminishes precipitously; the ultra-low-field magnetic susceptibility {\chi}(T) undergoes a sharp transition into a phase exhibiting an Edwards-Anderson order-parameter and ultra-slow spin-state relaxation. A Z2 QSL theory of spinon-mediated witness-spin interactions corresponds best to all these experimental observations, predicting slowing and intensification of witness-spin fluctuations and noise spectrum S_M({\omega},T) with cooling, with a transition into a unique spinon-mediated phase signified by rapidly diminishing spin noise, with S_M({\omega},T) {\propto} {\omega}^{-1}, a sharp cusp in the DC magnetic susceptibility {\chi}(T), and the appearance of an Edwards-Anderson order-parameter. We rule out numerous other mechanisms for these effects, so that only spinon-mediation by either a Z2 or U(1) QSL is consistent with all present herbertsmithite empirics, with the former model providing a closer match to data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11678v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroto Takahashi, Jack Murphy, Mitikorn Wood-Thanan, Pascal Puphal, Miguel Angel Sanchez-Martinez, Fabian Jerzembeck, Chun-Chih Hsu, Jonathan Ward, Masahiko Isobe, Yosuke Matsumoto, Hidenori Takagi, Stephen J. Blundell, Michael R. Norman, Felix Flicker, J. C. S\'eamus Davis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparing Symmetrized Determinant Neural Quantum States for the Hubbard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11710</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11710v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate simulations of the Hubbard model are crucial to understanding strongly correlated phenomena, where small energy differences between competing orders demand high numerical precision. In this work, Neural Quantum States are used to probe the strongly coupled and underdoped regime of the square-lattice Hubbard model. We systematically compare the Hidden Fermion Determinant State and the Jastrow-Backflow ansatz, parametrized by a Vision Transformer, finding that in practice, their accuracy is similar. We also test different symmetrization strategies, finding that output averaging yields the lowest energies, though it becomes costly for larger system sizes. On cylindrical systems, we consistently observe filled stripes. On the torus, our calculations display features consistent with a doped Mott insulator, including antiferromagnetic correlations and suppressed density fluctuations. Our results demonstrate both the promise and current challenges of neural quantum states for correlated fermions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11710v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louis Sharma, Ahmedeo Shokry, Rajah Nutakki, Olivier Simard, Michel Ferrero, Filippo Vicentini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random State Approach to Quantum Computation of Electronic-Structure Properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09999</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09999v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Classical computation of electronic properties in large-scale materials remains challenging. Quantum computation has the potential to offer advantages in memory footprint and computational scaling. However, general and practical quantum algorithms for simulating large-scale materials are still lacking. We propose and implement random-state quantum algorithms to calculate electronic-structure properties of real materials. Using a random state circuit with only a few qubits, we employ real-time evolution with first-order Trotter decomposition and Hadamard test to obtain electronic density of states, and we develop a modified quantum phase estimation algorithm to calculate real-space local density of states via direct quantum measurements. Furthermore, we validate these algorithms by numerically computing the density of states and spatial distributions of electronic states in graphene, twisted bilayer graphene quasicrystals, and fractal lattices, covering system sizes from hundreds to thousands of atoms. Our results manifest that the random-state quantum algorithms provide a general and qubit-efficient route to simulating electronic properties of large-scale periodic and aperiodic materials on quantum computers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09999v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiran Bai, Feng Xiong, Xueheng Kuang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconductivity in kagome metal YRu3Si2 with strong electron correlations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.11478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2109.11478v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report the detailed physical properties of YRu3Si2 with the Ru kagome lattice at normal and superconducting states. The results of resistivity and magnetization show that YRu3Si2 is a type-II bulk superconductor with Tc ~ 3.0 K. The specific heat measurement further suggests that this superconductivity could originate from the weak or moderate electron-phonon coupling. On the other hand, both large Kadawaki-Woods ratio and Wilson ratio indicate that there is a strong electron correlation effect in this system, which may have a connection with the featured flat band of kagome lattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2109.11478v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/0256-307X/39/8/087401</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chin. Phys. Lett. 39, 087401 (2022)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Chunsheng Gong, Shangjie Tian, Zhijun Tu, Qiangwei Yin, Yang Fu, Ruitao Luo, Hechang Lei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comment on paper: Evidence for Dirac flat band superconductivity enabled by quantum geometry, Nature 614, 440 (2023)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.06054</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.06054v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We demonstrate that an absolutely flat band retains the superconducting state at $T_c\to 0$. When $T_c&gt;0$ the flat band disappears, since it must be modified by the superconducting state. Thus, a number of the results on ultra-strong coupling superconductivity in flat band considered in the article ("Evidence for Dirac flat band superconductivity enabled by quantum geometry", Nature 614, 440 (2023)) were predicted and explained many years ago. One has to take into account that at $T_c&gt;0$ the flat band distorts, becoming tilted. As a result, the charge carriers' velocity $v_F\propto T_c$ becomes finite, rather than being extremely slow, as it is stated in the article. Thus, the statement "the charge carriers' group velocity $v_ F$ is extremely slow" is incorrect and leads the authors to the conceptional misunderstanding, confusing the reader.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.06054v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. R. Shaginyan, A. Z. Msezane, G. S. Japaridze</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charge Susceptibility and Kubo Response in Hatsugai-Kohmoto-related Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07522v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study in depth the charge susceptibility for the band Hatsugai-Kohmoto (HK) and orbital (OHK) models. As either of these models describes a Mott insulator, the charge susceptibility takes on the form of a modified density response function with lower and upper Hubbard bands, thereby giving rise to a multi-pole structure. The particle-hole continuum consists of hot spots along the $\omega$ vs $q$ axis arising from inter-band transitions. Such transitions, which are strongly suppressed in non-interacting systems, obtain here because of the non-rigidity of the Hubbard bands. This modified density response function gives rise to a plasmon dispersion that is inversely dependent on the momentum, resulting in an additional contribution to the conventional f-sum rule. This extra contribution originates from a long-range diamagnetic contribution to the current. This results in a non-commutativity of the long-wavelength ($q\rightarrow 0$) and thermodynamic ($L\rightarrow\infty$) limits. When the correct limits are taken, we find that the Kubo response computed with either open or periodic boundary conditions yields identical results that are consistent with the continuity equation contrary to recent claims. We also show that the long wavelength pathology of the current noted previously also plagues the Anderson impurity model interpretation of dynamical mean-field theory (DMFT).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07522v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuhao Ma, Jinchao Zhao, Edwin W. Huang, Dhruv Kush, Barry Bradlyn, Philip W. Phillips</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for Mott Gap Softening Coinciding with Spin Correlations Collapse in a-RuCl3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14697</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14697v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Mott insulator a-RuCl3, featuring the intertwined interplay of spin-orbit coupling (SOC) and Kitaev spin correlations, provides an unparalleled platform for probing quantum many-body physics. Using scanning tunneling microscopy/spectroscopy (STM/STS), we compare temperature-dependent dI/dV spectra between in-situ grown monolayers and exfoliated bulk samples. Both systems exhibit pronounced Mott gap softening near 110 K, manifested by spectral weight transfer from Hubbard bands toward the Fermi level, resulting in low-energy correlated charge delocalization. Although this gap softening coincides with Kitaev paramagnetic and structural phase transitions in bulk crystals, monolayer studies provide compelling insights. By eliminating structural phase transition in monolayer sample, we suggest that spin correlations, rather than Coulomb interactions alone, may govern charge dynamics within the Mott-Hubbard framework, challenging conventional Mott-Hubbard paradigms. These results resolve a long-standing controversy regarding the Mott gap magnitude in a-RuCl3 and experimentally confirm the critical role of spin correlations in Mott physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14697v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/nbfx-x8f6</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Wei Yue, Xiaohu Zheng, Chongli Yang, Kun Peng, Katsumi Tanigaki, Rui-Rui Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay of orbital-selective Mott criticality and flat-band physics in La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_6$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19617</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19617v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Superconductivity in nickelates apparently takes place in two different Ni oxidation regimes, namely either for infinite-layer-type compounds close to Ni$^{+}$, or for Ruddlesden-Popper materials close to Ni$^{2+}$. The reduced La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_6$ bilayer with a nominal Ni$^{1.5+}$ oxidation state may therefore serve as a normal-state mediator between the two known families of $3d^8$-like and $3d^9$-like superconducting nickelates. Using first-principles many-body theory, we explain its experimental 50\,meV charge gap as originating from a new type of correlated (quasi-)insulator. Flat-band electrons of Ni-$d_{z^2}$ character become localized from scattering with orbital-selective Mott-localized Ni-$d_{x^2-y^2}$ electrons, by trading in residual hopping energy for a gain in local exchange energy in a ferromagnetic Kondo-lattice scenario. Most importantly, the flat-band electrons offer another route to unconventional superconductivity in nickelates at ambient pressure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19617v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Frank Lechermann, Steffen B\"otzel, Ilya M. Eremin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-body contact of a Bose gas near the superfluid--Mott-insulator transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14884v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The two-body contact is a fundamental quantity of a dilute Bose gas that relates the thermodynamics to the short-distance two-body correlations. For a Bose gas in an optical lattice, near the superfluid--Mott-insulator transition, we show that a ``universal'' contact $C_{\rm univ}$ can be defined from the singular part $P-P_{\rm MI}$ of the pressure ($P_{\rm MI}$ is the pressure of the Mott insulator). Its expression $C_{\rm univ}=C_{\rm DBG}(|n-n^{\rm MI}|,a^*)$ coincides with that of a dilute Bose gas provided we consider the effective ``scattering length'' $a^*$ of the quasi-particles at the quantum critical point (QCP) rather than the scattering length in vacuum, and the excess density $|n-n^{\rm MI}|$ of particles (or holes) with respect to the Mott insulator. Close to the transition, we find that the singular part $n^{\rm sing}_{\bf k} = n_{\bf k} - n^{\rm MI}_{\bf k}$ of the momentum distribution exhibits a high-momentum tail of the form $Z_{\rm QP} C_{\rm univ}/|{\bf k}|^4$ over a broad region of the Brillouin zone, where $Z_{\rm QP}$ is the quasi-particle weight of the elementary excitations at the QCP. Our results demonstrate that the notion of contact extends to strongly correlated lattice bosons, and we argue that the contact $C_{\rm univ}$ can be measured in state-of-the-art experiments on Bose gases in optical lattices and magnetic insulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14884v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/35w3-7snk</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 112, L041301 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Moksh Bhateja, Nicolas Dupuis, Adam Ran\c{c}on</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong-coupling RPA theory of a Bose gas near the superfluid--Mott-insulator transition: universal thermodynamics and two-body contact</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14887</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14887v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a strong-coupling expansion of the Bose-Hubbard model based on a mean-field treatment of the hopping term, while onsite fluctuations are taken into account exactly. This random phase approximation (RPA) describes the universal features of the generic Mott-insulator--superfluid transition (induced by a density change) and the superfluid state near the phase transition. The critical quasi-particles at the quantum critical point have a quadratic dispersion with an effective mass $m^*$ and their mutual interaction is described by an effective $s$-wave scattering length $a^*$. The singular part of the pressure takes the same form as in a dilute Bose gas, provided we replace the boson mass $m$ and the scattering length in vacuum $a$ by $m^*$ and $a^*$, and the density $n$ by the excess density $|n-n_{\rm MI}|$ of particles (or holes) with respect to the Mott insulator. We define a ``universal'' two-body contact $C_{\rm univ}$ that controls the high-momentum tail $\sim 1/|{\bf k}|^4$ of the singular part $n^{\rm sing}_{\bf k}$ of the momentum distribution. We also apply the strong-coupling RPA to a lattice model of hard-core bosons and find that the high-momentum distribution is controlled by a universal contact, in complete agreement with the Bose-Hubbard model. Finally, we discuss a continuum model of bosons in an optical lattice and define two additional two-body contacts: a short-distance ``universal'' contact $C_{\rm univ}^{\rm sd}$ which controls the high-momentum tail of $n^{\rm sing}_{\bf k}$ at scales larger than the inverse lattice spacing, and a ``full'' contact $C$ which controls the high-momentum tail of the full momentum distribution $n_{\bf k}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14887v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/zhpw-crqc</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 112, 043304 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Dupuis, Moksh Bhateja, Adam Ran\c{c}on</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermoelectric properties of magic angle twisted bilayer graphene-superconductor hetero-junction: effect of valley polarization and trigonal warping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15882v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We theoretically investigate the thermoelectric properties (electronic contribution) of a normal-superconductor (NS) hybrid junction, where the normal region consists of magic-angle twisted bilayer graphene (MATBG). The superconducting region is characterized by a common $s$-wave superconductor closely proximitized to the MATBG. We compute various thermoelectric coefficients, including thermal conductance, thermopower, and the figure of merit ($zT$), using the scattering matrix formalism. These results are further supported by calculations based on a lattice-regularized version of the effective Hamiltonian. Additionally, we explore the impact of trigonal warping and valley polarization on the thermoelectric coefficients. Notably, we find a significant variation in $zT$ as a function of these parameters, reaching values as high as 2.5. Interestingly, we observe a violation of the Wiedemann-Franz law near the charge neutrality point with the superconducting correlation, indicating that MATBG electrons behave as slow Dirac fermions in this regime. This observation is further confirmed by the damped oscillatory behavior of the thermal conductance as a function of the barrier strength when an insulating barrier is modelled at the interface of the NS junction. Beyond theoretical insights, our findings suggest new possibilities for thermoelectric applications using MATBG based NS junctions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15882v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kamalesh Bera, Pritam Chatterjee, Priyanka Mohan, Arijit Saha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Realization of strain induced multiple topological phases in Cu$_2$SnS$_3$: An $ab$-$initio$ study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12722v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The search of multiple topological phases (TPs) and their transitions by tuning different parameters through chemical substitutions, electric field, magnetic field, strain and Floquet engineering, etc has garnered a widespread attention in recent time. In spite of great effort, the observations of multiple TPs in a single material and multiple TP transitions in the presence of one parameter remain elusive. Here we demonstrate the presence of multiple TPs and their transitions with uniaxial compressive strain (UCS) in orthorhombic Cu$_2$SnS$_3$ by using $state$-$of$-$the$-$art$ $ab$-$initio$ calculations. In the absence of spin-orbit coupling (SOC), the Cu$_2$SnS$_3$ exhibits a single (type-II) nodal-ring and in the presence of SOC, it hosts Weyl phase with seven Weyl points (three at $\Gamma$ and four at general positions) along with nodal arcs. On the application of UCS, it remains type-II nodal-ring $&lt;5.5$\%, which further evolves into type-III nodal-ring for $5.5\% \leq$ UCS $&lt;5.6$\%. Interestingly, at 5.6\% of UCS, it shows Weyl phase with four Weyl nodes even in the absence of SOC. All the above-mentioned seven Weyl points persist below $5$\% of UCS. For 5\% $\leq$ UCS $&lt;5.6$\%, four Weyl points (at general positions) disappear and nodal-arcs remain intact in all the studied range of UCS. The TPs observed in the absence of SOC appears to arise due to the presence of strain driven topological flat band, which is typically reported to be seen in kagome and Lieb lattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12722v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prakash Pandey, Sudhir K. Pandey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonequilibrium Statistics of Biased Kondo Resonance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14400</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14400v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Numerical renormalization group (NRG) is formulated for nonequilibrium steady-state by converting finite-lattice many-body eigenstates into scattering states. Extension of the full-density-matrix NRG for a biased Anderson impurity model, simplified by formulating with the original orbital basis as the Hamiltonian, enables detailed studies of the sub-Kondo spectral evolution in the zero-temperature limit, confirming the double-resonance structure at bias of the Kondo energy scale $T_K$. The distribution shows distinct multi-scale spectral features at energy $\omega$ below the Kondo scale ($\omega\lesssim T_K$) and near the bias ($\omega\gtrsim V$), leading to the nonequilibrium temperature $T_{\rm loc}$ local to the Kondo dot scaling as $k_BT_{\rm loc}\approx V$ for $V\gg T_K$. The current-voltage relation in the low-temperature limit ($T\ll T_K$) deviates from the unitary limit as the bias exceeds the Kondo scale ($V/2\gtrsim T_K$) and reaches the current saturation regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14400v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jong E. Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Hermitian band topology in twisted bilayer graphene aligned with hexagonal boron nitride</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00566v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Utilizing the established Bistritzer-MacDonald model for twisted bilayer graphene (tBLG), we theoretically investigate the non-Hermitian (NH) topological properties of this in the presence of non-reciprocal (NR) hopping on both layers and hexagonal boron nitride (hBN) induced mass term incorporated only on the top layer of the tBLG system. It is well known that the hBN mass term breaks the \(C_{2}\) symmetry of tBLG and gaps out the Dirac cones inducing a valley Hall insulating phase. However, when NR hopping is introduced, this system transits into a NH valley Hall insulator (NH-VHI). Our analysis reveals that, in the chiral limit, the bandwidth of the system vanishes under NH effects for a wide range of twist angles. Such range can be visibly expanded as we enhance the degree of non-Hermiticity (\(\beta\)). At the magic angle, we observe that enhancement of \(\beta\) inflates the robustness of the gapless Dirac points, requiring a progressively larger mass term to induce a gap in the NH tBLG system. Additionally, for a fixed NH parameter, we identify a range of twist angles where gap formation is significantly obstructed. To explore the topological aspects of the NH tBLG, we analyze the direct band gap in the Moir\'e Brillouin zone (mBZ) and compute the Chern number for the NH system. We find that the corresponding topological phase transitions are associated with corresponding direct band gap closings in the mBZ.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00566v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 155411 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kamalesh Bera, Debasish Mondal, Arijit Saha, Debashree Chowdhury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical Signatures of Band Flatness and Anisotropic Quantum Geometry in Magic-Angle Twisted Bilayer Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18152</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.18152v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the degree of band flatness and anisotropic quantum geometry in magic-angle twisted bilayer graphene by varying the twist angle and the lattice relaxation through optical conductivity. We show that the degree of band flatness and its quantum geometry can be revealed through optical absorption and its resulting optical bounds, which are based on the trace condition in quantum geometry. More specifically, the narrow and isolated peak of optical absorption in the low-energy region provides information about the bandwidth between two flat bands. When this value is smaller than the electron interaction, it serves as a critical condition for the emergence of flat band superconductivity. Furthermore, optical absorption also provides the gap value between the flat band and the dispersive band, and when this gap is larger than the electron interaction, it facilitates the realization of fractional Chern insulating phases. We show that the narrow and isolated peak of optical bound near zero energy decreases as lattice relaxation increases. Meanwhile, we demonstrate that the imaginary part of generalized optical Hall conductivity reveals the vanishing of the negative part of Berry curvature, which is enforced by the refined trace-determinant inequality. Accordingly, we show that the total amount of the negative part and component of the Berry curvature approaches zero in the single ideal flat-band case. In contrast, when considering all occupied bands, the total amount of the negative component is slightly different from zero. Finally, we demonstrate that the condition of vanishing of flat band velocities and the emergent chiral symmetry are sufficient for the saturation of the trace condition, which pertains to the isotropic case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.18152v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pok Man Chiu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coherent Optical Control of Electron Dynamics in Patterned Graphene Nanoribbons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.08678v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The field of coherent electronics aims to advance electronic functionalities by utilizing quantum coherence. Here, we demonstrate a viable and versatile methodology for controlling electron dynamics optically in graphene nanoribbons. In particular, we propose to flatten the band structure of armchair graphene nanoribbons via control electrodes, arranged periodically along the extended direction of the nanoribbon. This addresses a key mechanism for dephasing in solids, which derives from the momentum dependence of the energy gap between the valence and the conduction band. We design an optimal driving field pulse to produce collective Rabi oscillations between these bands, in their flattened configuration. As an example for coherent control, we show that these optimized pulses can be used to invert the entire electronic band population by a $\pi$ pulse in a reversible fashion, and to create a superposition state via a $\pi/2$ pulse, which generates an alternating photocurrent. Our proposal consists of a platform and methodological approach to optically control the electron dynamics of graphene nanoribbons, paving the way toward novel coherent electronic and quantum information processing devices in solid-state materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.08678v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riek H. R\"ustemeier, H. P. Ojeda Collado, Ludwig Mathey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Breakdown of the Kirchhoff's law of thermal radiation by a spatiotemporally modulated nonreciprocal metasurface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00463</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00463v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Kirchhoff's law of thermal radiation, which dictates that the emissivity of a surface equals its absorptivity under thermal equilibrium, which dictates that the emissivity of a surface equals its absorptivity under thermal equilibrium, fundamentally limits the efficiency of photonic systems by enforcing reciprocal energy exchange between source and detector. Breaking this reciprocity is particularly important for advancing photonic devices for energy conversion, radiative cooling, and mid-infrared sensing and imaging. Driven by the growing need for photonic platforms to overcome reciprocity constraints, we present the first demonstration of spatiotemporally modulated nonreciprocal metasurfaces operating at mid-infrared frequencies suitable for the violation of the Kirchhoff's law at room temperature. We fabricate a graphene-based integrated photonic structure and experimentally demonstrate nonreciprocal reflection from a metasurface modulated at gigahertz frequencies. We develop a theoretical framework to relate nonreciprocal scattering under spatiotemporal modulation with unequal absorptivity and emissivity for violation of the spectral directional Kirchhoff's law. Our experiment and theory imply effective decoupling of absorption and emission channels by breaking time-reversal symmetry at thermal wavelengths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00463v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anatoly Efimov, Chun-Chieh Chang, Simo Pajovic, Wilton J. M. Kort-Kamp, Dongsung Kim, Hou-Tong Chen, Diego A. R. Dalvit, Abul K. Azad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Symmetries and Deformations of Symmetric Product Orbifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12180v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct generalized symmetries in two-dimensional symmetric product orbifold CFTs $\text{Sym}^N(\mathcal{T}),$ for a generic seed CFT $\mathcal{T}$. These symmetries are more general than the universal and maximally symmetric ones previously constructed. We show that, up to one fine-tuned example when the number of copies $N$ equals four, the only symmetries that can be preserved under twisted sector marginal deformations are invertible and maximally symmetric. The results are obtained in two ways. First, using the mathematical machinery of $G$-equivariantization of fusion categories, and second, via the projector construction of topological defect lines. As an application, we classify all preserved symmetries in symmetric product orbifold CFTs with the seed CFT given by any $A$-series $\mathcal{N}=(2,2)$ minimal model. We comment on the implications of our results for holography.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12180v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nathan Benjamin, Suzanne Bintanja, Yu-Jui Chen, Michael Gutperle, Conghuan Luo, Dikshant Rathore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
