<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 05:00:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Transport Spectroscopy of Pseudomagnetic Field in Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.14888v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nonuniform strain in graphene acts as a valley-dependent gauge field, generating pseudomagnetic fields (PMFs) that mimic real magnetic fields but preserve global time-reversal symmetry. While local probes have visualized such fields, their quantitative detection via macroscopic transport has remained elusive. Here, we demonstrate that high-mobility graphene exhibits distinct beating patterns in Shubnikov-de Haas oscillations, arising from valley-resolved Landau quantization under different effective magnetic fields. Systematic analysis of these beats reveals universal quadratic and linear scaling of the node carrier density and Landau level filling factor with the applied magnetic field, enabling the extraction of PMFs as small as a few millitesla. Our results establish quantum oscillation spectroscopy as a robust and broadly applicable probe of strain-induced gauge fields in Dirac materials, opening avenues for mechanically tunable valleytronic and straintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.14888v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Divya Sahani, Sunit Das, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Amit Agarwal, Aveek Bid</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-lattice coupling induced chiral phonons and their signature in Raman Circular Dichroism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14902</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.14902v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent Raman experiments on the Kitaev material $\alpha$-RuCl$_3$ have reported a finite Raman circular dichroism (RCD), revealing chiral phonon behaviour not expected from lattice symmetry alone. To explain this observation, we develop a diagrammatic framework for the spin-phonon coupled Kitaev model. We demonstrate that bare phonons contribute no RCD, but coupling to the chiral spin excitation continuum under an applied magnetic field renormalizes the phonon propagator, mixing real polarization eigenvectors into complex superpositions with finite angular momentum. This interaction-induced modification generates a nonzero RCD accompanied by characteristic Fano line shapes in the Raman response, reflecting interference between discrete phonons and the continuum. The resulting signal grows with magnetic field strength, consistent with experiment, and directly tracks the field-induced chirality of the spin sector. More broadly, our results establish RCD as a powerful probe of interaction-induced chiral phonons in correlated quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.14902v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eduard Koller, Swetlana Swarup, Johannes Knolle, Natalia B. Perkins</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5d-mediated indirect exchange and effective spin Hamiltonians in Ce triangular-lattice delafossites</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.14904v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Anisotropic intersite exchange interactions in frustrated rare-earth magnets are difficult to assess both theoretically and experimentally. Here, we propose an ab initio force-theorem framework combining the quasi-atomic Hubbard-I approach to 4f correlations with a static mean-field treatment of the on-site intershell Coulomb interaction between rare-earth 4f and 5d states to simultaneously capture both 4f superexchange and 5d-mediated indirect exchange. Applying it to the triangular lattice Ce delafossites CsCeSe$_2$, KCeS$_2$, and RbCeO$_2$, we find that the indirect exchange dominates in the selenide, the superexchange in the oxide, while both mechanisms contribute almost equally in the sulfide. The magnetic exciation spectra of CsCeSe$_2$ and KCeS$_2$ evaluated from the calculated spin Hamiltonains are in good qualitative and quantitative agreement with experimental data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.14904v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonid V. Pourovskii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automated laboratory x-ray diffractometer and fluorescence spectrometer for high-throughput materials characterization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14905</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.14905v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The increasing importance of artificial intelligence and machine learning in materials research has created demand for automated, high-throughput characterization techniques capable of generating large data sets rapidly. We describe here a new instrument for simultaneous x-ray diffraction and x-ray fluorescence spectroscopy optimized for high-throughput studies of combinatorial specimens. A bright, focused, high-energy x-ray beam 24 keV) combined with a pixel array area detector allows rapid, spatially-resolved (250 {\mu}m) transmission diffraction measurements through thick (100 {\mu}m) specimens of structural metals with exposure times as short as 1 s. Simultaneously, a silicon drift detector records x-ray fluorescence from the specimen for spatially-resolved measurement of composition. Specimen handling is fully automated, with a robot inside the x-ray enclosure manipulating the sample for measurements at different locations. Data orchestration is also automated, with data streamed off the instrument and processed autonomously. In this paper we assess the performance of the instrument in terms of throughput, resolution, and signal-to-noise ratio, and provide an example of its capabilities through a combinatorial study of Cu-Ti alloys to demonstrate rapid data set creation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.14905v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hyun Sang Park, Timothy Long, Michael Wall, Alexander deJong, Ali Rachidi, Kacper Kowalik, David Elbert, Robert Drake, Todd C. Hufnagel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hydrothermal Synthesis of Ultra-high Aspect Ratio $\beta$-NaYF Disks via Methyliminodiacetic Acid (MIDA)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14933</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.14933v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The hexagonal $\beta$-phase of sodium yttrium fluoride (NaYF) is a leading host material for lanthanide upconversion and anti-Stokes fluorescence laser refrigeration based on its low phonon energies and high upconversion efficiency. Recently experiments have been proposed to use this material as an optically-levitated sensor of high-frequency gravitational waves. In order to maximize signal-to-noise in this experiment, the NaYF sensor must have both a two-dimensional, disk-like morphology and also a large mass. Here we report a novel hydrothermal process based on the chelation ligand methylimidodiacetic acid (MIDA) to realize hexagonal $\beta$-NaYF prisms with corner-to-corner diameters up to 44 $\mathrm{\mu m}$ while keeping the height around 1 $\mathrm{\mu m}$. The surface quality is comparable to particles synthesized with EDTA based on atomic force microscopy (AFM) measurements. Unlike particles synthesized with EDTA the $\beta$-NaYF particles show no lensing based on curvature of the hexagonal basal plane. Single crystal X-ray diffraction data were refined to the P-62c (#190) space group which to the best of our knowledge has not been reported in the literature. One of six 44 $\mathrm{\mu m}$ $\beta$-NaYF disks doped with 10% ytterbium showed laser refrigeration of ($-4.9 \pm 1.0$) K suggesting future applications in both levitated optomechanics and microoptics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.14933v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lars Forberger, Jacob T. Baillie, Zhaojie Feng, Rachel E. Gariepy, Sankhya Hirani, Daniel R. Gamelin, Shuai Zhang, Werner Kaminsky, Peter J. Pauzauskie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photoemission tomography of excitons in 2D systems: momentum-space signatures of correlated electron-hole wave functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14956</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.14956v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The momentum-space signatures of excitons can be experimentally accessed through time-resolved (pump-probe) photoelectron spectroscopy. In this work, we develop a computational framework for exciton photoemission orbital tomography (exPOT) in periodic systems, enabling the simulation and interpretation of experimental observables within many-body perturbation theory. By connecting the $GW$+Bethe-Salpeter Equation (BSE) approach to photoemission tomography, our formalism captures exciton photoemission in periodic systems, explicitly incorporating photoemission matrix element effects induced by the probe pulse. The correlated nature of electrons and holes introduces distinct consequences for excitonic photoemission, including a dependence on pump pulse polarization. Using the prototypical two-dimensional material hexagonal boron nitride, we demonstrate these effects and show how our framework extends to excitons with finite center-of-mass momentum, making it well-suited to studying momentum-dark excitons. This provides valuable insights into the microscopic nature of excitonic phenomena in quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.14956v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siegfried Kaidisch, Amir Kleiner, Sivan Refaely-Abramson, Peter Puschnig, Christian S. Kern</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterizing entanglement at finite temperature: how does a "classical" paramagnet become a quantum spin liquid?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15144</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15144v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum spin liquids (QSL) are phases of matter which are distinguished not by the symmetries they break, but rather by the patterns of entanglement within them. Although these entanglement properties have been widely discussed for ground states, the way in which QSL form at finite temperature remains an open question. Here we introduce a method of characterizing both the depth and spatial structure of entanglement, and use this to explore how patterns of entanglement form as temperature is reduced in two widely studied models of QSL, the Kitaev honeycomb model, and the spin-1/2 Heisenberg antiferromagnet on a Kagome lattice. These results enable us to evaluate both the temperature at which spins within the high-temperature paramagnet first become entangled, and the temperature at which the system first develops the structured, multipartite entanglement characteristic of its QSL ground state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15144v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Snigdh Sabharwal, Matthias Gohlke, Paul Skrzypczyk, Nic Shannon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wannier based analysis of the direct-indirect bandgap transition by stacking MoS$_2$ layers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15178</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15178v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Molybdenum disulfide (MoS$_2$), a layered van der Waals material, has attracted considerable attention as a promising alternative to graphene for applications in field-effect transistors and nanophotonic devices because of its sizable band gap, high carrier mobility, large on/off ratio, and strong photoluminescence efficiency. A particularly intriguing property of MoS$_2$ is the transition of its band gap character with layer thickness: while the monolayer exhibits a direct gap, the band gap becomes indirect in multilayer and bulk forms. To clarify the microscopic mechanism behind this transition, we performed first-principles calculations combined with Wannier-based modeling, focusing on the roles of atomic orbitals and interlayer interactions. While orbitals oriented perpendicular to the plane -- such as Mo-$d_{z^2}$ and S-$p_z$ -- have been considered the primary contributors, our analysis reveals that in-plane $p_x$ and $p_y$ orbitals of S atoms also play a significant role. These findings highlight the importance of both out-of-plane and in-plane orbital contributions in governing the electronic structure of layered MoS$_2$, providing deeper insight into its band gap engineering for future device applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15178v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shunsuke Hirai, Ibuki Terada, Michi-To Suzuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photoinduced topological phase transition in monolayer 1T$^\prime$-MoS$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15268</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15268v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the nonequilibrium topological phases of monolayer 1T$^\prime$--MoS$_2$ under high-frequency circularly polarized driving using a low-energy $k\!\cdot\!p$ Hamiltonian combined with a van Vleck expansion. The off-resonant field generates spin- and valley-dependent mass corrections that reshape the Berry curvature profile and shift the conditions for band inversion. By evaluating the quasienergy bands, Berry curvatures, Hall conductivities, and spin- valley-resolved Chern numbers, we identify a sequence of light-controlled topological transitions marked by well-defined gap closings. Depending on the Floquet coupling strength and the electric-field parameter, the system evolves between the equilibrium quantum spin Hall (QSH) state and a set of driven phases including spin-polarized quantum Hall insulator (S-QHI), quantum valley Hall (QVH or BI) and photo-induced quantum Hall insulator (P-QHI) regimes. The results establish 1T$^\prime$--MoS$_2$ as a tunable platform where circular driving selectively manipulates spin and valley degrees of freedom, enabling controlled access to non-equilibrium topological phases in transition-metal dichalcogenides.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15268v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Mortezaei Nobahari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On flat bands in the $J_1$-$J_2$-$J_3$ XXZ sawtooth chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15461</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15461v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a generalization of the XXZ model on the sawtooth spin chain with Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interactions in which all exchange constants (symmetric, antisymmetric and axial anisotropy) are different for the three different bonds of each triangle.
  We derive and resolve algebraic constraints on the exchange constants ensuring the appearance of a flat band in the one-magnon spectrum.
  The properties of the corresponding flat magnon bands and localized magnon states are analyzed.
  We further construct the mapping of the flat-band conditions for the Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya constants onto the Katsura-Nagaosa-Balatsky parameters.
  Based on the mapping the possibility of the electric field driven flat bands with aid of the magnetoelectric coupling is examined.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15461v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vadim Ohanyan, Johannes Richter, Michael Sekania, Lucas Giambattista, Alexei Andreanov, Marcus Kollar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long-Range Magnetic Order in Structurally Embedded Mesospin Metamaterials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15483</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15483v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Engineered assemblies of interacting magnetic elements-magnetic metamaterials-provide a powerful route to tailor collective magnetic order and dynamics. By structuring matter at the mesoscale, they bridge atomic magnetism and macroscopic functionality, enabling emergent behaviour inaccessible in conventional materials. However, realizing large-area metamaterials that combine high morphological uniformity with intrinsic long-range order has remained challenging, largely due to the structural disorder inherent to lithographic fabrication. Here we demonstrate a scalable route to structurally and magnetically coherent metamaterials by embedding iron-ions to form mesospins within a non-magnetic thin film palladium host matrix. Using controlled implantation, we realize morphologically uniform arrays that spontaneously develop extended antiferromagnetic order in the as-fabricated state - without the need of external annealing or field cycling. Resonant X-ray scattering and microscopy reveal sharp magnetic Bragg peaks modulated by the mesospin form factor, evidencing long-range antiferromagnetic order coupled to structural coherence. This embedded architecture establishes a platform for exploring coherent spin-photon interactions and functional X-ray scattering in magnetic metamaterials free from lithographic topography and disorder.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15483v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christina Vantaraki, Oier Bikondoa, Mat\'ias P. Grassi, Brindaban Ojha, Alkaios Stamatelatos, Natalia Kwiatek-Maroszek, Miguel Angel Ni\~no Orti, Michael Foerster, Thomas Saerbeck, Daniel Primetzhofer, Max Wolff, Nicolas Jaouen, Thomas P. A. Hase, Vassilios Kapaklis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atomic Visualization of Bulk and Surface Superconductivity in Weyl Semimetal {\gamma}-PtBi2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15538</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15538v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A bulk superconductor hosting intrinsic surface superconductivity provides a unique platform to study Majorana bound states. The superconductor, trigonal {\gamma}-PtBi2, is a promising candidate, as surface superconducting gaps and topological surface states have been observed. However, the simultaneous presence of bulk and surface superconductivity has not been resolved. Here, we directly visualize coexisting bulk and surface superconducting gaps in trigonal PtBi2 by using ultra-low-temperature scanning tunneling microscopy/spectroscopy. The bulk gap is {\Delta} ~ 0.053 meV with a critical temperature (Tc) ~ 0.5 K and a critical field below 0.01 T, accompanied by a vortex lattice and bound states, yielding a coherence length of ~200 nm. Remarkably, certain surface regions show a much larger gap of {\Delta} ~ 0.42 meV, persisting up to Tc ~ 3 K and surviving magnetic fields up to 2 T, yet lacking a static vortex lattice. This coexistence of robust surface and bulk superconductivity establishes {\gamma}-PtBi2 as a unique platform for investigating the interplay between bulk and surface Cooper pairings in superconducting topological materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15538v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chin. Phys. Lett. 42, 120708 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hao Zhang, Hui Chen, Zichen Huang, Zi-Ang Wang, Guangyuan Han, Ruisong Ma, Xiangde Zhu, Wei Ning, Chengmin Shen, Qing Huan, Hong-Jun Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Abelian Zero Modes in Fractional Quantum Hall-Superconductor Heterostructure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15547v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We discuss the emergence of non-Abelian zero modes from twist defects in Abelian topological phases. We consider a setup built from a fractional quantum Hall (FQH)-superconductor heterostructure, which effectively induces a phase transition, leading to a topological phase endowed with new anyonic symmetries, and accordingly supporting distinct types of zero modes at fixed filling. These defects are modeled at the interface between two copies of the same heterostructure arranged side by side, which produces counterpropagating modes that can be gapped by interactions that realize the anyonic symmetries. We characterize the parafermions associated with each anyonic symmetry and discuss how their presence affect the periodicity of Josephson tunneling current.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15547v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gustavo M. Yoshitome, Pedro R. S. Gomes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recent progress of scanning tunneling microscopy/spectroscopy study of pair density wave in superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15560v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A pair density wave (PDW) is a superconducting state characterized by an order parameter with finite center-of-mass momentum in the absence of an external magnetic field, thereby breaking the conventional translational symmetry in homogeneous superconductors. It is proposed that PDW emerges from magnetic interactions, strong electron-electron correlations, and their interplay with competing orders. In this review, we highlight recent advances in the detection and study of PDWs using scanning tunneling microscopy and spectroscopy (STM/STS). We focus on how the signatures of PDW have been experimentally visualized across a variety of extraordinary superconductors, including iron-based superconductors, cuprate superconductors, spin-triplet superconductors, kagome-lattice superconductors, and transition metal dichalcogenides. Beginning with an introduction to the fundamental concept of PDWs and the unique capabilities of STM/STS, particularly its atomic-scale spatial resolution and advanced data analysis techniques, we discuss key experimental findings, including the direct visualization of charge density modulations associated with PDWs. Finally, we discuss emerging challenges and future directions, aiming to inspire future research into the nature of PDWs in superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15560v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zi-Ang Wang, Bin Hu, Xianghe Han, Hui Chen, Hong-Jun Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structural phase transitions in the van der Waals ferromagnets Fe$_x$Pd$_{y}$Te$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15584v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Here, we provide a detailed study of the crystal structure and physical properties of the recently discovered vdW ferromagnet FePd$_2$Te$_2$. We find this compound has a relatively wide width of formation, and grow single crystals with compositions Fe$_x$Pd$_{y}$Te$_2$ where $x$ ranges from 0.9 to 1.1 and $y$ from 1.8 to 2.5, respectively. Temperature-dependent X-ray diffraction and transport measurements reveal that a first-order structural transition occurs in the range of $T$ = 360-420 K. Above the transition, the compounds with Pd fraction $y&gt;2$ adopt a disordered derivative of the tetragonal FeTe structure, with the Fe layer showing mixed Fe/Pd occupancy and the extra Pd atoms partially occupying interstitial sites. Below 370 K, the structure is incommensurately modulated. For $y&lt;2$, the composition Fe$_{1.1}$Pd$_{1.8}$Te$_2$ has monoclinic symmetry at room temperature that is consistent with the reported structure of FePd$_2$Te$_2$. This phase undergoes a structural transition at 420 K for which the high temperature structure is yet to be determined; however, based on the similarities with the $y &gt; 2$ compounds, we speculate that this composition also adopts a tetragonal structure above 420\,K. All compounds investigated in the Fe$_x$Pd$_{y}$Te$_2$ series show metallic behavior, with magnetic characterization indicating that they are easy-plane, hard, ferromagnets with $T_C$ spanning 98--180 K. Both the critical temperature for the structural transition and the Curie temperature are moderately suppressed with increasing Pd fraction $y$ and corresponding decreasing Fe fraction $x$, indicating that synthetic control over $x$ and $y$ paves way for the further exploration of these compounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15584v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafaela F. S. Penacchio, Siham Mohamed, S\'ergio L. Morelh\~ao, Sergey L. Bud'ko, Paul C. Canfield, Tyler J. Slade</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic quantum disorder in Yb2Ti2O7 and the quantum S=1/2 pyrochlore phase diagram</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15678v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an experimental and theoretical study of the anisotropic pyrochlore phase diagram. Inelastic field-dependent neutron scattering on Yb$_2$Ti$_2$O$_7$ shows intrinsic broadening and a flat low-energy magnon mode which is partially captured by interacting magnon models. Exact diagonalization reveals the existence of an emergent quantum phase between ferromagnetism and antiferromagnetism, in which Yb$_2$Ti$_2$O$_7$ Hamiltonian potentially resides. This behavior matches the phenomenology of quantum criticality in heavy fermion systems, and shows Yb$_2$Ti$_2$O$_7$ is a clean system which can be field-tuned from well-defined magnons to a nontrivial quantum ground state. This suggests that quantum criticality is a generic feature of the dipolar phase diagram.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15678v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shang-Shun Zhang, Anish Bhardwaj, S. M. Koohpayeh, D. M. Pajerowski, Jeffrey G. Rau, Hitesh J. Changlani, Allen Scheie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moir\'e-induced gapped phases in twisted nodal superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15708v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate the emergence of gapped phases driven by the moir\'{e} superlattice that trivialize the topological states in twisted nodal superconductors. The effect arises from umklapp tunneling between non-adjacent Dirac points in momentum space close to specific twist angles or chemical potentials, determined by the Fermi surface geometry. We confirm the robustness of the non-topological phase against interactions with self-consistent calculations and show that this gap competes with the previously predicted topological gapped phases, leading to topological phase transitions. These transitions were overlooked in prior literature, signifying the necessity of modifying the phase diagrams of topological phases exhibited in twisted nodal superconductors with and without an interlayer current. We also estimate the relevant twist angles and discuss experimental signatures, focusing on twisted Bi$_2$Sr$_2$CaCu$_2$O$_{8+x}$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15708v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin P. Lucht, J. H. Pixley, Pavel A. Volkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inhomogeneous SSH models and the doubling of orthogonal polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15527v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We analyze Su-Schrieffer-Heeger (SSH) models using the doubling method for orthogonal polynomial sequences. This approach yields the analytical spectrum and exact eigenstates of the models. We demonstrate that the standard SSH model is associated with the doubling of Chebyshev polynomials. Extending this technique to the doubling of other finite sequences enables the construction of Hamiltonians for inhomogeneous SSH models which are exactly solvable. We detail the specific cases associated with Krawtchouk and $q$-Racah polynomials. This work highlights the utility of polynomial-doubling techniques in obtaining exact solutions for physical models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15527v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Cramp\'e, Quentin Labriet, Lucia Morey, Gilles Parez, Luc Vinet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topology of contact points in Lieb-kagom\'e model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.14978</link>
      <description>arXiv:2106.14978v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We analyse Lieb-kagom\'e model, a three-band model with contact points showing particular examples of the merging of Dirac contact points. We prove that eigenstates can be parametrized in a classification surface, which is a hypersurface of a 4-dimension space. This classification surface is a powerful device giving topological properties of the energy band structure; the analysis of its fundamental group proves that all singularities of the band structure can be characterized by four independent winding (integer) numbers. Lieb case separates: its classification surface differs and there is only one winding number.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2106.14978v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjb/s10051-021-00113-y</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. B (2021) 94:132</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>G. Abramovici</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eigenstate solutions of the Fermi-Hubbard model via symmetry-enhanced variational quantum eigensolver</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15903</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15903v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Variational Quantum Eigensolver (VQE), as a hybrid quantum-classical algorithm, is an important tool for effective quantum computing in the current noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) era. However, the traditional hardware-efficient ansatz without taking into account symmetries requires more computational resources to explore the unnecessary regions in the Hilbert space. The conventional Subspace-Search VQE (SSVQE) algorithm, which can calculate excited states, is also unable to effectively handle degenerate states since the loss function only contains the expectation value of the Hamiltonian. In this study, the energy eigenstates of the one-dimensional Fermi-Hubbard model with two lattice sites and the two-dimensional Hubbard model with four lattice sites are calculated. By incorporating symmetries into the quantum circuits and loss function, we find that both the ground state and excited state calculations are improved greatly compared to the case without symmetries. The enhancement in excited state calculations is particularly significant. This is because quantum circuits that conserve the particle number are used, and appropriate penalty terms are added to the loss function, enabling the optimization process to correctly identify degenerate states. The results are verified through repeated simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15903v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shaohui Yao, Wenyu Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Optimally Accurate Lanczos Algorithm in the Matrix Product State Representation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21786v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We improve the convergence of the Lanczos algorithm using the matrix product state representation. As an alternative to the density matrix renormalization group (DMRG), the Lanczos algorithm avoids local minima and can directly find multiple low-lying eigenstates. However, its performance and accuracy are affected by the truncation required to maintain the efficiency of the tensor network representation. In this work, we propose the modified thick-block Lanczos method to enhance the convergence of the Lanczos algorithm with MPS representation. We benchmark our method on one-dimensional instances of the Fermi-Hubbard model and the Heisenberg model in an external field, using numerical experiments targeting the first five lowest eigenstates. Across these tests, our approach attains the best possible accuracy permitted by the given bond dimension. This work establishes the Lanczos method as a reliable and accurate framework for finding multiple low-lying states within a tensor-network representation</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21786v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Wang, Zhangyu Yang, Xingyao Wu, Christian B. Mendl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The planar parafermion algebra: The $\mathbb{Z}_{N}$ clock model and the coupled Temperley-Lieb algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01672</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01672v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Hamiltonian of the $N$-state clock model is written in terms of a coupled Temperley-Lieb (TL) algebra defined by $N-1$ types of TL generators. This generalizes a previous result for $N=3$ obtained by J. F. Fjelstad and T. M\r{a}nsson [J. Phys. A {\bf 45} (2012) 155208]. The $\mathbb{Z}_{N}$-symmetric clock chain Hamiltonian expressed in terms of the coupled TL algebra generalizes the well known correspondence between the $N$-state Potts model and the TL algebra. The algebra admits a pictorial description in terms of a planar algebra involving parafermionic operators attached to $n$ strands. A key ingredient in the resolution of diagrams is the string Fourier transform. The pictorial presentation also allows a description of the Hilbert space. We also give a pictorial description of the representation related to the staggered XX spin chain. Just as the pictorial representation of the TL algebra has proven to be particularly useful in providing a visual and intuitive way to understand and manipulate algebraic expressions, it is anticipated that the pictorial representation of the coupled TL algebra may lead to further progress in understanding various aspects of the $\mathbb{Z}_{N}$ clock model, including the superintegrable chiral Potts model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01672v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Remy Adderton, Murray T. Batchelor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Light Induced Quantum Anomalous Hall Effect in Cubic Rashba Spin-Orbit Coupled Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11228</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.11228v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate topological phase transitions in a two-dimensional electron system with cubic Rashba spin-orbit coupling driven by circularly polarized light. Within the Floquet framework, we demonstrate that light-matter interaction induces nontrivial band topology characterized by a quantized anomalous Hall response, with Chern insulating phases of C = 0, 1, and 3. These transitions are governed by gap closings at high-symmetry points in the Brillouin zone, controlled by the intensity and energy of the incident light. Introducing a weak linear Rashba term displaces Dirac points in momentum space without modifying the topology, whereas a purely linear Rashba system remains topologically trivial (C = 0). When both linear and cubic Rashba couplings are finite, the linear term confines nonzero-Chern phases to narrow parameter windows. In contrast, incorporating a linear Dresselhaus term into the cubic Rashba system can trigger topological transitions even at small coupling strengths. These results clarify the interplay between distinct spin-orbit interactions in Floquet-engineered Chern insulators and offer experimentally relevant pathways for achieving light-controlled topological phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.11228v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Debabrata Sinha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magneto-conductivity and CME in Dirac semimetals from Keldysh technique in Landau levels basis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.16266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.16266v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Negative magnetoresistance in Dirac semimetals is conventionally considered as a manifestation of chiral magnetic effect (CME), by means of a postulated Chiral Kinetic equation. In this paper we study magnetoconductivity in large Fermi energy Dirac semimetals, in one of which (ZrTe$_5$) the effect was observed for the first time. Starting with a Hamiltonian for a semi-realistic model of such a Dirac semimetal, we apply the Non-equilibrium Diagram Technique (NDT, or the Keldysh technique) to derive the kinetic equations, to investigate the electrons relaxation due to interaction with phonons and disorder, and, finally, to calculate the DC magnetoconductivity (the longitudinal to magnetic field component of conductivity) as a function of magnetic field strength and temperature. Finally, we compare the obtained temperature dependencies with available to us experimental data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.16266v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruslan A. Abramchuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spontaneous $\pi$ flux trapping in granular rings of unconventional superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24581v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study Josephson couplings in unconventional superconductors and generalize the Sigrist-Rice formula by incorporating symmetry constraints and interface orientation disorder. Applying this framework to granular superconducting rings, we establish a no-go result that single-band chiral superconductors cannot spontaneously trap a magnetic flux. This rules out chiral $p$-wave pairing in $\beta$-Bi$_2$Pd, in light of the half-quantum flux observed in recent Little-Parks experiments. Incorporating the full crystalline and time-reversal symmetries, we show that a fully gapped helical equal-spin pairing state, naturally stabilized by spin-orbit coupling arising from local inversion-symmetry breaking, is instead favored. We further find that granular rings of such superconductors can trap a spontaneous $\pi$ flux in a manner robust against interface disorder.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24581v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junyi Zhang, Yi Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Switching perpendicular magnets for Processing-in-memory with voltage gated Weyl Semimetals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03507</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03507v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Processing-in-memory (PIM) reduces data transfer latency by rolling memory and logic elements into one compute location. As an emergent material candidate for such an architecture, we propose a strained Weyl semimetal based spin-orbit-torque random-access memory (SWSM-SOTRAM) device. The spin-orbit torque (SOT) originates from two mechanisms: (1) the inverse spin Galvanic effect (iSGE), which generates nonequilibrium in-plane spin accumulation at interfaces, and (2) a bulk spin Hall effect (SHE), which produces a transverse spin current carrying out-of-plane spin angular momentum. The latter is tunable via an exchange Zeeman field. Both effects are evaluated using the tight-binding model coupled with a nonequilibrium Green's function (TB-NEGF) formalism for quantum transport. Information write is achieved through SOT switching of an out-of-plane free magnet. A piezo attached to a magnetostrictive selector modulates the strain in the latter, leading to the rotation of the magnetization and hence the exchange Zeeman field exerted on the Weyl semimetal. This strain-controlled exchange field enables the symmetry tuning of the Weyl semimetal and modulation of its spin Hall effect. The TB-NEGF calculations of SHE and iSGE, combined with Landau-Lifshitz-Gilbert (LLG) simulations of magnetization dynamics, establish the SOT switching mechanism and demonstrate a pathway toward the SWSM-SOTRAM PIM device.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03507v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Youjian Chen, Hamed Vakili, Md Golam Morshed, Avik W. Ghosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visible and Terahertz Nonlinear Responses in the Topological Noble Metal Dichalcogenide PdTe2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11493</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11493v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Nonlinear processes can offer pathways to next-generation sensors and frequency mixing devices to overcome modern imaging, detection, and communication challenges. In this article, we report on strong second and third-order nonlinear optical responses in visible and terahertz (THz) light in single crystals of the noble metal dichalcogenide PdTe2. We find that buried conduction and valence topological surface states of PdTe2 lead to resonant enhancement of optical second-harmonic generation. On the other hand, although the nonlinear responses obtained with THz excitation are not close to this resonance, they can be clearly observed in reflection geometry, even in the presence of broadband excitation, where optical filters are not necessary to observe the odd-order higher harmonic gain. By carefully considering the radiative photocurrent framework of stimulated THz emission, we are able to extract fingerprints of both second- and third-order processes in the THz regime, and show that PdTe2 is a promising material candidate for radio frequency rectification, frequency mixing, and beam focusing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11493v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>George J. de Coster, Lucas Lafeta, Stefan Heiserer, Cormac \'O Coile\'ain, Zdenek Sofer, Achim Hartschuh, Georg S. Duesberg, Paul Seifert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
