<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 01:35:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Antiferromagnetism and Stripe Channel Order in the $\mathrm{SU}(N)$-Symmetric Two-Channel Kondo Lattice Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12311</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12311v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We carry out large-scale, sign-problem-free determinant quantum Monte Carlo simulations of the square lattice $\mathrm{SU}(N)$-symmetric two-channel Kondo lattice model at half-filling. We map out the zero-temperature phase diagram for $N = 2, 4, 6$, and $8$, as a function of the Kondo coupling strength. In the weak-coupling regime, we observe antiferromagnetic order of the localized moments. Remarkably, for $N \geq 6$, sufficiently strong Kondo coupling induces spontaneous channel symmetry breaking, forming a stripe dimerization pattern with a wave vector $\boldsymbol{k}=(\pi,0)$ alternating between channels. These findings are supported by a complementary large-$N$ saddle point analysis, which identifies the striped hybridization pattern as the energetically preferred configuration. The spatial symmetry-breaking results in an anisotropic Fermi surface reconstruction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12311v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elyasaf Y. Cohen, Fakher F. Assaad, Snir Gazit</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Putting a new spin on the incommensurate Kekul\'e spiral: from spin-valley locking and collective modes to fermiology and implications for superconductivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12320</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12320v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We revisit the global phase diagram of magic-angle twisted bilayer and [symmetric] trilayer graphene (MA-TBG/TSTG) in light of recent scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) measurements on these materials. These experiments both confirmed the importance of strain in stabilizing the predicted incommensurate Kekul\'{e} spiral (IKS) order near filling $|\nu|=2$ of the weakly dispersive central bands in both systems, and suggested a key role for electron-phonon couplings and short-range Coulomb interactions in selecting between various competing orders at low strain in MA-TBG. Here, we show that such interactions $\textit{also}$ play a crucial role in selecting the spin structure of the strain-stabilized IKS state. This in turn influences the visibility of the IKS order in STM in a manner that allows us to infer their relative importance. We use this insight in conjunction with various other pieces of experimental data to build a more complete picture of the phase diagram, focusing on the spectrum of low-lying collective modes and the nature of the doped Fermi surfaces. We explore the broad phenomenological implications of these results for superconductivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12320v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziwei Wang, Glenn Wagner, Yves H. Kwan, Nick Bultinck, Steven H. Simon, S. A. Parameswaran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Particle-hole symmetry in the pseudogap phase of moderately underdoped cuprate high temperature superconductors evidenced from joint density of states analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12568</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12568v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In conventional superconductors, the energy scale associated with the superfluid stiffness is much larger compared to the pairing energy and hence, the superconducting transition temperature (Tc) is entirely dictated by the superconducting (SC) energy gap. The phase rigidity of the SC condensate in unconventional superconductors, on the other hand, can be low enough to enable destruction of superconductivity via phase incoherence and persistence of an energy gap even at the absence of macroscopic superconductivity above Tc. This is considered a possible mechanism of the pseudogap (PG) state of cuprate high temperature superconductors (HTSCs). We have investigated the electronic energy ({\omega}) and momentum-separation vector (q) dependence of the joint density of states (JDOS), derived from the autocorrelated Angle Resolved Photoemission Spectroscopy (ARPES) data, from moderately underdoped Bi2Sr2CaCu2O8+{\delta}HTSC samples at temperatures below and above Tc. We found that q-space structure of the constant {\omega} JDOS intensity maps and the dispersions of the JDOS peaks are essentially the same both below and above Tc. Furthermore, the dispersions of the JDOS peaks above Tc are particle-hole symmetric. These observations evince similarity between the nature of the energy gap below and above Tc, which supports preformed pairing scenario for the PG state at least in the moderately underdoped regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12568v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niraj Kumar Shah, Junjing Zhao, Utpal Chatterjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revealing superconducting gap in La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$-$\delta$ by Andreev reflection spectroscopy under high pressure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12601v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The recent discovery of compressed superconductivity at 80~K in La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$-$\delta$ has brought nickelates into the family of unconventional high-temperature superconductors. However, due to the challenges of directly probing the superconducting pairing mechanism under high pressure, the pairing symmetry and gap structures of nickelate superconductors remain under intense debate. In this work, we successfully determine the microscopic information on the superconducting gap structure of La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$-$\delta$ samples subjected to pressures exceeding 20~GPa, by constructing different conductance junctions within diamond anvil cells. By analyzing the temperature-dependent differential conductance spectra within the Blonder--Tinkham--Klapwijk (BTK) model, we have determined the superconducting energy gap at high pressure. The differential conductance curves reveal a two-gap structure with $\Delta_{1} = 23~\mathrm{meV}$ and $\Delta_{2} = 6~\mathrm{meV}$, while the BTK fitting is consistent with an $s$-like, two-gap spectrum. The gap ratio $2\Delta_{s1}(0) / k_{\mathrm{B}}T_{c}$ is found to be 7.61, belonging to a family of strongly coupled superconductors. Our findings provide valuable insights into the superconducting gap structures of the pressure-induced superconducting nickelates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12601v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianning Guo, Yuzhi Chen, Yulong Wang, Hualei Sun, Deyuan Hu, Meng Wang, Xiaoli Huang, Tian Cui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct Observation of d-Wave Superconducting Gap Symmetry in Pressurized La3Ni2O7-delta Single Crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12606</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12606v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The recent discovery of superconductivity in pressure-stabilized bulk La3Ni2O7-delta, with a critical temperature (Tc) exceeding 77 K, has opened a new frontier in high-temperature superconductivity research beyond cuprates. Yet, the superconducting gap amplitude and symmetry, the key parameters to characterize a superconductor, remain elusive due to the overwhelming challenges of gap studies under high pressure. Here, we introduce in situ directional point-contact spectroscopy conducted under truly hydrostatic pressure, enabling the direct mapping of the superconducting gap in pressurized La3Ni2O7-delta single crystals. Depending on the junction orientation, differential conductance (dI/dV) spectra exhibit distinct V-shaped quasiparticle features and a sharp zero-bias peak, indicating a predominant d-wave-like pairing symmetry. Measurement of the c-axis gap amplitude Delta yields a gap-to-Tc ratio of 2Delta/kBTc = 4.2(5), positioning La3Ni2O7-delta firmly among unconventional, nodal high-Tc superconductors. These findings set stringent constraints on theoretical models for nickelate superconductors and establish a robust spectroscopic approach for understanding superconductors under extreme pressures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12606v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zi-Yu Cao, Di Peng, Seokmin Choi, Fujun Lan, Lan Yu, Enkang Zhang, Zhenfang Xing, Yuxin Liu, Feiyang Zhang, Tao Luo, Lixing Chen, Vuong Thi Anh Hong, Seung-Yeop Paek, Harim Jang, Jinghong Xie, Huayu Liu, Hongbo Lou, Zhidan Zeng, Yang Ding, Jun Zhao, Cailong Liu, Tuson Park, Qiaoshi Zeng, Ho-kwang Mao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous inverse Faraday effect for graphene quantum dots in optical vortices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12654</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12654v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Chiral photon interactions with two-dimensional (2D) materials enable unprecedented control of quantum phenomena. In this paper, we report anomalous inverse Faraday effects (IFE) in graphene quantum dots (GQDs) under linearly polarized optical vortex illumination, where transferred orbital angular momentum (OAM) generates light-induced magnetic moments. Employing our recently developed time-dependent quantum perturbation framework [Phys. Rev. B 110, 085425 (2024)], we demonstrate a counterintuitive observation: some reversed magnetic moments at off-axis positions occur-manifested as counter-rotating currents to the vortex helical wavefront. Phase-difference analysis and eigenmode decomposition resolve this anomaly, revealing that the OAM transfer efficiency is orders of magnitude weaker than its spin counterpart. This work establishes a new paradigm for optical OAM-to-magnetization conversion in quantum-engineered 2D systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12654v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zi-Yang Xu, Wei E. I. Sha, Hang Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algebraic solution and thermodynamic properties of graphene in the presence of minimal length</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12793</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12793v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Graphene is a zero-gap semiconductor, where the electrons propagating inside are described by the ultra-relativistic Dirac equation normally reserved for very high energy massless particles. In this work, we show that graphene under a magnetic field in the presence of a minimal length has a hidden $su(1,1)$ symmetry. This symmetry allows us to construct the spectrum algebraically. In fact, a generalized uncertainty relation, leading to a non-zero minimum uncertainty on the position, would be closer to physical reality and allow us to control or create bound states in graphene. Using the partition function based on the Epstein zeta function, the thermodynamic properties are well determined. We find that the Dulong-Petit law is verified and the heat capacity is independent of the deformation parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12793v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Gb\`etoho, F. A. Dossa, G. Y. H. Avossevou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamic relation for the systems with inhomogeneous distribution of particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12797</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12797v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For the system with inhomogeneous distribution of macroscopic parameters we obtain thermodynamic relation which depends on the spatial point (coordinate). In our approach, to obtain such a relation we use the basic ideas of the method of nonequilibrium statistical operator combined with the Hubbard-Stratonovich transformation. First of all, we define the thermodynamic relation for the system with homogeneous distribution of particles. Possible behavior peculiarities of systems with different character of interaction in nonequilibrium case are predicted. By saddle-point method we find the dominant contributions to the partition function and obtain all thermodynamic parameters of the systems with different character of interaction. The formations of saddle state in all systems of interacting particles at different temperatures and particle distributions have the same physical nature and therefore they can be described in the same way. We consider the systems with attractive and repulsive interactions as well as self-gravitating systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12797v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. P. Rebesh, B. I. Lev, A. G. Zagorodny</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quintuplet condensation in the skyrmionic insulator Cu2OSeO3 at ultrahigh magnetic fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12802</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12802v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report ultrahigh magnetic field Faraday rotation results on the chiral helimagnet Cu2OSeO3, the first Mott insulator showing skyrmion lattice phases and a linear magnetoelectric effect. Between 180 and 300 T, we find signatures of a Bose-Einstein condensation (BEC) of magnons, which can be described as a canted XY ferrimagnet. Due to the magnetoelectric coupling, the transverse magnetic order of the indivual Cu2+ spins is accompanied by a characteristic dome-like electric polarization which is crucial for the observation of the condensate via the Faraday rotation effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12802v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Nomura, I. Rousochatzakis, O. Janson, M. Gen, X. -G. Zhou, Y. Ishii, S. Seki, Y. Kohama, Y. H. Matsuda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond conventional half-metals: gapless states and spin gapless semiconducting behavior in X$_2$MnGa (X = Ti, Ir) Heusler compounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12803v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The search for high-performance spintronic materials motivates the exploration of Heusler alloys with unconventional electronic properties. Using density functional theory with Hubbard correction (DFT+$U$, $U = 4$~eV), we investigate X$_2$MnGa (X = Ti, Ir) alloys, which stabilize in the ferromagnetic L2$_1$-type structure with strong thermodynamic stability. Electronic structure calculations reveal contrasting behaviors: Ti$_2$MnGa transitions from a metallic L2$_1$-type phase to a spin gapless semiconductor (SGS) in the XA-type, while Ir$_2$MnGa exhibits gapless half-metallicity behavior in the L2$_1$-type but becomes half-metallic in the XA-type. The magnetic properties are governed by spd hybridization between Mn-3$d$ and X-$d$/Ga-$p$ states, which stabilizes ferromagnetism and tailors electronic states near the Fermi level. The Hubbard $U$ correction proves essential for accurately describing the correlated Mn-3$d$ electrons. These alloys combine structural stability with tunable electronic and magnetic properties, offering a promising platform for spin-polarized transport in next-generation spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12803v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. Bouteldja, N. Hacini, I. Ouadha, H. Rached</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relaxation and Its Effects on Electronic Structure in Twisted Systems: An Analytical Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13114v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Lattice relaxation profoundly reshapes electronic structures in twisted materials. Prevailing treatments, however, typically rely on large-scale density functional theory (DFT), which is computationally costly and mechanistically opaque. Here, we develop a unified analytical framework to overcome these limitations. From continuum elastic theory, we derive closed-form solutions for both in-plane and out-of-plane relaxation fields. We further introduce an analytical phase factor expansion theory that maps relaxation into the electronic Hamiltonian. By applying this framework, the relaxation-mediated single-particle and many-body topological phase transitions in twisted MoTe$_{2}$ is accurately captured, and the evolution of flat bands in magic-angle graphene is quantitatively reproduced. Our work transforms the research of moir\'e relaxation from black-box numerical fitting to an analytical paradigm, offering fundamental insights, exceptional efficiency, and general applicability to a wide range of twisted materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13114v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junxi Yu, Bingbing Wang, Cheng-Cheng Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Instant prediction of relaxation in moir\'{e} superlattices using neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13147</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13147v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The relaxation of moir\'e superlattices in twisted bilayers of transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) has been modeled using a set of neural-network-based approaches. We implemented and compared several architectures, including (i) an interpolator combined with an autoencoder, (ii) an interpolator combined with a decoder, (iii) a direct generator mapping input parameters to displacement fields, and (iv) a physics-informed neural network (PINN). Among these, the direct generator architecture demonstrated the best performance, achieving machine-level precision with minimal training data. Remarkably, once trained, this simple fully connected network is able to predict the full displacement field of a moir\'e bilayer within a fraction of a second, whereas conventional continuum simulations require hours or even days. This finding highlights the low-dimensional nature of the relaxation process and establishes neural networks as a practical and efficient alternative to ab initio approaches for rapid modeling and high-throughput screening of 2D twisted heterostructures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13147v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleksei V. Belonovskii, Elizaveta I. Girshova, Erkki L\"ahderanta, Mikhail Kaliteevski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Engineering strong correlations in a perfectly aligned dual moir\'e system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13159</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13159v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Exotic collective phenomena emerge when bosons strongly interact within a lattice. However, creating a robust and tunable solid-state platform to explore such phenomena has been elusive. Dual moir\'e systems$-$compromising two Coulomb-coupled moir\'e lattices$-$offer a promising system for investigating strongly correlated dipolar excitons (composite bosons) with electrical control. Thus far, their implementation has been hindered by the relative misalignment and incommensurability of the two moir\'e patterns. Here we report a dual moir\'e system with perfect translational and rotational alignment, achieved by utilizing twisted hexagonal boron nitride (hBN) bilayer to both generate an electrostatic moir\'e potential and separate MoSe$_{2}$ and WSe$_{2}$ monolayers. We observe strongly correlated electron phases driven by intralayer interactions and identify interlayer Rydberg trions, which become trapped in the presence of the Mott insulating state. Importantly, our platform is electrostatically programmable, allowing the realization of different lattice symmetries with either repulsive or attractive interlayer interactions. In particular, we implement the latter scenario by optically injecting charges, which form a dipolar excitonic phase. Our results establish a versatile platform for the exploration and manipulation of exotic and topological bosonic quantum many-body phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13159v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amine Ben Mhenni, Elif \c{C}etiner, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Jonathan J. Finley, Nathan P. Wilson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Band geometric transverse current driven by inhomogeneous AC electric field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13242</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13242v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a semiclassical theory for electron wavepacket dynamics in the presence of an inhomogeneous AC electric field. While static electric-field gradients are known to generate charge transport governed by the quantum metric, we show that AC field gradients induce an additional geometric current that vanishes in the DC limit. This response originates from a novel band-geometric quantity, the higher-order connection (HOC) tensor, constructed from cubic products of interband Berry connections. We derive explicit expressions for the AC current and identify the symmetry conditions under which it arises. Remarkably, inhomogeneous AC fields can generate an anomalous Hall-like response even in nonmagnetic systems. Applying the theory to Bernal-stacked bilayer graphene, we demonstrate that the HOC-induced response produces a measurable Hall current peaking at band edges. These results establish inhomogeneous AC fields as a powerful probe of higher-order band geometric quantities beyond Berry curvature and the quantum metric.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13242v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Maneesh Kumar, Sanjay Sarkar, Amit Agarwal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Odd-parity longitudinal magnetoconductivity in time-reversal symmetry broken materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13277v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetotransport measurements are a sensitive probe of symmetry and electronic structure in quantum materials. While conventional metals exhibit longitudinal magnetoconductivity that is even in a magnetic field ($B$) for small $B$, we show that magnetic materials which intrinsically break time-reversal symmetry (TRS) show an {\it odd-parity magnetoconductivity} (OMC), with a leading linear-$B$ response. Using semiclassical transport theory, we derive explicit expressions for the longitudinal and transverse conductivities and identify their origin in Berry curvature and orbital magnetic moment. Crystalline symmetry analysis shows that longitudinal OMC follows the same point-group constraints as the anomalous Hall effect, while transverse OMC obeys distinct rules, providing an independent probe of TRS breaking. In the large $B$ quantum oscillation regime, we uncover both odd- and even-$B$ contributions, demonstrating OMC beyond the semiclassical picture. Explicit calculations in valley-polarized gapped graphene show that OMC peaks near the band edges, vanish in the band gap and follow the temperature dependence of the magnetic order parameter. Our results explain the odd-parity magnetoresistance recently observed in magnetized graphene and establish OMC as a robust transport signature of intrinsic TRS breaking in metals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13277v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sunit Das, Akash Adhikary, Divya Sahani, Aveek Bid, Amit Agarwal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From higher-order moments to time correlation functions in strongly correlated systems: A DMRG-based memory kernel coupling theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13140</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13140v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce a hybrid approach for computing dynamical observables in strongly correlated systems using higher-order moments. This method integrates memory kernel coupling theory (MKCT) with the density matrix renormalization group (DMRG), extending our recent work on MKCT to strongly correlated systems. The method establishes that correlation functions can be derived from the moments. Within our framework, operators and wavefunctions are represented as matrix product operators (MPOs) and matrix product states (MPSs), respectively. Crucially, the repeated application of the Liouville operator is achieved through an iterative procedure analogous to the DMRG algorithm itself. We demonstrate the effectiveness and efficiency of MKCT-DMRG by computing the spectral function of the Hubbard model. Furthermore, we successfully apply the method to compute the electronic friction in the Hubbard-Holstein model. In all cases, the results show excellent agreement with time-dependent DMRG (TD-DMRG) benchmarks. The advantage of MKCT-DMRG over TD-DMRG is the computational efficiency, which avoids expensive real-time propagation in TD-DMRG. These findings establish MKCT-DMRG as a promising and accurate framework for simulating challenging dynamical properties in strongly correlated quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13140v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunhao Liu, Wenjie Dou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Duality defect in a deformed transverse-field Ising model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17317v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Physical quantities with long lifetimes have both theoretical significance in the study of quantum many-body systems and practical implications for quantum technologies. In this manuscript, we investigate the roles played by topological defects in the construction of quasi-conserved quantities, using as a prototypical example the Kramers-Wannier duality defect in a deformed 1d quantum transverse field Ising model. We construct the duality defect Hamiltonian in three different ways: half-chain Kramers-Wannier transformation, utilization of techniques in the Ising fusion category, and defect-modified weak integrability breaking deformation. The third method is also applicable for the study of generic integrable defects under weak integrability breaking deformations. We also work out the deformation of defect-modified higher charges in the model and study their slower decay behavior. Furthermore, we consider the corresponding duality defect twisted deformed Floquet transverse field Ising model, and investigate the stability of the isolated zero mode associated with the duality defect in the integrable Floquet Ising model, under such weak integrability breaking deformation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17317v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/ctxg-k3b6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 7, 033198, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Fei Yan, Robert Konik, Aditi Mitra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Transport and Molecular Sensing in Reduced Graphene Oxide Measured with Scanning Probe Microscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17783v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report combined scanning probe microscopy and electrical measurements to investigate local electronic transport in reduced graphene oxide (rGO) devices. We demonstrate that quantum transport in these materials can be significantly tuned by the electrostatic potential applied with a conducting atomic force microscope (AFM) tip. Scanning gate microscopy (SGM) reveals a clear p-type response in which local gating modulates the source-drain current, while scanning impedance microscopy (SIM) indicates corresponding shifts of the Fermi level under different gating conditions. The observed transport behavior arises from the combined effects of the AFM tip induced Fermi level shifts and defect mediated scattering. These results show that resonant scattering associated with impurities or structural defects plays a central role and highlight the strong influence of local electrostatic potentials on rGO conduction. Consistent with this electrostatic control, the device also exhibits chemical gating and sensing: during exposure to electron-withdrawing molecules (acetone), the source-drain current increases reversibly and returns to baseline upon purging with air. Repeated cycles over 15 minutes show reproducible amplitudes and recovery. Using a simple transport model we estimate an increase of about 40 percent in carrier density during exposure, consistent with p-type doping by electron-accepting analytes. These findings link nanoscale electrostatic control to macroscopic sensing performance, advancing the understanding of charge transport in rGO and underscoring its promise for nanoscale electronics, flexible chemical sensors, and tunable optoelectronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17783v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julian Sutaria, Cristian Staii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relativistic Mott transitions and finite-temperature effects of quantum criticality in Dirac semimetals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.04911v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Gross-Neveu-Yukawa-type models such as the chiral Ising, chiral XY, and chiral Heisenberg models, serve as effective descriptions of two-dimensional Dirac semi-metals undergoing quantum phase transitions into various symmetry-broken ordered states. Their relativistic quantum critical points govern the systems' physical behavior in the vicinity of the transition also at finite temperatures, which is strongly influenced by critical order-parameter and chiral fermion fluctuations. Here, we explore the effect of these fluctuations at zero and finite temperature, both in the Dirac phase and in the Mott phases with spontaneously broken symmetry. To that end, we set up a functional renormalization group approach, which allows us to systematically calculate the quantum phase diagrams and scaling behavior at and near quantum criticality. We explicitly estimate quantum critical exponents, calculate the quasiparticle weight of the chiral Dirac excitations, and determine the extent of the quantum critical fan. Furthermore, we expose a semi-metallic precondensation regime where order-parameter fluctuations destroy order at finite temperature and we show the related manifestation of the Coleman-Hohenberg-Mermin-Wagner theorem. For the chiral XY model, we also expose signatures of Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless physics in a system that includes strong fermion fluctuations. In view of recent experimental developments on correlated phases in highly tunable two-dimensional Dirac materials, our work aims at a more comprehensive theoretical description of relativistic quantum criticality in semi-metals, including non-Dirac-liquid behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.04911v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/7kw4-8r3m</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 115133 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mireia Tolosa-Sime\'on, Laura Classen, Michael M. Scherer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Designer three-dimensional electronic bands in asymmetric transition metal dichalcogenide heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17947</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17947v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Van der Waals materials enable the construction of atomically sharp interfaces between compounds with distinct crystal and electronic properties. This is dramatically exploited in moir\'e systems, where a lattice mismatch or twist between monolayers generates an emergent in-plane periodicity, giving rise to electronic properties absent in the constituent materials. In contrast, vertical superlattices, formed by stacking dissimilar materials in the out-of-plane direction on the nanometer scale, have received far less attention despite their potential to realize analogous emergent phenomena in three dimensions. Through angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy and density functional theory, we investigate six-to-eight-layer transition metal dichalcogenide (TMD) heterostructures constructed from pairs of stacked few-layer materials. Counterintuitively, we find that even these single superlattice units can host fully-delocalised bands, evidencing a robust coherent interlayer coupling across lattice-mismatched interfaces over extended spatial scales. We show how uncompensated semimetallic phases and energetically-mismatched topological surface states are readily and exclusively stabilized within such asymmetrical architectures. These findings establish two-component heterostructures in the intermediate layer-regime as platforms to invoke and control unprecedented combinations and instances of the diverse quantum phases native to many-layer TMDs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17947v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oliver J. Clark, Anugrah Azhar, Ben A. Chambers, Daniel McEwen, Thi-Hai-Yen Vu, M. Tofajjol H. Bhuiyan, Rodion V. Belosludov, Aaron Bostwick, Chris Jozwiak, Eli Rotenberg, Seng Huat Lee, Zhiqiang Mao, Geetha Balakrishnan, Federico Mazzola, Sarah L. Harmer, Michael S. Fuhrer, M. Saeed Bahramy, Mark. T. Edmonds</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Concise Review of Recently Synthesized 2D Carbon Allotropes: Amorphous Carbon, Graphynes, Biphenylene and Fullerene Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01877</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01877v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2D) carbon allotropes have received considerable attention due to their unique properties and potential applications in several fields, including electronics, catalysis, energy storage, and sensing. Following the experimental realization of graphene, numerous other 2D carbon structures have been proposed and, in some cases, successfully synthesized. This work presents a concise review of the recently experimentally realized 2D carbon allotropes, including graphynes, biphenylene-based networks, fullerene networks, and monolayer amorphous carbon. For each class, we discuss structural characteristics, theoretical predictions, and synthesis methods, with emphasis on the interplay between theory and experiment. We also highlight instances where experimental studies overlooked relevant theoretical contributions. Finally, we identify theoretically predicted structures that remain unexplored experimentally, suggesting opportunities for synthesis-driven investigations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01877v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ricardo Paupitz, Alexandre F. Fonseca, Mizraim Bessa, Guilherme S. L. Fabris, William F. da Cunha, Leonardo D. Machado, Marcelo L. Pereira Junior, Luiz A. Ribeiro Junior, Douglas S. Galv\~ao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Design and Optimization of Spin Dynamics in Ge Quantum Dots: g-Factor Modulation, Dephasing Sweet Spots, and Phonon-Induced Relaxation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10731</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.10731v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Accurate modeling of spin dynamics in hole-based quantum dot qubits demands high-fidelity simulations that capture realistic device geometries, material interfaces, and self-consistent electrostatics. Here, we present a comprehensive three-dimensional study of gate-defined quantum dot hole spin qubits in strained Si$_{0.2}$Ge$_{0.8}$/Ge heterostructures. In contrast to prior work relying on idealized confinement or decoupled Poisson-Schr\"odinger treatments, our approach combines self-consistent electrostatics with a four-band Luttinger-Kohn Hamiltonian to resolve spin-orbit interactions, wavefunction asymmetries, and g-tensor anisotropies in realistic device structures. We quantify the impact of device size and gate bias on wavefunction localization, electric-field-induced g-factor modulation, and identify "sweet spots" in vertical electric field where g-factor sensitivity to charge noise is minimized, enhancing spin dephasing times. Spin relaxation due to phonon coupling is also modeled, revealing size-dependent T1 behavior consistent with strong Rashba-type spin-orbit coupling and a magnetic-field scaling near $B^{-8}$. This work establishes a predictive modeling framework for optimizing spin coherence in planar Ge quantum dots and provides quantitative design guidance for scalable, electrically controlled hole spin qubits in group-IV semiconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.10731v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ngoc Duong, Daryoosh Vashaee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
