<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 04:00:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Engineering phase-frustration induced flat bands in an aza-triangulene covalent Kagome lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16126</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16126v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Pi-conjugated covalent organic frameworks (COFs) provide a versatile platform for the realization of designer quantum nanomaterials. Strong electron-electron correlation within these artificial lattices can give rise to exotic phases of matter. Their experimental realization however requires precise control over orbital symmetry, charge localization, and band dispersion all arising from the effective hybridization between molecular linkers and nodes. Here, we present a modular strategy for constructing diatomic Kagome lattices from aza-[3]triangulene (A[3]T) nodes, in which a D3h symmetric ground state is stabilized through resonance contributions from a cumulenenic linker. First-principles density-functional theory and scanning tunnelling spectroscopy reveal that the hybridization of a sixfold degenerate set of edge-localized Wannier functions in the unit cell gives rise to orbital-phase frustration-induced non-trivial flat bands. These results establish a general design principle for engineering orbital interactions in organic lattices and open a pathway toward programmable COF-based quantum materials with correlated electronic ground states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16126v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuyi Yan, Fujia Liu, Weichen Tang, Han Xuan Wong, Boyu Qie, Steven G. Louie, Felix R. Fischer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite temperature magnetic interactions from first principles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16143</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16143v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Density functional theory has demonstrated remarkable predictive power in calculating magnetic properties at zero temperature. At finite temperatures, thermally excited phonons may affect magnetism. Efficient ab-initio methods to calculate the temperature dependence of magnetic exchange interactions are still lacking despite the importance of room temperature magnetism for applications. Exchange is controlled by an interplay between metal-ligand hybridization, Hubbard repulsion, band gap, interatomic distances and bond angles, all of which change with temperature. Here we present a method to calculate the exchange interactions at finite temperatures from first principles using only two supercell calculations and quantify these mechanisms. Changes in bond angles and the band gap are identified as a primary factors. In NiO with 180-degree bonds exchange decreases with temperature, while in Cr$_2$O$_3$ with the bond angles away from 180 degrees the exchange increases by 10% at room temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16143v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ravi Kaushik, Ryota Ono, Sergey Artyukhin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cavity-induced coherent magnetization and polaritons in altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16248</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16248v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Altermagnets feature antiparallel spin sublattices with $d$-, $g$-, or $i$-wave spin order, yielding nonrelativistic spin splitting without net magnetization. We show that embedding a two-dimensional $d$-wave altermagnet in a driven optical cavity induces a finite, tunable magnetization. Coherent photon driving couples selectively to electronic sublattices, and the resulting altermagnets' symmetry-broken spin texture yields a pronounced steady-state spin imbalance -- coherent magnetization -- absent in conventional antiferromagnets for the same lattice configuration. A mean-field Lindblad analysis reveals the dominance of quadratic over linear couplings. In the strong-coupling regime, distinct polariton signatures emerge in the steady state of induced magnetization. This work demonstrates cavity control of altermagnets for spintronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16248v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohsen Yarmohammadi, Libor \v{S}mejkal, James K. Freericks</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electron Localization in Non-Compact Covalent Bonds Captured by the r2SCAN+V Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16348v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In density functional theory, the SCAN (Strongly Constrained and Appropriately Normed) and r2SCAN functionals significantly improve over generalized gradient approximation functionals such as PBE (Perdew-Burke-Ernzerhof) in predicting electronic, magnetic, and structural properties across various materials, including transition-metal compounds. However, there remain puzzling cases where SCAN and r2SCAN underperform, such as in calculating the band structure of graphene, the magnetic moment of Fe, the potential energy curve of the Cr2 molecule, and the bond length of VO2. This research identifies a common characteristic among these challenging materials: non-compact covalent bonding through s-s, p-p, or d-d electron hybridization. While SCAN and r2SCAN excel at capturing electron localization at local atomic sites, they struggle to accurately describe electron localization in non-compact covalent bonds, resulting in a biased improvement. To address this issue, we propose the r2SCAN+V approach as a practical modification that improves accuracy across all the tested materials. The parameter V is 4 eV for metallic Fe, but substantially lower for the other cases. Our findings provide valuable insights for the future development of advanced functionals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16348v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yubo Zhang, Da Ke, Rohan Maniar, Timo Lebeda, Peihong Zhang, Jianwei Sun, John P. Perdew</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stacking-tunable multiferroic states in bilayer ScI2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16379</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16379v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two-dimensional(2D) multiferroic materials hold significant promise for advancing the miniaturization and integration of nanodevices. In this study, we demonstrate that 2D bilayer ScI2, which exhibits ferromagnetic(FM) ordering within each layer, enables the tuning of interlayer magnetic coupling, ferroelectricity, and valley polarization through interlayer sliding and rotation. Our first-principles calculations show that the AA stacking configuration induces antiferromagnetic (AFM) interlayer coupling, while a 180 rotation of one layer (resulting in the antialigned AA stacking) leads to FM interlayer coupling. Moreover, the interlayer magnetic coupling can be switched between AFM and FM by translating the stacking configuration: FM in the aligned AB and BA configurations, and AFM in the antialigned AB and BA configurations. This switching behavior is driven by variations in superexchange interactions due to orbital hopping between layers. Notably, the aligned stacking exhibits ferroelectricity upon sliding, which is induced by interlayer orbital hybridization and the resulting asymmetric charge redistribution, with maximal ferroelectric behavior occurring at the AB and BA stacking configurations. Additionally, for the AB and BA stackings, spontaneous valley polarization emerges from the manipulation of the spin orientation toward the out-of-plane direction. This valley polarization arises due to inversion symmetry breaking, either through ferroelectricity (in the AB and BA stackings) or AFM interlayer coupling , in combination with spin-orbit coupling. These results highlight the intricate interplay between magnetism, ferroelectricity, and valley polarization in bilayer ScI2, with each property being tunable via stacking configuration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16379v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yaxin Pan, Chongze Wang, Shuyuan Liu, Fengzhu Ren, Chang Liu, Bing Wang, Jun-Hyung Cho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surface Reactivity in Low Temperature Deposited Amorphous/Crystalline SnO2 Thin Films: Chemisorbed Oxygen Activity and CO Oxidation Pathways Revealed by In Situ XPS and Mass Spectrometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16512v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study investigates two critical aspects of the gas sensing mechanism in metal oxide sensors: (1) the conditions that maximize chemisorbed oxygen concentration as a function of temperature and oxygen partial pressure, and (2) which surface oxygen species (chemisorbed or lattice-bound) are primarily responsible for interaction with carbon monoxide (CO). SnO2 thin films, deposited at temperatures as low as 60 C and exhibiting mixed amorphous-crystalline phases with open, tortuous porosity, were evaluated for CO sensing at 200 C. Comprehensive characterization using EIS, MS, XPS, TEM, and sensor tests revealed a strong correlation between high sensing performance and the structural/electronic features of the defect rich low-temperature-deposited SnO2. Electrochemical impedance spectroscopy (EIS) was employed to identify the optimal sensing temperature. Mass spectroscopy (MS) used to analyze the exhaust gases after sensing reactions. The films exhibited oxygen under-stoichiometry and high concentrations of chemisorbed oxygen species. In situ XPS under 1 mbar (10000 ppm) O2 and CO exposures showed that chemisorbed oxygen, not lattice oxygen, was actively involved in CO oxidation, as further confirmed by CO2 detection via Mass spectroscopy (MS). Quantitative analysis revealed dynamic surface chemical status alternations, emphasizing the pivotal role of chemisorbed oxygen in the sensing mechanism at 200 C.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16512v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Engin Ciftyurek, Zheshen Li, Klaus Schierbaum</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High harmonic generation light source with polarization selectivity and sub-100-$\mu$m beam size for time- and angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16546</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16546v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High-quality ultrafast light sources are critical for developing advanced time- and angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (TrARPES). While the application of high harmonic generation (HHG) light sources in TrARPES has increased significantly over the past decade, the optimization of the HHG probe beam size and selective control of the light polarization, which are important for TrARPES measurements, have been rarely explored. In this work, we report the implementation of high-quality HHG probe source with an optimum beam size down to 57 $\mu$m $\times$ 90 $\mu$m and selective light polarization control, together with mid-infrared (MIR) pumping source for TrARPES measurements using a 10 kHz amplifier laser. The selective polarization control of the HHG probe source allows to enhance bands with different orbital contributions or symmetries, as demonstrated by experimental data measured on a few representative transition metal dichalcogenide materials (TMDCs) as well as topological insulator Bi$_2$Se$_3$. Furthermore, by combining the HHG probe source with MIR pumping at 2 $\mu$m wavelength, TrARPES on a bilayer graphene shows a time resolution of 140 fs, allowing to distinguish two different relaxation processes in graphene. Such high-quality HHG probe source together with the MIR pumping expands the capability of TrARPES in revealing the ultrafast dynamics and light-induced emerging phenomena in quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16546v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.34133/ultrafastscience.0063</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Ultrafast Sci. 4, 0063 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Haoyuan Zhong, Xuanxi Cai, Changhua Bao, Fei Wang, Tianyun Lin, Yudong Chen, Sainan Peng, Lin Tang, Chen Gu, Zhensheng Tao, Hongyun Zhang, Shuyun Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graph Neural Network for Unified Electronic and Interatomic Potentials: Strain-tunable Electronic Structures in 2D Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16605</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16605v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce UEIPNet, an equivariant graph neural network designed to predict both interatomic potentials and tight-binding (TB) Hamiltonians for an atomic structure. The UEIPNet is trained using density functional theory calculations followed by Wannier projection to predict energies and forces as node-level targets and Wannier-projected TB matrices as edge-level targets. This enables physically consistent modeling of coupled mechanical electronic responses with near-DFT accuracy. Trained on bilayer graphene and monolayer MoS2 DFT data, UEIPNet captures key deformation-electronic effects: in twisted bilayer graphene, it reveals how interlayer spacing, in-plane strain, and out-of-plane corrugation drive isolated flat-band formation, and further shows that modulating substrate interaction strength can generate flat bands even away from the magic angle. For monolayer MoS2, the UEIPNet accurately reproduces phonon dispersions, strain-dependent band-gap evolution, and local density of states modulations under non-uniform strain. The UEIPNet offers a generalized, efficient, and scalable framework for studying deformation-electronic coupling in large-scale atomistic systems, bridging classical atomistic simulations and electronic-structure calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16605v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Moon-ki Choi, Daniel Palmer, Harley T. Johnson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite-temperature signatures of underlying superconductivity in the electron-doped Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16616</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16616v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We perform numerically exact determinant quantum Monte Carlo simulations of the Hubbard model and analyze pairing tendencies by evaluating correlation functions at the imaginary-time midpoint ($\tau=\beta/2$), which suppresses high-frequency weight and emphasizes low-energy physics. Using this diagnostic, we identify clear finite-temperature signatures of underlying $d$-wave superconductivity for electron doping, while finding no clear indication upon cooling for hole doping. Our analysis enables direct comparison with ground-state DMRG, revealing consistent real-space pairing patterns. These results provide a practical route to bridge the gap between finite-temperature and ground-state numerically exact simulations of the Hubbard model despite the fermion sign problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16616v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen O. Wang, Thomas P. Devereaux</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semiconducting nanotubes derived from a rectangular graphyne: a DFT study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16659</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16659v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Proposing new ways to organize carbon in 2D nanomaterials has been a relevant strategy in the search for systems with targeted properties for different applications. One focus is the study of fully sp$^2$ non-graphitic networks, with successfully synthesized examples. Hybrid sp-sp$^2$ systems of the graphyne family are a related approach, and many systems have the honeycomb lattice as a base model. However, other examples have been inspired by other lattices as the recently proposed r$\gamma$GY sheet, which features a semiconducting behavior with highly localized \emph{quasi}-1D states. Here, we investigate how to tune r$\gamma$GY properties by folding this sheet into nanotube forms. We elucidate mechanisms that determine their electronic structure by means of density functional theory calculations, as well as we identify the interplay involving chirality, diameter, and the emergence of dispersive/localized frontier states on gap modulation through simple extrapolated methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16659v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wjefferson Henrique da Silva Brand\~ao, Anderson Gomes Vieira, Jonathan da Rocha Martins, Andrea Latg\'e, Marcelo Lopes Pereira Junior, Eduardo Costa Gir\~ao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Switchable axionic magnetoelectric effect via spin-flop transition in topological antiferromagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16760</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16760v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The MnBi$_2$Te$_4$ material family has emerged as a key platform for exploring magnetic topological phases, most notably exemplified by the experimental realization of the axion insulator state. While spin dynamics are known to significantly influence the axion state, a profound understanding of their interplay remains elusive. In this work, we employ an antiferromagnetic spin-chain model to demonstrate that an external magnetic field induces extrinsic perpendicular magnetic anisotropy. We find that an in-plane field stabilizes the antiferromagnetic order, whereas an out-of-plane field destabilizes it and triggers spin-flop transitions. Remarkably, near the surface spin-flop transition in even-layer MnBi$_2$Te$_4$ films, the axion insulator state undergoes a sharp switching behavior accompanied by distinct magnetoelectric responses. Furthermore, we propose that this switchable axionic magnetoelectric effect can be utilized to convert alternating magnetic field signals into measurable square-wave magneto-optical outputs, thereby realizing an axionic analog of a zero-crossing detector. Our findings could open a pathway toward potential applications of axion insulators in next-generation spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16760v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiliang Fan, Rongxiang Zhu, Tongshuai Zhu, Jianzhou Zhao, Huaiqiang Wang, Haijun Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning Accelerated First-Principles Quantum Transport Simulations at Nonequilibrium State</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16878v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The non-equilibrium Green's function method combined with density functional theory (NEGF-DFT) provides a rigorous framework for simulating nanoscale electronic transport, but its computational cost scales steeply with system size. Recent artificial intelligence (AI) approaches have sought to accelerate such simulations, yet most rely on conventional machine learning, lack atomic resolution, struggle to extrapolate to larger systems, and cannot predict multiple properties simultaneously. Here we introduce DeepQT, a deep-learning framework that integrates graph neural networks with transformer architectures to enable multi-property predictions of electronic structure and transport without manual feature engineering. By learning key intermediate quantities of NEGF-DFT, the equilibrium Hamiltonian and the non-equilibrium total potential difference, DeepQT reconstructs Hamiltonians under both equilibrium and bias conditions, yielding accurate transport predictions. Leveraging the principle of electronic nearsightedness, DeepQT generalizes from small training systems to much larger ones with high fidelity. Benchmarks on graphene, MoS2, and silicon diodes with varied defects and dopants show that DeepQT achieves first-principles accuracy while reducing computational cost by orders of magnitude. This scalable, transferable framework advances AI-assisted quantum transport, offering a powerful tool for next-generation nanoelectronic device design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16878v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zili Tang, Xiaoxin Xie, Guanwen Yao, Ligong Zhang, Xiaoyan Liu, Xing Zhang, Liu Fei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature Dependence of the Momentum-Resolved Static Spin Susceptibility in a Mott-Proximate Cuprate Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16884v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents the temperature dependence of the static spin susceptibility at $\mathbf{q} = (\pi, \pi)$ and $\mathbf{q} = (\pi, 0)$ in a Mott-proximate cuprate model with an antinodal pseudogap -- a model system for high-temperature superconducting (HTSC) cuprates.
  The results show the susceptibility onset temperature tracks the critical temperature ($T_c$) of HTSCs with a comparable scale across the electron filling factor. Also, as the electron filling decreases and the chemical potential approaches the antinodal van Hove region, the susceptibility at $\mathbf{q}=(\pi,0)$ -- the axial particle-hole response -- grows markedly.
  The emergence of cuprate superconductivity correlates with a suppression of low-energy antinodal spin response and associated particle-hole excitations, which would otherwise dephase $d$-wave pairing, commonly attributed to spin fluctuations. In this context, the pseudogap partially suppresses antinodal spectral weight near $\omega = 0$, thereby reducing the low-$\omega$ particle-hole phase space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16884v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keishichiro Tanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three-Stage Synthesis of a Cobalt-Embedded Graphene-like Carbon Framework with Long-Range Atomic Order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16954v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report a three-stage synthesis of a hybrid metal-carbon 2D material, in which cobalt atoms are covalently embedded in the graphene-like carbon (GLC) matrix. The resulting material (CoGLC) exhibits a distinctive XRD pattern indicative of the ordered arrangement of cobalt atoms in the layers. Furthermore, we demonstrate the fabrication of surfactant-free conductive inks from CoGLC via electrochemical exfoliation, making it a promising candidate for applications in in flexible electronics, spintronics or electrocatalysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16954v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. G. Ryzhkova, I. Yu. Kurochkin, T. N. Rudneva, A. V. Zotov, A. V. Moiseenko, G. M. Zirnik, D. A. Vinnik, V. I. Korepanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-Field Torque Magnetometry on the Kagome Antiferromagnet Karpenkoite</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17050</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.17050v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report torque magnetometry results on single crystals of karpenkoite Co3(V2O7)(OH)2 2H2O, a model candidate for the kagome antiferromagnet. No field-induced phase transition is detected up to 45 T for B||c and B||a. Instead, the torque reveals a continuous spin reorientation toward saturation, most likely governed by a dominant Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.17050v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hibiki Kunisawa, Ryuya Watanabe, Jun-ichi Yamaura, Yoshimitsu Kohama, Toshihiro Nomura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissociative Mechanism from NH3 and CH4 on Ni-Doped Graphene: Tuning Electronic and Optical Properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.17190v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study, we employ a multi-scale computational modeling approach, combining density functional theory (DFT) and self-consistent charge density functional tight binding (SCC-DFTB), to investigate hydrogen (H2) production and dissociation mechanisms from ammonia (NH3) and methane (CH4) on pristine and nickel-doped graphene. These two-dimensional materials hold significant potential for applications in advanced gas sensing and catalysis. Our analysis reveals that Ni-doped graphene, validated through work function calculations, is a promising material for gas separation and hydrogen production. The samples with adsorbed molecules are characterized by calculating chemical potential, chemical hardness, electronegativity, electrophilicity, vibrational frequencies, adsorbtion and Gibbs energies by DFT calculations. Methane molecules preferentially adsorb at the hexagonal ring centers of graphene, while ammonia inter-acts more strongly with carbon atoms, highlighting distinct molecular doping mechanisms for CH4 and NH3. Dynamic simulations show that CH4 splits into CH3+H, with Ni-doped graphene facilitating enhanced hydrogen transmission, while NH3 dissociates into NH2+H, which may lead to N2H4 formation. Our non-equilibrium Green's function (NEGF) simulations demonstrate increased H-atom transmission on Ni-doped graphene during gas interactions. These findings suggest that Ni-doped graphene is superior to pristine graphene for applications in gas separation, hydrogen production, and high-sensitivity sensors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.17190v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.apsusc.2024.162022</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>A. Aligayev, U. Jabbarli, U. Samadova, F. J. Dominguez-Gutierrez, S. Papanikolaou, Qing Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Attaining the Ground State of Kagome Artificial Spin Ice via Ultrafast Site-Specific Laser Annealing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17416</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.17416v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Artificial spin ices (ASIs) provide a versatile platform to explore magnetic frustration and emergent phenomena. However, in kagome ASI, experimental access to the ground state remains elusive due to dynamical freezing. Here, we demonstrate a deterministic and rewritable approach to attain the ground state using ultrafast, site-selective laser annealing. By engineering sublattice-dependent optical absorption through selective capping of the nanomagnets with Cr or utilizing different nanomagnet thicknesses, we achieve selective partial demagnetization of one sublattice under a sub-coercive magnetic field, driving the system into the ground state in a single switching step. Magnetic force microscopy reveals nearly perfect long-range ordering, while heat-transfer simulations confirm the sublattice-selective excitation mechanism. This work establishes an ultrafast method to attain the kagome ASI ground state, which does not require a modification of the geometry of the ASI or the materials used for the individual nanomagnets. Beyond ground-state writing, this site-selective activation provides an important tool for controlling the magnetic states, which is important for applications such as reconfigurable magnonic crystals, neuromorphic computing and programmable nanomagnetic logic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.17416v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Pecchio, S. Sahoo, V. Scagnoli, L. J. Heyderman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybridization in van der Waals epitaxy of PtSe2/h-BN and PtSe2/graphene heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.17464v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Van der Waals (vdW) heterostructures, which combine bi-dimensional materials of different properties, enable a range of quantum phenomena. Here, we present a comparative study between the electronic properties of mono- and bi-layer of platinum diselenide (PtSe2) grown on hexagonal boron nitride (h-BN) and graphene substrates using molecular beam epitaxy (MBE). Using angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) and density functional theory (DFT), the electronic structure of PtSe2/graphene and PtSe2/h-BN vdW heterostructures are investigated in systematic manner. In contrast to PtSe2/h-BN, the electronic structure of PtSe2/graphene reveals the presence of interlayer hybridization between PtSe2 and the graphene, which is evidenced by minigap openings in the {\pi}-band of graphene. Furthermore, our measurements show that the valence band maximum (VBM) of monolayer PtSe2 is located at the {\Gamma} point with different binding energies of about -0.9 eV and -0.55 eV relative to the Fermi level on h-BN and graphene and substrates, respectively. Our results represent a significant advance in the understanding of electronic hybridization between TMDs and different substrates, and they reaffirm the crucial role of the substrate in any nanoelectronic applications based on van der Waals heterostructures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.17464v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Meryem Bouaziz, Samir El Masaoudi, Aymen Mahmoudi, Eva Desgue, Marco Pala, Pavel Dudin, Mathieu G. Silly, Julien Chaste, Fabrice Oehler, Pierre Legagneux, Jose Avila, Iann C. Gerber, Abdelkarim Ouerghi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The advancement of Brillouin Light Scattering with the assistance of nanoplasmonic structures. Enhancement and amplification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17713</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.17713v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Brillouin light scattering (BLS) is a key technique in studying magnonic systems, but its sensitivity is often limited. While nanoplasmonic systems can enhance BLS through near-field effects, we propose a novel approach for additional amplification. In this conceptual paper, we show how to actively supply energy to a surface collective electromagnetic resonance (SCR) supported by a sparse layer of metal nanoparticles on a magnetic film. Proposed methods are designed to significantly amplify the efficiency of surface-enhanced Brillouin light scattering without increasing the intensity of the primary excitation. In the proposed scheme, the pump extends the propagation length of the SCR, leading directly to BLS amplification. We analyze the conditions for such amplification, with numerical estimates indicating a potential gain of more than an order of magnitude in the surface-wave amplitude. This gain far surpasses the modest increase achievable through passive enhancement alone. These findings outline a practical pathway to achieving BLS amplification in integrated magnonic platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.17713v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Bortchagovsky, A. V. Chumak, V. Lozovski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mott vs Kondo: Influence of Various Density Functional Based Methods on the Ce Isostructural Phase Transition Mechanism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.17755v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The cerium iso-structural phase transition (gamma to alpha) is dominated by f-electron localization changes that results in a magnetic ordering change and a volume collapse. Generally, these physics are difficult to capture with ab initio and first principles methods. However, previous works have shown various methods to be successful in predicting at least some of the physics of the gamma to alpha phase transition. Therefore, here, we perform a broad survey of density functional based methods across three levels of theory and types of functions (GGA, MetaGGA, and Hybrid functionals) and compare the results, focusing on hydrostatic compression across the phase boundary at zero Kelvin. For the methods that best reproduce experimental results, we directly probe the predicted mechanisms and frame the results in the Mott/Kondo debate, assessing how the underlying methods and assumptions of different functionals can assess the physical drivers in the phase transition, providing insight into the governing dynamics of this unique phase transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.17755v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brenden W. Hamilton, Alexander R. Mu\~noz, Travis E. Jones, Benjamin T. Nebgen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Brownian SYK-Hubbard Model: from Spectral Function to Quantum Chaos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16401v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Understanding the emergence of complex correlations in strongly interacting systems remains a fundamental challenge in quantum many-body physics. One fruitful approach is to develop solvable toy models that encapsulate universal properties shared by realistic systems. In this work, we introduce the Brownian SYK-Hubbard model, which combines the all-to-all random interactions of the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev (SYK) model with on-site Hubbard-type interactions. This hybrid construction enables the study of the interplay between nonlocal random dynamics and local correlation effects: (1) As the interaction strength increases, the single-particle spectrum exhibits a transition from a single peak to a two-peak structure, signaling the onset of Mottness. (2) The spectral form factor undergoes a sequence of dynamical transitions as the evolution time increases before reaching the plateau in the long-time limit under strong Hubbard interactions. (3) The out-of-time-order correlator is computed by summing a series of modified ladder diagrams, which determines the quantum Lyapunov exponent and reveals a violation of the bound on branching time. Our results establish a new analytically tractable platform for exploring the effects of Hubbard interactions in chaotic many-body systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16401v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ning Sun, Peng Zhang, Pengfei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atomic relaxation and flat bands in strain-engineered transition metal dichalcogenide bilayer moir\'{e} systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.01112</link>
      <description>arXiv:2108.01112v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Strain-induced lattice mismatch leads to moir\'{e} patterns in homobilayer transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs). We investigate the structural and electronic properties of such strained moir\'{e} patterns in TMD homobilayers. The moir\'{e} patterns in strained TMDs consist of several stacking domains which are separated by tensile solitons. Relaxation of these systems distributes the strain unevenly in the moir\'{e} superlattice, with the maximum strain energy concentrating at the highest energy stackings. The order parameter distribution shows the formation of aster topological defects at the same sites. In contrast, twisted TMDs host shear solitons at the domain walls, and the order parameter distribution in these systems shows the formation of vortex defects. The strained moir\'{e} systems also show the emergence of several well-separated flat bands at both the valence and conduction band edges, and we observe a significant reduction in the band gap. The flat bands in these strained moir\'{e} superlattices provide platforms for studying the Hubbard model on a triangular lattice as well as the ionic Hubbard model on a honeycomb lattice. Furthermore, we study the localization of the wave functions corresponding to these flat bands. The wave functions localize at different stackings compared to twisted TMDs, and our results are in excellent agreement with spectroscopic experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2108.01112v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/75fh-xf7g</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev B 112, 155412 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sudipta Kundu, Indrajit Maity, Robin Bajaj, H. R. Krishnamurthy, Manish Jain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlocal Andreev transport through a quantum dot in a magnetic field: Interplay between Kondo, Zeeman, and Cooper-pair correlations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.11434</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.11434v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the nonlocal magnetotransport through a strongly correlated quantum dot, connected to multiple terminals consisting of two normal and one superconducting (SC) leads. Specifically, we present a comprehensive view on the interplay between the crossed Andreev reflection (CAR), the Kondo effect, and the Zeeman splitting at zero temperature in the large SC gap limit. The ground state of this network shows an interesting variety, which varies continuously with the system parameters, such as the coupling strength $\Gamma_S^{}$ between the SC lead and the quantum dot, the Coulomb repulsion $U$, the impurity level $\varepsilon_d^{}$, and the magnetic field $b$. We show, using the many-body optical theorem which is derived from the Fermi-liquid theory, that the nonlocal conductance is determined by the transmission rate of the Cooper pairs $\mathcal{T}_{\mathrm{CP}}^{} = \frac{1}{4} \sin^2 \Theta\, \sin^2 \bigl(\delta_{\uparrow}+ \delta_{\downarrow})$ and that of the Bogoliubov particles $\mathcal{T}_{\mathrm{BG}}^{}= \frac{1}{2}\sum_{\sigma} \sin^2 \delta_{\sigma}^{}$. Here, $\delta_\sigma^{}$ is the phase shift of the renormalized Bogoliubov particles, and $\Theta \equiv \cot^{-1} (\xi_d^{}/ \Gamma_S^{})$ is the Bogoliubov-rotation angle in the Nambu pseudo spin space, with $\xi_d^{} =\varepsilon_d^{}+U/2$. It is also demonstrated, using Wilson's numerical renormalization group approach, that the CAR is enhanced in the crossover region between the Kondo regime and the SC-proximity-dominated regime at zero magnetic field. The magnetic fields induce another crossover between the Zeeman-dominated regime and the SC-dominated regime. We find that the CAR is enhanced and becomes less sensitive to magnetic fields in the SC-dominated regime close to the crossover region spreading over the angular range of $\pi/4 \lesssim \Theta \lesssim 3\pi/4$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.11434v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.035404</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 109, 035404 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Masashi Hashimoto, Yasuhiro Yamada, Yoichi Tanaka, Yoshimichi Teratani, Takuro Kemi, Norio Kawakami, Akira Oguri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Reconstruction of Complex Magnetic Profiles with Minimum Prior Assumptions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18882v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding intricate magnetic structures in materials is essential for advancing materials science, spintronics, and geology. Recent developments of quantum-enabled magnetometers, such as nitrogen-vacancy (NV) centers in diamond, have enabled direct imaging of magnetic field distributions across a wide range of magnetic profiles. However, reconstructing the magnetization from an experimentally measured magnetic field map is a complex inverse problem, further complicated by measurement noise, finite spatial resolution, and variations in sample-to-sensor distance. In this work, we present a novel and efficient GPU-accelerated method for reconstructing spatially varying magnetization density from measured magnetic fields with minimal prior assumptions. We validate our method by simulating diverse magnetic structures under realistic experimental conditions, including multi-domain ferromagnetism and magnetic spin textures such as skyrmion, anti-skyrmion, and meron. Experimentally, we reconstruct the magnetization of a micrometer-scale Apollo lunar mare basalt (sample 10003,184) and a nanometer-scale twisted double-trilayer CrI3. The basalt exhibits soft ferromagnetic domains consistent with previous paleomagnetic studies, whereas the CrI3 system reveals a well-defined hexagonal magnetic Moire superlattice. Our approach provides a versatile and universal tool for investigating complex magnetization profiles, paving the way for future quantum sensing experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18882v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Changyu Yao, Yue Yu, Yinyao Shi, Ji-In Jung, Zoltan Vaci, Yizhou Wang, Zhongyuan Liu, Chuanwei Zhang, Sonia Tikoo-Schantz, Chong Zu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fitness landscape for quantum state tomography from neutron scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10502</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10502v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently, a direct connection between static structure factors and quantum ground states for two-spin interaction Hamiltonians was proven. This suggests the possibility of quantum state tomography from neutron scattering. Here, we investigate the associated fitness landscape numerically. We find a linear relationship between the mean square distances of the structure factors and the associated state overlaps, implying a well-behaved fitness landscape. Furthermore, we find evidence suggesting that the approach can be generalized to thermal equilibrium states. We also extend the arguments to the cases of applied magnetic fields and finite clusters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10502v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/x9mb-x1gz</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B, 112, L140402 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tymoteusz Tula, Jorge Quintanilla, Gunnar M\"oller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay of correlations and Majorana mode from local solution perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00889</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00889v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the quasiparticle spectrum of a hybrid system, comprising a correlated (Anderson-type) quantum dot coupled to a topological superconducting nanowire hosting the Majorana boundarymodes. From the exact solution of the low-energy effective Hamiltonian, we uncover a subtle interplay between Coulomb repulsion and the Majorana mode. Our analytical expressions show that the spectral weight of the leaking Majorana mode is sensitive to both the quantum dot energy level and the repulsive potential. We compare our results with estimations by L.S. Ricco et al. Phys. Rev. B 99, 155159 (2019) obtained for the same hybrid structure using the Hubbard-type decoupling scheme, and analytically quantify the spectral weight of the zero-energy (topological) mode coexisting with the finite-energy (trivial) states of the quantum dot. We also show that empirical verification of these spectral weights could be feasible through spin-polarized Andreev spectroscopy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00889v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-648X/ad8ea2</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys.: Condens. Matter 37 055302 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jan Bara\'nski, Magdalena Bara\'nska, Tomasz Zienkiewicz, Tadeusz Doma\'nski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractionalized Prethermalization in the One-Dimensional Hubbard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09708v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Prethermalization phenomena in driven systems are generally understood via a local Floquet Hamiltonian obtained from a high-frequency expansion. Remarkably, recently it has been shown that a driven Kitaev spin liquid with fractionalized excitations can realize a quasi-stationary state that is not captured by this paradigm. Instead distinct types of fractionalized excitations are characterized by vastly different temperatures-a phenomenon dubbed "fractionalized prethermalization". In our work, we analyze fractionalized prethermalization in a driven one-dimensional Hubbard model at strong coupling which hosts spin-charge fractionalization. At intermediate frequencies quasi-steady states emerge which are characterized by a low spin and high charge temperature with lifetimes set by two competing processes: the lifetime of the quasiparticles determined by Fermi's Golden rule and the exponentially long lifetime of a Floquet prethermal plateau. We classify drives into three categories, each giving rise to distinct (fractional) prethermalization dynamics. Resorting to a time-dependent variant of the Schrieffer-Wolff transformation, we systematically analyze how these drive categories are linked to the underlying driven Hubbard model, thereby providing a general understanding of the emergent thermalization dynamics. We discuss routes towards an experimental realization of this phenomenon in quantum simulation platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09708v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton Romen, Johannes Knolle, Michael Knap</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Strong-to-Weak Spontaneous Symmetry Breaking in Decohered One Dimensional Critical States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14221</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14221v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Symmetry breaking has been a central theme in classifying quantum phases and phase transitions. Recently, this concept has been extended to the mixed states of open systems, attracting considerable attention due to the emergence of novel physics beyond closed systems. In this work, we reveal a new type of phase transition in mixed states, termed \emph{quantum} strong-to-weak spontaneous symmetry breaking (SWSSB). Using a combination of field theory calculations and large-scale matrix product state simulations, we map out the global phase diagram of the XXZ critical spin chain under local strong symmetry preserving decoherence, which features an SWSSB phase and a trivial Luttinger liquid phase, separated by a straight critical line that belongs to the boundary Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless universality class with a varying effective central charge. Importantly, we analyze this transition from two complementary perspectives: on one hand, through the behavior of order parameters that characterize the symmetry breaking; on the other hand, from a quantum information viewpoint by studying entropic quantities and the concept of quantum recoverability. Remarkably, the SWSSB transition in our case is \emph{purely quantum} in the sense that it can only be driven by tuning the Hamiltonian parameter even under arbitrary decoherence strength, fundamentally distinguishing it from the decoherence-driven SWSSB transitions extensively discussed in previous literature. Importantly, our unified theoretical framework is applicable to a broad class of one-dimensional quantum systems, including spin chains and fermionic systems, whose low-energy physics can be described by Luttinger liquid theory, under arbitrary symmetry-preserving decoherence channels. Finally, we also discuss the experimental relevance of our theory on quantum simulator platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14221v5</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/4vs5-l54f</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PRX Quantum 6, 040311, 16 October, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yuxuan Guo, Sheng Yang, Xue-Jia Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Suppression of the charge fluctuations by nonlocal correlations close to the Mott transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13288v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the impact of nonlocal correlations on charge fluctuations in the two-dimensional single-band Hubbard model close to the Mott metal-to-insulator transition, employing the ladder dynamical vertex approximation. At half filling and for interaction strengths and temperatures where the system is in the Mott insulating phase, charge fluctuations are strongly suppressed. Under these conditions, dynamical mean-field theory (DMFT) calculations predict a strong enhancement of the charge susceptibility at small (electron or hole) doping. However, these DMFT results include only the effects of purely local correlations despite the importance of nonlocal correlations in two-dimensional systems. We have, hence, carried out ladder dynamical vertex approximation (lD$\Gamma$A) simulations which allow for the inclusion of such nonlocal correlation effects while retaining the local ones of DMFT. Our lD$\Gamma$A numerical data show that close to half filling the large uniform charge susceptibility of DMFT is strongly suppressed by nonlocal fluctuations but gradually increases with (electron) doping. At a certain doping value, charge fluctuations eventually become larger in lD$\Gamma$A with respect to DMFT, indicating that the absence of nonlocal correlations underestimates the mobility of the charge carriers in this parameter regime. This metallization effect is also reflected in an enhancement of the lD$\Gamma$A kinetic and potential energies and a corresponding reduction of the (absolute value of the) lD$\Gamma$A Matsubara self-energy with respect to DMFT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13288v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/n2g3-nv58</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 155125 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Irakli Titvinidze, Julian Stobbe, Marvin Leusch, Georg Rohringer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher-order Topological States in Chiral Split Magnons of Honeycomb Altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22996</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.22996v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We theoretically explore higher-order topological magnons in collinear altermagnets, encompassing a dimensional hierarchy ranging from localized corner modes to propagating hinge excitations. By employing antiferromagnetic interlayer coupling in bosonic Bogoliubov-de Gennes (BdG) Hamiltonian, our work reveals anisotropic surface states and spatially distributed hinge modes propagating along facet intersections. We track the adiabatic evolution of Wannier centers to identify the bulk-polarization with second-order topological magnon insulator (SOTMI), where various magnon spectra demonstrate symmetry-protected band structure beyond conventional topology. Leveraging the stability and propagative properties of hinge modes, these unconventional magnons demonstrate manipulability in atomic-scale modifications of termination. Our study integrate altermagnetism with higher-order topology, which advance magnon-based quantum computing processing energy-efficient integrated architectures and information transfer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.22996v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuan Guo, Meng-Han Zhang, Dao-Xin Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fabrication and characterization of single-crystalline CoSn (10-10) kagome metal thin films for interconnect applications: structure and anisotropic electrical resistivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21711</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.21711v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: CoSn kagome metal is a pseudo-one-dimensional electronic conductor, exhibiting low resistivity (\r{ho}) along the [0001] direction (c-axis) and significantly higher \r{ho} along other crystallographic directions. Such anisotropic conduction is expected to mitigate resistivity increases in narrow interconnect wires at advanced semiconductor technology process nodes, making CoSn a promising candidate for future interconnect applications. In this study, CoSn thin films were fabricated by magnetron sputtering, and their resistivity anisotropy was investigated with respect to crystallographic orientation. Epitaxial growth of single-crystalline CoSn(10-10) films was achieved on a Ru(10-10) buffer layer at deposition temperatures above 350 {\deg}C. The CoSn films exhibited relatively low \r{ho} along [0001], reaching 13 micro{\Omega} cm for films thickner than 50 nm, and an approximately tenfold anisotropy of \r{ho} between [0001] and [2-1-10] (a-axis), consistent with previous reports on bulk CoSn single crystals. However, the CoSn(10-10) surface exhibited pronounced roughness, attributed to three-dimensional crystal growth during sputtering, which hinders accurate evaluation of the thickness dependence of resistivity. Scanning transmission electron microscopy revealed the growth of a CoSn(10-10) single-crystal with (11-20) and (01-10) side wall facets, as well as domain boundaries within the films. These results highlight both the potential and challenges of employing CoSn kagome metal in future interconnect technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.21711v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomoya Nakatani, Nattamon Suwannaharn, Taisuke Sasaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General Many-Body Perturbation Framework for Moir\'e Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19764</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19764v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Moir\'e superlattices host a rich variety of correlated topological states, including interaction-driven integer and fractional Chern insulators. A common approach to study interacting ground states at integer fillings is the Hartree-Fock mean-field method. However, this method neglects dynamical correlations, which often leads to an overestimation of spontaneous symmetry breaking and fails to provide quantitative descriptions of single-particle excitations. This work introduces a general many-body perturbation framework for moir\'e systems, combining all-band Hartree-Fock calculations with random phase approximation (RPA) correlation energies and $GW$ quasiparticle corrections. We apply this framework to hexagonal boron nitride aligned rhombohedral pentalayer graphene and magic-angle twisted bilayer graphene. We show that incorporating RPA correlation energy and $GW$ self-energy corrections yields phase diagrams and single-particle spectra that quantitatively align with experimental measurements. Our versatile framework provides a systematic beyond-mean-field approach applicable to generic moir\'e systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19764v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Lu, Yuanfan Yang, Zhongqing Guo, Jianpeng Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong enhancement of d-wave superconductivity in an extended checkerboard Hubbard ladder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24415v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: By employing the density-matrix renormalization group method, we study an extended checkerboard Hubbard model on the two-leg ladder, which includes an intraplaquette nearest-neighbour attraction V. The simulated results show that V plays a significant role in enhancing the d-wave superconductivity when the electron density is close to half-filling. In the homogeneous case t'=t (t and t' are the intraplaquette and interplaquette hopping integrals), large critical |Vc| is required to induce the superconducting ground state. With decreasing t', |Vc| is substantially diminished and the pair state has a nearly C4 symmetry. In the extremely inhomogeneous case t'&lt;0.2t, the system transits to the d-wave superconducting phase at V\sim-0.3t and V\sim-0.4t for U=8t and U=12t, respectively, accompanying with a shift of spin and single-particle excitations from gapless to gapped type.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24415v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xichen Huang, Saisai He, Jize Zhao, Zhong-Bing Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
