<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 05:00:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Parametric Instabilities of Correlated Quantum Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07527v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Strongly correlated quantum materials exhibit a rich landscape of ordered phases with highly tunable properties, making them an intriguing platform for exploring non-equilibrium phenomena. A key to many of these phases is collective bosonic excitations, encoding fluctuations of the underlying order. In this work, we develop a general theoretical framework for parametric driving of such modes, whereby periodic modulation of microscopic parameters generates resonant two-boson processes. We show that the feasibility and strength of this drive depend sensitively on whether the targeted parameter alters the properties of the bosonic excitations vacuum, linking potential parametric instabilities directly to the fidelity susceptibility of the ground state. The driving facilitates nonthermal melting of the parent orders, as well as stabilization of novel steady states with experimentally distinct signatures. Through microscopic case-studies of correlated electronic systems, we identify promising driving knobs, highlight the role of quantum geometry in the collective modes susceptibility, and propose realistic experimental probes. Collective excitations are a powerful resource for steering correlated phases out of equilibrium, and will likely have several applications in quantum science. Our work provides the toolbox for controlling these excitations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07527v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gal Shavit, Gil Refael</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Reciprocal Zone Boundary Magnon Propagation in Cu$_2$OSeO$_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07528v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Inelastic neutron scattering in the chiral magnet Cu$_2$OSeO$_3$ reveals strong non-reciprocal effects on magnon propagation at the boundary of the nuclear Brillouin zone. The non-reciprocal response is strongest at a central position between the zone corner and edge mid-point. We explain these results using an effective linear spin-wave model. While directional effects in chiral magnets have so far only been known to exist at low momenta close to the center of the Brillouin zone, the present study shows that non-reciprocity persists at the highest possible reduced momenta. The observed magnons show very little damping within the limits of our experimental resolution, making them of great interest for the fundamental research on compact, high-frequency magnonic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07528v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Weber, Niclas Heinsdorf, Michal Stekiel, Paul Steffens, Andreas Schnyder, Christian Pfleiderer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconductivity in the two-dimensional Hubbard model revealed by neural quantum states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07566v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Whether the ground state of the square lattice Hubbard model exhibits superconductivity re- mains a major open question, central to understanding high temperature cuprate superconductors and ultra-cold fermions in optical lattices. Numerical studies have found evidence for stripe-ordered states and superconductivity at strong coupling but the phase diagram remains controversial. Here, we show that one can resolve the subtle energetics of metallic, superconducting, and stripe phases using a new class of neural quantum state (NQS) wavefunctions that extend hidden fermion de- terminant states to Pfaffians. We simulate several hundred electrons using fast Pfaffian algorithms allowing us to measure off-diagonal long range order. At strong coupling and low hole-doping, we find that a non-superconducting filled stripe phase prevails, while superconductivity coexisting with partially-filled stripes is stabilized by a negative next neighbor hopping t-prime, with |t-prime| &gt; 0.1. At larger doping levels, we introduce momentum-space correlation functions to mitigate finite size effects that arise from weakly-bound pairs. These provide evidence for uniform d-wave superconductivity at U = 4, even when t-prime = 0. Our results highlight the potential of NQS approaches, and provide a fresh perspective on superconductivity in the square lattice Hubbard model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07566v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher Roth, Ao Chen, Anirvan Sengupta, Antoine Georges</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hidden symmetry-breaking in a kagome Ising ferromagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07606</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07606v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Kagome metals can host unconventional electronic phenomena that emerge from their frustrated lattice geometry and associated band topology. Correlated electronic orders, such as charge-density waves and superconductivity, are observed to intertwine with subtle time-reversal symmetry breaking whose microscopic origin is not currently understood. Here, we provide evidence for such time-reversal symmetry breaking in the kagome metal TbV$_6$Sn$_6$ arising from staggered magnetic moments within the kagome layers. TbV$_6$Sn$_6$ consists of metallic V kagome layers separated by Tb triangular layers that host Ising ferromagnetic order. Deep in the ferromagnetic state, the Tb Ising doublet ground state should display a single, dispersionless spin-flip excitation. Instead, inelastic neutron scattering reveals two sharp excitations associated with inequivalent Tb sites, demonstrating that a symmetry-broken phase coexists with Ising ferromagnetism. No additional structural or magnetic phase transitions are detected, and first-principles calculations rule out lattice distortions as the origin of the splitting. We attribute this effect to time-reversal symmetry breaking encoded by small V moments that couple to the Tb sublattice and leave a measurable spectral fingerprint. Our results establish rare-earth local moment spectroscopy as a sensitive probe of subtle broken symmetries and highlight an unexpected interplay between kagome magnetism and rare-earth local moment magnetism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07606v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tianxiong Han, Tyler J. Slade, Liqin Ke, Qing-Ping Ding, Minseong Lee, Ryan D. McKenzie, Bing Li, Durba R. Jaishi, Yongbin Lee, Daniel M. Pajerowski, Qiang Zhang, Tao Hong, Paul C. Canfield, Yuji Furukawa, Komalavalli Thirunavukkuarasu, Aashish Sapkota, Rebecca Flint, Robert J. McQueeney</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The pseudogap and strange metal states in the square-lattice Hubbard model: a comprehensive study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07726v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To clarify the origin of the pseudogap and strange metal states as well as their mutual relationship in cuprate superconductors, a comprehensive study on the spectral function, Fermi surface, resistivity and dynamical spin susceptivity of the Hubbard model on the square lattice has been conducted by means of the ladder dual-fermion approximation with an electron self-energy correction. It is found that the appearance of these two states requires that the characteristic hole concentration below which the Mott-Heisenberg and Slater mechanisms of electron localization occurs $p_{\rm MS}$ nearly coincides with the hole concentration where the Van Hove singularity (VHS) point is placed at the vicinity of the Fermi level. When this condition is met the VHS point is pined at which the nesting condition of the antiferromagnetic (AFM) fluctuation is fulfilled almost everywhere on the Fermi surface in wide range of the hole concentration in a metallic state, i.e., the strange metal state. The spin fluctuation of the strange metal state is nearly quantum critical and the dynamical spin susceptivity is well described by overdamped spin wave having the $\omega/T$ scaling with the relaxation rate at the Planckian limit. Because of these distinctive features of the strange metal state, the $k$ dependence of scattering rate of electrons is small and electrons behave as the marginal Fermi liquid, resulting in $T$-linear resistivity. In contrast, the pseudogap state is magnetically in the renormalized classical regime and the pseudogap is formed near the X point where the nesting condition of the short-range AFM order is fulfilled.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07726v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arata Tanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inhomogeneous dynamic state in the double trillium lattice antiferromagnet KBaFe$_2$(PO$_4$)$_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.07844v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The three-dimensional (3D) magnet KBaFe$_2$(PO$_4$)$_3$ hosts a double-trillium lattice of Fe$^{3+}$ (spin, $S=5/2$) ions offering a prototypical platform to study the frustration induced effects in 3D. Through magnetization, specific heat, $^{31}$P nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR), and muon spin relaxation ($\mu$SR) experiments, supported by first principles calculations, we uncover an unconventional ground state. Despite strong antiferromagnetic interactions with a large Curie-Weiss temperature $\theta_{\rm CW} = -70(2)$ K, no magnetic long-range order is observed down to 30 mK. Below $T^{\ast}\simeq 3.5$ K, the NMR linewidth becomes nearly field-independent and the spin-spin relaxation rate $1/T_2$ saturates, accompanied by an inhomogeneous distribution of transverse nuclear magnetization $M_{xy}$. The latter indicates the emergence of short-range dynamical correlations, which was further corroborated by a robust and field-insensitive broad maximum in specific heat. In $\mu$SR, we detect neither a static internal field nor spin freezing; instead the relaxation remains dynamic and is best described by two coexisting dynamic relaxation channels: a dominant fast (sporadic) channel and a slower Markovian component. Their differing weights and fluctuation rates suggest microscopic inhomogeneity in spin dynamics. Altogether, KBaFe$_2$(PO$_4$)$_3$ exemplifies a rare high-spin stochiometric 3D antiferromagnet that evades ordering and instead fosters a mosaic of spin dynamics driven by strong geometric frustration intrinsic to the trillium lattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.07844v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. J. Sebastian, S. S. Islam, R. Kolay, S. Mohanty, Q. P. Ding, Y. Skourski, J. Sichelschmidt, M. Baenitz, Jonas A. Krieger, T. J. Hicken, H. Luetkens, A. A. Tsirlin, Y. Furukawa, R. Nath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Implementation and application of a DFT$+U$$+V$ approach within the all-electron FLAPW method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08002</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08002v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an implementation of the density-functional theory DFT$+U$$+V$ formalism within the all-electron full-potential linearized augmented-plane-wave (FLAPW) method as implemented in the FLEUR code. The DFT$+U$$+V$ formalism extends DFT, supplemented by the onsite Coulomb interaction $U$, to address local correlation effects in localized states by incorporating intersite Coulomb interaction terms $V$. It holds promise for improving charge and bond disproportionation, charge and orbital ordering, charge density wave formation, charge transfer, and the intersite correlation resulting from hybridization between states of neighboring sites in a solid. $U$ and $V$ parameters are obtained from first principles using the constrained random-phase approximation (cRPA) employing two different atom basis representations to project the screened Coulomb interaction: the Wannier and the muffin-tin basis functions. We investigate in detail the impact of the $V$ term for typical covalently bonded materials like graphene, for bulk semiconductors such as silicon and germanium, and for charge-transfer insulators like NiO. Our results demonstrate an improvement in accuracy of specific properties across these systems, providing a framework for describing materials with different interaction regimes. We compare our DFT$+U$$+V$ results using our cRPA parameter sets with (i) previous DFT$+U$$+V$ calculation employing pseudopotential approximations, (ii) with experimental results and (iii) with our $GW$ results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08002v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wejdan Beida, Gustav Bihlmayer, Christoph Friedrich, Gregor Michalicek, Daniel Wortmann, Stefan Bl\"ugel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Role of Interlayer Electrons on the Frictional Behavior of Two-Dimensional Electrides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08131v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Friction accounts for up to 30% of global energy consumption, underscoring the urgent need for superlubricity in advanced materials. Two-dimensional (2D) electrides are layered materials with cationic layers separated by 2D confined electrons that act as anions. This study reveals the unique frictional properties of these compounds and the underlying mechanisms. We establish that interlayer friction correlates with the cationic charges and sliding-induced charge redistribution. Remarkably, the 2D electride Ba2N stands out for its lower interlayer friction than graphene, despite its stronger interlayer adhesion, defying conventional tribological understanding. This anomalous behavior arises from electron redistribution as the dominant energy dissipation pathway. Combining ab initio calculations and deep potential molecular dynamics (DPMD) simulations, we show that incommensurate twisted interfaces (2{\deg} &lt; {\theta} &lt; 58{\deg}) in Ba2N achieve structural superlubricity by suppressing out-of-plane buckling and energy corrugation. Notably, a critical normal load of 2.3 GPa enables barrier-free sliding in commensurate Ba2N ({\theta} = 0{\deg}), with an ultralow shear-to-load ratio of 0.001, suggesting the potential for superlubricity. Moreover, electron doping effectively reduces interlayer friction by controllably modulating stacking energies in 2D electrides. These findings establish 2D electrides as a transformative platform for energy-efficient tribology, enabling scalable superlubricity through twist engineering, load adaptation, or electrostatic gating. Our work advances the fundamental understanding of electron-mediated friction, with Ba2N serving a model system for cost-effective, high-performance material design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08131v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingcheng Qi, Giuliana Materzanini, Gian-Marco Rignanese, Maria Clelia Righi, Junjie Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Suppression of magnetism in Co$_3$Sn$_2$S$_2$ under external pressure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08141v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ability to control the magnetic state provides a powerful means to tune the underlying band topology, enabling transitions between distinct electronic phases and the emergence of novel quantum phenomena. In this work, we address the evolution of ferromagnetic state upon applying external pressures up to 10.8~GPa using a combined experimental and theoretical study. The standard \emph{ab initio} Density Functional Theory computation including ionic relaxations grossly overestimates the unit cell magnetization as a function of pressure. In our theoretical analysis we identify two possible mechanisms to remedy this shortcoming. Matching the experimental observations is achieved by a symmetry-preserving adjustment of the sulfur atoms position within the unit cell. Alternatively, we explore various combinations of the exchange and correlation parts of the effective potential which reproduce the experimental magnetization, the structural parameters and the measured optical conductivity spectra. Thus, the pressure-dependent behavior of magnetization demands a careful theoretical treatment and analysis of theoretical and experimental data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08141v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Chmeruk, D. Jones, R. Balducci, J. Ebad-Allah, F. Beiu\c{s}eanu, F. Schilberth, M. A. Kassem, U. Schade, A. Veber, L. Puskar, Y. Tabata, T. Waki, H. Nakamura, C. A. Kuntscher, A. \"Ostlin, L. Chioncel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Carrier-envelope phase control of ultrafast photocurrents in layered MoS$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08148</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08148v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate carrier-envelope-phase (CEP)-controlled photocurrents in mono-, bi-, and tri-layer MoS$_2$ driven by few-cycle laser pulses. The photocurrent in the two-terminal devices scales quadratically with the field amplitude, indicating perturbative carrier dynamics in the weak-field regime distinct from strong-field tunnelling. Our results extend light-field-sensitive current control from bulk dielectrics, semiconductors, and graphene to two-dimensional transition-metal dichalcogenides, highlighting their potential for electric-field sensitive optoelectronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08148v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johannes Schmuck, Bj\"orn Sinz, Nina Pettinger, Sergey Zherebtsov, Alexander W. Holleitner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Growth-Controlled Twinning and Magnetic Anisotropy in CeSb$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08176</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08176v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cerium diantimonide (CeSb$_2$) is a layered heavy-fermion Kondo lattice material that hosts complex magnetism and pressure-induced superconductivity. The interpretation of its in-plane anisotropy has remained unsettled due to structural twinning, which superimposes orthogonal magnetic responses. Here we combine controlled crystal growth with magnetization and rotational magnetometry to disentangle the effects of twinning. Nearly untwinned high-quality single crystals reveal the intrinsic in-plane anisotropy: the in-plane easy axis saturates at $M_{\text{easy}}(4~\text{T}) \approx 1.8~\mu_{\text{B}}$/Ce, while the in-plane hard axis magnetization is strongly suppressed, nearly linear, and comparable to the out-of-plane response. These results resolve long-standing discrepancies in reported magnetic measurements, in which in-plane metamagnetic transition fields and saturation magnetization varied significantly across previous studies. Growth experiments demonstrate that avoiding the proposed $\alpha$-$\beta$ structural transition $-$ through Sb-rich flux and slower cooling $-$ systematically reduces twinning. However, powder X-ray diffraction and differential thermal analysis measurements show no clear evidence of a distinct $\beta$ phase. Our results establish a consistent magnetic phase diagram and provide essential constraints for crystal-electric field models, enabling a clearer understanding of the interplay between anisotropic magnetism and unconventional superconductivity in CeSb$_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08176v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan T. Weber (Kristall- und Materiallabor, Physikalisches Institut, Goethe-Universit\"at Frankfurt, Germany, Ames National Laboratory, U.S. DOE, Ames, USA), Kristin Kliemt (Kristall- und Materiallabor, Physikalisches Institut, Goethe-Universit\"at Frankfurt, Germany), Sergey L. Bud'ko (Ames National Laboratory, U.S. DOE, Ames, USA, Department of Physics and Astronomy, Iowa State University, Ames, USA), Paul C. Canfield (Ames National Laboratory, U.S. DOE, Ames, USA, Department of Physics and Astronomy, Iowa State University, Ames, USA), Cornelius Krellner (Kristall- und Materiallabor, Physikalisches Institut, Goethe-Universit\"at Frankfurt, Germany)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cuprate Twistronics for Quantum Hardware</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08249</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08249v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent advances in the manipulation of complex oxide layers, particularly the fabrication of atomically thin cuprate superconducting films via molecular beam epitaxy, have revealed new ways in which nanoscale engineering can govern superconductivity and its interwoven electronic orders. In parallel, the creation of twisted cuprate heterostructures through cryogenic stacking techniques marks a pivotal step forward, exploiting cuprate superconductors to deepen our understanding of exotic quantum states and propel next-generation quantum technologies. This review explores over three decades of research in the emerging field of cuprate twistronics, examining both experimental breakthroughs and theoretical progress. It also highlights the methodologies poised to surmount the outstanding challenges in leveraging these complex quantum materials, underscoring their potential to expand the frontiers of quantum science and technology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08249v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/qute.202500203</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Adv Quantum Technol. 2025, 2500203</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tommaso Confalone, Flavia Lo Sardo, Yejin Lee, Sanaz Shokri, Giuseppe Serpico, Alessandro Coppo, Valerii M. Vinokur, Luca Chirolli, Valentina Brosco, Uri Vool, Domenico Montemurro, Francesco Tafuri, Golam Haider, Kornelius Nielsch, Nicola Poccia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>D-Wave Phonon Angular Momentum Texture in Altermagnets by Magnon-Phonon-Hybridization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08357</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08357v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In altermagnets, the magnon bands are anisotropically spin-split in reciprocal space without relativistic or dipolar spin-spin interactions. In this work, we theoretically study magnons and phonons coupled by spin-lattice interaction in a two-dimensional square-lattice $d$-wave altermagnet. We show that phonon-chirality-selective magnon-phonon hybridization can be caused by interfacial Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction leading to the emergence of hybrid quasiparticles that possess finite phonon angular momentum. These hybrid quasiparticles are called magnon polarons and consist of spin-polarized magnons and chiral phonons. Their phonon angular momentum texture follows the $d$-wave character of the magnon spin texture opening up the possibility of phononic counterparts to the electronic response effects in altermagnets, such as a \emph{phonon angular momentum splitter effect}, i.e., the generation of a transverse phonon angular momentum current induced by a temperature gradient -- the bosonic analogue of the spin-splitter effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08357v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hannah Bendin, Alexander Mook, Ingrid Mertig, Robin R. Neumann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Porous-B$_{18}$: An Ideal Topological Semimetal with Symmetry-Enforced Orthogonal Nodal-Line and Nodal-Surface States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08442v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Topological semimetals (TSMs) featuring symmetry-protected band degeneracies have attracted considerable attention due to their exotic quantum properties and potential applications. While nodal line (NL) and nodal surface (NS) semimetals have been extensively studied, the realization of a material where both NL and NS coexist and are intertwined, particularly with an ideal electronic band structure, remains a significant challenge. Here, we predict via first-principles calculations and symmetry analysis a metastable boron allotrope, Porous-B$_{18}$ (space group $P6_3/m$, No.~176), as a pristine TSM hosting a NS and two straight NLs near the Fermi level. The structure, a honeycomb-like porous 3D framework, exhibits excellent dynamical, thermal (stable up to 1000~K), and mechanical stability. Its electronic band structure is remarkably clean: only the highest valence band (HVB) and the lowest conduction band (LCB) cross linearly within a large energy window of 1.84~eV, free from trivial-band interference. The nodal surface lies on the $k_z = \pm \pi$ planes, protected by combined time-reversal symmetry ($T$) and twofold screw-rotational symmetry ($S_{2z}$), yielding a full-plane Kramers-like degeneracy. The two nodal lines along $K$--$H$ and $K'$--$H'$ are protected by inversion and time-reversal symmetries, carry a quantized Berry phase of $\pm \pi$, and connect orthogonally to the nodal surface, forming an intertwined nodal network. Drumhead surface states on the $(1\bar{1}0)$ surface further confirm the nontrivial topology. Porous-B$_{18}$ thus provides an ideal platform for investigating the interplay between nodal-line and nodal-surface fermions and exploring novel quantum transport phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08442v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao-jing Gao, Yanfeng Ge, Yan Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Second-Harmonic Magnetoacoustic Ultrasound from Magnetic Nanoparticles under Radiofrequency Electromagnetic Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08146v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report experimental evidence of mechanical wave generation by magnetic nanoparticles (MNPs) under radiofrequency electromagnetic fields (EMFs, 65mT, 800 kHz, at 100ms bursts) in the ultrasonic (US) frequency range. We developed an experimental setup to detect the second harmonic (SH) signal under isothermal conditions. This SH-US signal was observed only in samples containing MNPs and consequently originated from the EMF interaction on samples containing MNPs. These findings suggest that US generation due to magneto-acoustic interaction in the MNPs could be responsible for the cell damage induced by EMF in cells containing MNPs without increasing the temperature. Experiments performed on magnetically aligned MNP clusters in gelatin significantly enhance the amplitude of the SH signal compared to non-aligned samples. This phenomenon could pave the way for new theoretical and practical approaches as for 'in vivo' magnetoacoustics theragnostic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08146v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Marqu\'es-G\'omez, J. Melchor, A. C. Moreno Maldonado, C. Marquina, G. Goya, M. R. Ibarra, G. Rus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum annealing for lattice models with competing long-range interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08336</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08336v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We use superconducting qubit quantum annealing devices to determine the ground state of Ising models with algebraically decaying competing long-range interactions in the thermodynamic limit. This is enabled by a unit-cell-based optimization scheme, in which the finite optimizations on each unit cell are performed using commercial quantum annealing hardware. To demonstrate the capabilities of the approach, we choose three exemplary problems relevant for other quantum simulation platforms and material science: (i) the calculation of devil's staircases of magnetization plateaux of the long-range Ising model in a longitudinal field on the triangular lattice, motivated by atomic and molecular quantum simulators; (ii) the evaluation of the ground state of the same model on the Kagome lattice in the absence of a field, motivated by artificial spin ice metamaterials; (iii) the study of models with additional few-nearest-neighbor interactions relevant for frustrated Ising compounds with potential long-range interactions. The approach discussed in this work provides a useful and realistic application of existing quantum annealing technology, applicable across many research areas in which lattice problems with resummable long-range interactions are relevant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08336v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Alexander Koziol, Kai Phillip Schmidt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ferromagnetic CrBr$_3$-Induced Graphene Spintronics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07602</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07602v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Our proposed spin valve prototype showcases a sophisticated design featuring a two-dimensional graphene bilayer positioned between layers of ${CrBr}_3$ ferromagnetic insulators. In this model, proximity coupling plays a pivotal role, influencing the magnetization orientations of the graphene layers and significantly impacting the \textit{in-plane} conductivity of the ${CrBr}_3$ layers. In this present work, we position the graphene bilayer between two layers of the ferromagnetic insulator ${CrBr}_3$ to establish this configuration. Using density functional theory, we conduct detailed computations to analyze the electronic structure of this sandwiched system. Our findings reveal a notable finite gap at specific \textit{k}-points, particularly evident in the antiparallel configuration of the magnetizations. This finding represents a significant advancement in spintronics, underscoring the potential of our spin valve prototype to drive innovation in electronic device technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07602v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. K. Behera, P. C. Ramamurthy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nature of quantum criticality in the Ising ferromagnet TbV$_6$Sn$_6$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02010v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: TbV$_6$Sn$_6$ is a topological metal where ferromagnetic Tb ions with strong uniaxial magnetic anisotropy interact with V kagome layers. Inelastic neutron scattering (INS) measurements show that the Tb ions adopt an Ising doublet ground state. Here, we consider whether a transverse magnetic field can drive TbV$_6$Sn$_6$ toward a quantum critical point, providing a rare example of transverse-field Ising criticality in a metallic compound. High-field magnetization measurements reveal a first-order-like spin-reorientation transition at 25.6 T. Our INS-based magnetic model finds that this is caused by an avoided crossing of an excited-state singlet with the ground-state doublet. Surprisingly, our model predicts that quantum critical and tricritical points are accessible within the range of experimentally determined model parameters and may be reached by varying the direction of an applied magnetic field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02010v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/jlnl-y35t</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Tianxiong Han, R. D. McKenzie, Joanna Blawat, Tyler J. Slade, Bing Li, Y. Lee, D. M. Pajerowski, John Singleton, Paul C. Canfield, Liqin Ke, Ross McDonald, Rebecca Flint, R. J. McQueeney</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>X-ray particle tracking velocimetry for steady-state rheological characterization: Case study of a complex polymer melt flow in material extrusion additive manufacturing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.04830</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.04830v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce X-ray Particle Tracking Velocimetry (XPTV) as a promising method to quantitatively resolve the velocity field and associated rheological information of polymer melt flow within the nozzle of a fused filament fabrication (FFF) printer. Employing tungsten powder as tracer particles embedded within a polymer filament, we investigate melt flow dynamics through an aluminum nozzle in a custom setup comparable to commercial printers. The velocity profiles obtained via XPTV reveal significant deviations from classical Newtonian flow, highlighting complex heterogeneous and non-isothermal behavior within the melt. From these measurements, we determine the local infinitesimal strain rate tensor and correlate flow-induced non-Newtonian effects to spatially varying temperature distributions, reflecting incomplete thermal homogenization within the nozzle. We complement the experiments with computational fluid dynamics simulations of the flow inside the printing nozzle, incorporating filament melting through an enthalpy-porosity formulation and treating the air-polymer melt interface using a two-phase approach. The simulated velocity profiles agree closely with the XPTV measurements across the investigated operating conditions, supporting the experimental interpretation. Our findings demonstrate the capability of XPTV to quantify both velocity fields and rheological properties, underscoring its potential as a tool for investigating opaque polymer melt flows in additive manufacturing, industrial processing, and rheology. To our knowledge, this is the first application of XPTV to polymer melt rheology. It enables measurements that are inaccessible to conventional optical methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.04830v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julian Kattinger, Stefan Hiemer, Mike Kornely, Julian Ehrler, Phi-Long Chung, Christian Bonten, Marc Kreutzbruck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-dimensional Indium Oxide at the Epitaxial Graphene/SiC Interface: Synthesis, Structure, Properties, and Devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09370v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: High-quality two-dimensional (2D) dielectrics are crucial for fabricating 2D/3D hybrid vertical electronic devices such as metal-oxide-semiconductor (MOS) based Schottky diodes and hot electron transistors, the production of which is constrained by the scarcity of bulk layered wide bandgap semiconductors. In this research, we present the synthesis of a new 2D dielectric, monolayer InO2, which differs in stoichiometry from its bulk form, over a large area (&gt;300 um2) by intercalating at the epitaxial graphene (EG)/SiC interface. By adjusting the lateral size of graphene through optical lithography prior to the intercalation, we tune the thickness of InO2 where predominantly (~85%) monolayer InO2 is formed. The preference for monolayer formation of InO2 is explained using ReaxFF reactive molecular dynamics and density functional theory (DFT) calculations. Additionally, the band gap of InO2 is calculated to be 4.1 eV, differing from its bulk form (2.7 eV). Furthermore, MOS-based Schottky diode measurements on InO2 intercalated EG/n-SiC demonstrate that the EG/n-SiC junction transforms from ohmic to a Schottky junction upon intercalation, with a barrier height of 0.87 eV and a rectification ratio of ~10^5. These findings introduce a new addition to the 2D dielectric family, showing significant potential for monolayer InO2 to be used as a barrier in vertical electronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09370v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/adma.202516133</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Turker F. et al. "2D Indium Oxide at the Epitaxial Graphene/SiC Interface," Adv. Mater. 2025, e16133</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Furkan Turker, Bohan Xu, Chengye Dong, Michael Labella III, Nadire Nayir, Natalya Sheremetyeva, Zachary J. Trdinich, Duanchen Zhang, Gokay Adabasi, Bita Pourbahari, Wesley E. Auker, Ke Wang, Mehmet Z. Baykara, Vincent Meunier, Nabil Bassim, Adri C. T. van Duin, Vincent H. Crespi, Joshua A. Robinson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stacking-orientation and twist-angle control on integer and fractional Chern insulators in moir\'e rhombohedral graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01767</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01767v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Rhombohedral-stacked multilayer graphene aligned with hexagonal boron nitride has emerged as an excellent platform for investigating exotic quantum phenomena arising from the interplay between electron correlations and nontrivial topology. However, the microscopic mechanism governing the emergence of both the integer and fractional Chern insulator states in this system remains an open question. In this work, we systematically investigate the electrical transport properties of RMG/hBN moir\'e devices with controlled alignment orientations and twist angles. We demonstrate that alignment orientation strongly modulates correlated phenomena in the moir\'e-proximal regime, while having negligible influence on the formation of integer and fractional Chern insulators in the moir\'e-distant regime. Instead, the moir\'e periodicity, tuned by the twist angle, serves as the key parameter controlling the stability of these correlated topological states in the moir\'e-distant regime. Furthermore, in the moir\'e-proximal regime of one specific alignment, we observe anomalous Hall effect and a variety of competing phases near {\nu} = 1, including integer Chern insulator states, extended Chern insulator states, and trivial insulators, whose stability is highly sensitive to both the applied displacement electric field and magnetic field. Our results underscore the critical role of stacking-alignment and twist-angle engineering in exploring novel quantum states based on rhombohedral-stacked multilayer graphene moir\'e systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01767v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chushan Li, Chuanqi Zheng, Kai Liu, Ke Huang, Zheng Sun, Lei Qiao, Yifan Wei, Chenyu Zhang, Fan Xu, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Hao Yang, Dandan Guan, Liang Liu, Shiyong Wang, Yaoyi Li, Hao Zheng, Canhua Liu, Bingbing Tong, Li Lu, Jinfeng Jia, Zhiwen Shi, Jianpeng Liu, Xiao Li, Guorui Chen, Tingxin Li, Xiaoxue Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum transport in nitrogen-doped nanoporous graphenes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04892</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04892v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Bottom-up on-surface synthesized nanoporous graphenes (NPGs), realized as 2D arrays of laterally covalently bonded $\pi$-conjugated graphene nanoribbons (GNRs), are a family of carbon nanomaterials that are receiving increasing attention for nanoelectronics and biosensing. Recently, a so-called hybrid-NPG (hNPG) is synthesized, featuring an alternating sequence of doped and non-doped GNRs, resulting in a band staggering effect in its electronic structure. Such a feature is appealing for photo-catalysis, photovoltaics and even carbon nanocircuitry. However, to date, little is known about the transport properties of hNPG and its derivatives, which is key for most applications. Here, via Green's functions simulations, the quantum transport properties of hNPGs are studied. It is found that injected carriers in hNPG spread laterally through a number of GNRs, though such spreading may take place exclusively through GNRs of one type (doped or non-doped). A simple model is proposed to discern the key parameters determining the electronic propagation in hNPGs and explore alternative hNPG designs to control the spreading/confinement and anisotropy of charge transport in these systems. For one such design, it is found that it is possible to send directed electric signals with sub-nanometer precision for as long as one micrometer - a result first reported for any NPG.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04892v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/smll.202508850</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Gaetano Calogero, Isaac Alc\'on, Alan E. Anaya Morales, Nick Papior, Pol Febrer, Aron W. Cummings, Miguel Pruneda, Stephan Roche, Mads Brandbyge, "Quantum Transport in Nitrogen-Doped Nanoporous Graphenes." Small (2025): e08850</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Gaetano Calogero, Isaac Alc\'on, Alan E. Anaya Morales, Nick Papior, Pol Febrer, Aron W. Cummings, Miguel Pruneda, Stephan Roche, Mads Brandbyge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Third-order strong-coupling impurity solver for real-frequency DMFT: Accurate spectral functions for antiferromagnetic and photo-doped states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.20385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.20385v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a real-frequency third-order strong-coupling impurity solver which employs quantics tensor cross interpolation (QTCI) for an efficient evaluation of the diagram weights. Applying the method to dynamical mean-field theory (DMFT) calculations of the single-band Hubbard model on the Bethe lattice, we clarify the interaction and temperature range in which the third-order approach yields accurate results. Since the calculations are implemented on the real-time/frequency axis, the detailed structure of spectral functions can be obtained without analytical continuation, as we demonstrate with examples for paramagnetic, antiferromagnetic and photo-doped states. Our work establishes a viable path toward high-order, real-frequency impurity solvers for both equilibrium and non-equilibrium DMFT studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.20385v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Geng, Aaram J. Kim, Philipp Werner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ge as an orbitronic platform: giant orbital Hall effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20436v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: State-of-the-art developments in magnetic devices rely on manufacturing faster, more efficient memory elements. A significant development in this direction has been the discovery of orbital torques, which employ the orbital angular momentum of Bloch electrons to switch the magnetisation of an adjacent ferromagnet, and has motivated the search for orbitronic materials displaying strong orbital dynamics exemplified, by the orbital Hall effect (OHE). In this work we propose Ge, as an optimal orbitronic platform. We demonstrate that holes in bulk Ge exhibit a giant OHE, exceeding that of the bulk states of topological insulators, and exceeding the spin-Hall effect by four orders of magnitude. The calculation is performed within the framework of the Luttinger model and the modern theory of orbital magnetisation, while incorporating recently-discovered quantum corrections to the OHE. Our study constitutes a fundamental milestone in applying the modern theory to a system with inversion symmetry. Moreover, we argue that bulk Ge serves as an ideal testbed for the orbital torque resulting from a charge current, since the spin- and orbital-Edelstein effects in Ge are forbidden by symmetry. Our results provide a blueprint for producing strong orbital torques in magnetic devices with Ge, guiding future experimental work in this direction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20436v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James H. Cullen, Zhanning Wang, Dimitrie Culcer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetoelectric Switching of Magnetic Order in Rhombohedral Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24672</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24672v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A finite Hall conductance under zero magnetic field implies time reversal symmetry (TRS) breaking due to magnetic order. In rhombohedral stacked multilayer graphene, the angular momentum that breaks TRS can result from the orbital degree of freedom at the $K$ and $K'$ valleys. This leads to valley polarization and occupation-dependent anomalous Hall resistance (AHR) due to the chirality in Berry curvature at the valleys. We report magnetoelectric control of orbital magnetic order in crystalline rhombohedral hexalayer graphene (R6G), achieved without the introduction of a moir\'e superlattice. At moderate displacement fields and low carrier densities, we observe a non-volatile and hysteretic AHR that can be electrically toggled by sweeping either the carrier density or the displacement field. Upon the application of small perpendicular magnetic fields, the system reveals a characteristic double sign reversal of the AHR, indicating a competition between distinct magnetic ground states. This interplay between valley polarization and electric and magnetic field tuning demonstrates the rich multiferroic behavior of R6G. Our findings present crystalline R6G as a minimal, tunable platform for studying symmetry-breaking phases and magnetic order in flat-band systems, offering insights into the coupling between electronic structure and magnetoelectric response.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24672v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kilian Kr\"otzsch, Arsen Herasymchuk, Yaroslav Zhumagulov, Arnaud Magrez, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Sergei G. Sharapov, Oleg V. Yazyev, Mitali Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coupling between vibration and Luttinger liquid in mechanical nanowires</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25608</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25608v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The vibration of the mechanical nanowire coupled to photons via photon pressure and coupled to charges via the capacity has been widely explored in experiments in the past decades. This system is electrically neutral, thus its coupling to the other degrees of freedom is always challenging. Here, we show that the vibration can slightly change the nanowire length and the associated Fermi velocity, which leads to coupling between vibration and Luttinger liquid. We consider the transverse and longitudinal vibrations of the nanowires, showing that the transverse vibration is much more significant than the longitudinal vibration, which can be measured through the sizable frequency shift. We predict an instability of the vibration induced by this coupling when the frequency becomes negative at a critical temperature for the transverse vibrations in nanowires with low Fermi energy, which can be reached by tuning the chemical potential and magnetic field. The time-dependent oscillation of the conductance, which directly measures the Luttinger parameter, can provide evidence for this coupling. Our theory offers a new mechanism for exploring the coupling between the vibration and the electronic excitations, which may lead to intriguing applications in cooling and controlling the mechanical oscillators with currents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25608v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zeyu Rao, Yue-Xin Huang, Guang-Can Guo, Ming Gong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local thermodynamic DOS measurement and twist-angle mapping in graphene-hBN superlattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01246</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01246v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Moir\'e patterns arising from twisted van der Waals stacks fundamentally reshape their electronic properties, enabling band-structure engineering that has driven rapidly growing interest in this field. In studying electronic properties, however, structural disorder present in real devices often leads to twist-angle inhomogeneity and obscures angle-dependent electronic effects when measured with bulk-averaged measurements. Probes that can access local thermodynamic response of the electronic systems with high sensitivity would be highly valuable. Here, we adopt Kelvin probe force microscopy (KPFM) to locally investigate graphene-hBN superlattices. By additionally modulating the chemical potential of the system, we obtain the inverse compressibility with high signal-to-noise ratio, enabling extraction of the local thermodynamic DOS. From this information, we determine the local twist angle along the device and find that twist-angle deviations are strongly correlated with bubble-induced strain features. Furthermore, by simultaneously tracking the offsets in the contact potential difference and in the net charge, we identify which interface within the heterostructure hosts the trapped bubbles. This capability to identify local electro-chemical environments provides a practical tool for strain-based studies and future device designs utilizing nanoscale engineering in moir\'e systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01246v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Namkyung Lee, Hangyeol Park, Seungwon Jung, Baeksan Jang, Seonyu Lee, Joonho Jang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrafast symmetry modulation and induced magnetic excitation in the Kagome metal RbV3Sb5</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06389</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06389v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Light-matter interaction in frustrated Kagome metals enables access to hidden quantum states, yet the microscopic origin of symmetry breaking under ultrafast excitation remains elusive. Here, we uncover a microscopic mechanism for laser-induced symmetry breaking in RbV3Sb5 through first-principles real-time simulations. Selective excitation of a single-QM phonon mode dynamically breaks both rotational and time-reversal symmetries within the 2X2X1 charge density wave (CDW) superlattice. The resulting anisotropic lattice distortion lifts geometric frustration and stabilizes a nonequilibrium ferrimagnetic phase, accompanied by a sizable intrinsic anomalous Hall effect. Distinct from prior interpretations based on orbital antiferromagnetism or extrinsic perturbations, our findings reveal a spin-driven pathway for symmetry breaking under strong optical fields. These results provide a microscopic foundation for exploring how spin, lattice and charge degrees of freedom are intertwined in nonequilibrium correlated states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06389v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengxue Guan, Xiaodong Zhou, Jingyi Duan, Chaoxi Cui, Wei Jiang, Zeying Zhang, Binhua Zhang, Zhengwei Nie, Xun Shi, Zhiwei Wang, Yugui Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sub-Doppler cooling, state preparation, and optical trapping of a triel atom</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13470</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13470v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Ultracold gases of atoms from Main Group III (Group 13) of the Periodic Table, also known as "triel elements," have great potential for a new generation of quantum matter experiments. The first magneto-optical trap of a triel element (indium) was recently realized, but more progress is needed before a triel is ready for modern ultracold quantum science experiments in optical traps. Reaching this regime typically requires atoms that are cooled to the 10 uK level or below, prepared in pure quantum states, and confined in a laser field. Here we report the achievement of all three of these milestones in atomic indium. First, we perform polarization gradient cooling of an indium gas to 15 uK. Second, we spin polarize the gas into a single hyperfine sublevel of either the $5P_{1/2}$ indium ground state or the $5P_{3/2}$ metastable state. Third, we trap indium in a 1064 nm optical lattice, achieving a 3 s trap lifetime. With these results, indium is now a candidate for a next generation quantum research platform.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13470v2</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/1znr-p9nv</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PRX Quantum 6, 040328 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Putian Li, Xianquan Yu, Seth Hew Peng Chew, Jinchao Mo, Tiangao Lu, Travis L. Nicholson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
