<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 05:00:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Is disorder a friend or a foe to melting of Wigner-Mott insulators?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07932</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07932v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Wigner crystals are extremely fragile, which is shown to result from very strong geometric frustration germane to long-range Coulomb interactions. Physically, this is manifested by a very small characteristic energy scale for shear density fluctuations, which are gapless excitations in a translationally invariant system. The presence of disorder, however, breaks translational invariance, thus suppressing gapless excitations and pushing them to higher density. We illustrate this general principle by explicit microscopic model calculations, showing that this mechanism very effectively stabilizes disordered Wigner lattices to much higher temperatures and densities than in the clean limit. On the other hand, we argue that in two dimensions disorder significantly ``smears" the melting transition, producing spatial coexistence of solid-like and liquid-like regions -- just as recently observed in STM experiments. Our results paint a new physical picture for melting of Wigner-Mott solids in two dimensions, corresponding to a Mott-Hubbard model with spatially varying local electronic bandwidth.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07932v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammed Hammam, Cyprian Lewandowski, Vladimir Dobrosavljevic, Sandeep Joy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Geometry Driven Crystallization: A Neural-Network Variational Monte Carlo Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07947</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07947v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Wigner crystals are a paradigmatic form of interaction driven electronic order. A key open question is how Berry curvature and, more generally, quantum geometry reshape crystallization. The discovery of two-dimensional materials with relatively flat bands and pronounced Berry curvature has added fresh urgency to this question. Recent mean-field studies have proposed a topological variant of the Wigner crystal, the anomalous Hall crystal (AHC), with non-zero Chern number. However it remains unclear whether the AHC survives beyond the mean-field approximation. Here, we map out the ground-state phase diagram of the $\lambda$-jellium model - a simple model whose interaction strength and Berry curvature are independently tunable - using state-of-the-art neural-network variational Monte Carlo. The AHC is found to remain stable against quantum fluctuations. Surprisingly, quantum geometric effects are found to dramatically enhance crystallization. Both the AHC and the standard Wigner Crystal are stabilized at densities up to an order of magnitude above the critical density in the absence of quantum geometry, yet still significantly below the threshold predicted by mean-field theory. These striking results highlight the rich interplay between quantum fluctuations, quantum geometry, and crystallization, providing concrete guidance for experiments and enabling future explorations of fractionalized crystals and chiral superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07947v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Agnes Valenti, Yaar Vituri, Yubo Yang, Daniel E. Parker, Tomohiro Soejima, Junkai Dong, Miguel A. Morales, Ashvin Vishwanath, Erez Berg, Shiwei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moire-Engineered Ferroelectric Transistors for Nearly Trap-free, Low-Power and Non-Volatile 2D Electronics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08086v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Long-range moire patterns in twisted WSe2 enable a built-in, moire-length-scale ferroelectric polarization that can be directly harnessed in electronic devices. Such a built-in ferroic landscape offers a compelling means to enable ultralow-voltage and non-volatile electronic functionality in two-dimensional materials; however, achieving stable polarization control without charge trapping has remained a persistent challenge. Here, we demonstrate a moire-engineered ferroelectric field-effect transistor (FeFET) utilizing twisted WSe2 bilayers that leverages atomically clean van der Waals interfaces to achieve efficient polarization-channel coupling and trap-suppressed, ultralow-voltage operation (subthreshold swing of 64 mV per decade). The device exhibits a stable non-volatile memory window of 0.10 V and high mobility, exceeding the performance of previously reported two-dimensional FeFET and matching that of advanced silicon-based devices. In addition, capacitance-voltage spectroscopy, corroborated by self-consistent Landau-Ginzburg-Devonshire modeling, indicates ultrafast ferroelectric switching (~0.5 microseconds). These results establish moire-engineered ferroelectricity as a practical and scalable route toward ultraclean, low-power, and non-volatile 2D electronics, bridging atomistic lattice engineering with functional device architectures for next-generation memory and logic technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08086v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arup Singha, Shaili Sett, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Arindam Ghosh, Rahul Debnath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coalescence of multiple topological orders in quasi-one-dimensional bismuth halide chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08239v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Topology is being widely adopted to understand and to categorize quantum matter in modern physics. The nexus of topology orders, which engenders distinct quantum phases with benefits to both fundamental research and practical applications for future quantum devices, can be driven by topological phase transition through modulating intrinsic or extrinsic ordering parameters. The conjoined topology, however, is still elusive in experiments due to the lack of suitable material platforms. Here we use scanning tunneling microscopy, angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy, and theoretical calculations to investigate the doping-driven band structure evolution of a quasi-one-dimensional material system, bismuth halide, which contains rare multiple band inversions in two time-reversal-invariant momenta. According to the unique bulk-boundary correspondence in topological matter, we unveil a composite topological phase, the coexistence of a strong topological phase and a high-order topological phase, evoked by the band inversion associated with topological phase transition in this system. Moreover, we reveal multiple-stage topological phase transitions by varying the halide element ratio: from high-order topology to weak topology, the unusual dual topology, and trivial/weak topology subsequently. Our results not only realize an ideal material platform with composite topology, but also provide an insightful pathway to establish abundant topological phases in the framework of band inversion theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08239v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41467-025-56593-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Zhong, J., Yang, M., Zhao, W. et al. Coalescence of multiple topological orders in quasi-one-dimensional bismuth halide chains. Nat Commun 16, 1163 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jingyuan Zhong, Ming Yang, Wenxuan Zhao, Kaiyi Zhai, Xuan Zhen, Lifu Zhang, Dan Mu, Yundan Liu, Zhijian Shi, Ningyan Cheng, Wei Zhou, Jianfeng Wang, Weichang Hao, Zhenpeng Hu, Jincheng Zhuang, Jinhu L\"u, Yi Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological spin-up triplet excitonic condensation in two-dimensional electron-hole systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08370v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate topological spin-up triplet excitonic condensation and its competition with other stabilities in a two-dimensional interacting electron-hole system taking into account Rashba spin-orbit coupling and external magnetic fields. Using an unrestricted Hartree-Fock approach, we self-consistently evaluate spin-selective excitonic condensate order parameters and the Chern number. The ground state phase diagram in the dependence on magnetic field and Coulomb interaction shows a spin-up triplet excitonic condensate (EC) with a nonzero Chern number, emerging uniquely away from the topologically trivial singlet and spin-down triplet EC regions. Strong spin-polarized triplet excitonic fluctuations preceding the condensation are further revealed through the signatures of the dynamical excitonic susceptibility spectra. Our results establish a class of topological quantum phases driven by excitonic coherence and suggest a realistic pathway to its realization in a distorted Janus monolayer of transition metal dichalcogenides or some twisted van der Waals heterostructures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08370v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/7lp7-p8tk</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, L201110 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Van-Nham Phan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disorder-mediated linear and nonlinear magnetotransport in the charge-density-wave material ${\rm Ta_2NiSe_7 }$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08373v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report disorder-mediated first-order linear and higher-order nonlinear (magneto-)transport of Ta$_2$NiSe$_7$ (TNS) in the charge-density-wave (CDW) regime. CDW transition temperature ($T_{CDW}$) and carrier density are proportional and inversely proportional to residual resistance ratio of samples, respectively. Such relation helps to understand the unique CDW order therein. High-$T_{CDW}$ TNS exhibits negative first-harmonic magnetoresistance (MR$^{1\omega}$) under a magnetic field ($B$) parallel to the direction of alternating current ($I^{\omega}$), which may arise from the anomalous velocity induced by the Berry curvature of three-dimensional topological bands near the Fermi level. As $T_{CDW}$ drops, a positive-to-negative MR$^{1\omega}$ transition is observed with decreasing perpendicular $B$, which is likely due to the contribution of Zeeman effect on current pathways in the disordered system. Moreover, interestingly, the second-harmonic nonlinear signals are suppressed, while the third-harmonic signals are significant and sensitive to both $B$ and $T_{CDW}$. Such observations, together with scaling analysis, suggest the quantum geometry quadrupole at play and the modulation of disorder on third-order nonlinearity. Our results pave an avenue for tailoring distinct-order magnetoresistive phases in disordered topological materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08373v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/1zzj-lcf1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review Research 7, L042056 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xiaodong Sun, Jiabin Qiao, Yuanzhe Li, Wanli He, Jiali Chen, Jinjin Liu, Yuxiang Chen, Yuchen Ma, Meiling Jin, Jianlin Luo, Jie Chen, Wei Wu, Zhiwei Wang, Wei Jiang, Xiang Li, Yugui Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An extended low-frequency noise compact model for single-layer graphene FETs including correlated mobility fluctuations effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08388</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08388v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Correlated mobility fluctuations are considered in the physics-based carrier number fluctuation deltaN low-frequency noise (LFN) compact model of single-layer graphene field effect transistors (GFET) in the present study. Trapped charge density and Coulomb scattering coefficient deltaN LFN parameters are obtained after applying a parameter extraction methodology, adapted from conventional silicon technologies, to the linear ambipolar regions of GFETs. Appropriate adjustments are considered in the method according to GFETs physical characteristics. Afterwards, Hooge mobility as well as series resistance fluctuations LFN parameters can be extracted. The updated LFN model is validated with experimental data from various long and short-channel GFETs at an extended range of gate and drain bias conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08388v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TED.2025.3640600</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Transactions on Electron Devices 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nikolaos Mavredakis, Anibal Pacheco-Sanchez, David Jimenez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The unexpected dewetting during growth of silicene flakes with dendritic pyramids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08428v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Silicene growth on graphene has emerged as a novel method for fabricating silicon-based van der Waals heterostructures. However, the silicene flakes produced in this manner are the result of an exotic growth mode characterized by metastable nanostructures with varying degrees of deviation from equilibrium, with large two-dimensional flakes surrounded by a rim that coexist with small 3D islands, and, at large deposits, thick dendritic pyramids separated by a denuded zone. In order to rationalize and control this growth, a model is derived that revisits the dewetting thermodynamics and considers generally ignored adsorption and step-edge energies. The model is investigated using kinetic Monte-Carlo simulations and mean-field rate equations, and implemented by close inspection of microscopy images. This model perfectly reproduces the experimental outcomes, unveiling an anomalous growth mode, and provides guidelines on experimental conditions for high-quality silicene growth.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08428v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Results in Physics, 2026, 80, pp.108540</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kejian Wang (IM2NP), Mathieu Abel (IM2NP), Filippo Fabbri (IM2NP), Mathieu Koudia (IM2NP), Adrien Michon (SU, INSP), Adam Hassan Denawi (SU, INSP), Holger Vach (SU, INSP), Isabelle Berbezier (SU, INSP), Jean-No\"el Aqua (SU, INSP)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>YRu$_3$B$_2$ - a kagome lattice superconductor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08514</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08514v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report the synthesis and physical properties of a polycrystalline, hexagonal boride YRu$_3$B$_2$. Our resistivity and heat capacity measurements indicate that YRu$_3$B$_2$ is a weakly coupled superconductor, with critical temperature $T_c$ = 0.63 K and upper critical field $\mu_0 H_{c2}$ (0)=0.11 T. Density functional theory calculations, together with chemical-bonding analysis, reveal that the electronic states at and near the Fermi energy level are dominated by the Ru kagome sublattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08514v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Micha{\l} J. Winiarski, Dominik Walczak, Szymon Kr\'olak, Duygu Yazici, Robert J. Cava, Tomasz Klimczuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anisotropic transport in ballistic bilayer graphene cavities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08588</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08588v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Closing the gap between ray tracing simulations and experimentally observed electron jetting in bilayer graphene (BLG), we study all-electronic, gate-defined BLG cavities using tight-binding simulations and semiclassical equations of motion. Such cavities offer a rich playground to investigate anisotropic electron transport due to the trigonally warped Fermi surfaces. In this work, we achieve two things: First, we verify the existence of triangular modes (as predicted by classical ray tracing calculations) in the quantum solutions of closed circular BLG cavities. Then, we explore signatures of said triangular modes in transport through open BLG cavities connected to leads. We show that the triangular symmetry translates into anisotropic transport and present an optimal setup for experimental detection of the triangular modes as well as for controlled modulation of transport in preferred directions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08588v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Florian Schoeppl, Alina Mrenca-Kolasinska, Ming-Hao Liu, Korbinian Schwarzmaier, Klaus Richter, Angelika Knothe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Operator Lanczos Approach enabling Neural Quantum States as Real-Frequency Impurity Solvers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08624</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08624v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To understand the intricate exchange between electrons of different bands in strongly correlated materials, it is essential to treat multi-orbital models accurately. For this purpose, dynamical mean-field theory (DMFT) provides an established framework, whose scope crucially hinges on the availability of efficient quantum impurity solvers. Here we present a real-frequency impurity solver based on neural quantum states (NQS) combined with an operator-Lanczos construction. NQS are an asymptotically unbiased variational ground-state ansatz that employs neural networks to capture long-range correlations on complicated graph structures. We leverage this ability to solve multi-orbital impurity problems using a systematically improvable Segmented Commutator Operator-Lanczos (SCOL) construction. Our benchmarks on both the single-orbital Anderson model and the multi-orbital Hubbard-Kanamori impurity Hamiltonian reveal excellent ground-state precision and the capacity to accurately resolve zero temperature spectral functions and self-energies. These results open avenues for extending DMFT to more challenging problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08624v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonas B. Rigo, Markus Schmitt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disentangling the unusual magnetic anisotropy of the near-room-temperature ferromagnet Fe$_{4}$GeTe$_{2}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08722v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the quest for two-dimensional conducting materials with high ferromagnetic ordering temperature the new family of the layered Fe$_{n}$GeTe$_{2}$ compounds, especially the near-room-temperature ferromagnet Fe$_{4}$GeTe$_{2}$, receives a significant attention. Fe$_{4}$GeTe$_{2}$ features a peculiar spin reorientation transition at $T_\mathrm{SR} \sim 110$ K suggesting a non-trivial temperature evolution of the magnetic anisotropy (MA) - one of the main contributors to the stabilization of the magnetic order in the low-D systems. An electron spin resonance (ESR) spectroscopic study reported here provides quantitative insights into the unusual magnetic anisotropy of Fe$_{4}$GeTe$_{2}$. At high temperatures the total MA is mostly given by the demagnetization effect with a small contribution of the counteracting intrinsic magnetic anisotropy of an easy-axis type, whose growth below a characteristic temperature $T_{\rm shape} \sim 150$ K renders the sample seemingly isotropic at $T_\mathrm{SR}$. Below one further temperature $T_{\rm d} \sim 50$ K the intrinsic MA becomes even more complex. Importantly, all the characteristic temperatures found in the ESR experiment match those observed in transport measurements, suggesting an inherent coupling between magnetic and electronic degrees of freedom in Fe$_{4}$GeTe$_{2}$. This finding together with the observed signatures of the intrinsic two-dimensionality should facilitate optimization routes for the use of Fe$_{4}$GeTe$_{2}$ in the magneto-electronic devices, potentially even in the monolayer limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08722v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/adfm.202402551</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>R. Pal, J. J. Abraham, A. Mistonov, S. Mishra, N. Stilkerich, S. Mondal, P. Mandal, A. N. Pal, J. Geck, B. B\"uchner, V. Kataev, A. Alfonsov, Adv. Funct. Mater. 34, 2402551 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Riju Pal, Joyal J. Abraham, Alexander Mistonov, Swarnamayee Mishra, Nina Stilkerich, Suchanda Mondal, Prabhat Mandal, Atindra Nath Pal, Jochen Geck, Bernd B\"uchner, Vladislav Kataev, Alexey Alfonsov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Molybdenum Disulfide Bilayers Hybridized with Reduced Graphene Oxide Nanosheets for Enhanced Hydrogen Evolution Reaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08781v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2D) molybdenum disulfide (MoS2) nanosheets have attracted attention as a promising and cost-effective alternative catalyst for the hydrogen evolution reaction (HER). However, their aggregation and poor conductivity limit their catalytic activity. Consequently, researchers are exploring ways to improve the conductivity and density of electroactive edges of MoS2 through hybridization with akin advanced 2D materials. Here, reduced graphene oxide (rGO) nanosheets are added to a liquid-phase-exfoliated MoS2 dispersion to create drop-casting hybrid MoS2@rGO electrodes for HER. The findings reveal the formation of ~1.1 nm-thick MoS2 bilayers, with the catalytic performance of MoS2@rGO dependent on the degree of graphene oxide reduction. The rGO moderate reduction prevents the MoS2 bilayers from restacking, improves conductivity, retains oxygenated groups that enhance interlayer spacing, and exposes more electroactive edges. When hybridized with rGO crafted at optimal reduction time, the hybrid system eclipses the efficiency of pristine MoS2 bilayers by attaining the lowest overpotential (~70 mV) and the lowest Tafel slope (~46 mV dec-1). This shows that MoS2 bilayers hybridized with rGO offer a promising method to outperform the electrocatalytic efficiency of MoS2-based electrodes. These findings expand opportunities for future strain engineering, defect engineering, and high-end twist-angle assemblies for hybrid systems combining MoS2 bilayers and rGO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08781v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bruno Ferreira Brischi, Gabriela Frajtag, Jo\~ao Pedro da Silva Mariano, La\'is Fernanda Medeiros Ruela, Gustavo Duarte Ver\c{c}osa, Camila Desiderio Fernandes, Murilo Santhiago, Let\'icia Mari\^e Minatogau Ferro, Leandro Merces</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dominant Excitonic Superconductivity in a Three-component Hubbard Chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08784v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding superconductivity emerging from repulsive fermions remains a major challenge in condensed matter physics. In this paper, we investigate the pairing tendencies in a one-dimensional, three component repulsive Hubbard model, using the density matrix renormalization group method. At half-filling, the system exhibits density wave ground state due to strong Hubbard repulsions. Upon doping, we find that Cooper pairs can emerge, whose fluctuations predominate the long-range physics in the system across a wide parameter range. The effective attractions between Cooper pairs are mediated by the particle-hole fluctuations in the third non-pairing component, resembling an excitonic mechanism of superconductivity. The coexistence of multiple density waves and superconductivity at different fermion fillings is explored. We also present an analytical study of the pairing mechanism in both weak and strong coupling limits. Our results provide a new perspective for understanding and exploring unconventional superconductivities in strongly correlated fermionic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08784v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sheng Chen, Qiao Yang, W\'ei W\'u, Fadi Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low Energy Excitations of a 1D Fermi Gas with Attractive Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08866v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The low-energy excitations of a two-component repulsive Fermi gas confined to one dimension are linear dispersing spin- and charge-density waves whose respective propagation velocities depend on the strength and sign of their interaction. Quasi-1D fermions with attractive interaction realize the Luther-Emery liquid, which exhibits a rich array of phenomena, many of which are qualitatively different from those exhibited by their repulsive counterpart. We use a Feshbach resonance to access attractive interactions with $^6$Li atoms. We measured the spin and charge dynamic structure factors using Bragg spectroscopy and find that, contrary to repulsive interactions, the spin wave propagates faster than the charge density wave, thus producing an inversion of the classic spin-charge separation. We also find that a small spin polarization strongly suppresses the spin gap in the measured Bragg spectra. Evidence for pairing are a reduction in spin correlations with increasing attraction and RF spectra consistent with an atom/molecule mixture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08866v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aashish Kafle, Ruwan Senaratne, Danyel Cavazos-Cavazos, Hai-Ying Cui, Thierry Giamarchi, Han Pu, Xi-Wen Guan, Randall G. Hulet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-linear transport in multifold semimetals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08891</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08891v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Transport measurements are a powerful way to probe the electronic structure of quantum materials, but the information they contain is often convoluted. Yet, in particular for simple low-energy fermiologies, and by combining linear and non-linear responses, definite conclusion can be drawn -- such as, for instance, in the case of the circular photogalvanic effect in Weyl semimetals. Here, we derive the complete DC intrinsic transport response functions up to third order in the applied electric field within Boltzmann theory that hold combined information about quantum geometry and band dispersion. We discuss the responses for multifold fermions at high-symmetry momenta in time-reversal symmetric crystals as well as their reduction by symmetry constraints. We exemplify in detail the cases of space group 213 and space group 199, which realize different multifold fermions, and show under which conditions these low-energy excitations can be differentially addressed through their bulk nonlinear responses, enabling nonlinear valley-tronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08891v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Kouta Dagnino, Xiaoxiong Liu, Titus Neupert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dielectric permittivity tensor dynamics of in-plane hyperbolic van der Waals MoOCl2 and emergent chiral photonic applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08383</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.08383v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Van der Waals (vdW) crystals offer unique opportunities for modern nanophotonic applications owing to their intrinsic anisotropic nature. While most of them exhibit uniaxial anisotropy arising from weak out-of-plane vdW interaction, some of their representative families also exhibit an in-plane biaxial anisotropy. Among the latter, outstand vdW oxochlorides with in-plane axes of a different physical character (metallic or dielectric). Here, we present an accurate dynamics of dielectric permittivity tensor components of vdW MoOCl2 in the ultraviolet (UV) to visible (Vis) spectral region partly covering near-infrared (NIR). Addressing its enormously anisotropic optical constants, we focus on another hyperbolicity window of vdW MoOCl2 emerging in the UV spectral region that may potentially unlock rich light-matter interaction effects. Furthermore, we propose an approach towards designing nanoscale handedness preserved Vis light circular polarizers based on twisted helical vdW MoOCl2 heterostructures. Our findings display that vdW MoOCl2 provides a highly promising platform not only for hyperbolic, but also for chiral nanophotonic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.08383v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Artsruni Margaryan, Maksim Sargsyan, Meri Hayrapetyan, David Karakhanyan, Kostya S. Novoselov, Davit A. Ghazaryan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Triangular lattice models of the Kalmeyer-Laughlin spin liquid from coupled wires</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13223</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13223v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Chiral spin liquids (CSLs) are exotic phases of interacting spins in two dimensions, characterized by long-range entanglement and fractional excitations. We construct a local Hamiltonian on the triangular lattice that stabilizes the Kalmeyer-Laughlin CSL without requiring fine-tuning. Our approach employs coupled-wire constructions and introduces a lattice duality to construct a solvable chiral sliding Luttinger liquid, which is driven toward the CSL phase by generic perturbations. By combining symmetry analysis and bosonization, we make sharp predictions for the ground states on quasi-one-dimensional cylinders and tori, which exhibit a fourfold periodicity in the circumference. Extensive tensor network simulations demonstrating ground-state degeneracies, fractional quasiparticles, nonvanishing long-range order parameters, and entanglement signatures confirm the emergence of the CSL in the lattice Hamiltonian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13223v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/3nfx-fkfg</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 224415 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tingyu Gao, Niklas Tausendpfund, Erik L. Weerda, Jan Naumann, Matteo Rizzi, David F. Mross</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exactly solvable spin liquids in Kitaev bilayers and moir\'e superlattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04181</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04181v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Building on the recent advancements on moir\'e superlattices, we propose an exactly solvable model with Kitaev-type interactions on a bilayer honeycomb lattice for both AA stacking and moir\'e superlattices. Using Monte Carlo simulations and variational analysis, we uncover a rich variety of phases where the intra and interlayer $\mathbb{Z}_2$ fluxes (visons) are arranged in a periodic fashion in the ground state, tuned by interlayer coupling and out-of-plane external magnetic field. We further extend our model to moir\'e superlattices at various commensurate twist angles around two distinct twist centers represented by $C_{3z}$ and $C_{6z}$ of the honeycomb lattice. Our simulations reveal generalized arrangements of plaquette values that correlate with the AA or AB stacking regions across the moir\'e unit cell. Moreover, we find that, depending on the twist angle, twist center and interlayer coupling, moir\'e superlattices exhibit to a variety of gapped and gapless spin liquid phases and can also host corner and edge modes. Our results highlight the rich physics in bilayer and twisted bilayer models of exactly solvable quantum spin liquids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04181v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/2xvj-ns11</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 245118 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ivan Dutta, Anamitra Mukherjee, Onur Erten, Kush Saha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A molecule with half-M\"obius topology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03516</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03516v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Stereoisomers of C$_{13}$Cl$_2$ exhibiting helical orbitals around a ring of carbon atoms were synthesized by atom manipulation on NaCl surfaces. We resolved the enantiomeric geometries of the closed-shell singlet states by atomic force microscopy and mapped their helical orbital densities by scanning tunnelling microscopy. A ${\pi}$-orbital basis of the helical, non-planar singlets that twists by 90{\deg} in one circulation is consistent with a half-M\"obius topology. In such a topology, the ${\pi}$-orbital basis changes sign with respect to two circumnavigations and is periodic with respect to four circumnavigations. A quasiparticle on a ring with this boundary condition could be interpreted as carrying a Berry phase of ${\pi}$/2. We demonstrate reversible switching of the topology, between the two singlets of oppositely threaded half-M\"obius topology, and the planar, topologically trivial, triplet state. Multireference calculations, including large-scale sample-based ab initio calculations executed on quantum hardware, reveal that the switching is associated with a helical pseudo Jahn-Teller effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03516v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Igor Roncevic, Fabian Paschke, Yueze Gao, Leonard-Alexander Lieske, Lene A. G\"odde, Stefano Barison, Samuele Piccinelli, Alberto Baiardi, Ivano Tavernelli, Jascha Repp, Florian Albrecht, Harry L. Anderson, Leo Gross</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automated Construction of Artificial Lattice Structures with Designer Electronic States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02581v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Manipulating matter with a scanning tunneling microscope (STM) enables creation of atomically defined artificial structures that host designer quantum states. However, the time-consuming nature of the manipulation process, coupled with the sensitivity of the STM tip, constrains the exploration of diverse configurations and limits the size of designed features. In this study, we present a reinforcement learning (RL)-based framework for creating artificial structures by spatially manipulating carbon monoxide (CO) molecules on a copper substrate using the STM tip. The automated workflow combines molecule detection and manipulation, employing deep learning-based object detection to locate CO molecules and linear assignment algorithms to allocate these molecules to designated target sites. We initially perform molecule maneuvering based on randomized parameter sampling for sample bias, tunneling current setpoint and manipulation speed. This dataset is then structured into an action trajectory used to train an RL agent. The model is subsequently deployed on the STM for real-time fine-tuning of manipulation parameters during structure construction. Our approach incorporates path planning protocols coupled with active drift compensation to enable atomically precise fabrication of structures with significantly reduced human input while realizing larger-scale artificial lattices with desired electronic properties. Using our approach, we demonstrate the automated construction of an extended artificial graphene lattice and confirm the existence of characteristic Dirac point in its electronic structure. Further challenges to RL-based structural assembly scalability are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02581v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ganesh Narasimha, Mykola Telychko, Wooin Yang, Arthur P. Baddorf, P. Ganesh, An-Ping Li, Rama Vasudevan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact heat flux formula and its spectral decomposition in molecular dynamics for arbitrary many-body potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26044</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26044v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this study we have derived an exact framework for the calculation of the heat flux and its spectral decomposition in Molecular Dynamics (MD) for arbitrary many-body potentials. This work addresses several lacks and limitations of previous approaches and allows for the accurate computational study of thermal properties in a wide variety of many-body systems with MD. We have tested our modifications with Green-Kubo (GK) and Non-Equilibrium MD (NEMD) simulations for various 2D and 3D material systems using the Tersoff and Stillinger-Weber potentials as examples. The spectral decomposition of the heat current was also calculated for monolayer graphene (1LG) and MoS2 , for different system lengths. Our results show that the heat current calculated by our method is consistently in agreement with the thermostat current in NEMD, while previous implementations can estimate quite poorly the thermal conductivity both under GK and NEMD simulations, and both for 2D and 3D materials. The decomposition of the heat current also sheds light on the contribution of different phonon modes to thermal conductivity and its dependence on length. Our methodology is implemented in the widely used LAMMPS code specifically for the Tersoff and SW potentials, and it is readily applicable to the vast majority of many-body MD potentials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26044v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Markos Poulos, Donatas Surblys, Konstantinos Termentzidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay between Superconductivity and Altermagnetism in Disordered Materials and Heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04819</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04819v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the interplay between superconductivity and altermagnetism in disordered systems using recently derived quantum kinetic transport equations. Starting from this framework, we derive the Ginzburg-Landau free energy and identify, in addition to the conventional pair-breaking term, a coupling between the spin and the spatial variation of the superconducting order parameter. Two distinct effects emerge from this coupling. The first is a magnetoelectric effect, in which a supercurrent (i.e., a phase gradient) induces a spin texture; this contribution is quadratic in the phase gradient. The second effect arises when the magnitude, rather than the phase, of the superconducting order parameter varies in space, likewise leading to a finite magnetization. We show that these two contributions compete in the case of an Abrikosov vortex, where both the amplitude and phase of the order parameter vary spatially. The effect associated with amplitude variations also gives rise to a proximity-induced magnetization (PIM) in hybrid structures composed of a superconductor (S) and an altermagnet (AM). Using quasiclassical theory, we analyze the PIM in diffusive S/AM bilayers and S/AM/S Josephson junctions, and determine the induced magnetization profiles. In Josephson junctions, where both the PIM and the magnetoelectric effect coexist, we further predict the occurrence of $0$-$\pi$ transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04819v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rodrigo de las Heras, Tim Kokkeler, Stefan Ili\'c, Ilya V. Tokatly, F. Sebastian Bergeret</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
