<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 04:00:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Suppression of coherent light scattering in a three-dimensional atomic array</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10966</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10966v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding how atoms collectively interact with light is not only important for fundamental science, but also crucial for designing light-matter interfaces in quantum technologies. Over the past decades, numerous studies have focused on arranging atoms in ordered arrays and using constructive (destructive) interference to enhance (suppress) the coupling to electromagnetic fields, thereby tailoring collective light-matter interactions. These studies have mainly focused on one- and two-dimensional arrays. However, only three-dimensional (3D) arrays can demonstrate destructive interference of coherent light scattering in all directions. This omnidirectional suppression of coherent light scattering in 3D atomic arrays has thus far not been experimentally demonstrated. Here, we observe a strong reduction of light scattering in a 3D atomic array prepared in the form of a Mott insulator in optical lattices. The residual light scattering is shown to be caused by the delocalization of atoms, Raman scattering, and inelastic scattering associated with saturation. We also demonstrate how light scattering can be a sensitive probe for density fluctuations in many-body states in optical lattices, enabling us to characterize the superfluid-to-Mott insulator phase transition as well as defects generated by dynamical parameter ramps. The results of our work can be used to prepare subradiant states for photon storage and probe correlations for many-body systems in optical lattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10966v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Kun Lu, Hanzhen Lin, Jiahao Lyu, Yoo Kyung Lee, Vitaly Fedoseev, Wolfgang Ketterle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atomic perspective on the topological magnetism in kagome metal Co3Sn2S2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11140</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.11140v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Topological quantum materials with kagome lattices have attracted intense interest due to their unconventional electronic structures, which exhibit nontrivial topology, anomalous magnetism, and electronic correlations. Among these, Co3Sn2S2 stands out as a prototypical kagome metal, uniquely combining intrinsic ferromagnetism with topologically nontrivial electronic states. This perspective presents a systematic overview of recent advances in studying kagome metal Co3Sn2S2 achieved through scanning tunneling microscopy. We begin by introducing different methodologies for surface identification and propose using designer layer-selective chemical markers for conclusive surface identification. We then discuss the Berry curvature induced flat band orbital magnetism and the associated unconventional Zeeman effect. Furthermore, we explore boundary states arising from Weyl topology and analyze challenges in detecting Fermi arcs via quasiparticle interference patterns and in uncovering the topological aspect of the edge states. Finally, we review recent observations of spin-orbit-coupled quantum impurity states through spin-polarized tunneling spectroscopy, as well as their connection to Weyl topology and flat band magnetism. We also provide in-depth analysis and constructive comments on the limitations of the current research approach. This review highlights the critical role of scanning tunneling microscopy in unraveling the intricate interplay between topology, magnetism, and correlations at the atomic scale, and the methodology discussed here can be applied to study other topological quantum materials in general.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.11140v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guowei Liu, Wei Song, Titus Neupert, M. Zahid Hasan, Hanbin Deng, Jia-Xin Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fermi-liquid-like phase driven by next-nearest-neighbor couplings in a lightly doped kagome-lattice $t$-$J$ model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11322</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.11322v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Due to the interplay between charge fluctuation and geometry frustration, the doped kagome-lattice Mott insulator is a fascinating platform to realize exotic quantum states. Through the state-of-the-art density matrix renormalization group calculation, we explore the quantum phases of the lightly doped kagome-lattice $t$-$J$ model in the presence of the next-nearest-neighbor electron hopping $t_2$ and spin interaction $J_2$. On the $L_y = 3$ cylinder ($L_y$ is the number of unit cells along the circumference direction), we establish a quantum phase diagram with tuning $t_2 &gt; 0$ and $J_2 &gt; 0$, showing an emergent Fermi-liquid-like phase driven by increased $t_2$ and $J_2$, which sits at the neighbor of the previously identified charge density wave (CDW) phase. Compared with the CDW phase, the charge order is significantly suppressed in the Fermi-liquid-like phase, and most correlation functions are greatly enhanced with power-law decay. In particular, we find the absence of hole pairing and a strong three-sublattice magnetic correlation. On the wider $L_y = 4$ cylinder, this Fermi-liquid-like phase persists at low doping levels, strongly suggesting that this state might be stable in the two-dimensional kagome system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.11322v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xu-Yan Jia (School of Physics, Beihang University), Fan Yang (School of Physics, Beijing Institute of Technology), D. N. Sheng (Department of Physics and Astronomy, California State University Northridge, Northridge), Shou-Shu Gong (School of Physical Sciences, Great Bay University, Great Bay Institute for Advanced Study)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A non-Hermitian Su-Schrieffer-Heeger model with the energy levels of free parafermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.11601v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using a parent Hermitian tight-binding model on a bipartite lattice with chiral symmetry, we theoretically generate non-Hermitian models for free fermions with $p$ orbitals per unit cell satisfying a complex generalization of chiral symmetry. The $p$ complex energy bands in $k$ space are given by a common $k$-dependent real factor, determined by the bands of the parent model, multiplied by the $p$th roots of unity. When the parent model is the Su-Schrieffer-Heeger (SSH) model, the single-particle energy levels are the same as those of free parafermion solutions to Baxter's non-Hermitian clock model. This construction relies on fully unidirectional hopping to create Bloch Hamiltonians with the form of generalized permutation matrices, but we also describe the effect of partial unidirectional hopping. For fully bidirectional hopping, the Bloch Hamiltonians are Hermitian and may be separated into even and odd parity blocks with respect to inversion of the orbitals within the unit cell. Partially unidirectional hopping breaks the inversion symmetry and mixes the even and odd blocks, and the real energy spectrum evolves into a complex one as the degree of unidirectionality increases, with details determined by the topology of the parent model and the number of orbitals per unit cell, $p$. We describe this process in detail for $p=3$ and $p=4$ with the SSH model. We also apply our approach to graphene, and show that $AA$-stacked bilayer graphene evolves into a square root Hamiltonian of monolayer graphene with the introduction of unidirectional hopping. We show that higher-order exceptional points occur at edge states and solitons in the non-Hermitian SSH model, and at the Dirac point of non-Hermitian graphene.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.11601v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Edward McCann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Increasing the proximity induced spin-orbit coupling in bilayer graphene/WSe$_2$ heterostructures with pressure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.20062</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.20062v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Combining graphene with transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) leads to enhanced spin-orbit coupling (SOC) in the graphene. The induced SOC has a large effect on the low-energy part of the band structure leading to or stabilizing novel phases such as topological phases or superconductivity. Here, the pressure dependence of the SOC strength is investigated in bilayer graphene/WSe$_2$ heterostructures. We performed magnetoconductance studies, such as weak localization, quantum Hall, and Shubnikov-de Haas oscillation measurements to extract the different SOC terms which determine the low-energy band structure of BLG. We find the proximity-induced SOC strengths increased by more than 50\% as a result of applying 2\,GPa hydrostatic pressure. Our studies highlight the opportunity to increase the SOC coupling strength with pressure, which can be important for correlated phases or spin qubits in BLG/WSe$_2$ heterostructures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.20062v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.205415</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>B\'alint Szentp\'eteri, Albin M\'arffy, M\'at\'e Kedves, Endre T\'ov\'ari, B\'alint F\"ul\"op, Istv\'an K\"ukemezey, Andr\'as Magyarkuti, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Szabolcs Csonka, P\'eter Makk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonthermal order by disorder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02616</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02616v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The quench dynamics of systems exhibiting cooperative or almost competitive orders in equilibrium are explored using Ginzburg-Landau theory plus fluctuations. We show that when the renormalization of the free energy by fluctuations is taken into account, anisotropic stiffnesses and relaxation rates of the order parameters can lead to a stabilization of ordered states at transient free energy minima which are distinct from any (global or local) minima of the equilibrium free energy. This theory demonstrates that nonequilibrium fluctuations play a pivotal role in forming nonthermal orders. As nonthermal order and nonthermal fluctuations mutually stabilize each other over some time, this mechanism could be seen as a nonequilibrium variant of the order-by-disorder phenomenon. We discuss the potential relevance of these findings for systems with intertwined orders, such as superconductivity and density wave orders, relevant for high-temperature superconductors and the kagome metals, as well as for systems that show orbital ordering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02616v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.newton.2025.100169</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Newton 1, 6, 100169 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Grandi, Antonio Picano, Ronny Thomale, Dante M. Kennes, Martin Eckstein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phases and critical transport of the SU(N) Hofstadter-Hubbard model on the triangular lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10023</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10023v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report the study of phases and transitions of SU(N) Hofstadter-Hubbard model subject to commensurate magnetic field on the triangular lattice. At filling one fermion per site, for the number of fermion flavors 2 &lt;= N &lt;= 8, we identify three distinct phases and calculate critical interaction strength from parton mean-field approximation. Integer quantum Hall, chiral spin liquid, and valence bond solid states could be realized upon varying the Hubbard interaction U and the number of flavor N . We construct the critical theory for the putative continuous transition from quantum Hall states to chiral spin liquid and calculate the critical transport behavior using quantum Boltzmann equations for general N . These results could be validated in synthetic systems such as moir'e superlattices and cold atom platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10023v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lu Zhang, Rongning Liu, Xue-Yang Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vibration-assisted tunneling through single Au adatoms on two-dimensional WSe2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12055</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.12055v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) at 5 K was used to study individual Au atoms adsorbed on the surface of a WSe2 layer grown on epitaxial graphene. In line with theoretical predictions, scanning tunneling spectroscopy measurements reveal that the weakly bound adatom gives rise to an electronic state within the energy band gap of the WSe2 layer. Adatoms in different surface locations show different gap-state energy values that follow a random distribution around the Fermi level of the sample with a standard deviation of ~50 meV. The location-dependent shift is attributed to spatial variations in disorder potential. Tunneling via the gap state is accompanied by vibrational excitations as apparent from pronounced sideband peaks in the conductance spectra with Poisson-distributed intensities indicating significant electron-phonon coupling with a Huang-Rhys factor of S=2.8. STM tunneling through single Au adatoms on two-dimensional WSe2 constitutes a model case of resonant double-barrier tunneling accompanied by strong coupling to vibrational degrees of freedom.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.12055v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/nfd8-xrc4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 085414 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hitesh Kumar, Yu-Chuan Lin, Joshua A. Robinson, Stefan F\"olsch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum geometric origin of the Meissner effect and superfluid weight marker</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.17349v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The momentum space of conventional superconductors is recently recognized to possess a quantum metric defined from the overlap of filled quasihole states at neighboring momenta. For multiband superconductors with arbitrary intraband and interband s-wave pairing, we elaborate that their superfluid weight in London equations is given by the momentum integration of the elements of quantum metric times the quasiparticle energy, indicating the quantum geometric origins of Meissner effect and vortex state. The momentum integration of the quantum metric further yields a spread of quasihole Wannier functions that characterizes the stability of the superconducting state. Our formalism allows the diamagnetic response of conventional superconductors to be mapped to individual lattice sites as a superfluid weight marker, which can incorporate the effect of disorder through self-consistently solving the Bogoliubov-de Gennes equations. Using single-band s-wave superconductors in 2D and 3D as examples, our marker reveals a diamagnetic current that becomes turbulent in the presence of nonmagnetic impurities, and the increase of London penetration depth by disorder that is consistent with experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.17349v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/9fsf-9j53</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 054511 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>David Porlles, Wei Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconductivity in imbalanced bilayer Hubbard model: enhanced $d$-wave and weakened $s^\pm$-wave pairing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10503</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10503v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the bilayer model with two layers of imbalanced densities coupled by the interlayer hybridization. Using the large-scale dynamical cluster quantum Monte Carlo simulation, we discovered that increased hybridization induces a transition in the superconducting pairing from $d$-wave to $s^{\pm}$-wave and the superconducting $T_c$ of $d$-wave pairing exhibits a non-monotonic dependence on the density imbalance. Remarkably, the optimal SC occurs at a moderate imbalance, whose SC is solely hosted by the layer with higher density (lower hole doping). Our results support the possibility of $T_c$ enhancement in composite picture where the underdoped layer provides the pairing strength while the overdoped layer promotes the phase coherence. The uncovered SC hosted by a single layer is reminiscent of our recent exploration on the trilayer Hubbard model. Our present study thus provides new insight that the SC can be enhanced via the layer differentiation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10503v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziying Jia, Xun Liu, Mi Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
