<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 05:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Paramagnetic Phases of Strongly Correlated Ultracold Fermions Coupled to an Optical Cavity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10802</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10802v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We numerically study a gas of two-component fermions coupled to a transversely pumped optical cavity and confined to a two-dimensional static square optical lattice. In the dispersive regime, the steady state of the system is described by an extended Hubbard Hamiltonian with cavity-mediated long-range interactions. Using real-space dynamical mean-field theory (RDMFT), we investigate the formation of the (superradiant) checkerboard density-wave phase both at quarter and half filling. We focus on the paramagnetic phase assuming sufficiently high temperatures such that no magnetic long-range order develops. At quarter filling, we find a reentrant homogeneous Fermi liquid to density wave phase transition with increasing temperature, which is due to the higher entropy of the ordered phase. At half filling, in addition to the Fermi liquid to Mott insulator phase transition, marked by a vanishing quasiparticle residue at the Fermi level, we identify the transition into a density-wave phase. Due to perfect Fermi surface nesting at half filling, we find that arbitrarily small long-range interactions destabilize the system towards the density-wave phase in the absence of short-range interactions. By varying short- and long-range interactions at a fixed low temperature, we obtain the full phase diagram and identify a region of coexistence between the homogeneous Fermi liquid and Mott insulating phase with the density-wave phase. In this region, we determine the thermodynamic phase transition by comparing the energies of the different RDMFT solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10802v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Renan da Silva Souza, Youjiang Xu, Walter Hofstetter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anyonic Chern insulator in graphene induced by surface electromagnon vacuum fluctuations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10836</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10836v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Sub-wavelength cavities have emerged as a promising platform to realize strong light-matter coupling in condensed matter systems. Previous studies are limited to dielectric sub-wavelength cavities, which preserve time-reversal symmetry. Here, we lift this constraint by proposing a cavity system based on magneto-electric materials, which host surface electromagnons with non-orthogonal electric field and magnetic field components. The quantum fluctuations of the surface electromagnons drive a nearby graphene monolayer into an anyonic Chern insulator, characterized by anyonic quasi-particles and a topological gap that decays polynomially with the graphene-substrate distance. Our work opens a path to controllably break time-reversal symmetry and induce exotic quantum states through cavity vacuum fluctuations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10836v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinle Cheng, Emil Vi\~nas Bostr\"om, Frank Y. Gao, Edoardo Baldini, Dante M. Kennes, Angel Rubio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mechanistic Transition from Screw to Edge Dislocation Glide Enhances High-Temperature Strength in Refractory Complex Concentrated Alloys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10869v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The strength of body-centered cubic materials is traditionally known to be governed by screw dislocations. However, recent findings reveal that in certain refractory complex concentrated alloys, edge dislocations can instead control strength. This work integrates high-temperature mechanical testing, in-situ neutron scattering during heating and tension, scanning transmission electron microscopy, and molecular dynamics simulations to uncover the mechanism behind this behavior. In the Nb-Ta-Ti-V system, increasing the V content, due to its smaller atomic size, induces substantial atomic misfit that raises the glide barrier for edge dislocations relative to screw dislocations. This effect drives a gradual transition from screw to edge dislocation-controlled deformation, leading to markedly enhanced strength at elevated temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10869v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tamanna Zakia, Ayeman Nahin, Dunji Yu, Jacob Pustelnik, Juntan Li, Mason Kincheloe, Lia Amalia, Yan Chen, Peter K. Liaw, Haixuan Xu, Mingwei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lead-Free Europium Halide Perovskite Nanoplatelets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10873v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Metal halide perovskites possess desirable optical, material, and electrical properties which have had substantial impact on next-generation optoelectronics. However, given the toxicity of lead, alternative lead-free perovskite semiconductors are needed. By fully replacing lead with rare-earth elements, one can simultaneously address toxicity concerns and achieve comparable optoelectronic performance. Here, we demonstrate the synthesis of two-dimensional europium halide perovskite nanoplatelets governed by the formula $\mathrm{L_{2}EuX_{4}}$ where L is an organic ligand and X is a halide anion. The structure, morphology, and composition of the nanoplatelets are confirmed by XRD, AFM, and XPS. Deep blue-emitting $\mathrm{PEA_{2}EuBr_{4}}$ perovskite nanoplatelets are synthesized in both the solution- and solid-states with photoluminescence emission centered at 446 nm and CIE color coordinates of (0.1515, 0.0327) and (0.1515, 0.0342), respectively. Additionally, near-ultraviolet $\mathrm{PEA_{2}EuCl_{4}}$ perovskite nanoplatelets are synthesized in both the solution- and solid-states with photoluminescence emission centered at 400 nm and 401 nm, respectively. Overall, europium halide perovskite nanoplatelets offer a lead-free alternative for deep blue, violet, and near-ultraviolet light emission $\unicode{x2013}$ charting new pathways for optoelectronics in this energy regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10873v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Fern\'andez, Divine Mbachu, Manchen Hu, Han Cui, William Michaels, Pournima Narayanan, Tyler K. Colenbrander, Qi Zhou, Da Lin, Ona Segura Lecina, Guosong Hong, Daniel N. Congreve</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parametric resonance in a spin-1/2 chain: dynamical effects of nontrivial topology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10891</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10891v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Resonant parametric modulation is a major tool of studying magnetic systems. For a spin-1/2 chain in a strong magnetic field, the resulting excitations can be mapped on fermionic excitations in the Kitaev chain. We show that the response to the modulation turn-on allows one to reveal dynamical aspects of the nontrivial topology of the periodic chain. In the topological regime, depending on how fast the turn-on is, the system displays the absence of spatial magnetization correlations or their increase with the increasing detuning of the modulation from resonance. The transition between the topological and trivial regimes is controlled by the modulation frequency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10891v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahmoud T. Elewa, M. I. Dykman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of Nitrogen Atom Clusters and Vacancy Defects on Graphene: A Molecular Dynamics Investigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10908v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Graphene's exceptional mechanical properties are crucial for its integration into advanced technological applications. However, real-world synthesis and functionalization processes introduce structural modifications that can compromise its mechanical integrity. Nitrogen doping, while beneficial for electronic property tuning, often results in atomic clustering rather than uniform distribution, while concurrent vacancy defect formation represents another common structural alteration during processing. This study systematically investigates the comparative effects of nitrogen atom clusters and equivalent sized vacancy defects on the mechanical behavior of graphene sheets through molecular dynamics simulations. The Nitrogen clustering significantly degraded mechanical performance almost similarly to random doping. In comparison, systems with equivalent-sized vacancy defects showed higher stiffness and lower ductility than those with clusters. The study revealed distinct failure mechanisms between doped and defective configurations, with nitrogen clusters showing modified crack propagation patterns while vacancies acted as pronounced stress concentrators, leading to premature failure. However, this study also showed that defect morphology critically influences mechanical properties. These findings provide important insights for optimizing graphene synthesis and processing protocols, highlighting the differential mechanical risks associated with dopant clustering versus vacancy formation. The results inform defect-tolerant design strategies for graphene-based nanoelectronics, composites, and sensors, where mechanical reliability is paramount for device performance and longevity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10908v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Indranil Rudra, Md. Moktadir Billah Tahmid, Jahid Emon, Mohammad Jane Alam Khan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ripple-assisted adsorption of noble gases on graphene at room temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10951v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Controllable gas adsorption is critical for both scientific and industrial fields, and high-capacity adsorption of gases on solid surfaces provides a significant promise due to its high-safety and low-energy consumption. However, the adsorption of nonpolar gases, particularly noble gases, poses a considerable challenge under atmospheric pressure and room temperature (RT). Here, we theoretically simulate and experimentally realize the stable adsorption of noble gases like xenon (Xe), krypton (Kr), argon (Ar), and helium (He) on highly rippled graphene at RT. The elemental characteristics of adsorbed Xe are confirmed by electron energy loss spectroscopy and X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy. The adsorbed gas atoms are crystalized with periodic arrangements. These adsorbed noble gases on graphene exhibit high stability at RT and can be completely desorbed at approximately 350 {\deg}C without damaging the intrinsic lattice of graphene. The structural and physical properties of graphene are significantly influenced by the adsorbed gas, and they fully recover after desorption. Additionally, this controllable adsorption could be generalized to other layered adsorbents such as NbSe2, MoS2 and carbon nanotubes. We anticipate that this ripple-assisted adsorption will not only re-define the theoretical framework of gas adsorption, but also accelerate advancements in gas storage and separation technologies, as well as enhance the applications in catalysis, surface modification, and other related fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10951v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weilin Liu, Xianlei Huang, Li-Guo Dou, Qianglong Fang, Ang Li, Guowen Yuan, Yongjie Xu, Zhenjia Zhou, Jun Li, Yu Jiang, Zichong Huang, Zihao Fu, Peng-Xiang Hou, Chang Liu, Jinlan Wang, Wu Zhou, Ming-Gang Ju, Shao-Chun Li, Hui-Ming Cheng, Libo Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of doping on hot-carrier thermal breakdown in perforated graphene metasurfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10960</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10960v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We examine the robustness of the S-shaped current-voltage characteristics associated with hot-carrier-induced electrical breakdown in perforated graphene metasurfaces (PGMs) as a function of doping. The perforation of the graphene layer forms interdigital arrays of graphene microribbons (GMRs) interconnected by graphene nanoribbon (GNR) bridges. These GNR constrictions act as energy barriers for electrons and holes emitted from the GMRs and govern the inter-GMR thermionic current under an applied bias voltage. The doping and the voltage bias establish distinct electron and hole populations in adjacent GMRs. Peltier heating of these carriers within the GMRs increases their effective temperatures, thereby enhancing the inter-GMR current. The resulting positive feedback between carrier heating and current amplification can trigger an electrothermal breakdown, transforming a superlinear current-voltage dependence into an S-shaped characteristic exhibiting negative differential resistance. The degree of electron-hole asymmetry significantly influences this positive feedback and strongly modifies the overall current-voltage response. These results provide a framework for optimizing PGM-based devices employing GMR/GNR architectures, including voltage-controlled fast switches, incandescent emitters, and terahertz bolometric detectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10960v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Ryzhii, V. Ryzhii, C. Tang, T. Otsuji, M. S. Shur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nearly semi-elliptic relation between the minimal conductivity and Hall conductivity in unpaired Dirac fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10972v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Electric conductivities may reveal the topological and magnetic properties of band structures in solids, especially for two-dimensional unpaired Dirac fermions. In this work, we evaluate the longitudinal and Hall conductivity for unpaired Dirac fermions in the framework of the self-consistent Born approximation and find a nearly semi-elliptic relation between the minimal conductivity and Hall conductivities in the Dirac fermions. Near the charge neutrality point, disorder may drive a metal-insulator transition, and enhance the longitudinal conductivity. For the massless case, the minimal conductivity $\sigma_{xx}^*$ coexists with the half-quantized Hall conductivity $e^2/2h$, forming an indicator for the parity anomalous semimetal. The relation signals a disorder-induced metallic phase that bridges two topologically distinct insulating phases, and agrees with the recent experimental observation in magnetic topological insulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10972v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bo Fu, Kai-Zhi Bai, Shi-Hao Bi, Shun-Qing Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic structure of relaxor ferroelectrics from first principles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11097v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We hybridize swap Monte Carlo and geometric relaxation to determine the intrinsic compositional structure (CS) of lead magnesium niobate (PMN) relaxor. We verify the stability of a Nb-rich sublattice in PMN, as prescribed by the prevailing random-site model. But ions in the complementary sublattice are not randomly mixed. The majority of Nb ions collapse into a dominant Nb cluster which percolates the lattice with a mesh-like geometry that prevents large space charges. Subsequent molecular dynamics simulations predict a pair distribution function agreeing with neutron scattering experiments. Analysis of dipolar structures in the Nb cluster sheds light on the unique dielectric property of PMN.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11097v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinyu Xu, Kehan Cai, Pinchen Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Field-tunable partial antiferromagnetism, glassy spin dynamics, and magnetodielectric coupling in the quasi-one-dimensional spin-chain compound Ca3CoIrO6</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11127v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report a comprehensive investigation of the quasi-one-dimensional spin-chain compound Ca3CoIrO6 (CCIO) using a combination of structural, magnetic, thermodynamic, transport, Raman, and dielectric measurements. Temperature-dependent neutron powder diffraction confirms the rhombohedral R-3c structure down to 5 K without any structural phase transition. DC magnetization, ac susceptibility, and relaxation measurements reveal a gradual evolution from a high-temperature paramagnetic-like state to a partially disordered antiferromagnetic (PDA) state below 100 K, accompanied by slow cluster-like spin dynamics followed by a freezing transition near 30 K. Isothermal magnetic hysteresis M(H) loops demonstrate partial chain freezing, while robust exchange bias is observed in field-cooled protocols, highlighting the interplay between PDA ordering and frozen spins. Resistivity and specific heat data indicate strong coupling between spin and charge degrees of freedom, accompanied by activated transport behavior. Raman spectroscopy identifies pronounced anomalies in phonon frequencies and linewidths across multiple magnetic regimes, reflecting strong spin-lattice coupling. Polarization-electric field (P-E) measurements reveal temperature-dependent crossovers from linear dielectric to weakly hysteretic behavior, consistent with short-range polar correlations driven by spin-lattice interactions. These findings establish CCIO as a prototypical quasi-one-dimensional frustrated spin-chain system where geometric frustration, spin-orbit coupling, and low-dimensionality generate field-tunable PDA order, glassy spin dynamics, exchange bias, and magnetodielectric coupling. These results provide new insights into frustration-driven phases in low-dimensional oxides and point towards potential multifunctional applications based on intrinsic magnetodielectric and exchange bias phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11127v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Priyanka Mahalle (Solid State Physics Division, Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, Mumbai-400085, India, Homi Bhabha National Institute, Anushaktinagar, Mumbai-400094, India), A. Kumar (Solid State Physics Division, Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, Mumbai-400085, India, Homi Bhabha National Institute, Anushaktinagar, Mumbai-400094, India), Kumar Bharti (Department of Mechanical Engineering, Indian Institute of Technology Bombay, Mumbai 400076, India), Dipanshu Bansal (Department of Mechanical Engineering, Indian Institute of Technology Bombay, Mumbai 400076, India), P. D. Babu (UGC-DAE Consortium for Scientific Research, Mumbai Centre, BARC Campus, Mumbai 400 085, India), S. M. Yusuf (Solid State Physics Division, Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, Mumbai-400085, India, Homi Bhabha National Institute, Anushaktinagar, Mumbai-400094, India)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable electronic band structure in WSSe van der Waals Alloys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11146v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The electronic structure of semiconducting 2D materials such as transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) is known to be tunable by its environment, from simple external fields applied with electrical contacts up to complex van der Waals heterostructure assemblies. However, conventional alloying from reference binary TMD compounds to composition-controlled ternary alloys also offers unexplored opportunities. In this work, we use nano-angle resolved photoemission spectroscopy (nano-ARPES) and density functional theory (DFT) calculations to study the structural and electronic properties of different alloy compositions of bulk WS2(1-x)Se2x. Our results demonstrate the continuous variation of the band structure and the progressive evolution of the valence band splitting at the K points from 420 to 520 meV in bulk WS2(1-x)Se2x. We also carried out scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) measurements and DFT to understand the possible S or Se substitutions variants in WS2(1-x)Se2x alloys, with different local atomic configurations. Our work opens up perspectives for the fine control of the band dispersion in van der Waals materials and demonstrate how the band structure can be tuned in bulk TMDs. The collected information can serve as a reference for future applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11146v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PRB 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Meryem Bouaziz, Leonard Schue, Noeliarinala Felana Andriambelaza, Natalia Alyabyeva, Jean-Christophe Girard, Pavel Dudin, Fabian Cadiz, Jose Avila, Yannick Dappe, Cesar Gonzalez, Julien Chaste, Fabrice Oehler, Christine Giorgetti, Fausto Sirotti, Abdelkarim Ouerghi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic and magnetic properties of light rare-earth cubic Laves compounds derived from XMCD experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11260</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11260v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work presents electronic and magnetic properties of selected members in the cubic Laves phase series Nd1-xPrxCoNi and Ce0.25Pr0.75CoNi, together with the corresponding binary compositions (NdCo2, NdNi2, PrCo2, PrNi2, CeCo2, CeNi2), using soft x-ray absorption spectroscopy, x-ray magnetic circular dichroism (XMCD), density-functional theory, and crystal field multiplet calculations. All transition-metal moments saturate below 1 T, while the rare-earth moments do not saturate even at 5 T, consistent with van Vleck paramagnetic contributions and crystal field suppression. While the sum rules are widely used to extract element-specific magnetic moments from XMCD, we show that for 3d transition metals, their application requires accurate estimates of the number of unoccupied 3d states. We observe a finite magnetic moment on Ni, challenging the common assumption of its nonmagnetic character in Laves phases. The orbital magnetic moments were determined using the spin rules, while the spin moments were estimated from single-ion values from multiplet calculations, due to the invalidity of the spin sum rule for light rare-earth elements. The magnetic moments of Nd and Pr are found to be suppressed relative to their free-ion values, with multiplet theory indicating that this is due to crystal field effects. Our results confirm that Nd and Pr maintain localized 4f3 and 4f2 configurations, respectively, and that their element-specific magnetic moments are robust to rare-earth substitution. Ce, on the other hand, exhibits a tunable mixed-valent ground state with both magnetic 4f1 and nonmagnetic 4f0 components. The relative fraction of these states varies with the electronegativity of the surrounding 3d transition metals, revealing a pathway to tune Ce magnetism via composition. This work establishes a framework for accurately interpreting XMCD in light rare-earth-based intermetallics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11260v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vilde G. S. Lunde, Benedicte S. Ofstad, {\O}ystein S. Fjellv{\aa}g, Philippe Ohresser, Anja O. Sj{\aa}stad, Bj{\o}rn C. Hauback, Christoph Frommen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological states and flat bands in exactly solvable decorated Cayley trees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11261v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We derive the full spectrum of decorated Cayley trees that constitute tree analogs of selected two-dimensional Euclidean lattices; namely of the Lieb, the double Lieb, the kagome, and the star lattice. The common feature of these Euclidean lattices is that their nearest-neighbor models give rise to flat energy bands interpretable through compact localized states. We find that the tree analogs exhibit similar flat or nearly flat energy bands at the corresponding energies. Interestingly, such flat bands in the decorated Cayley trees acquire an interpretation that is absent in their Euclidean counterparts: as edge states localized to the inner or the outer boundary of the tree branches. In particular, we establish an exact correspondence between the Lieb-Cayley tree and an ensemble of one-dimensional Su-Schrieffer-Heeger chains, which maps topological edge states on one side of the chains to flat-band states localized in the bulk of the tree, furnishing the flat energy band with a topological stability. Similar mapping to topological edge states or to states bound to edge defects in one-dimensional chains is shown for flat-band states in all the considered tree decorations. We finally show that the persistence of exact flat bands on infinite decorated trees (i.e., Bethe lattices) arises naturally from a covering interpretation of tree graphs. Our findings reveal a rich landscape of flat-band and topological phenomena in non-Euclidean systems, where geometry alone can generate and stabilize unconventional quantum states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11261v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wanda P. Duss, Askar Iliasov, Tom\'a\v{s} Bzdu\v{s}ek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wiener-Hopf factorization and non-Hermitian topology for Amoeba formulation in one-dimensional multiband systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11349v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The non-Hermitian skin effect (NHSE), characterized by the extensive localization of bulk modes at the boundaries, has attracted significant attention as a hallmark feature of non-Hermitian topology. This localization invalidates the conventional Bloch band theory, necessitating an analysis under open boundary conditions even in the thermodynamic limit. The Amoeba formulation addresses this challenge by computing the spectral potential rather than the spectrum itself. Based on the (strong) Szeg\"o limit theorem and its topological generalization, this approach reduces the evaluation of the potential to an optimization problem involving the Ronkin function. However, while the generalized Szeg\"o limit theorem is formally applicable in arbitrary dimensions, its implementation is limited to single-band systems, and its applicability to multiband systems remains unclear. In this paper, we establish the Wiener-Hopf factorization (WHF) of the non-Bloch Hamiltonian as a powerful framework, providing a unified and rigorous foundation for Amoeba analysis in multiband systems. By combining the WHF with Hermitian doubling, we first elucidate the applicability criteria for the generalized Szeg\"o limit theorem in multiband systems. We then show that the WHF provides the natural mathematical origin for the symmetry-decomposed Ronkin function in symmetry class AII$^\dagger$, leading to a rigorous proof of the generalized Szeg\"o limit theorem for these systems and opening a path toward systematic generalizations to other symmetry classes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11349v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shin Kaneshiro, Robert Peters</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interlinking helical spin textures in nanopatterned chiral magnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11372</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11372v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nanoscale topologically non-trivial magnetization configurations generate significant interest due to both the fundamental properties of their knotted structures and their potential applications in ultra-efficient computing devices. While such textures have been widely studied in two dimensions, three-dimensional (3D) systems can yield more complex configurations, resulting in richer topologies and dynamic behaviors. However, reliably nucleating these 3D textures has proven challenging, and so far, 3D configurations such as vortex rings and hopfions can often only be observed forming spontaneously in relatively uncontrolled manners. Here, we demonstrate that through the 3D nanopatterning of chiral single crystal helimagnets into nano-tori, the controlled formation of a magnetic double helix can be achieved. This surface-localized topological state is stabilized by the interplay of intrinsic exchange interactions of the single crystal with the extrinsic emergent effects of the patterned geometry. These double helices host magnetic defects akin to supercoiling in circular DNA and climbing vines. We expect this study to serve as a foundation for future research combining single crystal systems with 3D nanopatterning, offering a new degree of control over emergent phenomena in nanoscale magnets and wider quantum material systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11372v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luke Alexander Turnbull, Max Thomas Birch, Marisel Di Pietro Mart\'inez, Rikako Yamamoto, Jeffrey Neethirajan, Marina Raboni Ferreira, Elina Zhakina, Hayden Jeffrey Binger, Young-Gwan Choi, Rachid Belkhou, Simone Finizio, Markus Weigand, Dieter Suess, Daniel Alexander Mayoh, Geetha Balakrishnan, Claas Abert, Sebastian Wintz, Claire Donnelly</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relaxation to an Ideal Chern Band through Coupling to a Markovian Bath</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11394</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11394v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a microscopic, weak-coupling mechanism by which generic Chern bands relax toward ideal bands. We consider coupling interacting electrons to a Caldeira-Leggett like Ohmic bosonic bath. Using the Born-Markov approximation, Slater determinant states of a Chern band under Hartree-Fock approximation evolve toward Slater determinant states corresponding to an ideal Chern band. We validate our proposal by performing numerical simulation of a massive Dirac model, showing that the Berry curvature and quantum metric indeed co-evolve to saturate the trace condition. Our proposal provides a concrete dissipative route to realize ideal Chern bands, a fundamental building block for the stabilization of fractional Chern insulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11394v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bruno Mera, Tomoki Ozawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ARPES signatures of trions in van der Waals materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11448v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) has recently emerged as a direct probe of excitonic correlations in two-dimensional semiconductors, resolving their dispersion and dynamics in energy-momentum space, including dark exciton states inaccessible to optical techniques. However, the ARPES fingerprint of charged excitons (trions), which plays a key role in all doped and gated 2D material systems, has remained unknown so far. We present a first theoretical analysis of trion signatures in monolayer transition-metal dichalcogenides, highlighting how the additional charge carrier modifies the spectral position and shape relative to neutral excitons in ARPES spectra. Interestingly, we further predict that mass-imbalanced trions yield a characteristic double-peak structure, clearly separated in energy and line shape from neutral excitons. The predicted temperature dependence of these features offers guidance for experimental investigations aimed at identifying trionic states, thereby establishing a framework for ARPES studies of many-body Coulomb complexes in doped two-dimensional semiconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11448v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giuseppe Meneghini, Maja L\"owe, Raul Perea-Causin, Jan Philipp Bange, Wiebke Bennecke, Marcel Reutzel, Stefan Mathias, Ermin Malic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coherent-state path integrals in quantum thermodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11547v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In these notes, we elucidate some subtle aspects of coherent-state path integrals, focusing on their application to the equilibrium thermodynamics of quantum many-particle systems. These subtleties emerge when evaluating path integrals in the continuum, either in imaginary time or in Matsubara-frequency space. Our central message is that, when handled with due care, the path integral yields results identical to those obtained from the canonical Hamiltonian approach. We illustrate this through a pedagogical treatment of several paradigmatic systems: the bosonic and fermionic harmonic oscillators, the single-site Bose-Hubbard and Hubbard models, the weakly-interacting Bose gas with contact and finite-range interactions, and the BCS superconductor with contact and finite-range interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11547v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Salasnich, Cesare Vianello</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Human-AI collaborative autonomous synthesis with pulsed laser deposition for remote epitaxy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11558v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Autonomous laboratories typically rely on data-driven decision-making, occasionally with human-in-the-loop oversight to inject domain expertise. Fully leveraging AI agents, however, requires tightly coupled, collaborative workflows spanning hypothesis generation, experimental planning, execution, and interpretation. To address this, we develop and deploy a human-AI collaborative (HAIC) workflow that integrates large language models for hypothesis generation and analysis, with collaborative policy updates driving autonomous pulsed laser deposition (PLD) experiments for remote epitaxy of BaTiO$_3$/graphene. HAIC accelerated the hypothesis formation and experimental design and efficiently mapped the growth space to graphene-damage. In situ Raman spectroscopy reveals that chemistry drives degradation while the highest energy plume components seed defects, identifying a low-O$_2$ pressure low-temperature synthesis window that preserves graphene but is incompatible with optimal BaTiO$_3$ growth. Thus, we show a two-step Ar/O$_2$ deposition is required to exfoliate ferroelectric BaTiO$_3$ while maintaining a monolayer graphene interlayer. HAIC stages human insight with AI reasoning between autonomous batches to drive rapid scientific progress, providing an evolution to many existing human-in-the-loop autonomous workflows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11558v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Asraful Haque, Daniel T. Yimam, Jawad Chowdhury, Ralph Bulanadi, Ivan Vlassiouk, John Lasseter, Sujoy Ghosh, Christopher M. Rouleau, Kai Xiao, Yongtao Liu, Eva Zarkadoula, Rama K. Vasudevan, Sumner B. Harris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous resonance in Weyl semimetals: A holographic study of non-linear effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10754v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider hairy, magnetic black brane solutions to Einstein-Maxwell-Chern-Simons-Dilaton theory with full back-reaction of the scalar and gauge fields and compute the time evolution with time dependent sources. The dual field theory's 't Hooft anomaly leads to long-lived current oscillations in the low temperature limit long after the electric pulse which created these modes has been switched off. We find that, generally, non-linear effects increase the decay rates of long-lived modes by a temperature dependent amount. Nonetheless, our results suggest that the life-time of time-translation symmetry breaking states can be made arbitrarily large if the temperature after the quench is sufficiently small. Experimentally this might be realizable in Weyl semimetals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10754v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maximilian Gaschler, Andreas Sch\"afer, Sebastian Waeber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-wavelength transparent microfluidics for UV-visible spectroscopy and X-ray scattering studies of photoactive systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11441</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11441v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Microfluidic devices are increasingly used in synchrotron-based experiments to deliver and probe liquid samples, offering advantages such as minimal sample consumption and reduced radiation damage. Despite their growing use, few devices have been specifically designed for monitoring liquids under photoexcitation, a promising approach for fast structural transitions. Here, a microfluidic device that is transparent to X-rays in one direction, and simulaneously transmits UV and visible light in the perpendicular direction is presented. The device is fabricated using lamination and UV lithography on a dry-film resist, eliminating the need for cleanroom facilities and simplifying production. Its multi-wavelength transparency was validated through UV-visible spectroscopy, where photoexcitation at different wavelengths induced reversible trans-to-cis isomerization of azobenzene and fluoro-azobenzene. X-ray transparency was validated through Small Angle X-ray Scattering (SAXS) measurements on hemoglobin and CO-ligated hemoglobin sensitive to quaternary structural changes. These resusts confirm the suitability of the device for resolving protein structures and photoinduced conformational dynamics. The design further supports, as some proof of concept results show, temperature-jump and time resolved pump-probe experiments, providing a versatile platform for studying structural evolution in liquid samples using synchrotron SAXS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11441v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benedetta Marmiroli, Sumea Klokic, Barbara Sartori, Marie Reissenbuechel, Alessio Turchet, Heinz Amenitsch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrability for the spectrum of Jordanian AdS/CFT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11521</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11521v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Jordanian deformations offer rare integrable realisations of non-AdS holography, whose solvability methods differ from conventional AdS/CFT examples. Here we study the $\mathfrak{sl}(2,R)$ sector of the Jordanian deformed $AdS_5\times S^5$ string and its weak-coupling spin chain counterpart: the $\mathrm{XXX}_{-1/2}$ model with a non abelian Jordanian Drinfel'd twist. While the twist breaks the usual highest-weight structure that underlies conventional Bethe ans\"atze, we show that the complete spectrum remains solvable within the Baxter framework. We argue that the functional form of the $TQ$-relation is unchanged, yet the structure of the $Q$-functions is nontrivially modified. This allows us to obtain analytic expressions at arbitrary spin chain length $J$, which match the deformed string spectrum at the one-loop level and to subleading order in the large-$J$ expansion, despite the severely reduced symmetry. Our results provide nontrivial tests of the Jordanian AdS/CFT correspondence and lay the groundwork for implementing the Separation of Variables program in non-abelian Drinfel'd-twisted models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11521v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sibylle Driezen, Fedor Levkovich-Maslyuk, Adrien Molines</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconductivity in Substitutional Ga-Hyperdoped Ge Epitaxial Thin Films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15421v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Doping-induced superconductivity in group IV elements may enable quantum functionalities in material systems accessible with well-established semiconductor technologies. Non-equilibrium hyperdoping of group III atoms into C, Si, or Ge can yield superconductivity; however, its origin is obscured by structural disorder and dopant clustering. Here, we report the epitaxial growth of hyperdoped Ga:Ge films and trilayer heterostructures by molecular beam epitaxy with extreme hole concentrations ($n_\textup{h} = 4.15 \times 10^{21}$~cm$^{-3}$, ~17.9\% Ga substitution) that yield superconductivity with a critical temperature of $T_{\textup{c}} = 3.5$~K and an out-of-plane critical field of 1~T at 270~mK. Synchrotron-based X-ray absorption and scattering methods reveal that Ga dopants are substitutionally incorporated within the Ge lattice, introducing a tetragonal distortion to the crystal unit cell. Our findings, corroborated by first-principles calculations, suggest that the structural order of Ga dopants creates a narrow band for the emergence of superconductivity in Ge, establishing hyperdoped Ga:Ge as a low-disorder, epitaxial superconductor-semiconductor platform.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15421v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41565-025-02042-8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nat. Nanotechnol. (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Julian A. Steele, Patrick J. Strohbeen, Carla Verdi, Ardeshir Baktash, Alisa Danilenko, Yi-Hsun Chen, Jechiel van Dijk, Frederik H. Knudsen, Axel Leblanc, David Perconte, Lianzhou Wang, Eugene Demler, Salva Salmani-Rezaie, Peter Jacobson, Javad Shabani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ratchet motion of magnetic skyrmions driven by surface acoustic sawtooth waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.09506v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The manipulation of skyrmions by surface acoustic waves (SAW) has garnered significant interest in the field of spintronic devices. Previous studies established that skyrmions can be generated and moved by strain pulses. In this study, we propose that sawtooth-SAWs can be used to drive a ratchet motion of magnetic skyrmions in the presence of pinning centers. This results in a net motion of the skyrmions orthogonal to the continuously applied SAW. The ratchet motion is fundamentally caused by non-vanishing pinning, so that a certain strain gradient magnitude is required to overcome pinning and start skyrmion motion. We demonstrate the feasibility of our concept by micromagnetic simulations and analytical model calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.09506v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philipp Schwenke, Ephraim Spindler, Vitaliy I. Vasyuchka, Alexandre Abbass Hamadeh, Philipp Pirro, Mathias Weiler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete time crystals detected by time-translation twist</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21461</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21461v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a boundary condition twisted by time translation as a novel probe to characterize dynamical phases in periodically driven (Floquet) quantum systems. Inspired by twisted boundary conditions in equilibrium systems, this approach modifies the temporal evolution of the system upon completing a spatial loop, enabling the identification of distinct Floquet phases, including discrete time crystals (DTCs). By studying the spectral form factor (SFF) and its response to the twist, we uncover signatures of time-crystalline order, which exhibits periodic dependence on the twist parameter analogous to the Little-Parks effect in superconductors. We apply this framework to the kicked Ising model, demonstrating that our twist can distinguish time-crystalline phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21461v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/1dc6-y1x8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 165138 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ryota Nakai, Taozhi Guo, Shinsei Ryu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chirality-selective proximity effect between chiral $p$-wave superconductors and quantum Hall insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00994</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00994v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Heterostructures of superconductors and quantum-Hall insulators are promising platforms of topological quantum computation. However, these two systems are incompatible in some aspects such as a strong magnetic field, the Meissner effect, and chirality. In this work, we address the condition that the superconducting proximity effect works in the bulk of quantum Hall states, and identify an essential role played by the vortex lattice regardless of pairing symmetry. We extend this finding to a heterostructure of a chiral $p$-wave superconductor in the mixed state and an integer quantum Hall insulator. The proximity effect works selectively in the lowest Landau level depending on relative chiralities. If the chiralities align, a topological phase transition to a topological superconductor occurs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00994v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/qxt1-ncfn</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 094520 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ryota Nakai, Koji Kudo, Hiroki Isobe, Kentaro Nomura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ten-valley excitonic complexes in charge-tunable monolayer WSe$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08923v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Excitons dominate the optical response of two-dimensional (2D) semiconductors. Strong interactions produce peculiar excitonic complexes, which provide a testing ground for exciton and quantum many-body theories. Here, we report a hitherto unobserved many-body exciton that emerges upon filling both the K and Q valleys of WSe$_2$. We optically probe the exciton landscape using charge-tunable devices with unusually thin dielectrics that facilitate doping up to several $10^{13}$ cm$^{-2}$. We observe the emergence of the thermodynamically stable complex when 10 valleys are electrostatically filled. We gain insight into its physics using magneto-optical measurements. Our results are well-described by a model where the number of distinguishable Fermi seas interacting with the photoexcited electron-hole pair defines the complex's behavior. In addition to expanding the repertoire of excitons in 2D semiconductors, this complex could probe the limit of exciton models and answer open questions about screened Coulomb interactions in 2D semiconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08923v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41467-025-65731-x</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Alain Dijkstra, Amine Ben Mhenni, Dinh Van Tuan, Elif \c{C}etiner, Muriel Schur-Wilkens, Junghwan Kim, Laurin Steiner, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Matteo Barbone, Nathan P. Wilson, Hanan Dery, Jonathan J. Finley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase Transition of Topological Index driven by Dephasing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04102</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04102v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study topological insulators under dephasing noise. With examples of both a $2d$ Chern insulator and a $3d$ topological insulator protected by time-reversal symmetry, we demonstrate that there is a phase transition at finite dephasing strength between phases with nontrivial and trivial topological indices. Here the topological index is defined through the correlation matrix. The transition can be diagnosed through the spectrum of the whole correlation matrix or of a local subsystem. Interestingly, even if the topological insulator is very close to the topological-trivial critical point in its Hamiltonian, it still takes finite strength of dephasing to change the topological index, suggesting the robustness of topological insulators under dephasing. We further consider Chern insulators in the presence of real-space disorder, which exhibit a ground-state transition between topological and Anderson insulating phases. We find that even strongly-disordered Chern insulators, close to the critical disorder strength, exhibit robustness with respect to dephasing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04102v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/8vtp-khnq</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, L201112 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Thomas G. Kiely, Cenke Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bosonization and Kramers-Wannier dualities in general dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20167</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20167v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is well known that the noninteracting Majorana chain is dual to the one-dimensional transverse-field Ising model, either through the Jordan-Wigner transformation or by gauging fermion parity. In this correspondence, the minimal translation of the Majorana chain maps to the celebrated Kramers-Wannier (KW) duality of the spin model, with the critical point mapped to the self-dual point. In this work, we generalize this mapping to two and higher dimensions by constructing a unitary equivalence between the parity-gauged fermionic system and a spin system defined on arbitrary polyhedral decompositions of space. Imposing the flatness condition on the gauge field yields a bosonization duality between the original (ungauged) fermionic system and a gauged spin system obeying a Gauss law. The dependence of the Gauss law in the spin system on the Kasteleyn orientation (and the discrete spin structure) of the fermionic system is made explicit. Applying this bosonization to one or two copies of Majorana fermions on translationally invariant lattices, we derive higher-dimensional analogs of KW (self-)dualities in spin systems arising from fermionic minimal translations. The KW (self-)dualities are non-invertible due to projections onto eigenspaces of higher-form symmetries in the associated symmetry operators. The bosonization framework we present is intuitive, general, and systematic, encompassing other known exact bosonization methods while offering a novel approach to establish new connections between fermionic and spin systems in arbitrary dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20167v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Su, Ivar Martin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inherent momentum-dependent gap structure of altermagnetic superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03247</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03247v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Altermagnetic metals break time-reversal symmetry and feature spin-split Fermi surfaces generated by compensated N\'eel-ordered collinear magnetic moments. Being metallic, such altermagnets may undergo a further instability at low temperatures to a superconducting state, and it is an interesting open question what are the salient features of such altermagnetic superconductors? We address this question on the basis of realistic microscopic models that capture the altermagnetic sublattice degrees of freedom. We find that the sublattice structure can strongly affect the superconducting gap structure in altermagnetic superconductors. In particular, it imposes nodes in the gap on the Brillouin zone edges for superconductors stabilized by momentum-independent bare attraction channels. We contrast this to the case of superconductivity generated by extended range interactions where pairing is allowed on the Brillouin zone edges and both spin-singlet and equal-spin-pairing triplet states can be stabilized. Equal-spin-pairing triplet superconductivity is generically favored in the limit of large altermagnetic spin-splitting of the bands compared to the superconducting gap scale, and features characteristic non-unitary properties due to the altermagnetic order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03247v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian L. H. Rasmussen, Jannik Gondolf, Mats Barkman, Merc\`e Roig, Daniel F. Agterberg, Andreas Kreisel, Brian M. Andersen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Bloch bands and Weiss oscillations in Dirac mass superlattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03359v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study two-dimensional Dirac fermions in a one-dimensional mass superlattice under a perpendicular magnetic field. Using exact solutions for isolated and finite arrays of domain walls, we demonstrate the persistence of Jackiw-Rebbi modes with a field-dependent renormalized velocity. For the periodic case, we adopt a gauge-invariant projection method onto magnetic Bloch states, valid for arbitrary fields and mass profiles, which yields dispersive Landau levels, and confirm its accuracy by comparison with finite arrays spectra. From the miniband spectra we predict modified quantum Hall plateaus and Weiss-like magnetoconductivity oscillations, characterized by a strongly reduced amplitude and a $\pi/2$ phase shift compared to electrostatic superlattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03359v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/zwrf-dywf</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>A. Anand, R. Egger, A. De Martino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital-Selective Band Structure Evolution in BaFe$_{2-x}$M$_x$As$_2$ (M = Cr, Co, Cu, Ru and Mn) Probed by Polarization-Dependent ARPES</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19190v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a systematic study of the evolution of the band structure in the Fe-based superconductor family BaFe$_{2-x}$M$_x$As$_2$ (M = Cr, Co, Cu, Ru and Mn) using polarization-dependent angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES). Low-substituted samples, with comparable spin-density wave transition temperatures ($T_\text{SDW}$), were chosen to facilitate controlled comparisons. The sizes of the central hole pockets ($\alpha$, $\beta$, and $\gamma$) remain largely unchanged across different substitutions, showing no clear correlation with either $T_\text{SDW}$ or the As height relative to the Fe planes. However, subtle trends are observed: a modest increase in the size of the $\eta_\text{X}$ electron pocket correlates with the suppression of $T_\text{SDW}$. Furthermore, the contraction of the $\eta_\text{X}$ pocket appears to be linked to an increase in the As height relative to the Fe planes. Our results suggest that the suppression of $T_\text{SDW}$ is primarily driven by changes in the Fe-As bond length, with the effect being more pronounced in electronic states with planar character. These findings provide insight into the electronic structure of BaFe$_{2-x}$M$_x$As$_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19190v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. R. Pakuszewski, M. R. Cantarino, I. Romanenko, A. P. Machado, M. M. Piva, G. S. Freitas, H. B. Pizzi, F. A. Garcia, P. G. Pagliuso, C. Adriano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electric field induced Berry curvature dipole and non-linear anomalous Hall effects in higher wave symmetric unconventional magnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20237v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the second-order anomalous Hall response in two-dimensional higher-wave symmetric magnets, including the recently discovered class of collinear magnets known as altermagnets, when subjected to a symmetry-breaking external electric field. In these systems, the first- and second-order anomalous Hall responses mediated by the first- and second-order multipoles of the Berry curvature over the occupied states vanish by symmetry. However, a symmetry-breaking dc electric field can induce a nonzero Berry curvature dipole by coupling to a non-vanishing quantum metric, also known as the Berry connection polarizability. An applied ac electric field can then generate a finite nonlinear transverse Hall effect characterized by a second harmonic response. In addition, the dc field itself can generate a finite third-order transverse Hall response. We discuss this remarkable effect in a class of higher-order symmetric unconventional magnets (of $p$, $d$, $f$, $g$, $i$ symmetry), including the subclass of altermagnets. We demonstrate that the electric-field-induced anomalous Hall effect in the higher-wave-symmetric magnets can serve not only as a probe of the underlying quantum metric of the occupied states but also as a means to distinguish the even ($d$-,$g$-wave) and odd ($p$-wave) order parameter symmetries defined on the square lattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20237v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Srimayi Korrapati, Snehasish Nandy, Sumanta Tewari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase Separation in Kitaev Chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20312</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20312v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Kitaev chain is a one-dimensional spinless fermion model that has $p$-wave superconducting (SC) states and Majorana zero modes at the edge. Usually this model is analyzed by taking only SC order parameter (OP) into account, but the situation significantly changes when OPs other than the SCOP are included. It turns out that the SC state in the latter case is prone to phase separation for moderate to strong attractiive interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20312v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazuhiro Kuboki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metallic electro-optic effects in topological chiral crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26992</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26992v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Topological chiral crystals have emerged as a fertile material platform for investigating optical phenomena derived from the distinctive Fermi surface Berry curvature and orbital magnetic moment textures around multifold chiral band crossings pinned at the time-reversal invariant momenta. In this work, by means of tight-binding model and first principles based calculations, we investigate metallic electro-optic (EO) responses stemming from the Berry curvature and orbital magnetic moment of Bloch electrons across 37 materials belonging to space group 198 (SG198). Previously thought to vanish in SG198, our findings reveal a nonzero Berry curvature dipole attributed to the energetic misalignment between topologically charged point nodes of opposite chirality. Moreover, we find that the recently predicted magnetoelectric EO effects, which arise from the interplay between the Berry curvature and magnetic moment on the Fermi surface, are readily accessible in BeAu under experimentally feasible electric biases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26992v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. O. Ascencio, D. J. P. de Sousa, Tony Low</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing interaction-driven restructuring of quantum Hall edge states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00156</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00156v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Many topological phases host gapless boundary modes that can be dramatically modified by electronic interactions. Even for the long-studied edge modes of quantum Hall phases, forming at the boundaries of two-dimensional (2D) electron systems, the nature of such interaction-induced changes has been elusive. Despite advances made using local probes, key experimental challenges persist: the lack of direct information about the internal structure of edge states on microscopic scales, and complications from edge disorder. Here, we use scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) to image pristine electrostatically defined quantum Hall edge states in graphene with high spatial resolution and demonstrate how correlations dictate the structures of edge channels on both magnetic and atomic length scales. For integer quantum Hall states in the zeroth Landau level, we show that interactions renormalize the edge velocity, dictate the spatial profile for copropagating modes, and induce unexpected edge valley polarization that differ from those of the bulk. While some of our findings can be understood by mean-field theory, others show breakdown of this picture, highlighting the roles of edge fluctuations and inter-channel couplings. We also extend our measurements to spatially resolve the edge state of fractional quantum Hall phases and detect spectroscopic signatures of interactions in this chiral Luttinger liquid. Our study establishes STM as a promising tool for exploring edge physics of the rapidly expanding 2D topological phases, including newly realized fractional Chern insulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00156v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiachen Yu, Haotan Han, Kristina G. Wolinski, Ruihua Fan, Amir S. Mohammadi, Tianle Wang, Taige Wang, Liam Cohen, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Andrea F. Young, Michael P. Zaletel, Ali Yazdani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-resolution magnetostriction measurements of the Pauli-limited superconductor Sr2RuO4</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06938</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06938v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We performed high-resolution magnetostriction measurements on the Pauli-limited superconductor Sr$_2$RuO$_4$ using high-quality single crystals. A first-order superconducting transition, accompanied by pronounced hysteresis, was observed under in-plane magnetic fields, where the relative length change of the sample, $\Delta L/L$, was on the order of $10^{-8}$. To ensure the reliability of the measurements, particular attention was paid to minimizing the influence of magnetic torque, which can significantly affect data under in-plane field configurations, via field-angle-resolved magnetostriction. Within the hysteresis regime, slightly below the Pauli-limited upper critical field, a hump-like anomaly in the magnetostriction coefficient was identified. Furthermore, a characteristic double-peak structure in the field-angle derivative of the magnetostriction provides additional support for this anomaly. Although these findings may reflect a lattice response associated with the emergence of the Fulde-Ferrell-Larkin-Ovchinnikov (FFLO) phase in Sr$_2$RuO$_4$, the possibility of a broadened first-order transition cannot be excluded. Notably, this magnetostriction anomaly qualitatively deviates from the FFLO phase boundary suggested by previous NMR measurements, highlighting the necessity for further experimental and theoretical investigations to elucidate the nature of the FFLO state in this material.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06938v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shunichiro Kittaka, Yohei Kono, Toshiro Sakakibara, Naoki Kikugawa, Shinya Uji, Dmitry A. Sokolov, Kazushige Machida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The True Parent Phase of K1.9Fe4.2Se5: A Stripe-type Orthorhombic Phase Requiring a Superconducting Distortion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10443v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The origin of the four-fold Tc amplification in A_xFe_{2-y}Se_2 (&gt;30 K) compared to FeSe (8 K) remains a central puzzle, complicated by a debate over the true superconducting (SC) parent phase--the I4/m (245) insulating matrix or a supposed I4/mmm metallic phase. Here, we resolve this ambiguity by identifying a novel "stripe-type orthorhombic phase" as the true parent phase of the high-Tc state, whose diffraction signature is the d2 peaks. Through decisive experiments, we demonstrate that this d2 parent phase is not intrinsically superconducting. Instead, superconductivity emerges only after this stripe phase undergoes a subsequent structural distortion, the definitive signature of which is the asymmetric broadening of the d1 main peaks. Our findings establish that the d2 peaks signal the formation of the parent phase, while the broadening of d1 peaks signals the transition into the superconducting state. This discovery of a two-step transition--formation of a stripe parent phase, followed by a superconducting distortion--provides a new mechanism for Tc amplification via controlled heterogeneity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10443v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chih-Han Wang, Jie-Yu Yang, Wu Phillip M, Gwo-Tzong Huang, Ming-Jye Wang, Maw-Kuen Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electrically-gated laser-induced spin dynamics in magneto-electric iron garnet at room temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20366</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.20366v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Ultrafast pump-probe imaging reveals that the efficiency of optical excitation of coherent spins waves in epitaxial iron garnet films can be effectively controlled by an external electric field at room temperature. Although a femtosecond laser pulse alone does not excite any pronounced coherent spin oscillations, an electrical gating with the field of 0.5 MV/m dramatically changes the outcome in a laser-induced launching of spin waves. The effect, demonstrated under room-temperature conditions, is estimated to be orders of magnitude larger than in magnetic van der Waals semiconductors observed at 10 K. This electrical gating of laser-induced spin dynamics enriches opto-magnonics with a new tool and thus opens up a new avenue in fundamental and applied magnonics research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.20366v3</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. T. Gareev, N. E. Khokhlov, L. K\"orber, A. P. Pyatakov, A. V. Kimel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A superinductor in a deep sub-micron integrated circuit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13202v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Superinductors are circuit elements characterised by an intrinsic impedance in excess of the superconducting resistance quantum ($R_\text{Q}\approx6.45~$k$\Omega$), with applications from metrology and sensing to quantum computing. However, they are typically obtained using exotic materials with high density inductance such as Josephson junctions, superconducting nanowires or twisted two-dimensional materials. Here, we present a superinductor realised within a silicon integrated circuit (IC), exploiting the high kinetic inductance ($\sim 1$~nH/$\square$) of TiN thin films native to the manufacturing process (22-nm FDSOI). By interfacing the superinductor to a silicon quantum dot formed within the same IC, we demonstrate a radio-frequency single-electron transistor (rfSET), the most widely used sensor in semiconductor-based quantum computers. The integrated nature of the rfSET reduces its parasitics which, together with the high impedance, yields a sensitivity improvement of more than two orders of magnitude over the state-of-the-art, combined with a 10,000-fold area reduction. Beyond providing the basis for dense arrays of integrated and high-performance qubit sensors, the realization of high-kinetic-inductance superconducting devices integrated within modern silicon ICs opens many opportunities, including kinetic-inductance detector arrays for astronomy and the study of metamaterials and quantum simulators based on 1D and 2D resonator arrays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13202v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. H. Swift, F. Olivieri, G. Aizpurua-Iraola, J. Kirkman, G. M. Noah, M. de Kruijf, F. E. von Horstig, A. Gomez-Saiz, J. J. L. Morton, M. F. Gonzalez-Zalba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Euler-Heisenberg action for fermions coupled to gauge and axial vectors: Hessian diagonalization, sector classification, and applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02118</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02118v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We derive the closed-form one-loop Euler--Heisenberg effective actions for Dirac fermions coupled simultaneously to classical electromagnetic vector and massive pseudo-vector backgrounds within a controlled quasi-static approximation. Through complete diagonalization of the functional Hessian, we systematically delineate the parameter space into distinct sectors characterized by stability properties and spectral structure. We identify subspaces that encompass and extend results from previous studies into a broader class, admitting propagating axial fields as physically viable regimes; strikingly, we note a sector presenting chirality-asymmetric instability. This addresses long-standing questions regarding the well-defined nature, diagonalizability, and stability of the model. From the effective action, we derive novel nonperturbative pair-production rates for simultaneously propagating electromagnetic and axial vector backgrounds; remarkably, we find pronounced vacuum stabilization compared to previous results. Furthermore, we demonstrate that this framework allows for a unified derivation of the chiral anomaly structures in the general case and show that the electromagnetic coupling induces instanton-like configurations for the axial field, even when it is not a fundamental gauge field. As a proof-of-concept, we analyze a cosmological toy model of baryogenesis driven by an axial vector, providing numerical estimates that support the viability of this hypothesis. Additionally, we outline qualitative predictions for Weyl/Dirac semi-metals and briefly discuss potential applications in related phenomena, such as the Strong-CP problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02118v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas Pereira de Souza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interferometric Braiding of Anyons in Chern Insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09445v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Coherent control and braiding of anyons remain central challenges in realizing topologically protected quantum operations. We propose a Ramsey interferometry protocol to directly access the geometric phases associated with anyons in fractional Chern insulators. Our approach employs impurities with individually addressable internal states that bind to the anyons, allowing their adiabatic motion and exchange under full spatial control. By combining Ramsey and spin-echo sequences using one and two impurities, the protocol gives independent access to the Aharonov-Bohm and exchange contributions to the total geometric phase, thereby providing an unambiguous probe of anyonic statistics. Our scheme can potentially be implemented in cold-atom quantum simulators as well as in van der Waals heterostructures. Complementary finite-size simulations in non-interacting Chern insulators quantify the system sizes required to faithfully extract geometric phases, highlighting the role of edge effects. Our results establish impurity-based interferometry as a feasible route toward direct anyon braiding experiments in quantum simulators and lay the groundwork for future explorations of non-Abelian braiding and topological quantum control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09445v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felix A. Palm, Nader Mostaan, Nathan Goldman, Fabian Grusdt</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
