<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 04:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Metal-insulator transition in a CuO chain created by Kondo interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25251v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Over twenty years ago Alexei Abrikosov [A.A. Abrikosov, Metal-insulator transition in layered cuprates (SDW model), Physica C: Supercond. Vol. 391, 2, 147-159 (2003)] considered the Spin-Density-Waves (SDW) model for the metal-insulator transition in layered cuprates. In one of those cuprates, YBa$_2$Cu$_3$O$_{7-\delta}$, there are one-dimensional (1D) CuO chains of copper and oxygen ions. In the present work we consider the metal-insulator transition in the model case of a 1D CuO chain in the regime of half-filling of the band. Our model is essentially the same, but as an exchange interaction causing the metal-insulator transition, we consider Kondo-Zener two-electron exchange, which successfully describes many of the electronic properties of the layered cuprates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25251v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Todor M. Mishonov, Albert M. Varonov, Kaloian D. Lozanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-efficiency Pt75Au25-based spintronic terahertz emitters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25303</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25303v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spintronic terahertz emitters (STEs) generate broadband THz radiation via ultrafast spin-charge conversion in magnetic multilayers, offering spectral coverage beyond that of photoconductive antennas and nonlinear optical crystals. Here, we demonstrate a new type of STE based on PtxAu100-x alloy that achieves signifi- cantly higher THz output power than widely used Pt-based devices. Alloy composition and layer thickness tuning yield Pt75Au25 as the optimal alloy providing a 30 % increase in THz power in CoFeB/Pt75Au25 bilayer STEs compared to the optimized CoFeB/Pt reference STE. In W/CoFeB/Pt75Au25 trilayer STEs, we observe a 10 % higher THz power than in the optimized W/CoFeB/Pt trilayer. The STE efficiency is reduced upon annealing for both Pt75Au25- and Pt-based STEs due to formation of interfacial alloys. Our results establish Pt75Au25 as a promising platform for high-performance STEs, where its giant spin Hall effect significantly enhances efficiency over conventional Pt-based devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25303v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenlu Shi, Gene D. Nelson, Han-Hsuan Wu, Yiwei Ju, Xiaoqing Pan, Wilson Ho, Ilya N. Krivorotov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum geometric origins of the orbital degrees of freedom of hybrid bosonic quasiparticles in magnetic systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25635</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25635v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The orbital degree of freedom has recently attracted significant attention due to the novel phenomena it enables in condensed matter systems. However, the interpretation of the orbital degree of freedom in bosonic quasiparticles remains conceptually ambiguous and the mechanisms governing the transfer of orbital angular moment (OAM) between distinct quasiparticles, such as magnons and phonons, are not yet fully understood. We investigate orbital dynamics in bosonic systems and identify two origins of OAM: (i) global rotational motion of the system, and (ii) the quantum geometry of wavefunctions. Focusing on the latter, we study strongly coupled magnon-phonon systems in two-dimensional antiferromagnets as a test case. We uncover finite OAM arising from quantum geometric effects via two mechanisms: (a) time-parity symmetry breaking, yielding intra band OAM, and (b) interband coupling, generating interband OAM. We propose that an electrical detection scheme based on the transverse voltage generated by hybrid magnon phonon modes can be used to experimentally probe the bosonic orbital degree of freedom. Our results establish a foundation for the emerging field of phonon orbitronics, providing both a conceptual bridge between phonon and magnon orbitronics and a tool for better understanding magnon-polarons. They also advance a unified framework for harnessing orbital degrees of freedom in bosonic systems and pave the way toward electrical control of magnetization and phononic transport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25635v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Quang To, Dai Q. Ho, Joshua M. O. Zide, Lars Gundlach, M. Benjamin Jungfleisch, Garnett W. Bryant, Anderson Janotti, Matthew F. Doty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Soliton Formation as a Dark-State Phase Transition in a Dissipative Superfluid Chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25707</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25707v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We identify and characterize a first-order dark-state phase transition between a discrete dark soliton and a uniform superfluid in a Bose-Hubbard chain with a single lossy site. Using classical-field (truncated-Wigner) simulations together with a Bogoliubov stability analysis, we show that the dark-state nature of the soliton suppresses fluctuations and shifts the critical point relative to the comparable phenomenon of optical bistability in driven-dissipative Kerr resonators. We then demonstrate that this mechanism quantitatively captures the bistability phase boundary observed in the experiment of R. Labouvie et al. [Phys. Rev. Lett. 116, 235302 (2016)], resolving substantial discrepancies in prior modeling efforts. Our results reveal how driving, dissipation and quantum coherence can interact to induce nonequilibrium phase transitions in ultra-cold atomic gases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25707v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robbe Ceulemans, Samuel E. Begg, Matthew J. Davis, Michiel Wouters</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact heat flux formula and its spectral decomposition in molecular dynamics for arbitrary many-body potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26044</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26044v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study we have derived an exact framework for the calculation of the heat flux and its spec- tral decomposition in Molecular Dynamics (MD) for arbitrary many-body potentials. This work addresses several lacks and limitations of previous approaches and allows for the accurate computa- tional study of thermal properties in a wide variety of many-body systems with MD. We have tested our modifications with Green-Kubo (GK) and Non-Equilibrium MD (NEMD) simulations for vari- ous 2D and 3D material systems using the Tersoff and Stillinger-Weber potentials as examples. The spectral decomposition of the heat current was also calculated for monolayer graphene (1LG) and MoS2 , for different system lengths. Our results show that the heat current calculated by our method is consistently in agreement with the thermostat current in NEMD, while previous implementations can estimate quite poorly the thermal conductivity both under GK and NEMD simulations, and both for 2D and 3D materials. The decomposition of the heat current also sheds light on the con- tribution of different phonon modes to thermal conductivity and its dependence on length. Our methodology is implemented in the widely used LAMMPS code specifically for the Tersoff and SW potentials, and it is readily applicable to the vast majority of many-body MD potentials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26044v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Markos Poulos, Donatas Surblys, Konstantinos Termentzidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anderson localization: a density matrix approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26206v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Anderson localization is a quantum phenomenon in which disorder localizes electronic wavefunctions. In this work, we propose a new approach to study Anderson localization based on the density matrix formalism. Drawing an analogy to the standard transfer matrix method, we extract the localization length from the modular density matrix in quasi-one-dimensional systems. This approach successfully captures the metal-insulator transition in the three-dimensional Anderson model and in the two-dimensional Anderson model with spin-orbit coupling. It can be also readily extended to multiorbital systems. We further generalize the formalism to interacting systems, showing that the one-dimensional spinless attractive model exhibits the expected metallic phase, consistent with previous studies. More importantly, we demonstrate the existence of a two-dimensional metallic phase in the presence of Hubbard interactions and disorder. This method offers a new perspective on Anderson localization and its interplay with interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26206v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziyue Qi, Yi Zhang, Mingpu Qin, Hongming Weng, Kun Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of non-Hermitian topology in cold Rydberg quantum gases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26256</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26256v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The pursuit of topological phenomena in non-Hermitian systems has unveiled new physics beyond the conventional Hermitian paradigm, yet their realization in interacting many-body platforms remains a critical challenge. Exploring this interplay is essential to understand how strong interactions and dissipation collectively shape topological phases in open quantum systems. Here, we experimentally demonstrate non-Hermitian spectra topology in a dissipative Rydberg atomic gas and characterize parameters-dependent winding numbers. By increasing the interaction strength, the system evolves from Hermitian to non-Hermitian regime, accompanying emergence of trajectory loop in the complex energy plane. As the scanning time is varied, the spectra topology becomes twisted in the complex energy plane manifesting as a topology phase transition with the sign winding number changed. When preparing the system in different initial states, we can access a nontrivial fractional phase within a parameter space that globally possesses an integer winding. Furthermore, by changing the scanning direction, we observe the differentiated loops, revealing the breaking of chirality symmetry. This work establishes cold Rydberg gases as a versatile platform for exploring the rich interplay between non-Hermitian topology, strong interactions, and dissipative quantum dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26256v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun Zhang, Ya-Jun Wang, Shi-Yao Shao, Bang Liu, Li-Hua Zhang, Zheng-Yuan Zhang, Xin Liu, Chao Yu, Qing Li, Han-Chao Chen, Yu Ma, Tian-Yu Han, Qi-Feng Wang, Jia-Dou Nan, Yi-Ming Yin, Dong-Yang Zhu, Qiao-Qiao Fang, Dong-Sheng Ding, Bao-Sen Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic phase transitions protected by topological quantum geometry transitions: effects of electron-electron interactions in the Creutz ladder system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26320</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26320v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The interplay between electronic correlations and band topology is a central theme in modern condensed matter physics. In this work, we investigate the effects of on-site Hubbard interactions on the topological, magnetic, and quantum geometric properties of the Creutz ladder, a paradigmatic model of a one-dimensional topological insulator. Using a self-consistent mean-field approach, we uncover a first-order, interaction-driven phase transition that is simultaneously magnetic and topological. We demonstrate that as the Hubbard interaction $U$ is increased, the system's ground state abruptly switches from an anti-ferromagnetic (AF) configuration to a ferromagnetic (F) one. This magnetic transition coincides with a topological transition, marked by a quantized jump in the Zak phase from $\pm\pi$ to $0$. We systematically compute the phase diagrams in the parameter space of on-site energy staggering ($\epsilon$) and inter-chain hopping asymmetry ($\lambda$), revealing the critical interaction strength $U_c$. Furthermore, we analyze the quantum geometry of the Bloch states by calculating the Fubini-Study metric, demonstrating that its components exhibit divergences that precisely signal the topological phase transition. By analyzing the full energy spectrum, we distinguish the true ground state from metastable excited states that emerge past the critical point. Our results establish the Creutz-Hubbard ladder as a minimal model for studying interaction-induced topological phenomena and suggest a potential route for controlling magnetic, topological, and geometric properties via electronic correlations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26320v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abdiel de Jes\'us Espinosa-Champo, Gerardo G. Naumis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient heat-energy conversion from a non-thermal Tomonaga-Luttinger liquid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26387</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26387v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Energy harvesting is a technique that generates useful work from waste heat. Conventional energy harvesters acting on local thermal equilibrium states are constrained by thermodynamic limits, such as the Carnot efficiency. Quantum heat engines with non-thermal reservoirs are expected to exceed such limits. Here, we demonstrate energy harvesting from a nonthermal Tomonaga-Luttinger (TL) liquid in quantum Hall edge channels, where the non-thermal state is naturally formed due to the absence of thermalization. The scheme is tested with a quantum-dot energy harvester working on a non-thermal TL liquid supplied with waste heat from a quantum-point-contact transistor. Compared to the quasi-thermalized TL liquid, the non-thermal state prepared under the same heat is capable of a larger electromotive force and higher conversion efficiency. These characteristics can be understood by considering a binary Fermi distribution function of the non-thermal state induced by entropy-conserving equilibration. TL liquids are attractive non-thermal carriers for excellent energy harvesting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26387v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s42005-025-02297-6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Commun. Phys. 8, 387 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hikaru Yamazaki, Masashi Uemura, Haruhi Tanaka, Tokuro Hata, Chaojing Lin, Takafumi Akiho, Koji Muraki, Toshimasa Fujisawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Half-filled metal and molecular-orbital-mediated pairing in cuprate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26472v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The cuprates exhibit anomalous momentum-space structure with antinodal gap and nodal arc in the underdoped regime, which evolves into a complete hole-type Fermi surface with a large Luttinger volume in the overdoped regime. The real-space electronic structure is also quite complex, as characterized by microscopic inhomogeneities and intertwined density wave orders. Here we show that doped holes in cuprate form localized electronic molecules consisting of 4a0 plaquettes, and each plaquette contains approximately two holes. The effective local doping level is thus around 1/8, which is sufficient to destroy the underlying AF order and more importantly, recovers the half-filled metallic state of the original CuO2 plane. The restored Fermi surface, hosting one hole per unit cell, is consistent with experimental results and satisfies the Luttinger theorem. We then construct the momentum-space structure of the half-filled metal by considering the real-space configuration of electronic molecules. We show that the electronic potential with 4a0 periodicity imposed by the plaquettes and the quantum size effect of electronic molecules obliterate the nested antinodal Fermi surface sheets, leaving behind short arcs with coherent quasiparticles around the node. We propose that two doped holes in each plaquette occupy the shared molecular orbital and form a spin singlet, which can mediate the pairing of itinerant holes on the remnant Fermi surface of the half-filled metal. The electric dipole moment between the molecular orbitals and the dopant ions may also provide a novel attractive interaction between itinerant holes. This phenomenological model for pair formation between itinerant holes on the half-filled Fermi surface mediated by localized molecular orbitals resolves several core issues concerning the mechanism of superconductivity in cuprates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26472v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sixuan Chen, Zhiheng Yao, Ning Xia, Shusen Ye, Hongrui Zhang, Jianfa Zhao, Qingqing Liu, Changqing Jin, Shuo Yang, Yayu Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Memristor-Driven Spike Encoding for Fully Implantable Cochlear Implants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26582</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26582v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Neurodynamic behavior of artificial neuron circuits made of Mott memristors provides versatile opportunities to utilize them for artificial sensing. Their small size and energy efficiency of generating spiking electrical signals enable usage in fully implantable cochlear implants. Here, we propose an auditory sensing unit realized by a piezo-MEMS (micro-electromechanical systems) cantilever connected to a VO$_2$ nanogap Mott memristor-based oscillator circuit. This auditory sensing unit is capable of frequency-selective detection of vibrations and subsequent emission of a neural spiking waveform. The auditory sensing unit is tested under biologically realistic vibration amplitudes, and spike rate-encoding of the incoming stimulus is demonstrated, similarly to natural hearing processes. The tunability of the output spiking frequency and the shape of the spiking waveform are also demonstrated to provide suitable voltage spikes for the nervous system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26582v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T\'imea N\'ora T\"or\"ok, Roland K\"ovecs, Ferenc Braun, Zsigmond Pollner, Tam\'as Zeffer, Nguyen Quoc Kh\'anh, L\'aszl\'o P\'osa, P\'eter R\'ev\'esz, Heungsoo Kim, Alberto Piqu\'e, Andr\'as Halbritter, J\'anos Volk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital altermagnetism on the kagome lattice and possible application to $A$V$_3$Sb$_5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26596</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26596v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Altermagnets, which encompass a broad landscape of materials, are compensated collinear magnetic phases in which the antiparallel magnetic moments are related by a crystalline rotation. Here, we argue that collinear altermagnetic-like states can also be realized in lattices with an odd number of sublattices, provided that the electronic interactions promote non-uniform magnetic moments. We demonstrate this idea for a kagome metal whose band filling places the Fermi level close to the van Hove singularity. Combining phenomenological and microscopic modeling, we show that the intertwined charge density-wave and loop-current instabilities of this model lead to a wide parameter range in which orbital ferromagnetic, antiferromagnetic, and altermagnetic phases emerge inside the charge-ordered state. In the presence of spin-orbit coupling, their electronic structures display the usual spin-split fingerprints associated with the three types of collinear magnetic order. We discuss the possible realization of orbital altermagnetic phases in the $A$V$_3$Sb$_5$ family of kagome metals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26596v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anzumaan R. Chakraborty, Fan Yang, Turan Birol, Rafael M. Fernandes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microwave-to-Optical Quantum Transduction of Photons for Quantum Interconnects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26349v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The quantum transduction, or equivalently quantum frequency conversion, is vital for the realization of, e.g., quantum networks, distributed quantum computing, and quantum repeaters. The microwave-to-optical quantum transduction is of particular interest in the field of superconducting quantum computing, since interconnecting dilution refrigerators is considered inevitable for realizing large-scale quantum computers with fault-tolerance. In this review, we overview recent theoretical and experimental studies on the quantum transduction between microwave and optical photons. We describe a generic theory for the quantum transduction employing the input-output formalism, from which the essential quantities characterizing the transduction, i.e., the expressions for the transduction efficiency, the added noise, and the transduction bandwidth are derived. We review the major transduction methods that have been experimentally demonstrated, focusing the transduction via the optomechanical effect, the electro-optic effect, the magneto-optic effect, and the atomic ensembles. We also briefly review the recent experimental progress on the quantum transduction from superconducting qubit to optical photon, which is an important step toward the quantum state transfer between distant superconducting qubits interconnected over optical fibers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26349v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akihiko Sekine, Ryo Murakami, Yoshiyasu Doi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disorder-induced diffusion transport in flat-band systems with quantum metric</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19056</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19056v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Our previous understanding of transport in disordered system depends on the assumption that there is a well-defined Fermi velocity. The Fermi velocity determines important length scales in the system such as the diffusion length and localization length. However, nearly flat band materials with vanishing Fermi velocity, it is uncertain how to understand the disorder effects and what quantities determine the characteristic length scales in the system. In the clean limit, it is expected that the bulk transport is absent. In this work, we demonstrate, with a diamond lattice, that disorder can induce diffusion transport in a flat-band system with finite quantum metric. As disorder increases, the bulk transmission channels are activated, and the conductance reaches a maximum before decays inversely with disorder strength. Importantly, via the calculation of the wave-packet dynamics numerically, we show that the quantum metric determines the diffusion length of the system. Analytically, we show that the interplay between the disorder and quantum geometry gives rise to an effective Fermi velocity, as captured by the self-consistent Born approximation. The diffusion coefficient is identified from the Bethe-Salpeter equation under the ladder approximation. Our results reveal a disorder-driven delocalization mechanism in flat-band systems with finite quantum metric which cannot be understood by well-established theories of quantum diffusion. Our theory is important for understanding the disorder effects and transport properties of flat band materials such as twisted bilayer graphene which are current under intense investigation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19056v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chun Wang Chau, Tian Xiang, Shuai A. Chen, K. T. Law</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal electronic structure of multi-layered nickelates via oxygen-centered planar orbitals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20450</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20450v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Superconductivity has been demonstrated in the family of multi-layered nickelates La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ and La$_4$Ni$_3$O$_{10}$. Key questions remain open regarding the low-energy electronic states that support superconductivity in these compounds. Here we take advantage of the natural polymorphism between bilayer (2222) and alternating monolayer-trilayer (1313) stacking sequences that arises in bulk La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ crystals, and by employing angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) we identify a universal low-energy electronic structure in this family of materials. We observe the fingerprint of a doping-dependent spin-density wave (SDW) instability -- strong and coherent enough to reconstruct the Fermi surface, both by gapping out regions of the low-energy electronic structure as well as translating the $\beta$ pocket by a vector $Q_{t\beta}$ consistent with the results of previous neutron and x-ray scattering experiments. Using an effective tight-binding model, we simulate the spectral weight distribution observed in our ARPES dichroism experiments and establish that the low-energy electronic phenomenology is dominated by oxygen-centered planar orbitals, which evolve from the $d_{3x^2-r^2}$ and $d_{3y^2-r^2}$ symmetry characteristic of 3-spin polarons (3SP) to the familiar $d_{x^2-y^2}$ Zhang-Rice singlets (ZRS) that support high-temperature superconductivity in cuprates. By inclusion of magnetic moments on plaquettes of oxygen orbitals in our model, we show that ZRS-like states mediate the SDW. Combined with the observation that oxygen annealing is required to induce superconductivity in both thin films and bulk La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$, this demonstrates that the ZRS population dictates whether the ground state favors density-wave order or superconductivity -- with hole doping suppressing the former and stabilizing the latter, as in the cuprates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20450v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christine C. Au-Yeung, X. Chen, S. Smit, M. Bluschke, V. Zimmermann, M. Michiardi, P. C. Moen, J. Kraan, C. S. B. Pang, C. T. Suen, S. Zhdanovich, M. Zonno, S. Gorovikov, Y. Liu, G. Levy, I. S. Elfimov, M. Berciu, G. A. Sawatzky, J. F. Mitchell, A. Damascelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moir\'e excitons and exciton-polaritons: A review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05204</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05204v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Distinguished by their long lifetimes, strong dipolar interactions, and periodic confinement, moir\'e excitons provide a fertile territory for realizing interaction-driven excitonic phases beyond conventional semiconductor systems. Formed in twisted or lattice-mismatched van der Waals heterostructures, these excitons are shaped by a periodic potential landscape that enables the engineering of flat bands, strong interactions, and long-lived localised states. This has opened pathways to explore strongly correlated phases, including excitonic insulators, superfluids, and supersolids, potentially stable even at room temperature. When embedded in optical cavities, moir\'e excitons hybridize with photons to form moir\'e exciton-polaritons, a new class of quasiparticles exhibiting enhanced optical nonlinearities and novel topological features.
  In this review, we survey the theoretical foundations and experimental progress in the field of moir\'e excitons and polaritons. We begin by introducing the formation mechanisms of moir\'e patterns in two-dimensional semiconductors, and describe their impact on exciton confinement, optical selection rules, and spin-valley physics. We then discuss recent advances in the realization of many-body excitonic phases and exciton-based probes of electronic correlations. Finally, we explore the novel aspects of moir\'e polaritons, highlighting their unique nonlinear and topological properties. By bridging quantum optics, nanophotonics, and correlated electron systems, moir\'e excitons offer a powerful solid-state platform for quantum simulation, optoelectronic applications, and many-body photonics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05204v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sa\'ul A. Herrera-Gonz\'alez, Hugo A. Lara-Garc\'ia, Giuseppe Pirruccio, David A. Ruiz-Tijerina, Arturo Camacho-Guardian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Topological Phases Controlled via Strain in Two-Dimensional Altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22474</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.22474v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Altermagnets (AMs) are an emergent class of magnetic materials that combine properties of ferromagnets and antiferromagnets, exhibiting spin-polarized Fermi surfaces and zero net magnetic moment due to combined time-reversal and crystal symmetry. Here, we construct a Kondo-lattice model on a two-dimensional square Lieb lattice to investigate the topological properties of AMs. We identify a type-II quantum spin Hall state characterized by spin-polarized counterpropagating edge states. Breaking the $C_{4z}\mathcal{T}$ symmetry, which connects magnetic sublattices, induces a transition to a quantum anomalous Hall state. We further establish a strain-induced mechanism to control these topological phase transitions and present the corresponding phase diagram. Finally, we demonstrate the predicted transitions in monolayer CrO, a realistic altermagnetic candidate, using first-principles calculations. Our findings highlight the potential of 2D AMs as a versatile platform for topological spintronics, enabling strain-tunable helical and chiral edge states within a single system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.22474v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zesen Fu, Mengli Hu, Aolin Li, Haiming Duan, Junwei Liu, Fangping Ouyang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectroscopic Evidence for Electron-Boson Coupling in Half-metallic CrO2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18867</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.18867v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report quasiparticle properties of the half-metal ferromagnet CrO2 by means of high-resolution angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES). We clearly observed the Fermi surface (FS) and band dispersion in good agreement with the previous reports. Moreover, the ARPES band dispersion reveals a distinct kink structure around 68 meV, providing the first spectroscopic evidence for the elementary excitations in CrO2. The energy scale of this feature is comparable to the Debye temperature and the $A\subm{1g}$ phonon mode, suggesting the electron-phonon interaction. From the detailed analysis, we have extracted the self-energy and found two characteristic structures in the real part of the self-energy. Assuming the existence of the electron-magnon interaction as well as the electron-phonon interaction, we could reproduce the evaluated real and imaginary parts of the self-energy as well as ARPES intensity. Our findings reveal the renormalized quasiparticle (QP) dynamics in CrO$_2$ and provide valuable insights into the fundamental many-body interactions governing half-metallic ferromagnets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.18867v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daiki Ootsuki, Hirokazu Fujiwara, Noriyuki Kataoka, Kensei Terashima, Miho Kitamura, Koji Horiba, Hiroshi Kumigashira, Shiv Kumar, Shin-ichiro Ideta, Kenya Shimada, Yuji Muraoka, Takayoshi Yokoya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Splitting of electronic spectrum in paramagnetic phase of itinerant ferromagnets and altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23396</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23396v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study self-energy effects, induced by strong magnetic fluctuations in paramagnetic phase of strongly-correlated itinerant magnets within the density functional theory combined with the dynamical mean field theory (DFT+DMFT approach) and its non-local extension. As concrete examples, we consider $\alpha$-iron, half metal CrO$_2$, van der Waals material CrTe$_2$, and altermagnet CrSb. We show that both local and non-local magnetic correlations yield splitting of the electronic spectrum in the paramagnetic phase, such that it closely resembles the DFT band structure in the ordered phase. The relative importance of non-local vs. local correlations depends on the proximity to half filling of $d$ states: closer to half filling, the role of local correlations increases. Although the obtained split bands do not possess a certain spin projection, their splitting suppresses spectral weight at the Fermi level. The obtained electronic states are also expected to be easily spin polarized by a weak external magnetic field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23396v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. A. Katanin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
