<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 05:00:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>AC magnetometry of van der Waals magnets using ultrasensitive Graphene Hall sensors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08962v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Probing the dynamical magnetic properties of two-dimensional (2D) materials requires sensitive techniques capable of detecting small magnetic fields from nanoscale samples. We demonstrate quantitative AC and DC magnetometry of a ferromagnetic Fe3-xGeTe2 nanoflakes using ultrasensitive graphene Hall sensors. These devices achieve record-low magnetic field detection noise at both cryogenic and room temperature, enabled by hBN encapsulation, low-resistance fluorographene contacts, and a novel fabrication process. We perform quantitative AC susceptibility measurements up to 1 kHz, resolving both real and imaginary components with nanotesla-scale sensitivity and milliradian phase accuracy, the first such measurement in a van der Waals magnet. Our results establish graphene Hall sensors as a powerful and broadly applicable platform for studying magnetic and superconducting phases near the 2D limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08962v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eugene Park, Jihoon Keum, Ji-Hwan Baek, Hyuncheol Kim, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Gwan-Hyoung Lee, Je-Geun Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetization plateau and anisotropic magnetoresistance in the frustrated Kondo-lattice compound Ce3ScBi5</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09096v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Kondo metals with geometric frustration offer fertile ground for exploring exotic states of matter with a field-induced fractional magnetization platform and nonsaturating magnetoresistance. Herein, a Ce3ScBi5 single crystal with anti-Hf5Sn3Cu hexagonal structure was successfully synthesized via the bismuth self-flux method, leading to the formation of cerium cations arranged in a frustrated structure within a distorted kagome lattice. Magnetic measurements exhibit two distinct antiferromagnetic transitions at 4.1 and 5.9 K. Specifically, the occurrence of multiple metamagnetic transitions between magnetization plateaus is evidenced upon applying magnetic fields perpendicular to the c axis. Transport measurements highlight remarkable Kondo-lattice characteristics and anisotropic magnetoresistance in Ce3ScBi5. The anomalous Hall contributions are observed at low temperatures under critical fields, suggesting Fermi surface reconstruction in a subset of the metamagnetic transitions. We have constructed a temperature-field phase diagram to provide comprehensive information on the complex magnetic structures arising from competitive interactions. Our work establishes Ce3ScBi5 and related materials as a unique platform for exploring low-dimensional quantum fluctuations in bulk crystals, and analyzes the critical role of geometric frustration in Kondo and Ruderman-Kittel-Kasuya-Yosida physical frameworks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09096v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B. 110, 165106, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zhongchen Xu, Yaxian Wang, Cuiwei Zhang, Hongxiong Liu, Xin Han, Liusuo Wu, Xianmin Zhang, Quansheng Wu, Youguo Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for spontaneous breaking of a continuous symmetry at a non-conformal quantum critical point</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09097v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we present evidence for the spontaneous breaking of a continuous symmetry in a nearest-neighbour interacting spin-1 chain tuned to a quantum critical point at $T=0$ between two XY quasi-long-range order phases differing by the spontaneous breaking of a $\mathbb{Z}_2$ symmetry. Despite the one-dimensional nature of the system, which typically prevents such a continuous symmetry breaking due to the Hohenberg-Mermin-Wagner theorem, the presence of a Berry phase term in the quantum model allows us to observe, using matrix product state methods, a finite perpendicular magnetization. Moreover, the quasi-long-range decay of the correlation function becomes truly long-range order, and the dynamical structure factor displays a characteristic Bragg peak together with sharp gapless modes. Our results imply the quantum phase transition has an anomalous dimension of $\eta \simeq 1$ together with the dynamical critical exponent $z\simeq 3/2$, known from the Kardar-Parisi-Zhang universality class in one dimension. We perform a perturbative renormalization group calculation about the upper critical dimension $d_c=2$ that we could close at second loop order. We find an interacting fixed point with critical exponents distinct from the Ising ones. Together, our findings suggest the nature of the fixed point to be non-perturbative. We propose a field-theory that we believe to improve the quantitative results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09097v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Flores-Calder\'on, M. Z\"undel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability Frontiers and Mixed-dimensional physics in the Kagome Intermetallics Ln3ScBi5 (Ln = La-Nd, Sm)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09113</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09113v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Low-dimensional physics provides profound insights into strongly correlated interactions, leading to enhanced quantum effects and the emergence of exotic quantum states. The Ln3ScBi5 family stands out as a chemically versatile kagome platform with mixed low-dimensional structural framework and tunable physical properties. Our research initiates with a comprehensive evaluation of the currently known Ln3ScBi5 (Ln = La-Nd, Sm) materials, providing a robust methodology for assessing their stability frontiers within this system. Focusing on Pr3ScBi5, we investigate the influence of the zigzag chains of quasi-one-dimensional (Q1D) motifs and the distorted kagome layers of quasi-two-dimensional (Q2D) networks in the mixed-dimensional structure on the intricate magnetic ground states and unique spin fluctuations. Our study reveals that the noncollinear antiferromagnetic (AFM) moments of Pr3+ ions are confined within the Q2D kagome planes, displaying minimal in-plane anisotropy. In contrast, a strong AFM coupling is observed within the Q1D zigzag chains, significantly constraining spin motion. Notably, the magnetic frustration is partially the consequence of coupling to conduction electrons via the Ruderman-Kittel-Kasuya Yosida (RKKY) interaction, highlighting a promising framework for future investigations into mixed-dimensional frustration in Ln3ScBi5 systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09113v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chin. Phys. Lett. 42, 100704, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zhongchen Xu, Wenbo Ma, Shijun Guo, Ziyi Zhang, Quansheng Wu, Xianmin Zhang, Xiuliang Yuan, Youguo Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Orbital Angular Momentum Induced by Chiral Phonons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09271v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that the orbital angular momentum (OAM) of electrons is dynamically induced by chiral phonons. The induced OAM originates from the adiabatic evolution in which electrons dynamically acquire Berry phase. By introducing a tight-binding model with p orbitals on a honeycomb lattice, we show a microscopic picture that chiral phonons modulate orbital overlaps of electrons, and calculate the generated OAM, whose sign depends on phonon chirality. We then construct an effective model for valley phonons with different phonon pseudoangular momenta (PAM) and identity their distinct intervalley-scattering channels. Our model obeys the selection rule between phonons and electrons with the orbital degree of freedom. Extending this framework to d-orbital electrons, our model is applied to describe the induced OAM in monolayer transition metal dichalcogenides. Our results reveal a direct lattice-OAM transfer mechanism that emerges even in materials with weak spin-orbital coupling, opening a new promising way for orbitronics applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09271v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dapeng Yao, Dongwook Go, Yuriy Mokrousov, Shuichi Murakami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infinite-component $BF$ field theory: Nexus of fracton order, Toeplitz braiding, and non-Hermitian amplification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09301v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Building on the recent study of Toeplitz braiding by Li et al. [Phys. Rev. B 110, 205108 (2024)], we introduce \textit{infinite-component} $BF$ (i$BF$) theories by stacking topological $BF$ theories along a fourth ($w$) spatial direction and coupling them in a translationally invariant manner. The i$BF$ framework captures the low-energy physics of 4D fracton topological orders in which both particle and loop excitations exhibit restricted mobility along the stacking direction, and their particle-loop braiding statistics are encoded in asymmetric, integer-valued Toeplitz $K$ matrices. We identify a novel form of particle-loop braiding, termed \textit{Toeplitz braiding}, originating from boundary zero singular modes (ZSMs) of the $K$ matrix. In the thermodynamic limit, nontrivial braiding phases persist even when the particle and loop reside on opposite 3D boundaries, as the boundary ZSMs dominate the nonvanishing off-diagonal elements of $K^{-1}$ and govern boundary-driven braiding behavior. Analytical and numerical studies of i$BF$ theories with Hatano-Nelson-type and non-Hermitian Su-Schrieffer-Heeger-type Toeplitz $K$ matrices confirm the correspondence between ZSMs and Toeplitz braiding. The i$BF$ construction thus forges a bridge between strongly correlated topological field theory and noninteracting non-Hermitian physics, where ZSMs underlie the non-Hermitian amplification effect. Possible extensions include 3-loop and Borromean-rings Toeplitz braiding induced by twisted topological terms, generalized entanglement renormalization, and foliation structures within i$BF$ theories. An intriguing analogy to the scenario of parallel universes is also briefly discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09301v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bo-Xi Li, Peng Ye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The parent state in kagome metals and superconductors: Chiral-nematic Fermi liquid state</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09402v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The kagome metals and superconductors hosting rich correlated and topological electronic states have captivated quantum materials research. These states are triggered by an unconventional chiral charge density wave (CDW) wherein a chiral superconductivity emerges at low temperatures, yet the origin of this chiral CDW order, the parent state, is unresolved. Here, we report the discovery of a parent chiral-nematic Fermi liquid state in kagome metals and superconductors. We use spectroscopic-imaging scanning tunneling microscopy to study Ti-doped CsV3Sb5 where the CDW is suppressed, and find that multiorbital Fermi surfaces break all mirror reflections and exhibit handedness. We observe the chiral low-energy quasiparticle dispersions, providing direct evidence for a chiral-nematic electronic structure. We further observe the direct transition from the parent state to a chiral-nematic superconducting state. Moreover, in the samples with chiral CDW, we also observe the residual chiral-nematic QPI features, demonstrating that the CDW-triggered exotic states descend from the chiral-nematic Fermi liquid. Our findings not only provide a plausible chiral-nematic parent state, but also establish a new conceptual framework for exploring the emergence and consequences of such exotic quantum phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09402v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zihao Huang, Hengxing Tan, Zhen Zhao, Zhan Wang, Chengmin Shen, Haitao Yang, Bent Weber, Binghai Yan, Hui Chen, Ziqiang Wang, Hong-Jun Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of Electron Correlations on Infinite-Layer Cuprates and Nickelates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09460</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09460v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Optimization of unconventional superconductivity involves a balance of interaction strengths. Precise determination of correlation strength across different material families is therefore important. Here, we present a combined X-ray absorption spectroscopy (XAS) and resonant inelastic X-ray scattering (RIXS) study of infinite-layer PrNiO$_2$ and SrCuO$_2$ that enables fair comparison of their interaction strengths. For both compounds, we study the orbital and magnetic excitations and extract their dispersions along high-symmetry directions. Using a single-band Hubbard model and including higher-order exchange interactions, we derive the correlation factor $U/t$ for both compounds. A key finding is that despite a smaller Coulomb repulsion $U$, PrNiO$_2$ exhibits a correlation strength that is 20% stronger than that of its isostructural cuprate counterpart SrCuO$_2$. This indicates that a moderation of the correlation strength may further optimize superconductivity in nickelates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09460v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xunyang Hong, Yuetong Wu, Ying Chan, Sze Tung Li, I. Bia{\l}o, L. Martinelli, A. Drewanowski, Qiang Gao, Xiaolin Ren, Xingjiang Zhou, Zhihai Zhu, A. Galdi, D. G. Schlom, K. M. Shen, J. Choi, M. Garcia Fernandez, Ke-Jin Zhou, N. B. Brookes, H. M. R{\o}nnow, Qisi Wang, J. Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing the features of electron dispersion by tunneling between slightly twisted bilayer graphene sheets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09550</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09550v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Tunneling conductance between two bilayer graphene (BLG) sheets separated by 2 nm-thick insulating barrier was measured in two devices with the twist angles between BLGs less than 1{\deg}. At small bias voltages, the tunneling occurs with conservation of energy and momentum at the points of intersection between two relatively shifted Fermi circles. Here, we experimentally found and theoretically described signatures of electron-hole asymmetric band structure of BLG: since holes are heavier, the tunneling conductance is enhanced at the hole doping due to the higher density of states. Another key feature of BLG that we explore is gap opening in a vertical electric field with a strong polarization of electron wave function at van Hove singularities near the gap edges. This polarization, by shifting electron wave function in one BLG closer to or father from the other BLG, gives rise to asymmetric tunneling resonances in the conductance around charge neutrality points, which result in strong sensitivity of the tunneling current to minor changes of the gate voltages. The observed phenomena are reproduced by our theoretical model taking into account electrostatics of the dual-gated structure, quantum capacitance effects, and self-consistent gap openings in both BLGs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09550v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexey A. Sokolik, Azat F. Aminov, Evgenii E. Vdovin, Yurii N. Khanin, Mikhail A. Kashchenko, Denis A. Bandurin, Davit A. Ghazaryan, Sergey V. Morozov, Kostya S. Novoselov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite-momentum pairing and superlattice superconductivity in valley-imbalanced rhombohedral graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15471v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Inspired by the recent experimental discovery of superconductivity emerging from a time-reversal symmetry-breaking normal state in tetralayer rhombohedral graphene, we here investigate superconducting instabilities in this system. We classify the possible pairing instabilities, including states with commensurate and incommensurate center of mass momenta. As rotational symmetry is broken in the latter type of pairing states, their momentum-space structure is most naturally characterized by a `valley-independent Chern number', measuring the relative chirality between the normal and superconducting state. We further demonstrate that superconductivity can condense at multiple incommensurate momenta simultaneously, leading to the spontaneous formation of a translational-symmetry-breaking superlattice superconductor. Studying multiple different pairing mechanisms and varying the degree of spin and valley polarization in the normal state, we compare the energetics of these superconductors. Our results demonstrate that valley-imbalanced rhombohedral tetralayer graphene can give rise to rich superconducting phenomenologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15471v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maine Christos, Pietro M. Bonetti, Mathias S. Scheurer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cavity-induced coherent magnetization and polaritons in altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16248</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16248v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Altermagnets feature antiparallel spin sublattices with $d$-, $g$-, or $i$-wave spin order, yielding nonrelativistic spin splitting without net magnetization. We show that embedding a two-dimensional $d$-wave altermagnet in a driven optical cavity induces a finite, tunable magnetization. Coherent photon driving couples selectively to electronic sublattices, and the resulting altermagnets' symmetry-broken spin texture yields a pronounced steady-state spin imbalance -- coherent magnetization -- absent in conventional antiferromagnets for the same lattice configuration. A mean-field Lindblad analysis reveals the dominance of quadratic over linear couplings. In the strong-coupling regime, distinct polariton signatures emerge in the steady state of induced magnetization. This work demonstrates cavity control of altermagnets for spintronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16248v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohsen Yarmohammadi, Libor \v{S}mejkal, James K. Freericks</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
