<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 04:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Robustness of Anyon Tunneling at $\nu = 1/3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11860</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11860v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The scaling exponent $g$ of the quasiparticle propagator for incompressible fractional quantum Hall states in the Laughlin sequence is expected to be robust against perturbations that do not close the gap. Here we probe the topological robustness of the chiral Luttinger liquid at the boundary of the $\nu=1/3$ state by measuring the tunneling conductance between counterpropagating edge modes as a function of quantum point contact transmission. We demonstrate that for transmission $t\geq 0.7$ the tunneling conductance is well-described by the first two terms of a perturbative series expansion corresponding to $g=1/3$. We further demonstrate that the measured scaling exponent is robustly pinned to $g=1/3$ across the plateau, only deviating as the bulk state becomes compressible. Finally we examine the impact of weak disorder on the scaling exponent, finding it insensitive. These measurements firmly establish the topological robustness of anyon tunneling at $\nu=1/3$ and substantiate the chiral Luttinger liquid description of the edge mode.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11860v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adithya Suresh, Ramon Guerrero-Suarez, Tanmay Maiti, Shuang Liang, Geoffrey Gardner, Claudio Chamon, Michael Manfra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modelling of magnetic vortex microdisc dynamics under varying magnetic field in biological viscoelastic environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11906v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetically driven microparticles provide a versatile platform for probing and manipulating biological systems, yet the physical framework governing their actuation in complex environments remains only partially explored. Within the field of cellular magneto-mechanical stimulation, vortex microdiscs have emerged as particularly promising candidates for developing novel therapeutic approaches. Here, we introduce a simplified two-dimensional model describing the magneto-mechanical response of such particles embedded in viscoelastic media under varying magnetic fields. Using a Maxwell description of the medium combined with simplified elasticity assumptions, we derive analytical expressions and support them with numerical simulations of particle motion under both oscillating and rotating magnetic fields. Our results show that rotating fields typically induce oscillatory dynamics and that the transition to asynchronous motion occurs at a critical frequency determined by viscosity and stiffness. The amplitude and phase of this motion is governed by the competition between magnetic and viscoelastic contributions, with particle motion being strongly impaired when the latter dominate. Energy-based considerations further demonstrate that, within the frequency range explored of few tens of Hertz, no heat is generated -- distinguishing this approach from magnetic hyperthermia -- while the elastic energy transferred to the surrounding medium is, in principle, sufficient to perturb major cellular processes. This work provides a simple framework to anticipate the first-order influence of rheological properties on magnetically driven microdisc dynamics, thereby enabling a better understanding of their impact in cells or extracellular materials and bridging the gap between experimental observations and theoretical modelling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11906v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Vison\`a, Robert Morel, H\'el\`ene Joisten, Bernard Dieny, Alice Nicolas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for easy-plane XY ferromagnetism in heavy-fermion quantum-critical CeRh6Ge4</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12006</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12006v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report $^{73}$Ge nuclear quadrupole resonance (NQR) and magnetic resonance (NMR) spectroscopy in the heavy-fermion quantum-critical ferromagnet CeRh$_6$Ge$_4$. NQR and NMR spectral measurements at the two non-equivalent Ge sites reveal electric field gradient tensors and the directions of their principal axes relative to the hexagonal basal plane. The spin-lattice relaxation rate $1/T_1$ experiments reveal a clear critical slowing down approaching the ferromagnetic transition. $1/T_1$ in the paramagnetic state is found to be predominantly caused by fluctuating 4$f$-local moments. The Knight shift shows Curie-Weiss behavior at high temperature and a deviation from this below $T^\ast$ $\approx$ 25 K possibly due to a mixture of crystalline electric field effects and Kondo screening. Order-parameter-like behavior of hyperfine fields at the Ge sites and ferromagnetic signal enhancement are observed in Zeeman-perturbed NQR, with uniform ferromagnetic order and a small ordered moment of $\approx$ 0.26 $\mu_B$/Ce confined within the $ab$-plane. The ordered moment shows a notable in-plane magnetic stiffness against out-of-plane radiofrequency fields and has an (XY-type) in-plane isotropic nature. Our results reveal a strong easy-plane anisotropy of 4$f$-electron moment and suggest an involved interplay of hybridization and local moment physics in this quantum critical heavy-fermion ferromagnet.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12006v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/z17k-jz1s</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Riku Yamamoto, Sejun Park, Zachary W. Riedel, Phurba Sherpa, Joe D. Thompson, Filip Ronning, Eric D. Bauer, Adam P. Dioguardi, Michihiro Hirata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chern-Selective multi-valley Flat Bands in Twisted Mono-Bilayer and Mono-Trilayer MoTe$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12127v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The interplay between moir\'e flat bands originating from different valleys can give rise to a variety of exotic quantum phases. In this work, we investigate the electronic properties of twisted mono-bilayer (A-AB) and mono-trilayer (A-ABA) MoTe$_2$ using first-principles calculations and continuum models. Unlike previous studies on twisted bilayer systems, in which low-energy flat bands originate solely from the $K/K'$ valleys, in A-AB and A-ABA twisted MoTe$_2$ (\tmt) the moir\'e bands at low energies arise from both the $\Gamma$ and $K/K'$ valleys, with spin Chern numbers $C_s=0$ (for $\Gamma$) and $C_{\uparrow/\downarrow}=\pm1$ (for $K/K'$), respectively. We show that the multi-valley moir\'e flat bands are governed by interlayer-hybridization effects, and that different stacking configurations and thicknesses tune the relative energy alignment between the $\Gamma$ and $K$ valley moir\'e flat bands. By constructing valley-resolved continuum models and performing Wannierization for the low-energy moir\'e bands, we further uncover that the Berry curvature and quantum metric distributions can be effectively tuned by the layer number and stacking configuration. Unlike other moir\'e systems, where only one kind of valley influenced the low energy physics, the simultaneous appearance of two distinct types of valleys, with different symmetries, establish A-AB and A-ABA \tmt\ as ideal platforms for studying layer-controlled multi-valley physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12127v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziyue Qi, Hanqi Pi, Yan Zhang, Jiaxuan Liu, Nicolas Regnault, Hongming Weng, B. Andrei Bernevig, Jiabin Yu, Quansheng Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Room temperature control of axial and basal antiferromagnetic anisotropies using strain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12222</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12222v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Antiferromagnetic materials are promising platforms for the development of ultra-fast spintronics and magnonics due to their robust magnetism, high-frequency relativistic dynamics, low-loss transport, and the ability to support topological textures. However, achieving deterministic control over antiferromagnetic order in thin films is a major challenge, due to the formation of multi-domain states stabilised by competing magnetic and destressing interactions. Thus, the successful implementation of antiferromagnetic materials necessitates careful engineering of their anisotropy. Here, we demonstrate strain-based robust control over multiple antiferromagnetic anisotropies and nanoscale domains in the promising spintronic candidate a-Fe2O3, at room temperature. By applying isotropic and anisotropic in-plane strains across a broad temperature-strain phase space, we systematically tune the interplay between magneto-crystalline and magneto-elastic interactions. We discover that strain-driven control steers the system towards an aligned antiferromagnetic state, whilst preserving topological spin textures, such as merons, antimerons and bimerons. We directly map the nanoscale antiferromagnetic order using linear dichroic scanning transmission X-ray microscopy integrated with in situ strain and temperature control. A Landau model and micromagnetic simulations reveal how strain reshapes the magnetic energy landscape. These findings suggest that strain could serve as a versatile control mechanism to reconfigure equilibrium or dynamic antiferromagnetic states on demand in a-Fe2O3, paving the way for next-generation spintronic and magnonic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12222v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jack Harrison, Junxiong Hu, Charles Godfrey, Jheng-Cyuan Lin, Tim A Butcher, J\"org Raabe, Simone Finizio, Hariom Jani, Paolo G Radaelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconductivity in monolayer-trilayer phase of La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ under high pressure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12250</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12250v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The discovery of 80 K superconductivity in pressurized bilayer Ruddlesden-Popper (RP) nickelate La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ has established a new high-temperature superconductor family. The quest to understand the governing principles of RP nickelate superconductivity has become a central focus in condensed matter physics. Here, we report a critical advance by synthesizing and investigating a distinct structural polymorph of the same compound: the monolayer-trilayer (1313) hybrid phase of La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$. Under high pressure, synchrotron X-ray diffraction and Raman spectroscopy reveal a structural transition from the orthorhombic $Cmmm$ to the tetragonal $P4/mmm$ space group at 13~GPa. Above 19 GPa, the phase exhibits a clear superconducting transition, confirmed by a zero-resistance state, albeit at a significantly reduced temperature of 3.6 K. The stark contrast with the 80 K transition in the bilayer phase provides a uniquely clean experimental comparison. Our results demonstrate that the superconducting transition temperature is directly governed by the nature of the interlayer coupling, and the bilayer NiO$_6$ block as the essential structural motif for achieving high-$T_\text{c}$ superconductivity in the RP nickelates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12250v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chaoxin Huang, Jingyuan Li, Xing Huang, Hengyuan Zhang, Deyuan Hu, Mengwu Huo, Xiang Chen, Zhen Chen, Hualei Sun, Meng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wiedemann-Franz behavior at the Weyl points in compressively strained HgTe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12339v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Weyl semimetals, with their unique electronic band structure, have drawn significant interest for their potential to explore quantum anomalies in condensed matter systems. In this study, we investigate the large positive magneto-thermal conductance associated with the gravitational anomaly -- one of the predicted anomalies -- for a Weyl semimetal based on a compressively strained HgTe layer. We clearly identify the Weyl regime in our device and accurately extract the thermal conductance by performing thermometry measurements at liquid helium temperatures using fully electronic methods. We observe the anticipated increase in thermal conductance, and it perfectly matches the electrical conductance according to the Wiedemann-Franz law. This finding indicates that, despite the unique electronic spectrum of Weyl semimetals, the mechanism governing heat transport in this system is the same as that for electrical transport, with no additional violations of conservation laws.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12339v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abu Alex Aravindnath, Yi-Ju Ho, Fabian Schmitt, Dongyun Chen, Johannes Kleinlein, Wouter Beugeling, Hartmut Buhmann, Stanislau U. Piatrusha, Laurens W. Molenkamp</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interlayer coupling enhanced superconductivity near 100 K in La$_{3-x}$Nd$_x$Ni$_2$O$_7$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12359v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Systematically controlling the superconducting transition temperature ($T_\text{c}$) in the bilayer Ruddlesden-Popper nickelate La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ remains a significant challenge. Here, we address this by synthesizing high-quality polycrystalline La$_{3-x}$Nd$_x$Ni$_2$O$_7$ ($0 \leq x \leq 2.4$) with record-level rare-earth substitution. Nd doping compresses the lattice, particularly along the $c$ axis, enhances the spin density wave transition temperature, and elevates the pressure required for the orthorhombic-to-tetragonal structural transition. Superconductivity is observed across all doping levels under high pressures, with the onset $T_\text{c}$ rising to $\sim$93~K for $x = 2.1$ and $2.4$ from the electronic transport measurement. Using the radio-frequency transmission technique, newly applied to nickelate superconductors, we detect signatures of superconductivity at $98 \pm 2$~K in the $x=2.4$ compound, pushing the $T_\text{c}$ frontier further. We identify a universal linear relationship where $T_\text{c}$ decreases with the $c$-axis lattice parameter at a rate of approximately $-28$~K/\AA, demonstrating that enhanced interlayer magnetic exchange coupling is the dominant mechanism for superconducting pairing. Our work establishes the critical role of magnetism and provides a unified structural descriptor for elevating $T_\text{c}$ in bilayer nickelates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12359v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhengyang Qiu, Junfeng Chen, Dmitrii V. Semenok, Qingyi Zhong, Di Zhou, Jingyuan Li, Peiyue Ma, Xing Huang, Mengwu Huo, Tao Xie, Xiang Chen, Ho-kwang Mao, Viktor Struzhkin, Hualei Sun, Meng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Possible high-Tc superconductivity at 45 K in the Ge-doped cluster Mott insulator GaNb4Se8</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12452</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12452v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Ge-doped GaNb4Se8 polycrystalline samples were synthesized by solid-state reaction method. Zero resistance transitions were observed in one batch of samples with the highest onset superconducting Tc at 45 K. This discovery may demonstrate a new class of Nb-based high-Tc superconductors arising from doped Mott insulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12452v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ji-Hai Yuan, Ya-Dong Gu, Yun-Qing Shi, Hao-Yu He, Qing-Song Liu, Jun-Kun Yi, Le-Wei Chen, Zheng-Xin Lin, Jia-Sheng Liu, Meng Wang, Zhi-An Ren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The spin Hall conductivity in the hole-doped bilayer Haldane-Hubbard model with odd-parity ALM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12602</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12602v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spin current generated electrically is among the core phenomena of spintronics for driving high-performance spin device applications. Here, on the basis of systematic investigations for the hole doped single-layer Haldane-Hubbard(HH) model, we propose a new bilayer HH model to realize the compensated odd-parity spin splitting and the $T$-even spin Hall conductivity where the two layers are connected by the time reversal transformation. Our results show that the vanishing layer-dependent electric potential $V_{L}$ gives rise to odd-parity ALM protected by the combined symmetry $TM_{xy}$ with $T$ and $M_{xy}$ being the time reversal and mirror reflection perpendicular to $z$ axis, and the $T$-even spin Hall conductivity simultaneously. In addition, though the staggered magnetization within each layer is substantially impacted by the layer-dependent electric potential, small $V_{L}$'s only bring negligible changes to the net magnetization and the spin Hall conductivity, indicating that the alternating spin splitting in momentum space and the spin Hall conductivity are insusceptible to external elements. Most importantly, our work provides a general framework for the simultaneous realization of the compensated odd-parity spin splitting in momentum space and the spin Hall conductivity in collinear magnets, in terms of stacked multi-layer systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12602v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minghuan Zeng, Ling Qin, Shiping Feng, Dong-Hui Xu, Rui Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissipationless transport by design in ultrathin magnetic topological insulator films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12610v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic topological insulators (MTIs) are among the prominent platforms for the next generation of high-speed and low-power spintronic devices. However, unlike their non-magnetic counterparts, where the surface spin-momentum locking prevents electrons from being scattered by non-magnetic impurities and results in a dissipationless electronic flow, magnetic impurities in MTIs cause dissipation by exerting magnetic torque on the electron spin. Decreasing this resistance is desired to reduce energy consumption and optimize performance of MTIs in envisaged applications. Here we reveal how electronic backscattering can be suppressed in a MTI thin film by external magnetic and/or electronic stimuli, to yield an entirely dissipationless spin-polarized charge transport. Our findings thus present an effective route to preserve spin coherence and enhance spin-current functionality in magnetic topological materials, suggesting design strategies for magneto-electronic and spintronic devices with strongly reduced energy consumption.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12610v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amir Sabzalipour, Mohammad Shafiei, Milorad V. Milo\v{s}evi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Possible Bose-Einstein condensation of magnons in a S = 5/2 honeycomb lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12682</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12682v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum magnets offer a unique platform for exploring exotic quantum phases and quantum phase transitions through external magnetic fields. A prominent example is the field-induced Bose--Einstein condensation (BEC) of magnons near the saturation field. While this behavior has been observed in low-spin systems, its realization in high-spin, quasi-two-dimensional magnets -- where multiple on-site excitations are possible -- remains exceptionally rare. Here, we report thermodynamic and density functional theory results on single crystals of the honeycomb-lattice antiferromagnet K$_{4}$MnMo$_{4}$O$_{15}$ with $S = 5/2$. The system undergoes a field-induced transition to a fully polarized state at the critical field $\mu_{0}H_{\rm s} = 6.4$~T. Our results reveal possible thermodynamic signatures of magnon BEC, $T_{\mathrm{N}} \sim (H_{\rm s} - H)^{2/d}$ ($d = 3$), expanding the purview of BEC-driven quantum criticality to a high-spin, quasi-two-dimensional antiferromagnets with negligibly small anisotropy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12682v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/8wdy-2zbw</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 134422, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>J. Khatua, S. M. Kumawat, G. Senthil Murugan, C. -L. Huang, Heung-Sik Kim, K. Sritharan, R. Sankar, Kwang-Yong Choi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Switchable chiral 2x2 pair density wave in pure CsV3Sb5</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12730</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12730v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate electron pairing in a super clean kagome superconductor CsV3Sb5 with a residual resistivity ratio (RRR) of 290. By using the dilution-refrigerator-based scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) at the Synergetic Extreme Condition User Facility (SECUF), we find that the pairing gap exhibits chiral 2x2 modulations, and their chirality can be controlled by magnetic field training. We introduce nonmagnetic impurities to observe the complete suppression of 2x2 pairing modulations in presence of persistent 2x2 charge order. This nonmagnetic pair-breaking effect provides phase-sensitive evidence for pair-density-wave (PDW) induced pairing modulations. Our results support switchable chiral 2x2 PDW in this super clean kagome superconductor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12730v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Song, Xiao-Yu Yan, Xin Yu, Desheng Wu, Deng Hu, Hailang Qin, Guowei Liu, Hanbin Deng, Chao Yan. Muwei Gao, Zhiwei Wang, Rui Wu, Jia-Xin Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>plasmonX: an Open-Source Code for Nanoplasmonics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12731</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12731v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the first public release of plasmonX, a novel open-source code for simulating the plasmonic response of complex nanostructures. The code supports both fully atomistic and implicit descriptions of nanomaterials. In particular, it employs the frequency-dependent fluctuating charges ($\omega$FQ) and dipoles ($\omega$FQF$\mu$) models to describe the response properties of atomistic structures, including simple and $d$-metals, graphene-based structures, and multi-metal nanostructures. For implicit representations, the Boundary Element Method is implemented in both the dielectric polarizable continuum model (DPCM) and integral equation formalism (IEF-PCM) variants. The distribution also includes a post-processing module that enables analysis of electric field-induced properties such as charge density and electric field patterns.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12731v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tommaso Giovannini, Pablo Grobas Illobre, Piero Lafiosca, Luca Nicoli, Luca Bonatti, Stefano Corni, Chiara Cappelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum criticality at the end of a pseudogap phase in superconducting infinite-layer nickelates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12786v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In many unconventional superconductors, the strange-metal regime is thought to emerge from quantum criticality, yet in cuprates this link is obscured by the enigmatic pseudogap. Superconducting infinite-layer nickelates provide a new arena to test this paradigm but are constrained to thin films, precluding calorimetry. We use the Seebeck coefficient as a low-temperature proxy for entropy per carrier and uncover a clear quantum-critical thermodynamic signature: in La$_{1-x}$Sr$_x$NiO$_2$ at the onset of $T$-linear resistivity ($x=0.20$), $S/T$ diverges logarithmically upon cooling, $S/T \propto \log T$. Boltzmann transport based on ARPES-derived band structure reproduces the high-temperature magnitude and sign of $S/T$ and reveals a threefold mass renormalization at the Fermi level. To identify the terminating phase, we analyze Hall data across Nd$_{1-x}$Sr$_x$NiO$_2$ and show that its temperature evolution is quantitatively captured by a minimal two-band model in which a strongly correlated Ni-$d_{x^2-y^2}$ Fermi surface exhibits Planckian $T$-linear scattering while the rare-earth Nd-$s$ pocket remains Fermi-liquid-like. Inverting the zero-temperature Hall response reveals a collapse of the Ni-$d_{x^2-y^2}$ band carrier density from $1+p$ to $p$ holes across the critical doping, without long-range magnetic order -- mirroring the cuprate pseudogap transition in cuprates. These results establish a quantum critical point at the end of a pseudogap-like phase in infinite-layer nickelates and unify the broader paradigm among correlated superconductors that strange metal behaviour is intimately linked to quantum criticality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12786v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Iorio-Duval, E. Beauchesne-Blanchet, F. Perreault, J. L. Santana Gonz\'alez, W. Sun, Y. F. Nie, A. Gourgout, G. Grissonnanche</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secret communication games and a hierarchy of quasiparticle statistics in 3 + 1D topological phases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11818</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11818v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that a family of secret communication challenge games naturally define a hierarchy of emergent quasiparticle statistics in three-dimensional (3D) topological phases. The winning strategies exploit a special class of the recently proposed $R$-paraparticles to allow nonlocal secret communication between the two participating players. We first give a high-level, axiomatic description of emergent $R$-paraparticles, and show that any physical system hosting such particles admits a winning strategy. We then analyze the games using the categorical description of topological phases (where point-like excitations in 3D are described by symmetric fusion categories), and show that only $R$-paraparticles can win the 3D challenge in a noise-robust way, and the winning strategy is essentially unique. This analysis associates emergent $R$-paraparticles to deconfined gauge theories based on an exotic class of finite groups. Thus, even though this special class of $R$-paraparticles are fermions or bosons under the categorical classification, their exchange statistics can still have nontrivial physical consequences in the presence of appropriate defects, and the $R$-paraparticle language offers a more convenient description of the winning strategies. Finally, while a subclass of non-Abelian anyons can win the game in 2D, we introduce twisted variants that exclude anyons, thereby singling out $R$-paraparticles in 2D as well. Our results establish the secret communication challenge as a versatile diagnostic for both identifying and classifying exotic exchange statistics in topological quantum matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11818v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiyuan Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anderson transition symmetries at the band-edge of a correlated Sn/Si monolayer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13878v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Anderson localization is predicted to enhance the critical temperature of disordered superconductors. Despite a huge body of theoretical work based on non-linear sigma models, experiments are lacking to understand correlated electrons in disordered potentials. In this study, we investigate a tin monolayer on silicon, a material known for its likely antiferromagnetic Mott-correlated groundstate. We analyze the statistical properties of tunneling conductance maps of increasingly localized states as we approach the edge of the valence band. Using multifractal analysis, we show that the system follows an exact symmetry relation based on the algebraic structure of nonlinear sigma-models (NLsMs). We anticipate that this symmetry may be broken in specific - e.g. chiral electronic phases. Finally, we point out that multifractal analysis can equally be applied to universal conductance fluctuations in magneto-transport experiments, thus providing a powerful tool to probe the underlying symmetries of disordered electronic phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13878v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mathieu Liz\'ee, Mohammadmehdi Torkzadeh, Fran\c{c}ois Debontridder, Marie Herv\'e, Christophe Brun, Igor Burmistrov, Tristan Cren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectroscopic probe of ultrafast magnetization dynamics in the extreme ultraviolet spectral range</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18312</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18312v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The development of spectroscopic techniques in the extreme ultraviolet (XUV) spectral range has significantly advanced the understanding of ultrafast interactions in magnetic systems triggered by optical excitation. In this work, we introduce a previously missing geometry that facilitates the observation of the ultrafast magnetization dynamics of magnetic systems with an out-of-plane magnetization grown on XUV opaque substrates. This approach to probing ultrafast magnetization dynamics combines the magneto-optical Kerr effect with the strong dependence of a sample's reflectance near its Brewster angle. It therefore works with linearly polarized light and does not require any additional polarizing optics. We provide a comprehensive analysis of the technique by presenting both simulations and experimental data as a function of the energy and the polarization of the XUV probe radiation as well as of the delay time after optical excitation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18312v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/kjg2-t36b</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, 214423, Published 13 June, 2025, Vol. 111, Iss. 21,1 June 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Johanna Richter, Somnath Jana, Robert Behrends, Carl S. Davies, Dieter W. Engel, Martin Hennecke, Daniel Schick, Clemens von Korff Schmising, Stefan Eisebitt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tuning Charge Order in $\kappa$-(BEDT-TTF)$_2$Hg(SCN)$_2$X (X=Br, Cl) via Uniaxial Strain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11547v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In condensed matter physics, experimental control of the properties of materials realizes the aspiration to physically govern the properties of materials and demonstrates an understanding of their underlying physics. In recent years, meaningful progress has been made towards a description of the physics of correlated electron systems, but examples of control of these systems remain rare. In this work, we confirm a phase diagram theoretically proposed for organic Mott insulators. We use $\kappa$-(BEDT-TTF)$_2$Hg(SCN)$_2$X (X=Br,Cl) (BEDT-TTF = bis(ethylenedithio)tetrathiafuvalene) materials as experimental realization of the proposed model and demonstrate the ability to tune them both ways across a phase border between a Mott insulator with a uniformly distributed charge and a charge ordered state through the application of uniaxial strain. We induce charge order at 33 K in the quantum dipole liquid material $\kappa$-(BEDT-TTF)$_2$Hg(SCN)$_2$Br through the application of tensile strain of 0.4% along the c-axis. We suppress charge order down to 10 K in $\kappa$-(BEDT-TTF)$_2$Hg(SCN)$_2$Cl by applying a tensile strain of 1.6% along the b-axis. We use Raman scattering spectroscopy to probe both the charge state and a soft mode of collective dipole fluctuations close to the phase border.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11547v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jesse Liebman, Svetlana Torunova, John A. Schlueter, Elena Zhilyaeva, Natalia Drichko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing fractional quantum Hall effect by photoluminescence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01577v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The recent discovery of fractional quantum anomalous Hall (FQAH) states - fractional quantum Hall (FQH) states realized without an external magnetic field - in twisted transition-metal dichalcogenide (TMD) bilayers represents a significant development in condensed matter physics. Notably, these states were first observed via photoluminescence (PL) spectroscopy. Surprisingly, a general theoretical understanding of PL is not available even for the standard FQH states. For an ideal two-dimensional system, the energy of the emitted photon is predicted to be independent of the correlations, but we show that the PL intensity contains valuable information. Specifically, we predict that at finite temperatures, the PL intensity peaks at the Jain fillings \nu = n/(2n \pm 1), and away from these fillings, the binding energies of the composite-fermion excitons and trions can be deduced from the temperature dependence of the intensity. We discuss implications for PL experiments in semiconductor quantum wells and twisted TMD bilayers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01577v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/gx4z-xddj</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 155303 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Aamir A. Makki, Mytraya Gattu, J. K. Jain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Construction of Kondo Chains by Engineering Porphyrin {\pi}-Radicals on Au(111)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.10729</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.10729v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum manipulation of molecular radical spins provides a crucial platform for exploring emergent phenomena in many-body systems. Here, we combine surface-confined synthesis with scanning tunneling microscopy(STM)tip-induced dehydrogenation to achieve atom-precise engineering of quasi-one-dimensional porphyrin-based Kondo chains (1-7 units) on Au(111). High-resolution STS measurements and low-energy effective modeling collectively demonstrate that {\pi}-radicals at each fused-porphyrin unit form Kondo singlets screened by conduction electrons. Adjacent singlets develop direct coherent coupling via quantum-state-overlap-enabled electron tunneling. Crucially, chiral symmetry in the effective model governs zero-mode distribution-present in odd-length chains yet absent in even-length chains-which dictates pronounced odd-even quantum effects in STS spectra of finite chains. Furthermore, the number of parallel porphyrin chains non-monotonically tunes the competition between the Kondo effect and spin exchange, showing opposing trends in strength and demonstrating that both wave-function overlap and the SOMO-LUMO gap collectively govern these interactions. This work simultaneously resolves the dimensional dependence of many-body correlations in confined quantum systems and pioneers approaches for quantum-critical manipulation in molecular spin architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.10729v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan Zhao, Kaiyue Jiang, Peng-Yi Liu, Jie Li, Ruoning Li, Xin Li, Xinchen Fang, Anjing Zhao, Yutong Zhu, Hongxiang Xu, Ting Chen, Dong Wang, Xiaodong Zhuang, Shimin Hou, Kai Wu, Song Gao, Qing-Feng Sun, Yajie Zhang, Yongfeng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Instability of the Haldane Phase: Roles of Charge Fluctuations and Hund's Coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05089</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05089v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We systematically investigate the stability of the symmetry-protected topological (SPT) Haldane phase in spin-1/2 Heisenberg and half-filled Hubbard ladders coupled by ferromagnetic Hund's interactions. Using density-matrix renormalization group (DMRG) method, we analyze key signatures of the Haldane phase: long-range string order, finite spin gap, and characteristic entanglement spectrum degeneracies. In spin-only Heisenberg ladders, we find immediate onset and continuous strengthening of the Haldane phase with increasing Hund's coupling. In contrast, the inclusion of charge fluctuations in Hubbard ladders leads to a nontrivial stability regime, revealing a robust yet bounded region where SPT order persists despite significant charge fluctuations. We identify distinct boundaries separating a trivial insulating phase from the Haldane SPT phase, governed by both Coulomb repulsion and Hund's coupling. Our results highlight the subtle interplay of spin and charge degrees of freedom in correlated itinerant systems and establish essential criteria for observing Haldane physics experimentally in fermionic ladder materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05089v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/8h2q-4wnt</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, L161102 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Satoshi Nishimoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Growth optimization of Ruddlesden-Popper nickelate high-temperature superconducting thin films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18107</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.18107v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The discovery of ambient-pressure nickelate high-temperature superconductivity provides a new platform for probing the underlying superconducting mechanisms. However, the thermodynamic metastability of Ruddlesden-Popper nickelates Lnn+1NinO3n+1 (Ln = lanthanide) presents significant challenges in achieving precise control over their structure and oxygen stoichiometry. This study establishes a systematic approach for growing phase-pure, high-quality Ln3Ni2O7 thin films on LaAlO3 and SrLaAlO4 substrates using gigantic-oxidative atomic-layer-by-layer epitaxy. The films grown under an ultrastrong oxidizing ozone atmosphere are superconducting without further post annealing. Specifically, the optimal Ln3Ni2O7/SrLaAlO4 superconducting film exhibits an onset transition temperature (Tc,onset) of 50 K. Four critical factors governing the crystalline quality and superconducting properties of Ln3Ni2O7 films are identified: 1) precise cation stoichiometric control suppresses secondary phase formation; 2) complete atomic layer-by-layer coverage coupled with 3) optimized interface reconstruction minimizes stacking faults; 4) accurate oxygen content regulation is essential for achieving a single superconducting transition and high Tc,onset. These findings provide valuable insights for the layer-by-layer epitaxy growth of diverse oxide high-temperature superconducting films.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.18107v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Lv, Zihao Nie, Heng Wang, Haoliang Huang, Guangdi Zhou, Qikun Xue, Zhuoyu Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>X-ray imaging of antiferromagnetic octupole domains in Mn$_3$Sn</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08998</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.08998v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Novel antiferromagnets with broken time reversal symmetry (TRS) have launched a new direction in spintronics research, combining the advantageous dynamical properties of conventional antiferromagnets with the controllability typically associated with ferromagnets. However, antiferromagnetic domains are notoriously challenging to image in real-space. X-ray magnetic circular dichroism (XMCD) offers a route to overcome this difficulty: XMCD contrast may be finite in TRS-breaking antiferromagnets with an appropriate magnetic space group. Here, we exploit this to image the octupole domains in a focused ion beam-fabricated device of the non-collinear antiferromagnet Mn$_3$Sn. Using scanning transmission x-ray microscopy, we spatially resolve the weak pre-edge XMCD contrast (of 0.2%) that is sensitive to $T_z$, achieving a contrast resolution better than 0.02%. We observe hysteretic switching of the octupole order through both the XMCD contrast and the corresponding anomalous Hall effect within the same device. These results confirm the bulk nature of this contrast, and establish XMCD-based microscopy as a powerful real space imaging method for TRS-breaking antiferromagnets, including altermagnets, enabling future studies of their dynamics, switching, and symmetry-tunable phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.08998v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Max T. Birch, Sebastian Wintz, Yuhan Sun, Akiko Kikkawa, Markus Weigand, Takahisa Arima, Yoshinori Tokura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transmon qutrit-based simulation of spin-1 AKLT systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19786v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Qutrit-based quantum circuits could help reduce the overall circuit depths, and hence the effect of noise, when the system of interest has a local dimension of three. Accessing second excited states in superconducting transmons provides a straightforward hardware realization of qutrits useful for such ternary encoding. In this work, we successfully calibrate microwave pulse gates to a low error rate to operate transmon qutrits. We use these qutrits to simulate one-dimensional spin-1 AKLT states (Affleck, Kennedy, Lieb, and Tasaki), which exhibit a multitude of interesting phenomena, such as topologically protected ground states, string order, and the existence of a robust Berry phase. We demonstrate the efficacy of qutrit-based simulation by preparing high-fidelity ground states of the AKLT Hamiltonian with open boundaries for various chain lengths. We then use ground state preparations of the perturbed AKLT Hamiltonian with periodic boundaries to calculate the Berry phase and illustrate non-trivial ground state topology. To establish the advantage of qutrits over qubits in the presence of noise, we present scalable methods for preparing the AKLT state and computing its Berry phase using tensor network simulations. Our work provides a pathway toward more general spin-1 physics simulations using transmon qutrits, with applications in chemistry, magnetism, and topological phases of matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19786v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keerthi Kumaran, Faisal Alam, Norhan Eassa, Kaelyn Ferris, Xiao Xiao, Lukasz Cincio, Nicholas Bronn, Arnab Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
