<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 04:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Q spin-valley order in twisted WSe2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12884v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report on a study of the interacting phase diagram of $3.65^\circ$-twisted WSe$_2$ at moir\'e hole filling $\nu=1$, in which we find previously-overlooked types of magnetism. Specifically, in part of the phase diagram we obtain a magnetic order parameter which modulates in space with four different non-zero wave vectors, corresponding to the three $M$-points and one $K$-point of the moir\'e Brillouin zone. These multi-Q orders, which can be coplanar or non-coplanar, are continuous deformations of the $120^\circ$ spin-valley anti-ferromagnet (AFM), where the unit cell has expanded by a factor of four. Interestingly, we find that the multi-Q states are stabilized for experimentally relevant values of interaction strength and displacement field, and are accompanied by a softening of the spin fluctuations near the $M$-points of the moir\'e</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12884v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arthur Bril, Nai Chao Hu, Nick Bultinck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exotic Surface Stripe Orders in Correlated Kagome Metal CsCr3Sb5</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12888v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The newly discovered kagome superconductor CsCr3Sb5 exhibits distinct features with flat bands and unique magnetism, providing a compelling platform for exploring novel quantum states of correlated electron systems. Emergent charge order in this material is a key for understanding unconventional superconductivity, but it remains unexplored at the atomic scale and the underlying physics is elusive. Here, we identify and unreported stripe orders on the surface which are distinct from the bulk and investigate the underlying bulk electronic properties using a combination of scanning tunneling microscopy (STM), angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) and density functional theory (DFT) calculations. Specifically, a mixture of 2a0 * a0 and 3a0 * a0 stripe order is found on Cs-terminated surface while 4a0 * root3a0 stripe order is found on the Sb-terminated surface. The electronic spectra exhibit strongly correlated features resembling that of high temperature superconductors, with kagome flat bands lying about 330 meV above EF, suggesting that the electron correlations arise from Coulomb interactions and Hund's coupling. Moreover, a distinct electron-boson coupling mode is observed at approximately 100 meV. These findings provide new insights into the interplay between surface and bulk charge orders in this strongly correlated kagome system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12888v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunxing Li, Peigen Li, Taimin Miao, Rui Xu, Yongqing Cai, Neng Cai, Bo Liang, Han Gao, Hanbo Xiao, Yongzhen Jiang, Jiefeng Cao, Fangyuan Zhu, Hongkun Wang, Jincheng Xie, Jingcheng Li, Zhongkai Liu, Chaoyu Chen, Yunwei Zhang, X. J. Zhou, Dingyong Zhong, Huichao Wang, Jianwei Huang, Donghui Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polarization dependency in Resonant Inelastic X-Ray Scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12891</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12891v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Resonant Inelastic X-Ray Scattering (RIXS) is a well-established tool for probing excitations in a wide range of materials. The measured spectra strongly depend on the scattering geometry, via its influence on the polarization of the incoming and outgoing light. By employing a tensor representation of the 4-point response function that governs the RIXS intensity, we disentangle the experimental geometry from the intrinsic material properties. In dipole-dipole RIXS processes and low-symmetry crystals, up to 81 linearly independent fundamental spectra can be measured as a function of light polarization. However, for crystals or molecules with symmetry, the number of independent fundamental spectra that define the RIXS tensor is significantly reduced.
  This work presents a systematic framework for determining the number of fundamental spectra and expressing the RIXS tensor in terms of these fundamental components. Given a specific experimental geometry, the measured spectrum can be represented as a linear combination of these fundamental spectra. To validate our approach, we performed calculations for different point group symmetries, both with and without an applied magnetic field. Within the same framework, we derived expressions for powder spectra in momentum-independent processes and spectra obtained using Bragg spectrometers. This formalism provides a valuable toolkit for optimizing experiment planning, data interpretation, and RIXS simulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12891v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michelangelo Tagliavini, Fabian Wenzel, Maurits W. Haverkort</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Incommensurate Twisted Bilayer Graphene: emerging quasi-periodicity and stability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12918</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12918v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a lattice model of Twisted Bilayer Graphene (TBG). The presence of incommensurate angles produces an emerging quasi-periodicity manifesting itself in large momenta Umklapp interactions that almost connect the Dirac points. We rigorously establish the stability of the semimetallic phase via a Renormalization Group analysis combined with number theoretical properties of irrationals, similar to the ones used in Kolmogorov-Arnold-Moser (KAM) theory for the stability of invariant tori. The interlayer hopping is weak and short ranged and the angles are chosen in a large measure set. The result provides a justification, in the above regime, to the effective continuum description of TBG in which large momenta interlayer interactions are neglected.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12918v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ian Jauslin, Vieri Mastropietro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid light-matter boundaries of graphene in a chiral cavity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13373v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent advances in chiral cavities that can couple coherently to two-dimensional materials have opened a powerful route to reshape electronic topology without an external drive. Here we establish the bulk-boundary correspondence for graphene embedded in a circularly polarized cavity. By combining exact diagonalization (ED) of zigzag ribbons, a semi-analytic T-matrix for half-infinite lattices, and analytical insights from a Dirac-Jaynes-Cummings model, we show that (i) every light-matter interaction-induced gap hosts pairs of unidirectional light-matter edge currents depending on the Chern number of the band while some of them are even bright; (ii) these chiral states persist throughout the entire photon ladder; and (iii) their dispersion, localization length and photon distribution exhibit a universal scaling controlled by the light-matter interaction. Time-evolution simulations further demonstrate that a dark electronic edge excitation can be converted into a bright and unidirectionally propagating current, that remains coherent over long time scales. Our results predict an experimental signature of the hybrid band topology and a blueprint for reconfigurable chiral channels in next-generation quantum-optical devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13373v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Volker Karle, Oriana K. Diessel, Vasil Rokaj, Ceren B. Da\u{g}</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Buckling and flat bands in twisted bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13471v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magic-angle twisted bilayer graphene (TBG) with its flat bands provides a rich platform for exploring emergent electronic orders. Similarly, periodically buckled monolayer graphene has been proposed as a tunable alternative for realizing flat bands. Here, we investigate the combined effect of buckling and twisting in bilayer graphene. We find that periodic buckling in large-angle TBG initially enhances band flattening compared to monolayer graphene, but for sufficiently strong buckling, it instead increases the band dispersion. This occurs both because of the presence of interlayer coupling, which reduces the in-plane kinetic energy, and due to the opening of a gap at the Dirac point resulting from inversion-symmetry breaking. Additionally, we find that buckling-induced band flattening competes with twist-induced band flattening. While the former breaks sublattice symmetry, generating a sublattice polarization, the latter prefers to preserve it. This prevents buckling from generating even flatter bands at the magic angle. Nevertheless, we find that buckled TBG can exhibit flatter bands than pristine TBG over a wide range of twist angles, with a flatness similar to that of pristine magic-angle TBG.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13471v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jannes van Poppelen, Annica M. Black-Schaffer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay of magnetic and thermodynamic responses in the kagome-triangular system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13530</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13530v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Inspired by the recent experimental progress in pyrochlore derivative \ce{RE3Sb3A2O14 (A=Mg, Zn)}, we investigate the Hubbard model on the kagome lattice with an additional hopping $t'/t$, which enables continuous interpolation between the kagome and triangular lattices by using determinant quantum Monte Carlo simulations. We analyze the evolution of magnetic correlations and thermodynamic responses across different values of $t'/t$ and on-site interaction $U$. It is found that increasing $t'/t$ suppresses short-range antiferromagnetic correlations, while the next-nearest-neighbor correlations exhibit a sign change near $t'/t \approx 0.3 \text{--} 0.4$. Within this regime, the specific heat shows a pronounced low-temperature peak, indicating an emergent spin-related energy scale. Increasing $U$ enhances magnetic correlations and shifts the associated $t'/t$ crossover points to larger values. We also discuss the sign problem to clarify which parameter region of our numerical simulations is accessible and reliable. Our results uncover the competition between frustration and correlations and the interplay of magnetic and thermodynamic responses in the kagome lattice, providing insights into correlated states in frustrated materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13530v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zixuan Jia, Lufeng Zhang, Qingzhuo Duan, Zenghui Fan, Jingyao Wang, Bing Huang, Tianxing Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Momentum-Resolved Spectroscopy of Superconductivity with the Quantum Twisting Microscope</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13641v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a theoretical framework for probing superconductivity with momentum resolution using the quantum twisting microscope (QTM), a planar tunneling device where a graphene tip is rotated relative to a two-dimensional sample. Due to in-plane momentum conservation, the QTM directly measures the superconducting spectral function along well-defined trajectories in momentum space. The relative intensities of electron and hole excitations encode the Bogoliubov coherence factors, revealing the momentum dependence of the pairing magnitude. Three $C_{3z}$-related tunneling channels enable direct detection of rotational symmetry breaking, as well as nodal points in the superconducting order parameter. We apply our framework to superconductivity within the Bistritzer-MacDonald model of noninteracting electrons and the Topological Heavy Fermion model, which accounts for electron-electron interactions. Together, these capabilities establish the QTM as a direct probe of the pairing symmetry and microscopic origin of superconductivity in two-dimensional materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13641v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuval Waschitz, Ady Stern, Yuval Oreg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Excitonic correlations in the equilibrium and voltage-biased bilayer Hubbard model: multi-orbital two-particle self-consistent approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13667v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a nonequilibrium multi-orbital extension of the two-particle self-consistent theory and apply it to the bilayer Hubbard model as a minimal platform to investigate correlation effects in the presence of interlayer interactions and tunneling. The method determines vertex corrections in the spin and charge channels self-consistently at the two-particle level, thereby avoiding the spurious finite-temperature phase transitions that limit dynamical mean-field theory in two dimensions. We derive the spectral self-energy and implement the framework directly on the real-frequency axis within the Keldysh nonequilibrium Green's function formalism, enabling the treatment of both equilibrium and non-equilibrium steady states without relying on numerical analytic continuation. As an application, we demonstrate that a pseudogap can emerge in the bilayer Hubbard model when spin, charge, or excitonic fluctuations become sufficiently strong. Instabilities in different channels are also evaluated in an unbiased manner across the parameter space. Remarkably, we find that the excitonic susceptibility grows with increasing interlayer bias, before it gets suppressed at large biases by the charge imbalance between the layers. This work establishes a versatile and computationally efficient framework for investigating correlated multi-orbital systems under nonequilibrium conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13667v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiawei Yan, Jonas B. Profe, Yuta Murakami, Philipp Werner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strain-induced Moir\'e Reconstruction and Memorization in Two-Dimensional Materials without Twist</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13699</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13699v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2D) materials with a twist between layers exhibit a moir\'e interference pattern with larger periodicity than any of the constituent layer unit cells. In these systems, a wealth of exotic phases appear that result from moir\'e-dependent many-body electron correlation effects or non-trivial band topology. One problem with using twist to generate moir\'e interference has been the difficulty in creating high-quality, uniform, and repeatable samples due to fabrication through mechanical stacking with viscoelastic stamps. Here we show, a new method to generate moir\'e interference through the controlled application of layer-by-layer strain (heterostrain) on non-twisted 2D materials, where moir\'e interference results from strain-induced lattice mismatch without twisting or stacking. Heterostrain generation is achieved by depositing stressed thin films onto 2D materials to apply large strains to the top layers while leaving layers further down less strained. We achieve deterministic control of moir\'e periodicity and symmetry in non-twisted 2D multilayers and bilayers, with 97% yield, through varying stressor film force (film thickness X film stress) and geometry. Moir\'e reconstruction effects are memorized after the removal of the stressor layers. Control over the strain degree-of-freedom opens the door to a completely unexplored set of unrealized tunable moir\'e geometric symmetries, which may now be achieved in a high-yield and user-skill independent process taking only hours. This technique solves a long-standing throughput bottleneck in new moir\'e quantum materials discovery and opens the door to industrially-compatible manufacturing for 2D moir\'e-based electronic or optical devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13699v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nazmul Hasan, Tara Pe\~na, Aditya Dey, Dongyoung Yoon, Zakaria Islam, Yue Zhang, Maria Vitoria Guimaraes Leal, Arend M. van der Zande, Hesam Askari, Stephen M. Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structural origin of resonant diffraction in RuO$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13767</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13767v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report Ru L$_3$-edge resonant X-ray diffraction studies on single crystal and (001) epitaxial films of RuO$_2$. We investigate the distinct $\mathbf{Q} = (100)$ and $(001)$ reflections as a function of incident energy, azimuthal angle, and temperature. The results show that the observed resonant diffraction in RuO$_2$ is fully consistent with a resonant charge anisotropy signal of structural origin permitted by the parent (non-magnetic) rutile $P4_2/mnm$ space group. These results significantly constrain the magnetic contribution to the resonant diffraction signal and indicate the unlikely existence of $\mathbf{k} = 0$ antiferromagnetic order in RuO$_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13767v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Connor A Occhialini, Christie Nelson, Alessandro Bombardi, Shiyu Fan, Raul Acevedo-Esteves, Riccardo Comin, Dmitri N Basov, Maki Musashi, Masashi Kawasaki, Masaki Uchida, Hoydoo You, John Mitchell, Valentina Bisogni, Claudio Mazzoli, Jonathan Pelliciari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical Response of Graphene Quantum Dots in the Visible Spectrum: A Combined DFT-QED Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13769</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13769v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a model based on density functional theory (DFT) and quantum electrodynamics (QED) to study the dynamical characteristics of graphene quantum dots (GQDs). We assume the GQD edges are saturated with hydrogen atoms, effectively making it a polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon (PAH) such as coronene. By combining the GQD spectrum calculated from a time-dependent DFT (TDDFT) with the dynamical behavior of a QD model derived from QED, we calculate the main optical characteristics of the GQD, such as its transition frequencies, the dipole moment associated to each of those transitions, life-time and the population dynamics of the molecular levels. Owing to the close match between the calculated spectrum and experimental results, our results represent a significant contribution to research on quantum treatments of light-matter interactions in realistic 2D nanomaterials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13769v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Olivo, J. Blengino Albrieu, Mauro Cuevas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resonant diffraction and photoemission inconsistent with altermagnetism in epitaxial RuO$_2$ films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13781v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Excitement about the magnetic and electronic properties of RuO$_2$ is growing, fueled by reports of antiferromagnetism, strain-induced superconductivity, and its recent classification as a member of a newly proposed magnetic class, altermagnets, with RuO$_2$ widely regarded as the paradigmatic example. Nevertheless, the magnetic ground state of RuO$_2$ remains contentious, as several recent experiments report no evidence of magnetic order. To address this discrepancy, we performed resonant elastic scattering measurements on a series of epitaxial RuO$_2$ thin films grown on the (100)-plane of TiO$_2$ substrates across a range of strain states. Leveraging full polarization control and azimuthal scans of the structurally forbidden 100 Bragg reflection, we systematically tested for signatures of colinear antiferromagnetic order. We found that the resonant elastic scattering signal in RuO$_2$ thin films likely originates from anisotropic charge scattering, not long-range antiferromagnetic order. Using angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy we uncover a band structure without altermagnetic band splitting that is consistent with a nonmagnetic phase. Similarly, anisotropic magnetoresistance results show no evidence of magnetism. The combination of three independent measurements suggests the absence of altermagnetism in RuO$_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13781v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Z. Gregory, Neha Wadehra, Shuyuan Zhang, Yi Wu, Samuel Poage, J\"org Strempfer, Asish K. Kundu, Anil Rajapitamahuni, Elio Vescovo, Anita Verma, Bet\"ul Pamuk, Jacob Ruf, Hari Nair, Nathaniel J. Schreiber, Kaveh Ahadi, Kyle M. Shen, Darrell G. Schlom, Andrej Singer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent Discrete Time Crystals on Digital Quantum Computers: Boundary-Protected and Ancilla-Induced Disorder Mechanisms of Thermalization Slowdown</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.13577v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Periodically driven (Floquet) systems typically evolve toward an infinite-temperature thermal state due to continuous energy absorption. Before reaching equilibrium, however, they can transiently exhibit long-lived prethermal states that host exotic nonequilibrium phenomena, such as discrete time crystals (DTCs). In this study, we investigate the relaxation dynamics of periodically driven product states in a kicked Ising model implemented on the IBM Quantum Eagle and Heron processors. By using ancilla qubits to mediate interactions, we construct Kagome and Lieb lattices on superconducting qubits with heavy-hex connectivity. We identify two distinct types of noise-induced DTCs on Kagome and Lieb lattices, both arising from quantum noise in ancilla qubits. Type-I DTCs originate from robust boundary-mode period-doubling oscillations, stabilized by symmetry charge pumping, that are redistributed into the bulk due to ancilla noise. Type-II DTCs, in contrast, emerge in systems without charge-pumped qubits, where quantum noise unexpectedly stabilizes period-doubling oscillations that would otherwise rapidly decay. On the noisier Eagle device (ibm_kyiv), we observe both type-I and type-II DTCs on 53-qubit Kagome lattices with and without charge-pumped qubits, respectively. In contrast, on the lower-noise Heron device (ibm_marrakesh), period-doubling oscillations are confined to boundary-localized oscillations on 82-qubit Kagome and 40-qubit Lieb lattices, as redistribution into the bulk is suppressed. These experimental findings are supported by noisy matrix-product-state simulations, in which ancilla noise is modeled as random sign flips in the two-qubit gate rotation angles. Our results demonstrate that quantum noise in ancilla qubits can give rise to novel classes of prethermal dynamical phases, including boundary-protected and noise-induced DTCs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.13577v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazuya Shinjo, Kazuhiro Seki, Seiji Yunoki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum geometry of bosonic Bogoliubov quasiparticles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12981</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12981v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Bosonic Bogoliubov de Gennes (BBdG) Hamiltonians describe the excitations of weakly interacting Bose condensates as well as photonic systems under parametric driving. Their topological features have been studied mainly by utilizing a generalized symplectic version of the Berry curvature and related Chern numbers. However, a full characterization of geometrical features in BBdG systems is still lacking. Here, we propose a symplectic quantum geometric tensor (SQGT), whose imaginary part leads to the previously studied symplectic Berry curvature, while the real part gives rise to a symplectic quantum metric, providing a natural distance measure in the space of bosonic Bogoliubov modes. The SQGT is directly related to observable properties of BBdG systems. We show how to measure all components of the SQGT by extracting excitation rates in response to periodic modulations of the systems' parameters. Moreover, we connect the symplectic Berry curvature to a generalized symplectic anomalous velocity term for Bogoliubov-Bloch wave packets. We test our results for a bosonic Bogoliubov-Haldane model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12981v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/1sz1-nwzf</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Isaac Tesfaye, Andr\'e Eckardt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bose-Hubbard simulator with long-range hopping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17162</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17162v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Enriching condensed-matter systems with quantum optical phenomena currently drives intense research efforts, particularly to introduce collective quantum correlations. Here we access this paradigm, by confining dipolar excitons in a nanoscopic lattice where long-range hopping, and nearest-neighbour dipolar repulsions, dress the Bose-Hubbard Hamiltonian. Long-range hopping is evidenced by the spontaneous buildup of many-body sub-radiance, signalled by an algebraic slowdown of excitons radiative dissipation. In addition, we observe a threshold increase of temporal coherence for dipolar quantum solids only. It suggests that excitons condense in a single sub-radiant state for Mott-like phases. These combine then spatial order and collectively extended coherence, in a single degree of freedom. Our study unveils that nanoscopic exciton arrays provide a unique platform to design new frontiers of strongly-correlated lattice models with long-range correlations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17162v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Camille Lagoin, Corentin Morin, Kirk Baldwin, Loren Pfeiffer, Francois Dubin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral finite-momentum superconductivity in the tetralayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07145</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07145v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Motivated by the recent experimental discovery of superconductivity in rhombohedral tetralayer graphene, we investigate the pairing mechanism arising from the density-density interactions within the random-phase approximation. This approach successfully highlights the dominance of the chiral $p$-wave pairing between electrons with the same spin and valley index at low densities, while also predicting the superconducting range in agreement with experimental findings. Furthermore, we examine the characteristics of distinct superconducting regions: SC1 and SC2 exhibit chiral finite-momentum superconductivity with pronounced phase fluctuations, whereas SC4 displays zero-momentum superconductivity, with its transition temperature constrained by the pairing strength.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07145v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiong Qin, Congjun Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnon-phonon interactions from first principles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05385v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Modeling spin-wave (magnon) dynamics in novel materials is important to advance spintronics and spin-based quantum technologies. The interactions between magnons and lattice vibrations (phonons) limit the length scale for magnon transport. However, quantifying these interactions remains challenging. Here we show many-body calculations of magnon-phonon (mag-ph) coupling based on the ab initio Bethe-Salpeter equation. We derive expressions for mag-ph coupling matrices and compute them in 2D ferromagnets, focusing on hydrogenated graphene and monolayer CrI3. Our analysis shows that electron-phonon (e-ph) and mag-ph interactions differ significantly, where modes with weak e-ph coupling can exhibit strong mag-ph coupling (and vice versa), and reveals which phonon modes couple more strongly with magnons. In both materials studied here, the inelastic magnon relaxation time is found to decrease abruptly above the threshold for emission of strongly coupled phonons, thereby defining a low-energy window for efficient magnon transport. By averaging in this window, we compute the temperature-dependent magnon mean-free path, a key figure of merit for spintronics, entirely from first principles. The theory and computational tools shown in this work enable studies of magnon interactions, scattering, and dynamics in generic materials, advancing the design of magnetic systems and magnon- and spin-based devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05385v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Khoa B. Le, Ali Esquembre-Kucukalic, Hsiao-Yi Chen, Ivan Maliyov, Yao Luo, Jin-Jian Zhou, Davide Sangalli, Alejandro Molina-Sanchez, Marco Bernardi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phonons in Electron Crystals with Berry Curvature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16390</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16390v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent advances in 2D materials featuring nonzero Berry curvature have inspired extensions of the Wigner crystallization paradigm. This paper derives a low-energy effective theory for such quantum crystals, including the anomalous Hall crystal (AHC) with nonzero Chern number. First we show that the low frequency dispersion of phonons in AHC, despite the presence of Berry curvature, resembles that of the zero field (rather than finite magnetic field) Wigner crystal due to the commutation of translation generators. We explain how key parameters of the phonon theory such as elastic constants and effective mass can be extracted from microscopic models, and apply them to two families of models: the recently introduced $\lambda$-jellium model and a model of rhombohedral multilayer graphene (RMG). In the $\lambda$-jellium model, we explore the energy landscape as crystal geometry shifts, revealing that AHC can become `soft' under certain conditions. This causes transitions in lattice geometry, although the quantized Hall response remains unchanged. Surprisingly, the Berry curvature seems to enhance the effective mass, leading to a reduction in phonon speed. For the AHC in RMG, we obtain estimates of phonon speed and shear stiffness. We also identify a previously overlooked `kineo-elastic' term in the phonon effective action that is present in the symmetry setting of RMG, and leads to dramatic differences in phonon speeds in opposite directions. We numerically confirm these predictions of the effective actions by time-dependent Hartree-Fock calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16390v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1073/pnas.2515532122</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PNAS 122 (38), e2515532122 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Junkai Dong, Ophelia Evelyn Sommer, Tomohiro Soejima, Daniel E. Parker, Ashvin Vishwanath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Terahertz Landau level spectroscopy of Dirac fermions in millimeter-scale twisted bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20156</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.20156v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Exotic electronic physics including correlated insulating states and fractional Chern insulators have been observed in twisted bilayer graphene in a magnetic field when the Fermi velocity vanishes, however a question remains as to the stability of these states which is controlled by the gap to the first excited state. Free-space terahertz magneto-optics can directly probe the gap to charge excitations which bounds the stability of electronic states, but this measurement has thus-far been inaccessible due to the micron size of twisted bilayer graphene samples, while the wavelength of terahertz light is up to a millimeter. Here we leverage advances in fabrication to create twisted bilayer graphene samples over 5 mm x 5 mm in size with a uniform twist angle and study the magnetic field dependence of the cyclotron resonance by a complex Faraday rotation experiment in p-doped large angle twisted bilayer graphene. These measurements directly probe charge excitations in inter-Landau level transitions and determine the Fermi velocity as a function of twist angle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.20156v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin F. Mead, Spenser Talkington, An-Hsi Chen, Debarghya Mallick, Zhaodong Chu, Xingyue Han, Seong-Jun Yang, Cheol-Joo Kim, Matthew Brahlek, Eugene J. Mele, Liang Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic structure and exchange interactions in altermagnetic MnGeP$_2$ in the quasiparticle-self-consistent $GW$ approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02934</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02934v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The QS$GW$ method is used to study the electronic band structure, optical dielectric function, and exchange interactions in chalcopyrite, $I\bar{4}2d$, structure MnGeP$_2$. The material is found to be an antiferromagnetic semiconductor with the lowest direct gap of 2.44 eV at the $\Gamma$ point and an indirect gap of 1.87 eV. The material is an altermagnet, with the two magnetic atoms of opposite spin related by a two-fold rotation operation perpendicular to the main 4-fold rotation inversion axis. The spin splittings along a low symmetry line like $PN$ are sizable, while at k-points on the diagonal mirror planes or on the twofold symmetry axes, the spin splitting is zero. The exchange interactions are calculated using a linear response approach. The antiferromagnetic exchange-interaction between nearest neighbors in the primitive unit cell is dominating and found to be slightly decreasing upon carrier doping. The transverse spin susceptibilities, which provide interatomic site exchange interactions after averaging over the muffin-tin spheres, are calculated from the $GW$ band structure and wave functions. From these exchange interactions, the spin wave spectra are obtained along the high symmetry lines and the N\'{e}el temperature is calculated using the mean-field and Tyablikov (RPA) estimations. The dielectric function and the optical absorption spectra are calculated, including excitonic effects, using the Bethe-Salpeter equation. The exchange interactions around Mn$_{\rm Ge}$ defect sites are also studied. While we find it can generate ferromagnetic interactions with neighboring spins, we did not find evidence of producing an overall ferromagnetic phase. If Mn antisites are introduced by exchanging Mn with a nearby Ge, the interactions stay largely antiferromagnetic. Adding Mn antisites leads to a metallic band structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02934v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ilteris K. Turan, Walter R L. Lambrecht, Jerome Jackson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunneling conductance in superconducting junctions with $p$-wave unconventional magnets breaking time-reversal symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13372</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13372v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A new type of magnet called $p$-wave unconventional magnet is proposed, stimulated by the discovery of altermagnet. We study the tunneling conductance of $p$-wave unconventional magnet/superconductor junctions by adopting the effective Hamiltonian of $p$-wave unconventional magnets with time-reversal symmetry breaking, suggested in Ref [arXiv: 2309.01607 (2024)]. The tunneling conductance shows an asymmetric behavior with respect to bias voltage in the helical $p$-wave superconductor junctions. It is caused by the missing of helical edge states contributing to the charge conductance owing to the momentum-dependent spin-split feature of the Fermi surface in $p$-wave unconventional magnets. In chiral $d$ and $p$-wave superconductor junctions, the resulting spin-resolved tunneling conductance takes a different value for spin sectors due to the time-reversal symmetry breaking in superconductors. Our results qualitatively reproduce the results based on the simplified Hamiltonian in Ref [J.\ Phys.\ Soc.\ Jpn.\ \textbf{93}, 114703 (2024)], where only the odd function of the exchange coupling of $p$-wave unconventional magnets is taken into account, which gives the shift of the Fermi surface and preserves the time-reversal symmetry similar to the spin-orbit coupling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13372v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuri Fukaya, Keiji Yada, Yukio Tanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strain-tunable anomalous Hall effect in hexagonal MnTe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19582</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19582v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The ability to control and manipulate time-reversal ($T$) symmetry-breaking phases with near-zero net magnetization is a sought-after goal in spintronic devices. The recently discovered hexagonal altermagnet manganese telluride ($\alpha$-MnTe) is a prime example. It has a compensated altermagnetic ground state where the magnetic moments are aligned in each layer and stacked antiparallel along the $c$ axis, yet it exhibits a spontaneous anomalous Hall effect (AHE) that breaks the $T$-symmetry with a vanishingly small $c$-axis ferromagnetic (FM) moment. However, the presence of three 120$^\circ$ separated in-plane magnetic domains presents a challenge in understanding the origin of the AHE and the effective control of the altermagnetic state. Here we use neutron scattering to show that a compressive uniaxial strain along the next-nearest-neighbor Mn-Mn bond direction detwins $\alpha$-MnTe into a single in-plane magnetic domain, aligning the in-plane moments along the same axis. Furthermore, we find that uniaxial strain (-0.2% to 0.1%) significantly sharpens the magnetic hysteresis loop and switches the sign of the AHE near room temperature. Remarkably, this is achieved without altering the altermagnetic phase-transition temperature or substantially changing the small $c$-axis FM moment. Combined with our phenomenological model, we argue that these effects result from the modification of the electronic Berry curvature by a combination of both spin-orbit coupling and strain. Our work not only unambiguously establishes the relationship between the in-plane moment direction and the AHE in $\alpha$-MnTe but also paves the way for future applications in highly scalable, strain-tunable magnetic sensors and spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19582v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhaoyu Liu, Sijie Xu, Jonathan M. DeStefano, Elliott Rosenberg, Tingjun Zhang, Jinyulin Li, Matthew B. Stone, Feng Ye, Rong Cong, Siyu Pan, Ching-Wu Chu, Liangzi Deng, Emilia Morosan, Rafael M. Fernandes, Jiun-Haw Chu, Pengcheng Dai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement and the density matrix renormalisation group in the generalised Landau paradigm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.06334</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.06334v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The fields of entanglement theory and tensor networks have recently emerged as central tools for characterising quantum phases of matter. In this article, we determine the entanglement structure of ground states of gapped symmetric quantum lattice models, and use this to obtain the most efficient tensor network representation of those ground states. We do this by showing that degeneracies in the entanglement spectrum arise through a duality transformation of the original model to the unique dual model where the entire dual (generalised) symmetry is spontaneously broken and subsequently no degeneracies are present. Physically, this duality transformation amounts to a (twisted) gauging of the unbroken symmetry in the original ground state. This result has strong implications for the complexity of simulating many-body systems using variational tensor network methods. For every phase in the phase diagram, the dual representation of the ground state that completely breaks the symmetry minimises both the entanglement entropy and the required number of variational parameters. We demonstrate the applicability of this idea by developing a generalised density matrix renormalisation group algorithm that works on (dual) constrained Hilbert spaces, and quantify the computational gains obtained over traditional tensor network methods in a perturbed Heisenberg model. Our work testifies to the usefulness of generalised non-invertible symmetries and their formal category theoretic description for the practical simulation of strongly correlated systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.06334v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41567-025-02961-2</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nat. Phys. 21, 1657-1663 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Laurens Lootens, Clement Delcamp, Frank Verstraete</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
