<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 04:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Coherent Optical Control of Electron Dynamics in Patterned Graphene Nanoribbons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.08678v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The field of coherent electronics aims to advance electronic functionalities by utilizing quantum coherence. Here, we demonstrate a viable and versatile methodology for controlling electron dynamics optically in graphene nanoribbons. In particular, we propose to flatten the band structure of armchair graphene nanoribbons via control electrodes, arranged periodically along the extended direction of the nanoribbon. This addresses a key mechanism for dephasing in solids, which derives from the momentum dependence of the energy gap between the valence and the conduction band. We design an optimal driving field pulse to produce collective Rabi oscillations between these bands, in their flattened configuration. As an example for coherent control, we show that these optimized pulses can be used to invert the entire electronic band population by a $\pi$ pulse in a reversible fashion, and to create a superposition state via a $\pi/2$ pulse, which generates an alternating photocurrent. Our proposal consists of a platform and methodological approach to optically control the electron dynamics of graphene nanoribbons, paving the way toward novel coherent electronic and quantum information processing devices in solid-state materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.08678v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riek H. R\"ustemeier, H. P. Ojeda Collado, Ludwig Mathey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theory of non-resonant Raman scattering from electrons in nodal and flat bands</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08690</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.08690v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Raman scattering is emerging as a surprising probe of electron topology in quantum materials. It has been used recently to detect and characterize a topological phase transition that accompanies the magnetic transition in Nd$_2$Ir$_2$O$_7$. Here we present a theory of Raman scattering from nodal electrons with Weyl and quadratic band touching spectra, which has to reach beyond the standard effective mass approximation. After reviewing and providing the details of our previous theory development, we discuss several new results. We show that the light-polarization dependence of Raman scattering is universal in the case of Weyl electrons and given by an analytic expression, while it contains symmetry-protected features in the case of quadratic band-touching nodes. We also analyze modifications of the Raman signal due to the ubiquitous tilting of the Weyl spectrum, and argue that universality is lost only in a finite frequency range that springs out of the threshold frequency for untilted nodes. Finally, we explore the frequency dependence of Raman scattering for the case of Dirac electrons coexisting with a flat band in the same region of the first Brillouin zone, which is inspired by the material V$_{1/3}$NbS$_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.08690v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Predrag Nikoli\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-Throughput Screening of Transition Metal-Based 2D Multilayer Kagome Materials via the "1 + 3" Design Strategy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08903</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.08903v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2D) kagome materials have drawn extensive research interest due to their unique electronic properties, like flat bands, magnetic frustration, and topological quantum states, which enable precise quantum state control and novel device innovation. Yet, simultaneously achieving high stability, tunability, and multifunctionality in 2D kagome systems remains a key material design challenge. In this study, we innovatively propose a new paradigm for constructing two-dimensional multi-kagome-layer materials based on the "1+3" design concept. By seamlessly integrating high-throughput screening techniques, we have successfully identified 6,379 novel 2D multilayer kagome candidates from a vast pool of candidates. These materials exhibit a rich diversity of types, encompassing 173 metals, 27 semimetals, 166 ferromagnetic semiconductors, and as many as 6,013 semiconductors. Furthermore, based on the 2D flat-band scoring criteria, we conducted a detailed analysis of the flat-band characteristics of the energy bands near the Fermi level in the predicted systems. Our findings reveal that approximately two-thirds of the systems meet the 2D flat-band scoring criteria, and notably, several systems exhibit nearly perfect flat-band characteristics. Our work provides an excellent paradigm for the design and research of 2D multilayer kagome materials</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.08903v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xing-Yu Wang, En-Qi Bao, Su-Yang Shen, Jun-Hui Yuan, Jiafu Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>X-ray imaging of antiferromagnetic octupole domains in Mn$_3$Sn</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08998</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.08998v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Novel antiferromagnets with broken time reversal symmetry (TRS) have launched a new direction in spintronics research, combining the advantageous dynamical properties of conventional antiferromagnets with the controllability typically associated with ferromagnets. However, antiferromagnetic domains are notoriously challenging to image in real-space. X-ray magnetic circular dichroism (XMCD) offers a route to overcome this difficulty: XMCD contrast may be finite in TRS-breaking antiferromagnets with an appropriate magnetic space group. Here, we exploit this to image the octupole domains in a focused ion beam-fabricated device of the non-collinear antiferromagnet Mn$_3$Sn. Using scanning transmission x-ray microscopy, we spatially resolve the weak pre-edge XMCD contrast (of 0.2%) that is sensitive to $T_z$, achieving a contrast resolution better than 0.02%. We observe hysteretic switching of the octupole order through both the XMCD contrast and the corresponding anomalous Hall effect within the same device. These results confirm the bulk nature of this contrast, and establish XMCD-based microscopy as a powerful real space imaging method for TRS-breaking antiferromagnets, including altermagnets, enabling future studies of their dynamics, switching, and symmetry-tunable phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.08998v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Max T. Birch, Sebastian Wintz, Yuhan Sun, Akiko Kikkawa, Markus Weigand, Takahisa Arima, Yoshinori Tokura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chern insulators and topological flat bands in cavity-embedded kagome systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09150v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate topological band structures of a kagome system coupled to a circularly polarized cavity mode, using a model based on a muffin-tin potential and quantum light-matter interaction. We show that Chern insulating phases emerge in the cavity-embedded kagome system due to the light-matter interaction that breaks time-reversal symmetry. We also find that a nearly flat band can be topologically nontrivial with a nonzero Chern number. By varying the light-matter interaction, we also reveal that topological phase transitions occur between different Chern insulating phases in the ultrastrong coupling regime. The phase transitions change the sign of the Chern number, switching the direction of the edge current. We demonstrate the existence of topological edge modes in the cavity-embedded kagome Chern insulators by constructing a low-energy effective tight-binding model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09150v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hikaru Goto, Ryo Okugawa, Takami Tohyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nematic Fluctuations and Electronic Correlations in Heavily Hole-Doped Ba$_{1-x}$K$_x$Fe$_2$As$_2$ Probed by Elastoresistance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09151</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09151v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work investigates nematic fluctuations and electronic correlations in the hole-doped iron pnictide superconductor Ba$_{1-x}$K$_x$Fe$_2$As$_2$ by means of longitudinal and transverse elastoresistance measurements over a wide doping range ($0.63 &lt; x &lt; 0.98$). For this purpose, the orbital character of the electronic response was revealed by decomposition of the elastoresistance into the $A_{1g}$ and $B_{2g}$ symmetry channels. It was shown that at lower doping levels nematic fluctuations in the $B_{2g}$ channel dominate, while for $x &gt; 0.68$ the $A_{1g}$ channel becomes dominant and reaches a pronounced maximum at $x \approx 0.8$ which indicates strong orbital-selective electronic correlations. Despite the dominance of the $A_{1g}$ signal at high doping, a weak contribution in the $B_{2g}$ channel persists, which can be interpreted as a remnant of nematic fluctuations. Model calculations based on a five-orbital tight-binding Hamiltonian with interactions attribute the observed enhancement in the $A_{1g}$ channel to an orbital-selective Kondo-like resonance, predominantly involving the $d_{xy}$ orbital. We discuss our results in relation to the evolution of the Sommerfeld coefficient reported in the literature and a reported change of the superconducting order parameter. All this indicates that for $x &gt; 0.68$ qualitatively new physics emerges. Our findings suggest that electronic correlations in the strongly hole-doped regime play an important role in superconductivity, while the detectable weak nematic fluctuations may also be of relevance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09151v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Franz Eckelt, Steffen Sykora, Xiaochen Hong, Vilmos Koscis, Vadim Grinenko, Bernd B\"uchner, Kunihiro Kihou, Chu-Ho Lee, Christian Hess</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasiparticle effects and strong excitonic features in exfoliable 1D semiconducting materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09194v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report a comprehensive first-principles study of the electronic and optical properties of recently identified exfoliable one-dimensional semiconducting materials, focusing on chalcogenide-based atomic chains derived from van der Waals-bonded bulk crystals. Specifically, we investigate covalently bonded S3 and Te3 chains, and polar-bonded As2S3 and Bi2Te3 chains, using a fully first-principles approach that combines density-functional theory (DFT), density-functional perturbation theory (DFPT), and many-body perturbation theory within the GW approximation and Bethe-Salpeter equation (BSE). Our vibrational analysis shows that freestanding isolated wires remain dynamically stable, with the zone-center optical phonon modes leading to infrared activity. The main finding of this study is the presence of very strong exciton binding energies (1-3 eV), which make these novel 1D materials ideal platforms for room-temperature excitonic applications. Interestingly, the exciton character remains Wannier-Mott-like, as indicated by average electron-hole separations larger than the lattice constant. Notably, the optical gaps of these materials span a wide range - from infrared (0.8 eV, Bi2Te3), through visible spectrum (yellow: 2.17 eV, Te3; blue: 2.71 eV, As2S3), up to ultraviolet (4.07 eV, S3) - highlighting their versatility for broadband optoelectronic applications. Our results offer a detailed, many-body perspective on the optoelectronic behavior of these low-dimensional materials and underscore their potential for applications in next-generation nanoscale optoelectronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09194v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simone Grillo, Chiara Cignarella, Friedhelm Bechstedt, Paola Gori, Maurizia Palummo, Davide Campi, Nicola Marzari, Olivia Pulci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum fluctuation-induced first-order breaking of time-reversal symmetry in unconventional superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09234</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09234v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spontaneous time-reversal symmetry breaking in superconductors with competing non-degenerate pairing channels is an exotic quantum phase transition that could give rise to robust topological superconductivity and unusual magnetism. It is proposed mostly in two-dimensional systems and is signaled by a nonzero relative phase between the two superconducting order parameters, hence it should particularly be prone to order-parameter phase fluctuations. Nevertheless, the existing understanding of it is still at the mean-field level. Here, we illustrate the non-negligible effects of the phase fluctuations on such quantum phase transitions using the hole-doped square-lattice $t$-$J$ model as an example. We derive the phase fluctuation-corrected free energy and show that under the quantum phase fluctuations, the time-reversal asymmetric $s+id$ phase region splits off a dome featuring a first-order border with the $d$ phase, indicating the possibility of a phase separation into the time-reversal symmetric and asymmetric phases. The phase fluctuations also narrow the range of the $s+id$ phase considerably. We further discuss the implications of our findings for recent experiments on disorder-induced first-order quantum breakdown of superconductivity and promising high-temperature topological superconductivity in twisted cuprate Josephson junctions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09234v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yin Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable Chern Insulator States with Coexisting Magnonic and Electronic Topology in 2D Honeycomb Kitaev Ferromagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09235</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09235v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The coexistence of topological magnons and electrons in magnetic materials presents a compelling route toward developing low-dissipation, multifunctional spintronic devices. However, material systems enabling their simultaneous realization and control remain largely unexplored. Here, we propose the coexistence and concurrent tunability of magnonic and electronic Chern insulator phases in Kitaev magnets and use MnBr$_{3}$ monolayer as a prototype. We find the significant Kitaev interaction in MnBr$_{3}$ induces the magnonic Chern insulator phase, manifesting as the magnon thermal Hall effect. Concurrently, MnBr$_{3}$ exhibits the quantum anomalous Hall effect driven by its electronic Chern insulator phase. Crucially, we demonstrate that these dual topological phases can be simultaneously controlled by reorienting the in-plane spins with an external magnetic field. Our findings not only deepen the fundamental understanding of spin excitations in Kitaev magnets but also provide a promising platform for exploring the interplay between electronic and magnonic topology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09235v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haozhou Cai, Zhiming Xu, Jian Wu, Weiyi Pan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cubic magnetic anisotropy in $B$20 magnets: Interplay of anisotropy and magnetic order in Fe$_{1-x}$Co$_{x}$Si</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09268</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09268v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The metallic systems MnSi and Fe$_{1-x}$Co$_{x}$Si are known to feature a generic magnetic phase diagram primarily determined by the isotropic exchange and Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interactions. However, additional weaker anisotropies, lowest in the hierarchy of energy scales, play a crucial role: they determine the relative order of phases in the phase diagram and may even enable skyrmion stability far below the ordering temperature. Among cubic B20 helimagnets, the insulator Cu$_2$OSeO$_3$ is currently the only known example exhibiting a low-temperature, anisotropy-induced skyrmion pocket. In this manuscript, we present a systematic study of cubic magnetocrystalline anisotropy by means of angle-resolved SQUID magnetization measurements in MnSi and Fe$_{1-x}$Co$_{x}$Si ($0.08 \leq x \leq 0.70$) single crystals and provide quantitative values of the anisotropy constants. For Fe$_{1-x}$Co$_{x}$Si, the cubic anisotropy is found to be strongly dependent on the Co concentration $x$. In particular, for low Co concentrations ($x \sim 0.10$), the anisotropy is sufficiently strong to stabilize a low-temperature skyrmion lattice, in agreement with theoretical predictions. This finding suggests that Fe$_{1-x}$Co$_{x}$Si may represent the first chiral metallic system to exhibit a low-temperature skyrmion phase controllably stabilized by cubic anisotropy for specific directions of the magnetic field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09268v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. G\"odecke, A. O. Leonov, J. Grefe, S. S\"ullow, D. Menzel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Field-induced magnetic phases in the Kitaev candidate Na$_3$Co$_2$SbO$_6$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09282</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09282v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report a rich anisotropic magnetic phase diagram of Na$_3$Co$_2$SbO$_6$, a previously proposed cobaltate Kitaev candidate, based on field- and temperature-dependent magnetization, specific heat, and magnetocaloric effect studies. At low temperatures, our experiments uncover a low-lying $j_{\textrm{eff}} = \frac{1}{2}$ state with an antiferromagnetic ground state and pronounced in-plane versus out-of-plane anisotropy. The experimentally identified magnetic phases are theoretically characterized through classical Monte Carlo simulations within an extended Kitaev-Heisenberg model with additional ring exchange interactions. The resulting phase diagram reveals a variety of exotic field-induced magnetic phases, including double-$\textbf{q}$, $\frac{1}{3}$-AFM, zigzag, and vortex phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09282v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kranthi Kumar Bestha (Leibniz IFW Dresden, Institute of Solid State Research, Dresden, Germany, Institut f\"ur Festk\"orper- und Materialphysik and W\"urzburg-Dresden Cluster of Excellence ct.qmat, Technische Universit\"at Dresden, Dresden, Germany), Manaswini Sahoo (Leibniz IFW Dresden, Institute of Solid State Research, Dresden, Germany, Institut f\"ur Festk\"orper- und Materialphysik and W\"urzburg-Dresden Cluster of Excellence ct.qmat, Technische Universit\"at Dresden, Dresden, Germany), Niccol\`o Francini (Institut f\"ur Theoretische Physik and W\"urzburg-Dresden Cluster of Excellence ct.qmat, Technische Universit\"at Dresden, Dresden, Germany), Robert Kluge (Leibniz IFW Dresden, Institute of Solid State Research, Dresden, Germany), Ryan Morrow (Leibniz IFW Dresden, Institute of Solid State Research, Dresden, Germany), Andrey Maljuk (Leibniz IFW Dresden, Institute of Solid State Research, Dresden, Germany), Sabine Wurmehl (Leibniz IFW Dresden, Institute of Solid State Research, Dresden, Germany), Sven Luther (Hochfeld-Magnetlabor Dresden, Helmholtz-Zentrum Dresden-Rossendorf, Dresden, Germany), Yurii Skourski (Hochfeld-Magnetlabor Dresden, Helmholtz-Zentrum Dresden-Rossendorf, Dresden, Germany), Hannes K\"uhne (Hochfeld-Magnetlabor Dresden, Helmholtz-Zentrum Dresden-Rossendorf, Dresden, Germany), Swarnamayee Mishra (Institut f\"ur Festk\"orper- und Materialphysik and W\"urzburg-Dresden Cluster of Excellence ct.qmat, Technische Universit\"at Dresden, Dresden, Germany), Jochen Geck (Institut f\"ur Festk\"orper- und Materialphysik and W\"urzburg-Dresden Cluster of Excellence ct.qmat, Technische Universit\"at Dresden, Dresden, Germany), Manuel Brando (Max Planck Institute for Chemical Physics of Solids, Dresden, Germany), Bernd B\"uchner (Leibniz IFW Dresden, Institute of Solid State Research, Dresden, Germany, Institut f\"ur Festk\"orper- und Materialphysik and W\"urzburg-Dresden Cluster of Excellence ct.qmat, Technische Universit\"at Dresden, Dresden, Germany), Laura T. Corredor (Leibniz IFW Dresden, Institute of Solid State Research, Dresden, Germany), Lukas Janssen (Institut f\"ur Theoretische Physik and W\"urzburg-Dresden Cluster of Excellence ct.qmat, Technische Universit\"at Dresden, Dresden, Germany), Anja U. B. Wolter (Leibniz IFW Dresden, Institute of Solid State Research, Dresden, Germany)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconductivity in the repulsive Hubbard model on different geometries induced by density-assisted hopping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09363</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09363v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the effect of density-assisted hopping on different dimerized lattice geometries, such as bilayers and ladder structures. We show analytically that the density-assisted hopping induces an attractive interaction in the lower (bonding) band of the dimer structure and a repulsion in the upper (anti-bonding) band. Overcoming the onsite repulsion, this can lead to the appearance of superconductivity. The superconductivity depends strongly on the filling, and present a pairing structure more complex than s-wave pairing. Combining numerical and analytical methods such as the matrix product states ansatz, bosonization and perturbative calculations we map out the phase diagram of the two-leg ladder system and identify its superconducting phase. We characterize the transition from the non-density-assisted repulsive regime to the spin-gapped superconducting regime as a Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09363v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Franco T. Lisandrini, Edmond Orignac, Roberta Citro, Ameneh Sheikhan, Corinna Kollath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep prior-based denoising for state-of-the-art scientific imaging and metrology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09410v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Deep learning has revolutionized computer vision, yet a major gap persists between complex, data-hungry deep learning models and the practical demands of state-of-the-art scientific measurements. To fundamentally bridge this gap, we propose deep prior-based denoising, a robust deep learning model that requires no training data. We demonstrate its effectiveness by removing grid artifacts in angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES), a long-standing and critical data analysis challenge in materials science. Our results demonstrate that deep prior-based denoising yields clearer ARPES images in a fraction of the time required by conventional, experiment-based denoising methods. This ultra-efficient approach to ARPES will enable high-speed, high-resolution three-dimensional band structure mapping in momentum space, thereby dramatically accelerating our understanding of microscopic electronic structures of materials. Beyond ARPES, deep prior-based denoising represents a versatile tool that could become a new standard in any advanced scientific measurement fields where data acquisition is limited.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09410v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuichi Yokoyama, Kohei Yamagami, Yuta Sumiya, Hayaru Shouno, Masaichiro Mizumaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Room temperature optical control of spin states in organic diradicals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09440</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09440v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report a family of luminescent alternant diradicals which, at room temperature, support a ground-state spin-triplet, near-unity photoluminescence quantum yields, and optical spin addressability. These diradicals comprise trityl groups meta-linked via pyridyl or phenyl groups, enabling optically bright triplet-to-triplet and singlet-to-singlet transitions. At room temperature, we observe optically detected magnetic resonance in these systems at zero magnetic field and a strong magneto-photoluminescence (10% modulation at 2 mT applied magnetic field). Distinct photoluminescence bands (at 630 nm and 700 nm) show opposite-sign spin-optical responses, arising from spin-selective intersystem crossing between triplet and singlet manifolds. These bright, all-organic diradicals offer a new set of chemically tunable materials for room temperature spin-optical interfaces, paving the way for application as quantum sensors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09440v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rituparno Chowdhury, Alistair Inglis, Lucy E. Walker, Petri Murto, Chiara Delpiano-Cordeiro, Colin Morrison, Naitik A. Panjwani, Yao Fu, Yan Sun, Wei Zhou, Peter J. Skabara, Akshay Rao, Alexei Chepelianskii, Hugo Bronstein, Sam L. Bayliss, Richard H. Friend</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advances in momentum-resolved EELS of phonons, excitons and plasmons in 2D materials and their heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09444</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09444v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Functional nanomaterials, including 2D materials and their heterostructures are expected to impact fields ranging from catalysis, optoelectronics to nanophotonics. To realize their potential, novel experimental approaches need to be developed to characterize the combined materials and their components. Techniques using fast electrons, such as electron energy-loss spectroscopy (EELS), probe phenomena over an unrivaled energy range with high resolution. In addition, momentum-resolved EELS simultaneously records energy and momentum transfer to the sample and thus generates two-dimensional data sets for each beam position. This allows excitations that occur at large momentum transfer to be resolved, including those outside of the light cone and beyond the first Brillouin zone, all whilst retaining nanometer sized spatial selectivity. Such capabilities are particularly important when probing phonons, plasmons, excitons and their coupling in 2D materials and their heterostructures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09444v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cana Elgvin, Fredrik S. Hage, Khairi F. Elyas, Katja H\"oflich, {\O}ystein Prytz, Christoph T. Koch, Hannah C. Nerl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A microscopic approach to nonlinear theory of spin-charge separation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09515</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09515v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The fate of spin-charge separation beyond the low energy remains elusive up to now. Here we develop a microscopic theory of the correlation functions using the strong coupling expansion of the Hubbard model and demonstrate its validity down to the experimentally relevant $r_{\rm s}&gt;1$. Evaluating the spectral function, we show the general stability of the nonlinear spin-charge modes in whole energy band and investigate all the nonlinear features systematically. We confirm the general prediction experimentally in semiconductor quantum wires. Furthermore, we observe a signal consistent with a continuum of the nonlinear excitations and with a final spectral density around the $3 k_{\rm F}$ point, indicating the robustness of the Hubbard model predictions for a finite range interaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09515v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleksandr Tsyplyatyev, Yiqing Jin, Mar\'ia Moreno, Wooi Kiat Tan, Christopher J. B. Ford</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mapping the moir\'e potential in multi-layer rhombohedral graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09548</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09548v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rhombohedral graphene (rG) aligned with hexagonal boron nitride (hBN) has been shown to host flat bands that stabilize various strongly correlated quantum phases, including Mott insulators, integer, and fractional quantum anomalous Hall phases. In this work, we use scanning tunneling microscopy/spectroscopy (STM/STS) to visualize the dispersion of flat bands with doping and applied displacement fields in a hBN-aligned rhombohedral trilayer graphene (rtG)/hBN moir\'e superlattice. In addition to the intrinsic flat bands of rtG induced by the displacement field, we observe low-energy features originating from moir\'e potential-induced band folding. Real-space variations of the spectroscopic features allow us to quantify the spatial structure of the moir\'e potential at the rtG/hBN interface. Importantly, we find that accurately capturing the moir\'e site-dependent spectra requires incorporating a moir\'e potential acting on the top graphene layer with a sign opposite to that of the bottom layer into the continuum model. Our results thus provide key experimental and theoretical insights into understanding the role of the moire superlattice in rG/hBN heterostructures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09548v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric Seewald, Sanat Ghosh, Nishchhal Verma, John Cenker, Yinan Dong, Birui Yang, Amit Basu, Takashi Taniguchi, Kenji Watanabe, Mandar M. Deshmukh, Dmitri N. Basov, Raquel Queiroz, Cory Dean, Abhay N. Pasupathy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalised fractional Rabi problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08167</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.08167v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fractional quantum dynamics provides a natural framework to capture nonlocal temporal behavior and memory effects in quantum systems. In this work, we analyze the physical consequences of fractional-order quantum evolution using a Green's function formulation based on the Caputo fractional derivative. Explicit iterative expressions for the evolved state are derived and applied to an extended two-level Rabi model, a paradigmatic setting for coherent quantum control. We find that even in the absence of external driving, the static Hamiltonian term induces non-trivial spin dynamics with damping features directly linked to the fractional temporal nonlocality. When a periodically varying driving field is introduced, the competition between energy injection and memory effects gives rise to a richer dynamical behavior, manifest in the evolution of spin polarization, autocorrelation function, and fidelity. Unlike the standard Rabi oscillations characterized by a fixed frequency, the fractional regime introduces controllable damping and dephasing governed by the degree of fractionality. These distinctive signatures could be observable through the Loschmidt echo and autocorrelation function, and would offer potential routes to probe fractional quantum dynamics experimentally. Our findings open pathways toward exploring memory-induced dynamical phenomena in other systems effectively described by a two-level approximation, such as graphene-like materials and topological SSH chains, where non-integer order evolution may reveal novel topological or relaxation effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.08167v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Lopez, S\'ebastien Fumeron, Malte Henkel, Trifce Sandev, Esther D. Guti\'errez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hubbard-like Interactions and Emergent Dynamical Regimes Between Modulational Instability and Self-Trapping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.08781v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the modulational instability of uniform wave packets governed by a discrete third-order nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation in finite square lattices, modeling light propagation in two-dimensional nonlinear waveguide arrays. We analyze how initially stable uniform distributions evolve into self-trapped (localized) regimes and the influence of a refractive index detuning selectively applied along the diagonal waveguides on this transition. This detuning effectively emulates the effect of on-site Hubbard-like interactions $U$ in photonic analogs of interacting particles in a one-dimensional lattice. While for $U = 0$ the system exhibits the known direct transition from stable uniform states to asymptotically localized profiles, we show that $U &gt; 0$ induces an emergence of intermediate dynamical regimes. These regimes include coherent breathing modes that can be either confined along diagonal or off-diagonal waveguides, as well as chaotic-like propagation patterns. At higher nonlinearities, we identify distinct self-trapped regimes characterized by diagonal or off-diagonal localized modes, depending on the strength of $U$. The critical nonlinear strengths separating the existing regimes are shown in the phase diagram, underscoring the competing trends imposed by the Hubbard-like interaction on the optical field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.08781v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. J. R. Bezerra Jr., W. S. Dias</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiplexed back focal plane imaging with on-chip integrated microlens array</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09348v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: On-chip optical architectures that enable angle-resolved spectroscopy are essential for advancing photonic platforms towards low-volume, scalable, and cryo-compatible devices. Here, we introduce spatially resolved momentum-space imaging using arrays of 3D-printed microlenses directly integrated onto semiconductor optical microcavities. Each microlens functions as an independent optical element with a high numerical aperture (approx. 0.95), enabling parallel back focal plane imaging across, in our implementation, 64 distinct locations. This approach eliminates the need for bulky microscope objectives while maintaining broad wavevector access, even under cryogenic conditions. We demonstrate its versatility across various cavity systems, including dielectric planar resonators, GaAs-based polariton microcavities, and CdTe platforms supporting nonequilibrium Bose-Einstein condensation of exciton-polaritons. The microlenses not only enhance collection efficiency but also enable tightly focused excitation, yielding an order of magnitude reduction in condensation thresholds compared with conventional setups. Our results establish 3D-printed microlens arrays as a compact, versatile, integrated platform for next-generation angle-resolved spectroscopy in nanophotonics and quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09348v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Magdalena Furman, Marcin Muszy\'nski, Przemys{\l}aw Oliwa, {\L}ukasz Zinkiewicz, Aleksander Bogucki, Jacek Szczytko, Piotr Wasylczyk, Wojciech Pacuski, Mateusz Kr\'ol, Barbara Pi\k{e}tka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hallmarks of spin textures for high-harmonic generation in two-dimensional materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04545v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Spin-orbit coupling and quantum geometry are fundamental aspects in modern condensed matter physics, with their primary manifestations in momentum space being spin textures and Berry curvature. In this work, we investigate their interplay with high-harmonic generation (HHG) in two-dimensional non-centrosymmetric materials, with an emphasis on even-order harmonics. Our analysis reveals that the emergence of finite even-order harmonics necessarily requires a broken twofold rotational symmetry in the spin texture, as well as a non-trivial Berry curvature in systems with time-reversal invariance. This symmetry breaking can arise across various degrees of freedom and impact both spin textures and optical response via spin-orbit interactions. We also show that HHG is particularly sensitive to dynamical rotational-symmetry breaking, as even high-order components can be modulated by a time-dependent symmetry breaking. These findings underscore the potential of HHG as a tool for exploring electronic phases with broken rotational symmetry, as well as the associated phase transitions in two-dimensional materials, and provide novel perspectives for designing symmetry-dependent nonlinear optical phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04545v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Gabriele, Carmine Ortix, Mario Cuoco, Filomena Forte</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum geometric bounds in spinful systems with trivial band topology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16428v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We derive quantum geometric bounds in spinful systems with spin topology characterized by a single $\mathbb{Z}$ index protected by a spin gap. Our bounds provide geometric conditions on the spin topology, distinct from the known quantum geometric bounds associated with Wilson loops and nontrivial band topologies. As a result, we obtain broader bounds in time-reversal symmetric systems with a nontrivial $\mathbb{Z}_2$ index and also bounds in systems with a trivial $\mathbb{Z}_2$ index, where the quantum metric should be otherwise unbounded. We benchmark these findings with first-principles calculations in elemental bismuth realizing a nontrivial even spin-Chern number. Moreover, we connect these bounds to optical responses and show their robustness in the presence of disorder within a real space marker formulation, demonstrating that spin-resolved quantum geometry is observable in realistic experimental settings of impure materials. Finally, we connect spin bounds to quantum Cram\'er-Rao bounds that are central to quantum metrology, showing that elemental Bi and other spin-topological phases hold promises for topological free fermion quantum sensors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16428v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/zlxq-fxgc</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 7, L042011 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Wojciech J. Jankowski, Robert-Jan Slager, Gunnar F. Lange</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Domain Wall Sliding-induced Polarization Switching in Multilayer Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.06874</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.06874v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Electric polarization and metallicity are long believed not to coexist until the emergence of exceptionally rare material examples including the bulk polar metals and more recently two-dimensional (2D) van der Waals (vdW) materials such as 1T' WTe2. The electric polarization for the latter represents a new and distinguishable paradigm in materials science and physics because its electric polarization states embedded in the conduction electron sea are able to couple with (and controlled by) the external electric field. However, the microscopic polarization switching process and mechanism in these 2D vdW metallic materials have not been experimentally observed and remain elusive. Here, we report the first direct experimental imaging of the microscopic mechanism behind electric-field-coupled polarization switching in a metallic system. Our gate-tunable nanoscale optical imaging identifies the robust coexistence of electric polarization and appreciable carrier densities in adjacent polar domains hosting opposite electric polarizations in a 2D elemental metallic material, tetralayer graphene. We directly visualize and verify that the sliding domain wall (DW) solitons confined at the middlemost interface are responsible for the polarization switching in tetralayer graphene upon the application of electric fields and mechanical forces. Our work provides the first direct visualization of domain wall sliding-induced polarization switching in 2D elemental carbon at room temperature, significantly expanding and advancing the research of "ferroelectric metal" initially dubbed by P. W. Anderson and coauthors in 1965.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.06874v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhou Zhou, Xiyao Peng, Jianfeng Bi, Fei Xue, Jie Jiang, Huizhen Wu, Zhiwen Shi, Haoliang Qian, Toshikaze Kariyado, Sihan Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Modulated Symmetries in $\mathbb{Z}_2$ Topological Ordered Phases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.10819</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.10819v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study $\mathbb{Z}_2$ topological ordered phases in 2+1 dimensions characterized by generalized modulated symmetries. Such phases have explicit realizations in terms of fixed-point Hamiltonians involving commuting projectors with support $h=3,5,7,\ldots$ in the horizontal direction, which dictates the modulation of the generalized symmetries. These symmetries are sensitive to the lattice sizes. For certain sizes, they are spontaneously broken and the ground state is degenerated, while for the remaining ones, the symmetries are explicitly broken and the ground state is unique. The ground state dependence on the lattice sizes is a manifestation of the ultraviolet/infrared (UV/IR) mixing. The structure of the modulated symmetries implies that the anyons can move only in rigid steps of size $h$, leading to the notion of position-dependent anyons. The phases exhibit rich boundary physics with a variety of gapped phases, including trivial, partial and total symmetry-breaking, and SPT phases. Effective field theory descriptions are discussed, making transparent the relation between the generalized modulated symmetries and the restrictions on anyon mobility, incorporating the boundary physics in a natural way, and showing how the short-distance details can be incorporated into the continuum by means of twisted boundary conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.10819v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/mj42-xf2b</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, (2025) 115139</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Gustavo M. Yoshitome, Heitor Casasola, Rodrigo Corso, Pedro R. S. Gomes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hydrogen modes in KH$_2$PO$_4$ under pressure from ab initio calculation and inelastic neutron scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17536v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The nature of the phonon triplet in the region of OH-stretching modes in hydrogen-bonded materials is often explained by the interplay of OH-stretching modes and combinations and overtones of OH-bending modes. In order to elucidate the both contributions in KH$_2$PO$_4$ (KDP), we compare the pressure dependence of the OH-bending and stretching modes from ab initio calculation and inelastic neutron scattering (INS) measurements. The ab initio calculation predicts a hardening of OH-bending modes and a softening of OH-stretching modes with pressure. At the same time, INS measurements in the region of OH-stretching modes indicate a hardening of the phonon triplet together with the bending modes. This means that this triplet in INS measurements is mainly due to combinations and overtones of OH-bending modes, while the intensity of OH-stretching modes appears to be relatively low. This conclusion may also apply to other hydrogen-bonded materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17536v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. A. Abalmasov, A. S. Ivanov, R. A. Sadykov, A. V. Belushkin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Memristor-Driven Spike Encoding for Fully Implantable Cochlear Implants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26582</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26582v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Objective: This work aims to demonstrate a low-power, biomimetic auditory sensing concept for fully implantable cochlear implants. The approach draws inspiration from the frequency selectivity and temporal encoding of the cochlea, and uses neuromorphic spike generation to replace conventional signal processing blocks. The goal is to establish a compact, energy-efficient front-end architecture suitable for future implantable systems. Methods: An auditory sensing unit was implemented, consisting of a piezoelectric MEMS cantilever mechanically coupled to a single VO$_2$ nanogap Mott memristor-based oscillator. This configuration enables FFT-free, frequency-selective sensing and direct spike generation, forming a biomimetic auditory front end. The concept was experimentally examined using controlled mechanical excitation. Results: The sensing unit exhibited frequency-selective detection of mechanical vibrations in the nanometer to tens-of-nanometers displacement range and generated biomimetic spiking waveforms. Spike rate-encoding of the input amplitude was demonstrated, with output spiking frequencies tunable between approximately 100 Hz and 1 kHz depending on the excitation level. The waveform was finally converted to a biphasic shape suitable for cochlear implant stimulation. Significance: Temporal encoding is fundamental to natural auditory signal processing in the nervous system. By implementing this principle through neuromorphic spike encoding, the proposed approach can provide significant benefits for cochlear implants. In addition, the circuit has the potential to reduce footprint, energy consumption, and latencies compared with current commercial solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26582v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T\'imea N\'ora T\"or\"ok, Roland K\"ovecs, Ferenc Braun, Zsigmond Pollner, Tam\'as Zeffer, Nguyen Quoc Kh\'anh, L\'aszl\'o P\'osa, P\'eter R\'ev\'esz, Heungsoo Kim, Alberto Piqu\'e, Andr\'as Halbritter, J\'anos Volk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coherent oscillations in weakly anharmonic NbSe2 qubit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17160</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.17160v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The functionalization of quantum devices to increase their performance and extend their fields of application is an extremely active research area. One of the most promising approaches is to replace aluminum with more performant materials. Within this context, van der Waals (vdW) materials are ideal candidates since they would allow to embed their unique properties into qubits. However, the realization of qubits based on vdW materials other than graphene is yet to be achieved. In this work we present a weakly anharmonic NbSe2 qubit. Our device exhibits a relaxation time T1 = 6.5 +\- 0.4 us which is roughly 2 orders of magnitude larger of other vdW qubits in addition to robustness to photon noise up to 5-10 thermal photons. Our work serves as a demonstrator of the advantage of integration of vdW materials into quantum technologies as well as serving as the first step toward the application of quantum non demolition photon detection protocols in the challenging field of dark matter search.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.17160v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. DElia, F. Chiarello, D. Di Gioacchino, A. S. Piedjou Komnang, A. Giachero, C. Ligi, G. Maccarrone, F. Mattioli, C. Pira, A. Rettaroli, J. Rezvani, S. Tocci, C. Gatti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
