<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 04:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Switchable Exchange Bias Resulting from Correlated Domain Structures in Orthogonally Coupled Antiferromagnet/Ferromagnet van der Waals Heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00082v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Van der Waals (vdW) magnetic heterostructures offer a versatile platform for engineering interfacial spin interactions with atomic precision, enabling nontrivial spin textures and dynamic behaviors. In this work, we report robust asymmetric magnetization reversal and exchange bias in Fe3GeTe2 (FGT), driven by interlayer exchange coupling with the A-type antiferromagnet CrSBr. Despite the orthogonal magnetic anisotropies out-of-plane easy axis in FGT and in-plane in CrSBr, we observe a strong interfacial exchange interaction that gives rise to pronounced and switchable exchange bias and asymmetric switching in FGT, persisting up to the N\'eel temperature of CrSBr (132 K) as revealed by anomalous Hall effect measurements.
  We uncover the microscopic origin of this behavior through cross-sectional magnetic imaging of the domain structure using off-axis electron holography. The results reveal that the asymmetric switching and exchange bias arise from the influence of CrSBr on the domain configuration of FGT, where the in-plane antiferromagnetic state of CrSBr promotes the formation of stripe-like domain structures in FGT with circular rotation of magnetization in the cross-sectional bc plane defined by the easy axes of both FGT and CrSBr. These findings elucidate the mechanism of exchange bias in orthogonally coupled van der Waals systems and demonstrate a pathway for stabilizing three-dimensional domain structures in ferromagnets through interfacial exchange interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00082v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aditya Kumar, Sadeed Hameed, Thibaud Denneulin, Aravind Puthirath Balan, Joseph Vas, Kilian Leutner, Lei Gao, Olena Gomonay, Jairo Sinova, Rafal E. Dunin-Borkowski, Mathias Kl\"aui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical mean field theory with quantum computing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00118</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00118v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Near-term quantum processors are limited in terms of the number of qubits and gates they can afford. They nevertheless give unprecedented access to programmable quantum systems that can efficiently, although imperfectly, simulate quantum time evolutions. Dynamical mean field theory, on the other hand, maps strongly-correlated lattice models like the Hubbard model onto simpler, yet still many-body models called impurity models. Its computational bottleneck boils down to investigating the dynamics of the impurity upon addition or removal of one particle. This task is notoriously difficult for classical algorithms, which has warranted the development of specific classical algorithms called "impurity solvers" that work well in some regimes, but still struggle to reach some parameter regimes. In these lecture notes, we introduce the tools and methods of quantum computing that could be used to overcome the limitations of these classical impurity solvers, either in the long term -- with fully quantum algorithms, or in the short term -- with hybrid quantum-classical algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00118v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Autumn School on Correlated Electrons: Understanding Correlated Materials with DMFT, Vol. 15, edited by E. Pavarini and E. Koch (Forschungszentrum Juelich, 2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Ayral</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of Metal Cation on Chiral Properties of 2D Halide Perovskites</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00158v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Chiral two-dimensional (2D) halide perovskites are formed by embedding chiral organic cations in a perovskite crystal structure. The chirality arises from distortions of the 2D metal halide layers induced by the packing of these organic cations. Sn-based octahedra spontaneously distort, but it remains unclear whether this intrinsic structural instability enhances the chirality. We investigate the effect of the metal cation on structural and phonon chirality in MBA$_{2}$Sn$_{\mathrm{x}}$Pb$_{1-\mathrm{x}}$I$_{4}$ (x = 0, 1/2, and 1). Incorporating Sn does distort the metal halide octehedra, yet it only has a minor impact on the structural chirality. In contrast, the phonons in MBA$_{2}$SnI$_{4}$ are substantially more chiral than in MBA$_{2}$PbI$_{4}$, especially the in-plane acoustic modes. However, this enhanced phonon chirality does not lead to a generation of a larger angular momentum under a temperature gradient, because the contributions of different chiral phonons tend to compensate one another.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00158v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mike Pols, Helena Boom, Geert Brocks, Sof\'ia Calero, Shuxia Tao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-fidelity electronic structure and properties of InSb: $G_0W_0$ and Bayesian-optimized hybrid functionals and DFT+$U$ approaches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00290v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study presents a refined approach to computing the electronic structure of indium antimonide (InSb) using advanced \textit{ab initio} techniques with the In and Sb $4d^{10}$ semicore electrons included in the valence states. These states are modeled using fully relativistic projector augmented waves (PAW) and optimized norm-conserving Vanderbilt (ONCV) pseudopotentials. However, standard Kohn-Sham density-functional theory (DFT) calculations with these pseudopotentials often produce non-physical band inversions and incorrect band gaps at the $\Gamma$-point due to $5p$-$4d$ repulsion and self-interaction errors (SIE). To resolve these issues, we apply a combination of hybrid Heyd-Scuseria-Ernzerhof (HSE) exchange-correlation (XC) functionals, many-body perturbation theory (MBPT) via quasiparticle $G_0W_0$, and DFT+$U$, significantly improving the accuracy of the band structure over previous studies. A Bayesian optimization framework is used to refine key parameters, including the inverse screening length ($\mu$) and Hartree-Fock (HF) exchange fraction ($\alpha$) in HSE-based XC functionals, as well as the Hubbard $U$ parameters in DFT+$U$, leading to significantly improved band structure predictions. This approach yields highly precise band gaps, bulk moduli, effective masses, Luttinger parameters, valence bandwidth, and $4d$ band positions, achieving unprecedented agreement with experimental data. The resulting model resolves the long-standing incomplete description of InSb's electronic band structure and provides a transferable computational framework for accurate electronic structure predictions across diverse material systems, offering valuable insights for future electronic, optoelectronic, energy, and quantum applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00290v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/8k47-hv4d</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Ritwik Das, Anne-Sophie Grimault-Jacquin, Fr\'ed\'eric Aniel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High harmonic generation reflecting the sub-cycle evolution of the Mott transition under a mid-infrared electric field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00296</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00296v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Solids in an intense laser field show high-harmonic generation (HHG), which can provide information on carrier dynamics and band structures in weakly correlated systems. In strongly correlated systems, a laser field can induce a transition between the various electronic phases formed by the entanglement of charge, spin, and orbital degrees of freedom via carrier generation. The HHG accompanying this process should contain information on the nonequilibrium electronic-state dynamics along the oscillating field - an aspect that remains unresolved to date. Here, we show that an intense mid-infrared (MIR) pulse induces a Mott insulator-metal transition in a one-dimensional cuprate, Sr2CuO3, the evolution of which is reflected by the spectral features of HHs. When the electric-field amplitude exceeds 6 MV/cm, carriers are efficiently generated and each harmonic frequency decreases from odd multiples of the MIR frequency. Dynamical mean-field theory indicates that these redshifts originate from a series of electronic-structure reconstructions in each electric-field cycle during the melting of the Mott-insulator state, which modifies the radiation phase from carrier recombination cycle-by-cycle. This phenomenon is negligible in rigid-band systems. This experimental-theoretical study confirms that HH spectroscopy research can potentially unravel the sub-cycle dynamics of nonequilibrium phase transitions in correlated materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00296v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryohei Ikeda, Yuta Murakami, Daiki Sakai, Tatsuya Miyamoto, Toshimitsu Ito, Hiroshi Okamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large phonon-drag thermopower polarity reversal in Ba-doped KTaO3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00313v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study reports the observation of phonon-drag thermopower polarity reversal in Ba-doped KTaO3 thin films, mediated by electron-phonon Umklapp scattering. Epitaxial films with distinct carrier concentrations (3.7 x 10^20 cm^-3 and 4.9 x 10^19 cm^-3) were grown via molecular-beam epitaxy. In heavily doped samples, where the Fermi surface spans 80% of the Brillouin zone, the Umklapp condition is satisfied, reversing electron momentum. This manifests as a sign-reversal in the thermopower around 80 K upon cooling despite the sample having only n-type carriers. On the other hand, the lightly doped sample (4.9 x 10^19 cm^-3) exhibits only a negative thermopower down to 2 K. These results advance the understanding of Umklapp electron-phonon drag in oxides and highlight KTaO3's potential for engineering unconventional thermoelectric materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00313v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed Nawwar, Samuel Poage, Tobias Schwaigert, Maria N. Gastiasoro, Salva Salmani-Rezaie, Darrell G. Schlom, Kaveh Ahadi, Brandi L. Wooten, Joseph P. Heremans</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniform electronic states and $s$-wave superconductivity in a strongly disordered high-entropy compound (RuRhPdIr)$_{0.6}$Pt$_{0.4}$Sb</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00342v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High-entropy compounds, where multiple elements occupy a single crystallographic site in a highly disordered manner, challenge conventional understandings of electronic structure based on periodicity and well-defined band dispersion. Here, we report a detailed nuclear magnetic resonance study of the high-entropy superconductor (RuRhPdIr)$_{0.6}$Pt$_{0.4}$Sb, revealing a spatially homogeneous electronic environment in the normal state, in stark contrast to its crystallographically disordered lattice. The superconducting state exhibits a small but solid Hebel-Slichter coherence peak followed by a significant decrease in the nuclear spin-lattice relaxation rate, providing compelling evidence for fully gapped $s$-wave pairing. Our findings not only deepen the understanding of superconductivity in highly disordered quantum materials but also open a new pathway for exploring novel superconducting states in entropy-stabilized systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00342v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/b4nw-c4zy</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, L020508 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yufu Yamada, Shunsaku Kitagawa, Taishi Ihara, Kenji Ishida, Naoto Uematsu, Daigorou Hirai, Koshi Takenaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extrinsic nature of the polarization in hafnia ferroelectrics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00372</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00372v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hafnia and related fluorites defy our understanding of ferroelectricity, even if we restrict ourselves to the intrinsic properties of ideal crystals. Here we focus on a critical puzzle, namely, the sign of the electric polarization. Using first-principles simulations, we show that a polar hafnia layer with a fixed atomic configuration can give rise to depolarizing fields of either positive or negative sign, depending on the environment. This implies that (the sign of) the polarization in hafnia is extrinsic in nature. We explain this result and discuss its relevance to other ferroelectric families.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00372v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Binayak Mukherjee (Luxembourg Institute of Science and Technology), Natalya S. Fedorova (Luxembourg Institute of Science and Technology), Jorge \'I\~niguez-Gonz\'alez (Luxembourg Institute of Science and Technology, University of Luxembourg)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gapless superconductivity from extremely dilute magnetic disorder in 2H-NbSe2-xSx</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00435</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00435v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Most superconducting materials exhibit a vanishing density of states at the Fermi level and Anderson's theorem posits that the superconducting gap is robust against nonmagnetic disorder. Although dilute magnetic impurities lead to localized in-gap states, these states typically have no bearing on the material's bulk superconducting properties. However, numerous experiments reveal a finite density of states at the Fermi level in systems with an apparently negligible number of magnetic impurities. Here, using scanning tunneling microscopy and self-consistent Bogoliubov-de Gennes calculations, we find that gapless superconductivity emerges in 2H-NbSe2-xSx at remarkably low magnetic impurity concentrations. Furthermore, our density functional theory calculations and in-gap quasiparticle interference measurements demonstrate that the Se-S substitution significantly modifies the band structure. This modification favours nesting and dictates the in-gap scattering for x&gt;0, in stark contrast to the dominant charge density wave interactions in pure 2H-NbSe2. Our findings reveal an unusual superconducting response to disorder and highlight the importance of incorporating material-specific band structures in the understanding of a superconductor's response to even very low concentrations of magnetic impurities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00435v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jose Antonio Moreno, Merc\`e Roig, V\'ictor Barrena, Edwin Herrera, Alberto M. Ruiz, Samuel Ma\~nas-Valero, Ant\'on Fente, Anita Smeets, Jazm\'in Arag\'on, Yanina Fasano, Beilun Wu, Maria N. Gastiasoro, Eugenio Coronado, Jos\'e J. Baldov\'i, Brian M. Andersen, Isabel Guillam\'on, Hermann Suderow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid magnon -- Nambu-Goldstone excitations in topological superconductor/ferromagnetic insulator thin-film heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00460</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00460v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We address a previously unexplored type of dynamical proximity effect that occurs in s-wave topological superconductor/ferromagnetic insulator (TS/FI) heterostructures. It is predicted that magnons in the FI and the Nambu-Goldstone (NG) collective superconducting phase mode in the TS are coupled, forming composite magnon-NG excitations. The mechanism of this coupling is associated with the complete spin-momentum locking of electrons in the helical surface state of the TS. The strength of the magnon-NG coupling is strongly anisotropic with respect to the mutual orientation of the magnon wave vector and the equilibrium magnetization of the FI. This effect provides a mechanism for the interconversion of spin signals and the spinless signals carried by collective superconducting excitations, thereby giving new impetus to the development of superconducting spintronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00460v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Karabassov, I. V. Bobkova, A. M. Bobkov, A. S. Vasenko, A. A. Golubov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Bose-Hubbard polaron from weak to strong coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00486</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00486v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the zero-temperature properties of a mobile impurity immersed in a bath of bosonic particles confined to a square lattice. We analyze the regimes of attractive and repulsive coupling between the impurity and the bath particles for different strengths of boson-boson interactions in the bath, using exact large-scale quantum Monte-Carlo simulations in the grand canonical ensemble. For weak coupling, the polaron mass ratio is found to decrease around the Mott insulator (MI) to superfluid (SF) transition of the bath, as predicted by recent theory, confirming the possible use of the impurity as a probe for the transition. For strong coupling in the MI regime, instead, the impurity is found to modify the bath density by binding to an extra bath particle or a hole, depending on the sign of the polaron-bath interactions. While the binding prevent the aforementioned use of the polaron mass ratio as an MI-SF transition probe, we show that it can be used instead as a probe of the binding itself. Our exact numerical results provide a benchmark for comparing lattice Bose polaron theories and are relevant for experiments with cold atoms trapped in optical lattices, where the presence of a confining harmonic potential can be modeled by a slowly varying local chemical potential.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00486v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tom Hartweg, Tanul Gupta, Guido Pupillo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theory of hybrid collective excitations in topological superconductor/ferromagnetic insulator heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00499</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00499v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a linear response theory for the dynamical proximity effect in topological superconductor/ferromagnetic insulator (TS/FI) hybrid structures. Our approach combines the nonequilibrium quasiclassical Keldysh-Usadel equations for the electronic Green's functions in the TS with the Landau-Lifshitz-Gilbert equation governing the magnetization dynamics in the FI. Within this framework, we study the proximity-induced coupling between magnons and superconducting collective excitations. We find that the spin-momentum locking intrinsic to the surface state of the TS leads to a hybridization between the superconducting Nambu-Goldstone (phase) collective mode and magnons, resulting in the emergence of composite magnon-Nambu-Goldstone excitations. The dependence of the coupling strength on relevant physical parameters is analyzed both analytically and numerically. In contrast, we show that the Higgs (amplitude) mode does not couple to magnons at linear order and therefore does not participate in the formation of hybrid collective excitations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00499v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Karabassov, I. V. Bobkova, A. M. Bobkov, A. S. Vasenko, A. A. Golubov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Triplet correlations in superconductor/antiferromagnet heterostructures: dependence on type of antiferromagnetic ordering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00566v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In recent years, a number of studies have predicted the emergence of a nontrivial proximity effect in superconductor/antiferromagnet (S/AF) heterostructures. This effect is of considerable interest for the efficient integration of antiferromagnetic materials into the fields of superconducting spintronics and electronics. A key element of this proximity effect is the Neel triplet correlations, initially predicted for S/AF heterostructures with checkerboard G-type antiferromagnetic ordering. However, various forms of antiferromagnetic ordering exist, and an important open question concerns the generalization of these results to such cases. In this paper, we develop a theory of the proximity effect in S/AF heterostructures with arbitrary two-sublattice antiferromagnetic ordering, aiming to clarify which antiferromagnets are capable of inducing triplet correlations and what structure these correlations may exhibit. We show that, in S/AF heterostructures with collinear compensated antiferromagnets, the dominant superconducting triplet correlations are of the checkerboard Neel type, as originally predicted for G-type antiferromagnets. In contrast, layered Neel triplet correlations, although potentially generated by layered antiferromagnets, are significantly weaker. Consequently, in S/AF heterostructures with layered antiferromagnetic ordering, the proximity-induced triplet correlations may exhibit either a checkerboard Neel or a conventional ferromagnetic structure, depending on the specific antiferromagnet and its orientation relative to the S/AF interface.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00566v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. A. Bobkov, V. A. Bobkov, I. V. Bobkova, A. M. Bobkov, A. A. Golubov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic properties of Kagome metal YbV$_3$Sb$_4$: A First-Principles Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00655</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00655v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We have investigated the vanadium-based Kagome metal YbV$_3$Sb$_4$ using density functional theory (DFT) combined with the Wannier function analysis. We explore the electronic properties, de Haas-van Alphen (dHvA) effect and Fermi surface. The inclusion of spin-orbit coupling SOC induces the splitting of Yb-4f states, while its impact on the V-3d states is moderate. Furthermore, we have incorporated SOC+U, where U being the Hubbard parameter, which drastically changes the Yb-4f states creating additional splitting leading to three distinct peaks in the density of states (DOS). The V-3d atoms with the Kagome lattice contribute maximum to the transport properties, exhibits flat bands near the EF while being protected under SOC and U+SOC. Herein, we report the vulnerability of the Yb-4f states under SOC and U+SOC. Furthurmore, The Fermi surface is found to comprise of quasi-2D cylindrical sheets centered at the Gamma-point, along with smaller pockets near the Brillouin zone boundaries, which under combined U+SOC, a small spherical pocket emerges and the cylindrical sheet exhibits slight deformations. The dHvA frequencies reach as high as 70 kilotesla, which increase with tilt angle, exhibiting a nearly parabolic trend as expected for cylindrical orbits, while a low-frequency branch remains below 1 kT. Only the U+SOC case shows noticeable modification in both the Fermi surface and the dHvA oscillation. Crucially, the $Z_2$ invariant calculation identifies YbV$_3$Sb$_4$ as a strong topological metal ($r_0 = 1$). These findings not only advance our understanding of the underlying quantum phenomena in rare-earth Kagome systems, but also establish YbV$_3$Sb$_4$ as a compelling and promising platform for exploring intertwined topology and electron correlations in kagome lattices, thereby offering valuable insights for engineering quantum phases in layered materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00655v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Gurung, Keshav Shrestha, Shalika R. Bhandari, Samy Brahimi, Samir Lounis, D. P. Rai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lippmann-Schwinger Approach for Accurate Photoelectron Wavefunctions and Angle-Resolved Photoemission Spectra from First Principles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00683</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00683v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a conceptually simple and technically straightforward method for calculating photoelectron wavefunctions that is easily integrable with standard wavefunction-based density-functional-theory packages. Our method is based on the Lippmann-Schwinger equation, naturally incorporating the boundary condition that the final photoelectron state must satisfy. The calculated results are in good agreement with the measured photon-energy- and polarization-dependence of the angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) of graphene, the photon-energy-dependent evolution of the so-called dark corridor arising from the pseudospin, and WSe\textsubscript{2}, the circular dichroism reflecting the hidden orbital polarization. Our study opens doors to do-it-yourself simulations of ARPES with standard density-functional-theory packages, of crucial importance in the era of ``quantum materials,'' whose key experimental tool is ARPES.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00683v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/gwmm-6l57</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 056403 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ji Hoon Ryoo, Cheol-Hwan Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>XANES absorption spectra of penta-graphene and penta-SiC2 with different terminations: a computational study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00704</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00704v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In recent research, penta-graphene and penta-SiC2 have emerged as innovative 2D materials consisting exclusively of pentagons. However, there is still a significant gap in the theoretical characterization of these materials, which hinders progress in their synthesis and potential technological applications. This study aims to close this gap by investigating the X-ray absorption near-edge spectroscopy (XANES) of these materials through ab initio calculations. In particular, we analyze the XANES spectra of penta-graphene in its pristine, hydrogenated, and hydroxylated states, and we investigate the effects of substitution by a single silicon in both penta-graphene and pentagraphane. In addition, we calculate the XANES spectra for pristine and hydrogenated penta-SiC2. This work sets the stage for the possible identification of penta-graphene and penta-SiC2 phases by X-ray spectroscopy at the experimental level and lays the foundation for the future engineering of the absorption properties of these materials in optical devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00704v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Pedrielli, Tommaso Morresi, Simone Taioli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Persistent spin textures, altermagnetism and charge-to-spin conversion in metallic chiral crystals TM$_{3}$X$_{6}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00789</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00789v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Chiral crystals, due to the lack of inversion and mirror symmetries, exhibit unique spin responses to external fields, enabling physical effects rarely observed in high-symmetry systems. Here, we show that materials from the chiral dichalcogenide family TM$_3$X$_6$ (T = 3d, M = 4d/5d, X = S) exhibit persistent spin texture (PST) - unidirectional spin polarization of states across large regions of the reciprocal space - in their nonmagnetic metallic phase. Using the example of NiTa$_{3}$S$_{6}$ and NiNb$_{3}$S$_{6}$, we show that PSTs cover the full Fermi surface, a rare and desirable feature that enables efficient charge-to-spin conversion and suggests long spin lifetimes and coherent spin transport above magnetic ordering temperatures. At low temperatures, the materials that order antiferromagnetically become chiral altermagnets, where spin textures originating from spin-orbit coupling and altermagnetism combine in a way that sensitively depends on the orientation of the Neel vector. Using symmetry analysis and first-principles calculations, we classify magnetic ground states across the family, identify cases with weak ferromagnetism, and track the evolution of spin textures and charge-to-spin conversion across magnetic phases and different Neel vector orientations, revealing spin transport signatures that allow one to distinguish Neel vector directions. These findings establish TM$_3$X$_6$ as a tunable platform for efficient charge-to-spin conversion and spin transport, combining structural chirality, persistent spin textures, and altermagnetism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00789v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karma Tenzin, Berkay Kilic, Raghottam Sattigeri, Zhiren He, Chao Chen Ye, Marcio Costa, Marco Buongiorno Nardelli, Carmine Autieri, Jagoda Slawinska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Octupole Hall Effect in d-Wave Altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00794</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00794v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Order parameters not only characterize symmetry-broken equilibrium phases but also govern transport phenomena in the nonequilibrium regime. Altermagnets, a class of magnetic systems integrating ferromagnetic and antiferromagnetic features, host multipolar orders in addition to dipolar Neel order. In this work, we demonstrate the multipole Hall effect in d-wave altermagnets--a transverse flow of multipole moments induced by an electric field. Using symmetry analysis and linear response theory, we show that the magnetic octupole Hall effect persists even in symmetries where the spin-splitter effect is forbidden and thus provides a robust experimental signature. In addition, we identify a sizable electric quadrupole Hall effect, originating from quadrupole splittings in the band structure. Our results expand the family of Hall effects to include higher-order multipolar responses and establish altermagnets as a versatile platform for exploring multipole transport beyond spin and orbital degrees of freedom.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00794v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hye-Won Ko, Kyung-Jin Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral anomaly-induced nonlinear Hall effect in spin-orbit coupled noncentrosymmetric metals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00821</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00821v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent studies have shown that chiral anomaly is not limited to WSMs, but are also shown by a larger class of materials called spin orbit coupled noncentrosymmetric metals (SOC-NCMs),which has shed more insight into the origin of chiral anomaly as a Fermi surface property rather than a nodal property. In this study, we explore nonlinear transport responses in SOC-NCMswithin the framework of semiclassical dynamics, employing the Maxwell-Boltzmann transport theory augmented by charge conservation and momentum-dependent scattering processes. We take into account both non-magnetic and magnetic impurity scattering mechanisms. We demonstrate that the chiral-anomaly-induced nonlinear Hall (CNLH) response exhibits a characteristic quadratic dependence on the applied magnetic field and remains negative for both types of impurities. We find that magnetic scatterers leading to enhanced/suppressed interband scattering modifies the magnitude of the signal, but does not affect its qualitative behavior. In contrast, the presence of tilt in the band dispersion induces a pronounced anisotropic response, including a magnetic-field-direction dependent sign reversal that can be categorized into weak and strong regimes. Furthermore, the CNLH response shows substantial directional anisotropy governed by the relative orientation of the external magnetic field and the tilt vector. Our findings will be helpful in designing the experimental setup to get direction-dependent conductivity, which can be tuned externally with the help of magnetic impurity sites.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00821v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gautham Varma K, Mohd. Hashim Raza, Azaz Ahmad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vector spin Seebeck effect and spin swapping effect in antiferromagnetic insulators with non-collinear spin structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.03382</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.03382v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Antiferromagnets (AFs) are prospective for next-generation high-density and high-speed spintronic applications due to their negligible stray field and ultrafast spin dynamics, notwithstanding the challenges in detecting and manipulating AF order with no magnetization (M = 0). Among the AFs, non-collinear AFs are of particular interest because of their unique properties arising from the non-collinear spin structure and the small magnetization M. In this work, we describe the recently observed vector spin Seebeck effect in non-collinear LuFeO$_3$, where the magneto-thermovoltage under an in-plane temperature gradient, not previously observed, is consistent with the predicted spin swapping effect. Our results shed light on the importance of the non-collinear spin structure in the emerging spin phenomena in non-collinear AFs and offer a new class of materials for AF spintronics and spin caloritronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.03382v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0156379</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>APL Mater. 11, 091102 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jinsong Xu, Weiwei Lin, Jiaming He, J. -S. Zhou, Danru Qu, Ssu-Yen Huang, C. L. Chien</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of Doping on the phase stability and Superconductivity in LaH10</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.11354</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.11354v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a computational investigation into the effects of chemical doping with 15 different elements on phase stability and superconductivity in the LaH10 structure. Most doping elements were found to induce softening of phonon modes, enhancing electron-phonon coupling and improving critical superconducting temperature while weakening dynamical stability. Unlike these dopants, Ce was found to extend the range of dynamical stability for LaH10 by eliminating the van Hove singularity near the Fermi level. The doped compound, La0.75Ce0.25H10, maintains high-temperature superconductivity. We also demonstrate that different Ce doping configurations in the LaH10 structure have a minimal effect on energetic stability and electron-phonon coupling strength. Our findings suggest that Ce is a promising dopant to stabilize LaH10 at lower pressures while preserving its high-temperature superconductivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.11354v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevMaterials.7.L101801</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Zepeng Wu, Yang Sun, Artur P. Durajski, Feng Zheng, Vladimir Antropov, Kai-Ming Ho, Shunqing Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collapse of density wave and emergence of superconductivity in pressurized-La$_4$Ni$_3$O$_{10}$ evidenced by ultrafast spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05176</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05176v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent discoveries of superconductivity in Ruddlesden-Popper nickelates realize a rare category of superconductors. However, the use of high-pressure diamond anvil cells limits spectroscopic characterization of the density waves and superconducting gaps. Here, we systematically studied the pressure evolution of La$_{4}$Ni$_{3}$O$_{10}$ using ultrafast optical pump-probe spectroscopy. We found that the transition temperature and energy gap of density waves are suppressed with increasing pressure and disappear suddenly near 17 GPa where structural transition appears. In addition, the observation of a single density wave gap indicates that the spin density wave and charge density wave remain coupled as pressure increases, rather than decoupling. After the density wave collapse, a distinct low-temperature regime emerges, characterized by a small gap consistent with potential superconducting pairing. The separated phase region of superconductivity and density waves suggests that superconductivity in pressurized-La$_4$Ni$_3$O$_{10}$ competes strongly with density waves, offering new insights into the interplay between these two phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05176v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41467-025-62294-9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature Communications 16, 7039 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shuxiang Xu, Hao Wang, Mengwu Huo, Deyuan Hu, Qiong Wu, Li Yue, Dong Wu, Meng Wang, Tao Dong, Nanlin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Imaging Ultrafast Dynamical Diffraction wavefronts of femtosecond laser-induced lattice distortions inside crystalline semiconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10420v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Material processing with femtosecond lasers has attracted enormous attention because of its potential for technology and industrial applications. In parallel, time-resolved x-ray diffraction has been successfully used to study ultrafast structural distortion dynamics in semiconductor thin films or surface layers. However, real-world processing applications mostly are concerned with bulk materials, which prevents the use of x-ray surface based techniques. For processing applications, a fast and depth-sensitive probe is needed. To address this, we present a novel technique based on ultrafast x-ray dynamical diffraction (UDD) capable of imaging transient strain distributions inside bulk crystals upon laser excitation. This pump-probe technique provides a complete picture of thetemporal evolution of ultrafast distorted lattice depth profiles. We demonstrate the potential of UDD by studying a thin Si single crystal upon single pulse femtosecond optical excitation. Our study reveals that below the melting threshold strong lattice distortions not only longitudinal, but also transversal to the propagation of the strain wave appear on picosecond time scales along the single crystal. The observation of this transversal deformation after laser excitation contradicts previous work that were not able to observed it, what could be related to the high sensitivity of dynamical diffraction with respect to the lattice distortions. The speed of propagation of this ultrafast transversal strain deformation is observed to be slower to the longitudinal sound speed for Si as described in the bibliography.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10420v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Angel Rodr\'iguez-Fern\'andez, Jan-Etienne Pudell, Roman Shayduk, Wonhyuk Jo, James Wrigley, Johannes M\"oller, Peter Zalden, Alexey Zozulya, J\"org Hallmann, Anders Madsen, Pablo Villanueva-Perez, Zdenek Matej, Thies J. Albert, Dominik Kaczmarek, Klaus Sokolowski-Tinten, Antonowicz Jerzy, Ryszard Sobierajski, Rahimi Mosafer, Oleksii I. Liubchenko, Javier Solis, Jan Siegel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direction-dependent linear response for gapped nodal-line semimetals in planar-Hall configurations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10712v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We compute the magnetoelectric conductivity for ideal nodal-line semimetals (NLSMs), with a finite but tiny mass-gap, in distinct planar-Hall set-ups. Each differing configuration results from the relative orientation of the nodal-ring's plane with respect to the plane spanned by the electric ($\mathbf E $) and magnetic ($\mathbf B$) fields. The net conductivity tensor has components comprising the Drude, anomalous-Hall, in-plane (with $\mathbf E$ and $\mathbf B$) longitudinal and transverse, and Lorentz-force-operator-induced parts. Our results feature the signatures of the inherent topology of a gapped NLSM, revealed through nonzero values of the Berry curvature and the orbital magnetic moment. In particular, we show that both of these vector fields, arising in the momentum space, give rise to terms of comparable magnitudes in the resulting response. Our explicit theoretical expressions will help identify unique signatures of NLSMs in contemporary experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10712v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fasil Hussain Rather, Firdous Haidar, Muhammed Jaffar A., Ipsita Mandal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic structure and exchange interactions in altermagnetic MnGeP$_2$ in the quasiparticle-self-consistent $GW$ approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02934</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02934v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The QS$GW$ method is used to study the electronic band structure, optical dielectric function, and exchange interactions in chalcopyrite, $I\bar{4}2d$, structure MnGeP$_2$. The material is found to be an antiferromagnetic semiconductor with the lowest direct gap of 2.44 eV at the $\Gamma$ point and an indirect gap of 1.87 eV. The material is an altermagnet, with the two magnetic atoms of opposite spin related by a two-fold rotation operation perpendicular to the main 4-fold rotation inversion axis. The spin splittings along a low symmetry line like $PN$ are sizable, while at k-points on the diagonal mirror planes or on the twofold symmetry axes, the spin splitting is zero. The exchange interactions are calculated using a linear response approach. The antiferromagnetic exchange-interaction between nearest neighbors in the primitive unit cell is dominating and found to be slightly decreasing upon carrier doping. The transverse spin susceptibilities, which provide interatomic site exchange interactions after averaging over the muffin-tin spheres, are calculated from the $GW$ band structure and wave functions. From these exchange interactions, the spin wave spectra are obtained along the high symmetry lines and the N\'{e}el temperature is calculated using the mean-field and Tyablikov (RPA) estimations. The dielectric function and the optical absorption spectra are calculated, including excitonic effects, using the Bethe-Salpeter equation. The exchange interactions around Mn$_{\rm Ge}$ defect sites are also studied. While we find it can generate ferromagnetic interactions with neighboring spins, we did not find evidence of producing an overall ferromagnetic phase. If Mn antisites are introduced by exchanging Mn with a nearby Ge, the interactions stay largely antiferromagnetic. Adding Mn antisites leads to a metallic band structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02934v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ilteris K. Turan, Walter R L. Lambrecht, Jerome Jackson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strongly correlated altermagnet CaCrO$_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14081</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14081v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Altermagnetism, a newly discovered magnetic phase, has spurred growing research activity. Studies from a perspective of dynamical electronic correlation still remain scarce. Employing density functional theory plus dynamical mean-field theory (DFT+DMFT) that incorporates dynamical electronic correlation, we demonstrate that CaCrO$_3$ is a strongly correlated altermagnet. Our DFT+DMFT calculations successfully reproduce the correlated metallic behavior of CaCrO$_3$ and quantitatively capture the incoherent state observed experimentally. We also identify that the altermagnetic CaCrO$_3$ is a Hund's metal. The incoherent state is attributed to Hund's coupling, which gives rise to a non-Fermi liquid behavior. Moreover, we find that altermagnetism can induce flat bands, and these incipient flat bands are further promoted by the strong renormalization from Hundness, which further drives a heavy-fermion behavior. Hence, we establish CaCrO$_3$ as a strongly correlated altermagnet and propose that Hund's metals provide an ideal platform for investigating the interplay between electronic correlation and altermagnetism. Our work will promote the study of strongly correlated altermagnetism physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14081v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhenfeng Ouyang, Peng-Jie Guo, Rong-Qiang He, Zhong-Yi Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hamiltonian parameter inference from RIXS spectra with active learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16021</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.16021v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Identifying model Hamiltonians is a vital step toward creating predictive models of materials. Here, we combine Bayesian optimization with the EDRIXS numerical package to infer Hamiltonian parameters from resonant inelastic X-ray scattering (RIXS) spectra within the single atom approximation. To evaluate the efficacy of our method, we test it on experimental RIXS spectra of NiPS3, NiCl2, Ca3LiOsO6, and Fe2O3, and demonstrate that it can reproduce results obtained from hand-fitted parameters to a precision similar to expert human analysis while providing a more systematic mapping of parameter space. Our work provides a key first step toward solving the inverse scattering problem to extract effective multi-orbital models from information-dense RIXS measurements, which can be applied to a host of quantum materials. We also propose atomic model parameter sets for two materials, Ca3LiOsO6 and Fe2O3, that were previously missing from the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.16021v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marton K. Lajer, Xin Dai, Kipton Barros, Matthew R. Carbone, S. Johnston, M. P. M. Dean</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonequilibrium transport through an interacting monitored quantum dot</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.20779</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.20779v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the interplay between strong correlations and Markovian dephasing, resulting from monitoring the charge or spin degrees of freedom of a quantum dot described by a dissipative Anderson impurity model. Using the Auxiliary master equation approach we compute the steady-state spectral function and occupation of the dot and discuss the role of dephasing on Kondo physics. Furthermore, we consider a two-lead setup which allows to compute the steady-state current and conductance. We show that the Kondo steady-state is robust to moderate charge dephasing but not to spin dephasing, which we interpret in terms of dephasing-induced heating of low-energy excitations. Finally, we show universal scaling collapse of the non-linear conductance with a dephasing-dependent Kondo scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.20779v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Werner, Matthieu Vanhoecke, Marco Schir\`o, Enrico Arrigoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Broadband ferromagnetic resonance in Ni-Mn-Ga single crystal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22600</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.22600v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a broadband ferromagnetic resonance study in single crystalline Ni$_{50}$Mn$_{28.1}$Ga$_{21.9}$ in the temperature range from room temperature to 120 {\deg}C in which the transformation from martensite to austenite phase takes place. Our measurements demonstrate that a large change (an order of magnitude) in the magnetocrystalline anisotropy at the martensitic phase transformation results in a sharp change of the resonance magnetic field. In a single variant martensite phase, the resonance fields satisfy the Kittel's resonance condition for a thin film with the gyromagnetic factor g = 2.0. With the magnetic field parallel to the easy c-axis of the single variant martensite, the resonance is observed only for frequencies larger than 22 GHz. For the multivariant martensite case, the magnetic coupling between the twin variants can be taken into account for the satisfactory Kittel's fit. We observe a weak magnetocrystalline anisotropy in the austenite phase, just above the reverse martensite transformation, comparable to the previous reports based on different magnetic measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.22600v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jmmm.2025.173330</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Magnetism and Magnetic Materials 629 (2025) 173330</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lud\v{e}k Kraus, Denys Musiienko, Martin Kempa, Jaroslav \v{C}apek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
