<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 05:00:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>High-order coupling as a driver for Mott insulating behavior in Holography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11645</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11645v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct a simple holographic model incorporating higher-order coupling terms for electron self-interactions. It can exhibit typical behavior of a Mott insulator, including a metal-insulator transition and a decrease in DC conductivity with the increase of charge density. In the analysis of AC conductivity, a soft gap is generally observed. Notably, when the DC conductivity approaches zero, the AC conductivity reveals a multi-peak structure, which can be attributed to the Mott and charge-transfer gaps observed experimentally in transition metals. With the increase of DC conductivity, the multi-peak structure gradually reverts to soft-gap behavior or even metallic conductivity. The numerical reliability is confirmed by the agreement between zero-frequency AC and DC conductivities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11645v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lin-Yue Bai, Ren\'e Meyer, Zhen-Hua Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Floquet Engineering Magnetism and Superconductivity in the Square-Lattice Hubbard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11798v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the interplay of magnetic order and superconductivity in the square-lattice Hubbard model under periodic driving with circularly polarized light. Formulating diagrammatic techniques based on the random-phase approximation in terms of Floquet Green's functions, allows us to analyze fluctuation-driven unconventional pairing for weak-to-moderate interactions. The interplay of repulsive interactions and photo-assisted hopping of electrons gives rise to a rich magnetic phase diagram featuring an antiferromagnetic-to-ferromagnetic crossover prior to a Floquet Lifshitz transition. Close to the antiferromagnetic transition, topological $d+id$-wave superconductivity prevails in the phase diagram for a wide range of drive parameters. At intermediate-to-high frequency driving near the Floquet Lifshitz transition, superconducting orders are tuned from spin-singlet $d$-wave to spin-triplet $p$-wave character, providing an effective protocol for Floquet engineering topological superconductivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11798v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan-Niklas Herre, Takuya Okugawa, Ammon Fischer, Christoph Karrasch, Dante M. Kennes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for atomic-scale vibron-mediated electron bunching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11803v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Due to the Coulomb blockade effect, electrons rarely bunch during transport, a phenomenon observed only in a few specially engineered mesoscopic configurations. In this work, we introduce an atomically resolved shot-noise study to demonstrate the possibility of electron bunching through vibrational coupling which takes place in an atomically sized nano-electro-mechanical system. Using tunnelling spectroscopy, we observe signatures of vibron-assisted tunnelling on an Fe impurity in Bi$_2$Se$_3$. Notably, simultaneous shot-noise measurements at the centre of the vibrating impurity reveal super-Poissonian noise. In the absence of alternative sources of super-Poissonian noise, this implies vibronic-coupling-induced bunching of electrons during the tunnelling process through the impurity, as theoretically predicted decades ago. As a future outlook, if coherence between electrons can be implemented, vibron-mediated electron bunching at single atomic sites may be exploited as a local injection source of $N$-paired electrons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11803v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Maiti, M. Amato, V. S. Stolyarov, H. Aubin, J. Est\`eve, F. Pistolesi, M. Aprili, F. Massee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Layer breathing Raman mode in two-dimensional van der Waals material $\mathrm{Cr_2Ge_2Te_6}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11852v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2D) van der Waals (vdW) magnetic materials have emerged as key materials for next-generation magneto-electric and spintronic devices, where understanding the relationship between layer number, lattice dynamics, and magnetic interactions is very important. In this work, we report the observation of the layer breathing mode (LBM) in few-layer $\mathrm{Cr_2Ge_2Te_6}$, a ferromagnetic semiconductor with thickness dependent electronic, magnetic and optical properties, using Raman spectroscopy, which serves as a direct fingerprint of interlayer coupling and lattice symmetry. Group-theoretical symmetry analysis confirms that the CGT falls under the non-polar category of layered material. The evolution of the LBM-frequency with increasing layer number (N) reveals a distinct softening trend, characteristic of weakening restoring forces in thicker flakes. By fitting the experimental Raman data using the Linear Chain Model (LCM), we quantitatively extract the interlayer force constant ($\mathrm{K_c}$), providing a measure of the vdW coupling strength between layers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11852v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nilesh Choudhury,  Sandeep, Neesha Yadav, Mayank Shukla, Pintu Das</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Acoustic Metamaterials with Positive and Negative Couplings: Modular and One Piece Architectures for Topological Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11876v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We describe two 3D-printing approaches for realizing tight-binding models in acoustic metamaterials using H-shaped resonators: a modular system with tunable interconnections and an integrated one-piece design for reducing dissipation. The platform supports both positive and negative coupling through geometric control, enabling accurate acoustic analogs of topological models. By tuning the coupling length (CL), we eliminate detuning effects and preserve particle-hole symmetry. We further quantify the influence of the Total Coupling Area (TCA) on band topology and derive conditions for constant-area coupling. The system was tested on SSH and Kitaev chains, revealing midgap edge and interface states, confirming topological behavior in both configurations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11876v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jackson Saunders, Camelia Prodan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-orbit coupled periodic Anderson model: Kondo-Dirac semimetal and orbital-selective antiferromagnetic semimetal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.11972v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the periodic Anderson model composed of an itinerant $c$-band and a strongly localized $f$-band, featuring on-site electron-electron interactions in the $f$-orbitals. The two bands interact via a hybridization term with spin-orbit coupling, which enables spin-flip processes. In the non-interacting limit, these profoundly alter the electronic structure, leading to the emergence of flat bands, van Hove singularities, and, most notably, Dirac cones within a single Kondo-Dirac semimetal order. The strongly interacting regime is explored via the determinant quantum Monte Carlo method, in the absence of the sign problem, where we unveil a complete ground-state phase diagram revealing two distinct phases, the Kondo-Dirac semimetal phase and a novel antiferromagnetic semimetal phase. Their characterization by the spectral functions establishes an orbital-selective Mott transition in the antiferromagnetic semimetal phase, marked by the opening of a gap exclusively in the $f$-orbital while Dirac cones persist in the $c$-orbital. Conversely, in the Kondo-Dirac semimetal phase, both $c$- and $f$-orbitals sustain robust Dirac cones. We establish that spin-orbit coupling in the hybridization term gives rise to Dirac cones, which, combined with additional symmetry-breaking conditions, can generate novel topological states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.11972v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebasti\~ao dos Anjos Sousa-J\'unior, Juli\'an Fa\'undez, Rubem Mondaini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for quantum-tricritical-point in antiferromagnet CeRu$_2$(Si$_{1-x}$Ge$_x$)$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12078v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: CeRu$_2$Si$_2$ is a well-known heavy fermion paramagnet, and substituting Ge for Si induces antiferromagnetism. This antiferromagnetism is Ising-like and has a tricritical point in the magnetic field ($H$) -temperature ($T$) phase diagram. Since the temperature of the tricritical point is expected to decrease with increasing pressure ($P$), we investigated the pressure dependence of the magnetic phase transitions. We determined the $H$-$P$ phase diagram and revealed that a first-order phase-transition line changes to a quantum critical line, which implies the existence of the quantum tricritical point. A ferromagnetic quantum fluctuation arises in the vicinity of the possible quantum tricritical point.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12078v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. Shinya, F. Ito, N. Kabeya, Y. Mizukami, N. Kimura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ba-substitution induced evolution of structural and magnetic properties of La2-xBaxCoIrO6 double perovskites</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12128</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12128v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Iridium-based oxides are the subject of great recent interest due to the non-conventional physics that may emerge from the strong spin-orbit coupling present in 5d ions. Here, we explore the coupling between Ir and Co in the La2-xBaxCoIrO6 perovskites (x = 0, 0.5, 0.75 and 1.0), where the structural, electronic, and magnetic properties of the series are investigated by means of x-ray powder diffraction and magnetometry. The system's crystal structure evolves from the monoclinic P2_1/n to the triclinic I-1 space group as the Ba concentration increases. Measurements of magnetization revealed ferrimagnetic behavior in x = 0, 0.5 and 0.75 compounds, possibly resulting from antiferromagnetic coupling between Co2+/3+ and Ir4+. In contrast, for x = 1.0 a clear collinear antiferromagnetic character is observed for the Co2+ ions, resulting from the quenching of the Ir5+ magnetic moment. The evolution of the magnetic properties of the series is discussed in terms of the structural and electronic changes, as well as the spin-orbit coupling in Ir.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12128v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jmmm.2025.173678</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Magnetism and Magnetic Materials 636, 173678 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>C. A. S. Vieira, B. J. Santos, J. G. Duque, E. M. Bittar, L. Bufai\c{c}al</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractional Chern Insulators Transition in Non-ideal Flat Bands of Twisted Mono-bilayer Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12231</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12231v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fractional Chern insulators (FCIs) in ideal $|C|&gt;1$ flat bands can be viewed as color-entangled composites of $C$ lowest Landau levels, but in realistic moir\'e systems non-ideal quantum geometry complicates this picture, leaving their stabilization mechanism incompletely understood. Using twisted monolayer-bilayer graphene (tMBG) as a platform, we observe two FCIs joined by a continuous transition controlled by continuum model parameter $\kappa$, arising from a geometric instability of the Bloch wave functions. For $\kappa$ below the transition, the target $C=2$ conduction band is geometrically stable and effectively decomposes into two independent $C=1$ color sectors. Although the flat band is non-ideal, the resulting fractional phase is naturally accounted for by the non-chiral Halperin-(112) state with counterpropagating edge modes. Above the transition, the system enters a Laughlin-$1/3$ phase that persists despite further degradation of quantum-geometry indicators. To account for this robustness, we propose a color-separation mechanism beyond global geometric indicators: when the Bloch wave function is geometrically unstable, interactions dynamically split a non-ideal flat band into an ideal subcomponent that hosts the FCI and non-ideal remnants. We corroborate this picture by applying a weak perpendicular magnetic field that acts as a "color separator," explicitly visualizing the ideal subcomponent at the single-particle level. Together, these results establish two different routes by which non-ideal flat bands stabilize FCIs, expanding their viable parameter space and clarifying the interplay between geometry and topological order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12231v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Moru Song, Kai Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deterministic Switching of Perpendicular Ferromagnets by Higher-order Spin-orbit Torque in Noncentrosymmetric Weyl Semimetals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12324</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12324v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Field-free deterministic switching of perpendicular ferromagnets is a central challenge for spintronics applications, typically requiring explicit symmetry breaking. Here we show that deterministic switching can instead be achieved through higher-order (in magnetization angles) spin-orbit torques, even in systems that preserve in-plane mirror symmetry. Using a vector spherical harmonics expansion, we demonstrate that higher-order torque terms naturally give rise to additional out-of-equator fixed points, enabling reliable magnetization reversal when their magnitude is comparable to conventional lowest-order torques. We illustrate this mechanism with first-principles calculations on the noncentrosymmetric Weyl ferromagnet PrAlGe, where the combination of Weyl-node band topology and strong spin-orbit coupling produces sizable higher-order torque components. Because the Fermi surface is small, the conventional lowest-order torques are relatively weak, allowing the higher-order harmonics to compete on equal footing and strongly reshape the magnetization dynamics. The resulting spin dynamics confirm deterministic switching without additional symmetry breaking. Our results establish higher-order spin-orbit torque as a key ingredient for understanding and controlling magnetization dynamics in topological and spintronic materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12324v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naomi Fokkens, Fei Xue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stoichiometry and Phase Control in K$_{1-x}$CrSe$_2$ via Self-Flux Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12338v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Layered delafossite-type magnetic materials, such as KCrSe$_2$, are promising platforms for studying magnetic systems and potential frustration on triangular lattices. Synthesis, structure-type control, and off-stoichiometries remain major challenges in the investigation of these delafossite-type magnets. Starting from the same self-flux composition (K:Cr:Se = 8:1:8), we isolated three distinct K$_{1-x}$CrSe$_2$ phases with $x$ = 0, 0.13--0.17, and 0.32--0.35, each adopting a different structure type depending on the quenching temperature applied. The phase evolution indicates a sequence of transformations during synthesis between compounds with varying degrees of potassium deficiency. Building on these insights into phase stability and crystal growth, we successfully grew single crystals of full-stoichiometric KCrSe$_2$ -- enabling direction-dependent magnetization measurements. These measurements reveal a pronounced field dependence of the N\'{e}el temperature at low external fields, as well as a weak metamagnetic transition. Our findings demonstrate that even a simple parameter -- such as quenching temperature -- can be used to control stoichiometry, direct phase formation, and ultimately tune the magnetic properties of delafossite-type materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12338v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.chemmater.5c02075</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chemistry of Materials 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Felix Eder, Catherine Witteveen, Enrico Giannini, Fabian O. von Rohr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crystal-Field--Driven Magnetoelectric Coupling in the Non-Kramers Hexaaluminate PrMgAl11O19</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12355</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12355v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report broadband dielectric spectra of the non-Kramers hexaaluminate PrMgAl(*{11})O(*{19}), revealing a pronounced interplay between permittivity and magnetization at cryogenic temperatures. The zero-field dielectric response follows a Barrett-type quantum-paraelectric form, while a broad dielectric anomaly near 5 K shifts systematically to higher temperatures under applied magnetic fields, evidencing robust magnetoelectric coupling. The inverse permittivity (\varepsilon'^{-1}(T,H)) scales linearly with (M^{2}), consistent with a biquadratic (P^{2}M^{2}) term in a Landau framework. Fits yield temperature-dependent coupling constants (\lambda(T)) that decrease with heating, reflecting the thermal population of low-lying energy levels of Pr(^{3+}).
  These results identify PrMgAl(*{11})O(*{19}) as a paradigmatic non-Kramers hexaaluminate where quantum paraelectricity and magnetoelectric interactions are intrinsically entangled, establishing hexaaluminates as a tunable platform for magnetoelectric physics in frustrated quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12355v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sonu Kumar, Gael Bastien, Petr Proschek, Maxim Savinov, Malgorzata Sliwinska-Bartkowiak, Stanislav Kamba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Valley Transport in Bilayer Graphene Induced by Interlayer Sliding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12427</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12427v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Interlayer sliding, together with twist angle, is a crucial parameter that defines the atomic registry and thus determines the properties of two-dimensional (2D) material homobilayers. Here, we theoretically demonstrate that controlled interlayer sliding in bilayer graphene induces Berry curvature reversals, leading to topological states confined within a one-dimensional moir\'e channel. We experimentally realize interlayer sliding by bending the bilayer graphene geometry across a nanoridge. Systematic electronic transport measurements reveal topological valley transport when the Fermi energy resides within the band gap, consistent with theoretical predictions of eight topological channels. Our findings establish interlayer sliding as a powerful tool for tuning the electronic properties of bilayer graphene and underscore its potential for broad application across 2D material systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12427v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/26q7-dsm1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 126603(2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jie Pan, Huanhuan Wang, Lin Zou, Xiaoyu Wang, Lihao Zhang, Xueyan Dong, Haibo Xie, Yi Ding, Yuze Zhang, Takashi Taniguchi, Kenji Watanabe, Shuxi Wang, Zhe Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Principal Component Analysis of Competing Correlations in Quarter-Filled Hubbard Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12551v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a data-driven analysis of correlation hierarchies in the quarter-filled simple and extended Hubbard models by applying principal component analysis (PCA) to exact-diagonalization (ED) data on 3x4 and 4x4 cylindrical clusters. While the non-interacting limit (U=0) provides a finite-size reference, increasing on-site repulsion U induces localization and reorganizes the low-energy spectrum. For the extended model, we examine moderate (U=4) and strong (U=10) coupling regimes, where conventional structure factors reveal familiar crossovers among charge, spin and local-pairing correlations. PCA of the corresponding correlation matrices captures these crossovers directly from the data, without assuming predefined order parameters by identifying charge-dominated, spin-dominated and pairing-dominated regimes through variance condensation into leading components. This establishes PCA as a transparent, model-agnostic framework for uncovering the hierarchy and competition of correlation channels in finite Hubbard lattice clusters, providing a bridge between exact diagonalization and modern machine-learning diagnostics in strongly correlated systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12551v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Md Fahad Equbal, S R Hassan, M. A. H. Ahsan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse determination of light-matter coupling in disordered systems from transmittance spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12647</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12647v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate quantum inverse problems in one-dimensional (1D) electronic disordered systems strongly coupled to optical cavities. More specifically, we consider the Anderson and the Aubry-Andre-Harper models connected to electronic reservoirs and embedded in a single-mode optical cavity. The light-matter interaction enables photon-assisted hopping processes that significantly modify the transmittance spectrum. Within the nonequilibrium Green's function formalism, we implement an inversion-based approach capable of accurately extracting the electron-photon coupling strength directly from transmittance spectra. While cavity coupling acts as a minor perturbation within the Anderson model, yielding broad yet precise parameter estimates, its influence is markedly different in the Aubry-Andr\'e-Harper model. The latter exhibits a sharp metal-insulator transition in 1D, thus resulting in more pronounced cavity-induced spectral changes. This renders even more accurate inverse solutions, offering unparalleled precision in the characterization of low-dimensional disordered systems. Altogether, our results demonstrate that the quantum inverse problem provides a robust diagnostic tool for quantum materials, particularly effective for systems exhibiting metal-insulator transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12647v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thales F. Macedo, Juli\'an Fa\'undez, Ant\^onio S. Coelho, Caio Lewenkopf, Mauro S. Ferreira, Felipe A. Pinheiro, Natanael C. Costa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable Luttinger liquid and correlated insulating states in one-dimensional moir\'e superlattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12655</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12655v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two-dimensional moir\'e superlattices have been extensively studied, and a variety of correlated phenomena have been observed. However, their lower-dimensional counterpart, one-dimensional (1D) moir\'e superlattices, remain largely unexplored. Electrons in 1D are generally described by Luttinger liquid theory, with universal scaling relations depending only on the Luttinger parameter g. In particular, at half-filling, Umklapp scattering plays a crucial role, as it can significantly change the conductance-temperature scaling relation and lead to Mott insulators. However, this prediction has never been observed since doping an empty band to half-filling was extremely difficult. Here, we show that the marriage of moir\'e superlattices and 1D electrons makes it possible to study the Luttinger liquid in an exceptionally wide filling region simply by electrical gating. We perform transport measurements on 1D moir\'e superlattices of carbon nanotubes on hexagonal boron nitride (hBN) substrates, and observe correlated insulating states at 1/4 and 1/2 fillings of the superlattice mini-band, where Umklapp scattering becomes dominant. We also observe a T-linear conductance at these commensurate fillings over a range of temperatures. Strikingly, the T-linear conductance leads to a strongly suppressed Luttinger parameter, suggesting a state of extreme correlation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12655v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiajun Chen, Bosai Lyu, Liguo Wang, Shuo Lou, Xianliang Zhou, Tongyao Wu, Jingxu Xie, Yi Chen, Cheng Hu, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Guibai Xie, Mengzhou Liao, Wei Yang, Guangyu Zhang, Binbin Wei, Xiaoqun Wang, Qi Liang, Guohua Wang, Jie Ma, Dong Qian, Guorui Chen, Tingxin Li, Mingpu Qin, Xiao Yan Xu, Zhiwen Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bloch diode</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12719v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a SQUID tuned away from half-integer flux (in units of the superconducting flux quantum), the concurrence of multiple Josephson harmonics and an asymmetry between the junctions leads to the Josephson diode effect -- a nonreciprocal current-voltage characteristic manifested as an asymmetry of critical currents at opposite polarities. We predict a dual version of this effect in a gate-tunable Cooper pair transistor placed in series with a highly resistive environment. When tuned away from half-integer gate charge (in units of the Cooper pair charge) it shows an asymmetry of critical voltages at opposite polarities -- a dual diode effect we refer to as the Bloch diode effect. It arises from an asymmetry in the dispersion of the transistor's Bloch bands. A highly resistive environment can be realized with a Josephson junction array, suggesting that such a diode could be implemented using conventional superconducting quantum circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12719v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Houzet, T. Vakhtel, J. S. Meyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kagome metals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12731</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12731v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Three important driving forces for creating qualitatively new phases in quantum materials are the topology of the materials' electronic band structures, frustration in the electrons' motion or magnetic interactions, and strong correlations between their charge, spin, and orbital degrees of freedom. In very few material systems do all of these aspects come together to contribute on an equal footing to stabilize new electronic states with unprecedented properties; however the search for such systems can be guided by models of configurational motifs or key sublattices that can host such physics. One of the most fascinating structural motifs for realizing this rich interplay of frustration, electronic topology, and electron correlation effects is the kagome lattice. In this review, we provide an overview of the theoretical underpinnings driving the physics of kagome lattices, and we then discuss experimental progress in realizing novel states enabled by kagome networks in crystalline materials. Different material classes are discussed with an emphasis on the phenomenologies of their electronic states and how they map to interactions arising from their kagome lattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12731v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Domenico Di Sante, Titus Neupert, Giorgio Sangiovanni, Ronny Thomale, Riccardo Comin, Ilija Zeljkovic, Joseph G. Checkelsky, Stephen D. Wilson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Giant number-parity effect and scalable spin squeezing in Luttinger liquids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12746v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Finite-size quantum spin systems can be magnetized by the application of a symmetry-breaking field, but in general their symmetry is expected to be restored once the field is turned off adiabatically. Recently (F. Caleca et al., arXiv:2412.15493) we have shown that systems of half-integer spins with an odd number of sites and a parity-preserving Hamiltonian can retain a finite magnetization, hence exhibiting spontaneous symmetry breaking (SSB) at finite size. Here we generalize this phenomenon to spin chains whose low-energy physics (in zero field) realizes a Luttinger-liquid phase. We observe that odd-sized chains can exhibit a phenomenon of finite-size quasi-SSB, in which a net sub-extensive magnetization, $M \sim N^{1-1/(4K)}$ is retained, where $N$ is the number of sites and $K$ the Luttinger exponent. Interestingly, the states prepared by turning off the symmetry-breaking field quasi-adiabatically display scalable spin squeezing -- namely stronger the bigger the system -- regardless of the parity of $N$. The scaling of the squeezing parameter is dictated again by the Luttinger exponent, $\xi_R^2 \sim N^{-1+1/(2K)}$. This result shows that scalable quantum correlations with metrological significance, associated typically with high-dimensional systems, can be found as well in gapless one-dimensional ones; and they are a direct consequence of the critical nature of Luttinger liquids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12746v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Filippo Caleca, Saverio Bocini, Fabio Mezzacapo, Tommaso Roscilde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced Superconductivity at Quantum-Critical KTaO3 Interfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12904v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Superconductivity at oxide interfaces has intrigued researchers for decades, yet the underlying pairing mechanism remains elusive. Here we demonstrate that proximity to a ferroelectric quantum critical point dramatically enhances interfacial superconductivity in KTaO3. By precisely tuning KTaO3 to its quantum critical composition through 0.8% niobium doping, we achieve a near-doubling of the superconducting transition temperature, reaching 2.9 K. Remarkably, a dome-shaped carrier density dependence emerges exclusively at the quantum critical point, contrasting sharply with the linear scaling observed in undoped interfaces. Our findings establish ferroelectric quantum criticality as a powerful mechanism for enhancing superconductivity and provide compelling evidence for soft-phonon-mediated pairing in these systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12904v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jieun Kim, Muqing Yu, Ahmed Omran, Jiangfeng Yang, Ranjani Ramachandran, William O. Nachlas, Patrick Irvin, Jeremy Levy, Chang-Beom Eom</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunneling in multi-site mesoscopic quantum Hall circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12933</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12933v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Transport properties of the single- and two-site mesoscoipc quantum Hall (QH) circuits at high transparencies can be described in terms of the lowest-order backscattering perturbations, and mapping to the boundary sine-Gordon model can be exploited in full generality. While the higher-order backscattering processes are exactly marginal in the case of corresponding three-site circuits, they become crucial in a device with four or more sites. Here, we explore the transport properties of a multi-site QH circuit with special focus on that with four sites, and report their unique quantum critical behaviors that can be accessed via transport measurements. Tunneling phenomena in multichannel QH circuits based on multi-site geometry are also investigated, and a promising route to realizing different aspects of quantum critical phenomena is offered</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12933v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. B. Karki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signatures of magnetism in zigzag graphene nanoribbon embedded in h-BN lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13075</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13075v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Zigzag edges of graphene have long been predicted to exhibit magnetic electronic state near the Fermi level, which can cause spin-related phenomena and offer unique potentials for graphene-based spintronics. However, the magnetic conduction channels along these edges have yet been reported experimentally. Here, we report the observation on signatures of magnetism in zigzag graphene nanoribbons (zGNRs) embedded in hexagonal boron nitride (h-BN). The in-plane bonding with BN can stabilize the edges of zGNRs, and thus enable a direct probing of the intrinsic magnetism. Firstly, the presence of magnetism of a zGNR was confirmed by scanning NV center microscopy. And then, zGNR was fabricated into a transistor with a width of ~9 nm wide and a channel length of sub-50 nm. By performing magneto-transport measurements, Fabry-P\'erot interference patterns were observed in the transistor at 4 Kelvin, which indicates a coherent transport through the channel. A large magnetoresistance of ~175 {\Omega}, corresponding to a ratio of ~1.3 %, was observed at the same temperature. More importantly, such magneto-transport signal is highly anisotropic on the magnetic field direction, and its appearance extends well above room temperature. All these evidences corroborate the existence of robust magnetic ordering in the edge state of zGNR. The findings on zGNR embedded in h-BN provide an effective platform for the future exploration of graphene-based spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13075v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41563-025-02317-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature Materials 24,15921-599(2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Chengxin Jiang, Hui Shan Wang, Chen Chen, Lingxiu Chen, Xiujun Wang, Yibo Wang, Ziqiang Kong, Yuhan Feng, Yixin Liu, Yu Feng, Chenxi Liu, Yu Zhang, Zhipeng Wei, Maosen Guo, Aomei Tong, Gang Mu, Yumeng Yang, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Wangzhou Shi, Haomin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Phases in Non-Hermitian Nonlinear-Eigenvalue Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13076</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13076v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The discovery of topological phases has ushered in a new era of condensed matter physics and revealed a variety of natural and artificial materials. They obey the bulk-boundary correspondence (BBC), which guarantees the emergence of boundary states with non-zero topological invariants in the bulk. A wide attention has been paid to extending topological phases to nonlinear and non-Hermitian systems. However, the BBC and topological invariants of non-Hermitian nonlinear systems remain largely unexplored. Here, we establish a complete BBC and topological characterization of the topological phases in a class of non-Hermitian nonlinear-eigenvalue systems by introducing an auxiliary system. We restore the BBC broken by non-Hermiticity via employing the generalized Brillouin zone on the auxiliary system. Remarkably, we discover that the interplay between non-Hermiticity and nonlinearity creates an exotic complex-band topological phase that coexists with the real-band topological phase. Our results enrich the family of nonlinear topological phases and lay a foundation for exploring novel topological physics in metamaterial systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13076v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Peng Ma, Ming-Jian Gao, Jun-Hong An</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological phase transitions by time-dependent electromagnetic fields in frustrated magnets: Role of dynamical and static magnetic fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13136v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We theoretically investigate the effects of time-dependent electromagnetic fields on frustrated magnets with the spatial inversion symmetry. Two types of external-field setups are considered: One is a circularly polarized electromagnetic field and the other is a combination of a circularly polarized electric field and a static magnetic field. The system is modeled by a classical frustrated Heisenberg model on a triangular lattice, whose ground state is a single-$Q$ spiral spin configuration. The effects of irradiated electric and magnetic fields are taken into account by the inverse Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya (DM) interaction and the Zeeman coupling, respectively, without heating effects. By numerically solving the Landau-Lifshitz-Gilbert equation, we find that the two field configurations lead to distinct skyrmion crystal (SkX) phases and their associated topological phase transitions: in the former setup, SkXs composed of skyrmions with skyrmion numbers of one and two with opposite signs emerge, whereas in the latter setup, SkXs with the same sign appear. The stabilization mechanisms of these SkXs are accounted for by the competition among electromagnetic-field-induced chiral DM interactions, electric-field-induced three-spin interactions, and the Zeeman coupling based on the high-frequency expansion within the Floquet formalism. Furthermore, for the latter setup, we find that the stability region of the SkX phase varies significantly depending on the timing of the application of the circularly polarized electric field and the static magnetic field. Our findings would broaden the possible routes to generate and control SkXs by time-dependent electromagnetic fields, advancing both the theoretical comprehension and experimental control of topological spin crystals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13136v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tatsuya Shirato, Ryota Yambe, Satoru Hayami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A tractable framework for phase transitions in phase-fluctuating disordered 2D superconductors: applications to bilayer MoS$_2$ and disordered InO$_x$ thin films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13268</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13268v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Starting from the purely microscopic model, we go beyond conventional mean-field theory and develop a self-consistent microscopic thermodynamic framework for disordered 2D superconductors. It incorporates the fermionic Bogoliubov quasiparticles, bosonic Nambu-Goldstone (NG) quantum and thermal phase fluctuations in the presence of long-range Coulomb interactions, and topological Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless (BKT) vortex-antivortex fluctuations on an equal footing, to self-consistently treat the superconducting gap and superfluid density. This unified phase-fluctuating description naturally recovers the previously known limiting results: the superconducting gap in the 2D limit can remain robust against long-wavelength NG phase fluctuations at $T=0^+$ due to Coulomb-induced regularization, while the gradual proliferation of BKT fluctuations as the system approaches criticality drives a separation between the global superconducting transition temperature $T_c$ and the gap-closing temperature $T^*$. In contrast to mean-field theory, which predicts 2D superconductivity to be independent of carrier density and non-magnetic disorder (Anderson theorem), the incorporation of phase fluctuations generates a density- and disorder-dependent zero-point gap $\Delta(0)$ and consequently $T_c$ and $T^*$. Remarkably, applications to bilayer MoS$_2$ [Nat. Nanotechnol. 14, 1123 (2019)] and disordered InO$_x$ thin films [Nat. Phys. 21, 104 (2025)] quantitatively reproduce key experimental observations in excellent agreement. The framework offers a useful theoretical tool for understanding phase-fluctuation-dominated superconductivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13268v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Yang, L. Q. Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-orbit driven $J_{eff} = 1/2$ magnetism in a d$^7$ triangular-lattice monolayer cobaltate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13325</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13325v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent theoretical and experimental advances have identified cobaltates with a high-spin $d^7$ electronic configuration as promising hosts for spin-orbit entangled $J_{eff} = 1/2$ magnetism that can support bond-dependent exchange interactions. In two-dimensional triangular lattices, the coexistence of such exchange frustration along with geometric frustration gives rise to a rich landscape of competing magnetic phases, establishing monolayer triangular $d^7$ cobaltates as a compelling platform for frustrated magnetism. Here we investigate a representative triangular-lattice monolayer cobaltate CoBr$_2$, where first-principles density functional theory (DFT) calculations reveal a dominant nearest-neighbor $t_{2g}$-$e_g$ hopping channel that enhances the ferromagnetic Kitaev-type exchange interactions. In contrast, the nearest-neighbor Heisenberg term is highly sensitive to a direct $t_{2g}$-$t_{2g}$ hopping path and electronic correlations. The magnetic exchange parameters are evaluated using the hopping amplitudes obtained from DFT calculations within an exact diagonalization framework. We construct the first and third nearest neighbor Heisenberg exchange dependent $J_1$-$J_3$ magnetic phase diagram in the physically relevant regime and identify multiple competing ground states, including ferromagnetic, stripy, spiral, and $120^{\circ}$ antiferromagnetic orders. The Luttinger-Tisza analysis further predicts a Z$_2$ vortex crystal phase, while exact diagonalization reveals a bond-nematic phase stabilized by the longer-range couplings. Going beyond the conventional bond-independent XXZ picture typically applied to Co$^{2+}$ systems, our results on monolayer CoBr$_2$ establish d$^7$ cobalt dihalides as a promising platform to explore the interplay of long-range Heisenberg and bond-dependent exchange interactions that can stabilize diverse magnetic ground states on a triangular lattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13325v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ritwik Das, Soumen Basak, Mohammad Rezwan Habib, Indra Dasgupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nontrivial flat bands and quantum Hall crossovers in square-octagon lattice materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13349v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Coexistence of nontrivial topology and flat electronic bands in low-energy lattices provides a fertile platform for correlated quantum states. The square-octagon lattice hosts Dirac nodes and flat bands at half-filling, yet the influence of intrinsic spin-orbit coupling (SOC) and staggered magnetic flux on its topological and flat-band properties remains largely unexplored. Here, we examine this lattice using tight-binding models that include SOC and magnetic flux, uncovering a quantum spin Hall phase with spin Chern number $C_s=1$, crossovers to quantum anomalous Hall phases with $C=1$ and $C=2$, and higher-order topological insulator phases carrying quantized quadrupolar corner charges. The initially dispersionless flat bands evolve into quasi-flat, topologically nontrivial bands with uniform quantum geometry and large flatness ratios, conducive to fractional Chern insulator states. We further identify realistic material candidates, including octagraphene, transition-metal dichalcogenides, synthetic $\mathrm{MoSi_2N_4}$, and magnetic $\alpha$-MnO$_2$, as potential candidates for realizing tunable topological phases intertwined with flat-band physics, opening new opportunities for correlated topological matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13349v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amrita Mukherjee, Rahul Verma, Pritesh Srivastava, Bahadur Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pressure-induced superconductivity in LaP2 with graphenelike phosphorus layer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13405</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13405v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Materials with graphene-like layers attract tremendous attention due to their electronic structures and superconducting properties. In this study, we synthesized LaP2 polycrystalline and observed a superconducting transition around 30 GPa. The critical temperature Tc increases monotonically with pressure, which is nearing saturation and reaches 7.8 K at 78 GPa. The synchrotron X-ray diffraction experiments confirm the superconducting transition originates from a structure transition to the P6/mmm phase under high pressure, suggesting the observation of graphene-like phosphorus layers in transition metal phosphides. By first-principles calculations, we provide more evidence for the stability of the graphene-like phosphorus layers in LaP2. Our findings are helpful for the understanding of the LaP2 phase diagram under high pressure, and could shed light on the research of unique structures in transition metal phosphides under high pressure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13405v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/t445-8hck</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review B 112, 184108 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mingxin Zhang, Cuiying Pei, Bangshuai Zhu, Qi Wang, Juefei Wu, Yanpeng Qi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Aubry-Andr\'{e}-Harper model with power-law quasiperiodic potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13464v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate a generalized Aubry-Andr\'{e}-Harper (AAH) model with non-reciprocal hopping and power-law quasiperiodic potentials $V(i) = V\left[ \cos(2\pi \beta i) \right]^p$. Our study reveals that the interplay between nonreciprocity, quasiperiodicity, and the power-law exponent $p$ gives rise to a variety of phase transitions and localization phenomena. In the Hermitian case, the system undergoes a direct transition from extended to localized phases for $p=1, 2$, while for \(p \geq 3\), an intermediate mixed phase emerges, characterized by the coexistence of extended and localized states and the presence of mobility edges. Importantly, we find that high inverse participation ratio (IPR) states appear at specific energy levels, whose positions are accurately described by the universal relation \(x_n = n\beta - \lfloor n\beta \rfloor\), with a mirror-symmetric spatial distribution. In the non-Hermitian regime, the energy spectrum becomes complex and the \(\mathcal{PT}\) transition coincides with the extended-to-localized phase boundary for \(p = 1, 2\), whereas for \(p \geq 3\), \(\mathcal{PT}\)-symmetry breaking occurs at the mixed-to-localized phase transition. This work reveals how power-law quasiperiodic potentials and non-reciprocal hopping govern phase transitions, providing new insight into localization phenomena of quasiperiodic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13464v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ya-Nan Wang, Wen-Long You, Zhihao Xu, Gaoyong Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin Accumulation based deep MOKE Microscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13468v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic imaging techniques are widespread critical tools used in fields such as magnetism, spintronics or even superconductivity. Among them, one of the most versatile methods is the magneto-optical Kerr effect. However, as soon as light is blocked from interacting with the magnetic layer, such as in deeply buried layers, optical techniques become ineffective. In this work, we present a spin-accumulation based magneto-optical Kerr effect (SA-MOKE) microscopy technique that enables imaging of a magnetic thin-films covered by thick and opaque metallic layers. The technique is based on the generation and detection of transient spin-accumulations that propagate through the thick metallic layer. These spin-accumulation signals are directly triggered and detected optically on the same side, lifting any substrate transparency requirements. The spin-accumulation signals detected on a Cu layer decay with a characteristic length of 60 nm, much longer than the 12 nm optical penetration depth, allowing for detection of magnetic contrast with Cu capping layers up to hundreds of nm. This method should enable magnetic imaging in a wide-range of experiments where the surface of interest is covered by electrodes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13468v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean Rodriguez, Holger Grisk, Alberto Anad\'on, Harjinder Singh, Gregory Malinowski, Michel Hehn, Javier Curiale, Jon Gorchon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-Lattice Relaxation in Two-Dimensional Superconducting BKT Transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13486</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13486v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two-dimensional superconductors undergo a Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless transition driven by vortex-antivortex unbinding, yet experimental signatures beyond transport remain limited. Here, we show that the spin-lattice relaxation rate provides a direct probe of this transition. In a 2-dimensional $s$-wave superconductor, $1/T_1T$ develops a Hebel-Slichter-like peak around $T_{\rm{BKT}}$, originating from the emergence of coherence peaks in the density of states, while no peak appears at the pair formation scale $T_{\rm{BCS}}$. We further extend our analysis to the $d$-wave superconductor. Our results highlight spin-lattice relaxation rate as a sensitive tool to detect the superconducting BKT transition and open routes to exploring its manifestation in unconventional pairing states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13486v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Wei Yang, Shao-Hang Shi, Zongsheng Zhou, Zi-Xiang Li, Kun Jiang, Jiangping Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tuning of Weyl point emergence in multi-terminal Josephson junctions using quantum point contacts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13493</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13493v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multi-terminal Josephson junction with three or more superconductors is an attractive quantum system to emerge and tune exotic electronic states. In four terminal Josephson junctions, the Weyl physics, namely topologically protected zero energy state, emerges without assuming any exotic materials. In this study, we consider the four-terminal Josephson junction with the quantum point contact structures between the mesoscopic normal region and four superconducting terminals. The quantum point contacts can tune electrically the number of conduction channels. We theoretically investigate an effect of the increase of channels on the emergence of Weyl points. The increase of channels causes the increase of Andreev bound states in the system, which increase the emergence probability of Weyl points. When all terminals have two channels, the emergence probability is up to 17\%, which is about four times larger than that for all single channel junctions. We consider the balance of the number of conduction channels in the four terminals. When the number of channels is unbalanced, the increase of emergence probability is suppressed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13493v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kento Takemura, Mikio Eto, Tomohiro Yokoyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of the Next-Nearest-Neighbor Hopping on the Low-Dimensional Hubbard Model: Ferromagnetism, Antiferromagnetism, and Superconductivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13534</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13534v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Hubbard model has attracted considerable interest due to its prototypical role in describing strongly interacting electronic systems, such as high-critical-temperature superconductors as well as many novel quantum materials. By introducing next-nearest-neighbor (NNN) hoppings to the Hubbard model, the phase diagram becomes richer, and fascinating phenomena arise in both, one-dimensional chains and square lattices, such as: antiferromagnetism (AFM), ferromagnetism (FM), superconductivity (SC), as well as charge orders, among others. Moreover, NNN hoppings play a fundamental role in understanding effects of doping on magnetism and pairing orders in strongly interacting regimes. In this article, we review the recent progress in understanding the different competing phases of this model in one and two dimensions from a computational perspective. We comment on the pressing technical challenges, illustrate the controversial results concerning the emergence of the SC phase, and conclude with our perspectives on future explorations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13534v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luhang Yang, Adrian E. Feiguin, Thomas P. Devereaux, Elbio Dagotto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lieb-Schultz-Mattis-Type and Laughlin-Type Argument for the Quantum Hall Effect in Lattice Fermions with Spiral Boundary Conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13594v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We derive the condition for the occurrence of the quantum Hall effect in two-dimensional lattice systems, expressed as $\phi\nu-\rho\in\mathbb{Z}$, where $\phi$, $\nu$, and $\rho$ denote the magnetic flux, the Chern number, and the electron density, respectively. By employing spiral boundary conditions, which treat the system as an extended one-dimensional chain, this condition is obtained directly through a Lieb-Schultz-Mattis-type and Laughlin-type argument. This approach improves upon the preceding work based on conventional periodic boundary conditions, where the condition was derived indirectly containing redundant system-size dependence. The key to this approach is that the spatial directions of the external force and the response can be manipulated by a factor of the system size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13594v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masaaki Nakamura, Masanori Yamanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A High-Efficiency Three-Stroke Quantum Isochoric Heat Engine: From Infinite Potential Wells to Magic Angle Twisted Bilayer Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13652</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13652v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a three-stroke quantum isochoric cycle that functions as a heat engine operating between two thermal reservoirs. Implemented for a particle confined in a one-dimensional infinite potential well, the cycle's performance is benchmarked against the classical three-stroke triangular and isochoric engines. We find that the quantum isochoric cycle achieves a higher efficiency than both classical counterparts and also surpasses the efficiency of the recently proposed three-stroke quantum isoenergetic cycle. Owing to its reduced number of strokes, the design substantially lowers control complexity in nanoscale thermodynamic devices, offering a more feasible route to experimental realization compared to conventional four-stroke architectures. We further evaluate the cycle in graphene-based systems under an external magnetic field, including monolayer graphene (MLG), AB-stacked bilayer graphene (BLG), and twisted bilayer graphene (TBG) at both magic and non-magic twist angles. Among these platforms, magic-angle twisted bilayer graphene (MATBG) attains the highest efficiency at fixed work output, highlighting its promise for quantum thermodynamic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13652v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hadi Mohammed Soufy, Colin Benjamin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Survival of Hermitian Criticality in the Non-Hermitian Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12246</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12246v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we investigate many-body phase transitions in a one-dimensional anisotropic XY model subject to a complex-valued transverse field. Within the biorthogonal framework, we calculate the ground-state correlation functions and entanglement entropy, confirming that their scaling behavior remains identical to that in the Hermitian XY model. The preservation of Hermitian phase transition features in the non-Hermitian setting is rooted in the persistence and emergence of symmetries and their breaking. Specifically, the ferromagnetic (FM) phase arises from the breaking of a $Z_2$ symmetry, while the Luttinger liquid (LL) phase is enabled by the emergence of a $U(1)$ symmetry together with the degeneracy of the real part of the energy spectrum. The nontrivial topology of the LL phase are characterized by the winding number around the exceptional point (EP). Given that non-Hermitian systems are inherently open, this research opens a new avenue for exploring conventional quantum phase transitions that are typically vulnerable to decoherence and environmental disruption in open quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12246v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fei Wang, Guoying Liang, Zecheng Zhao, Lin-Yue Luo, Da-Jian Zhang, Bao-Ming Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skyrmionic qubits stabilized by Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction as platforms for qubits and quantum gates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12250</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12250v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum computation departs from the classical paradigm of deterministic, bit-based processing by exploiting inherently quantum phenomena such as superposition and entanglement. We propose a framework for qubit realization based on skyrmionic states stabilized by the Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction (DMI) in two-dimensional spin lattices. The model incorporates competing exchange interactions, perpendicular magnetic anisotropy, and Zeeman coupling, solved via exact diagonalization under periodic (PBC) and open boundary conditions (OBC). A quantum skyrmionic phase emerges for PBC within a parameter space defined by DMI, exchange, field, and anisotropy, while OBC favor classical-like, topologically protected skyrmions. Quantum logic gates (Pauli X, Y, Z, Hadamard) are implemented on both skyrmion types. Energy density and entanglement entropy analyses reveal that quantum skyrmions suffer from DMI-driven decoherence and reduced gate fidelity, whereas classical-like skyrmions maintain stability. Exact simulations of qubit dynamics, including drive effects and Lindblad decoherence, demonstrate tunable anharmonic energy levels and coherent Bloch-sphere manipulation, making these skyrmionic states promising candidates for qubit implementation. Overall, the Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction plays a dual role-stabilizing skyrmionic qubits while simultaneously inducing decoherence during gate operations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12250v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/wq2b-b9fq</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Doru Sticlet, Romulus Tetean, Coriolan Tiusan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissipative Dynamics of Charged Graphene Quantum Batteries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12666</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12666v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate dissipative dynamics in a graphene-based quantum battery modeled as a four level spin valley system. The battery is charged via a Gaussian pulse and subsequently evolves under amplitude damping, dephasing, and both Markovian and non Markovian reservoirs. We find that amplitude damping, while inducing energy loss, can stabilize non passive steady states with finite ergotropy, whereas pure dephasing suppresses coherence and eliminates work extraction. On the other hand, non-Markovian memory slows ergotropy loss and enables partial recovery through information backflow. These results identify coherence and reservoir memory as essential resources for enhancing the long-time performance of graphene quantum batteries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12666v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Disha Verma, Indrajith VS, R. Sankaranarayanan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orientations of Orbi-K-Theory measuring Topological Phases and Brane Charges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12720v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Topological Chern phases of quantum materials, as well as brane charges on M-theory orbifolds, have famously been argued to be classified by (orbi) topological K-theory, or possibly by other stable and, notably, complex-oriented cohomology theories, such as elliptic cohomology or Morava K-theory.
  However, closer inspection reveals that the most fine-grained "fragile" microscopic classification in both cases is in (orbi) Cohomotopy, which is the primordial "unstable" or nonabelian generalized cohomology. Coarsening takes the latter (fragile) to the former (stable) cohomology along an nonabelian cohomology operations. But what then is the role of complex orientation on the stable side?
  We observe here (i) that over gapped nodal lines in the 2D Brillouin torus and on probe M5-branes in 11D spacetime, the cohomotopical phases/charges lift through the complex/quaternionic Hopf fibration, and (ii) that measuring this fragile situation in stable cohomology means equivalently to ask for universal complex/quaternionic orientation on stable cohomology in four/ten dimensions!
  Then we give an explicit realization of such unstable four/ten-dimensional complex/quaternionic orientation in U(2)/Sp(2)-equivariant K-theory, using real division-algebraic tools within a new model of twisted orbifold K-theory in cohesive homotopy theory; and we explain this as an extraordinary character map from orbi Cohomotopy-twisted Cohomotopy to relative orbi K-theory.
  Finally, we discuss an application to the classification of 2-band crystalline topological insulator phases sensitive to the topology in the gapping process of their nodal line semimetal parent phase, and to the measurement of M-string charges inside M5-brane probes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12720v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hisham Sati, Urs Schreiber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orthogonal Attosecond Control of Solid-State Harmonics by Optical Waveforms and Quantum Geometry Engineering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13114v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: High-harmonic generation (HHG) in two-dimensional materials offers a compelling route toward compact extreme ultraviolet sources and probing electron dynamics on the attosecond scale. However, achieving precise control over the emission and disentangling the complex interplay between intraband and interband quantum pathways remains a central challenge. Here, we demonstrate through first-principles simulations that HHG in monolayer WS2 can be subjected to precise, complementary control by combining all-optical two-color laser fields with mechanical strain engineering. This dual-mode strategy provides unprecedented, orthogonal control over harmonic yield, polarization, and spectral features. We reveal that sculpting the two-color field's relative phase provides a sub-femtosecond switch for the quantum coherence of electron-hole pairs, thereby maximizing harmonic emission. Crucially, we uncover that tensile strain acts as a powerful amplifier through a dual mechanism - while strain-modified band dispersion enhances the intraband current, a profound reshaping of the Berry curvature (BC) dramatically boosts the anomalous velocity contribution to the interband response. This quantum geometric effect manifests as a robust, linear dependence of the harmonic yield on strain and a significant amplification of the perpendicularly polarized harmonics, providing a clear experimental signature for probing quantum geometric effects. Our findings establish a versatile framework for optimizing solid-state HHG and introduce a powerful all-optical method to map strain and quantum geometric properties of materials, positioning monolayer WS2 as a model system for exploring attosecond physics at the nexus of bulk and atomic scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13114v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhenjiang Zhao, Zhihua Zheng, Zhiyi Xu, Xing Ran, Xiaolong Yao, Fangping Ouyang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamics of the Fermi-Hubbard Model through Stochastic Calculus and Girsanov Transformation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13581v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We apply the methodology of our recent paper 'The Dynamics of the Hubbard Model through Stochastic Calculus and Girsanov Transformation' [1] to thermodynamic correlation functions in the Fermi-Hubbard model. They can be obtained from a stochastic differential equation (SDE) system. To this SDE system, a Girsanov transformation can be applied. This has the effect that the usual determinant or pfaffian which shows up in a pfaffian quantum Monte Carlo (PfQMC) representation [2] basically gets absorbed into the new integration variables and information from that pfaffian moves into the drift part of the transformed SDE system. While the PfQMC representation depends heavily on the choice of how the quartic interaction has been factorized into quadratic quantities in the beginning, the Girsanov transformed formula has the very remarkable property that it is nearly independent of that choice, the drift part of the transformed SDE system as well as a remaining exponential which has the obvious meaning of energy are always the same and do not depend on the Hubbard-Stratonovich details. The resulting formula may serve as a starting point for further theoretical or numerical investigations. Here we consider the spin-spin correlation at half-filling on a bipartite lattice and obtain an analytical proof that the signs of these correlations have to be of antiferromagnetic type, at arbitrary temperatures. Also, by checking against available benchmark data [3], we find that approximate ground state energies can be obtained from an ODE system. This may even hold for exact ground state energies, but future work would be required to prove or disprove this. As in [1], the methodology is generic and can be applied to arbitrary quantum many body or quantum field theoretical models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13581v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Detlef Lehmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dirac Electrons in AC-Magnetic Fields: $\pi$-Landau Levels and Chiral Anomaly-Induced Homodyne Effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08115</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.08115v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Floquet engineering, which involves controlling systems through time-periodic driving, is a method for coherently manipulating quantum materials and realizing dynamical states with novel functionalities. Most research in solid-state systems has focused on the use of AC-electric fields as the controlling drive. In this study, we investigate the effects of AC-magnetic fields on two-dimensional (2D) Dirac electrons and report the emergence of new states and new transport phenomena. In a magnetic field that temporarily changes its direction, the 2D Dirac electrons form a new localized state with a flat band dispersion, dubbed as a $\pi$-Landau level. Its wave function is a superposition of the clockwise and counterclockwise cyclotron orbits with time-periodic amplitudes, resulting in a novel closed trajectory shaped like a figure eight. Then, what would be the counterpart of the Hall effect in AC-magnetic fields? We find that a DC-current in the transverse direction, i.e. a homodyne Hall current, is generated when an additional AC-electric field is applied. In the case of Dirac electrons, several electronic states contribute to this phenomenon including the $\pi$-Landau level. However, when the chemical potential $\mu$ is near the Dirac point, the dominant contribution comes from the low-energy electrons and we numerically find the homodyne Hall current to behave as $I_y=-\frac{e}{h}\mu$ per valley and spin. We explain this phenomenon through the high-frequency effective Floquet Hamiltonian which resembles the chiral Landau level Hamiltonian of three-dimensional Weyl Hamiltonian exhibiting chiral anomaly. We discuss the experimental feasibility and conclude that it is possible to realize this new exotic state using techniques such as THz metamaterial enhancement of magnetic fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.08115v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sota Kitamura, Takashi Oka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Making s-wave superconductors topological with magnetic field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.15266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.15266v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that a two-dimensional $s$-wave superconductor may become topological in the presence of a magnetic field that leads to the formation of an Abrikosov vortex lattice. Below the upper critical field, a superconducting state with a nontrivial even topological number emerges, which we call the Abrikosov-Chern superconducting state. Deeper in the superconducting domain, the topological number changes in steps, always remaining even and thus not supporting Majorana states, and eventually reaches zero. Our theory uncovers the nature of evolution from an integer quantum Hall state having a cyclotron gap above the upper critical field to the topologically trivial $s$-wave superconductor carrying finite-energy Caroli-de Gennes-Matricon levels at low field. Topological transitions manifest as changes in the number of edge modes, detectable through tunneling spectroscopy and thermal or spin transport measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.15266v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/dqkm-1792</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 134508 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Daniil S. Antonenko, Liang Fu, Leonid. I Glazman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ferromagnetic fragmented state in the pyrochlore Ho$_2$Ru$_2$O$_7$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.10078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.10078v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The consecutive magnetic ordering of the Ho and Ru ions in the pyrochlore Ho2Ru2O7 and their interplay are investigated by neutron scattering, magnetic and specific heat measurements. The Ru moments order at 95 K into a $\Gamma_5$ easy-plane antiferromagnetic state. At 1.55 K the Ho moments order into an unusual $\Gamma_9$ ferromagnetic state with extensive ground state entropy and structured spin dynamics. It is shown how the internal fields with $\Gamma_5$ and $\Gamma_9$ geometry allow for two symmetry breaking transitions. The lower temperature ordering is driven by ruthenium mediated interactions between holmium moments as spin ice correlations develop. The unsaturated order is compatible with a fragmented ferromagnetic state equivalent to pyrochlore kagome ice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.10078v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Museur, J. Robert, F. Morineau, N. Bujault, V. Simonet, E. Pachoud, A. Hadj-Azzem, C. Colin, L. Mangin-Thro, P. Manuel, J. R. Stewart, P. C. W. Holdsworth, E. Lhotel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unsupervised Classification of Non-Hermitian Topological Phases under Symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20882v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The integration of artificial intelligence (AI) into fundamental science has opened new possibilities to address long-standing scientific challenges rooted in mathematical limitations. For example, topological invariants are used to characterize topology, but there is no universally applicable one. This limitation explains why, in the past decades-long classification of topological phases of matter -- mainly focused on Hermitian systems -- many phases initially classified ``trivial" were later identified as topological. Recently, the discovery of non-Hermitian band topology has spurred substantial efforts in non-Hermitian topological classification, including the development of new topological invariants. However, such classifications similarly risk overlooking key topological features. Here, without relying on any topological invariant, we develop an AI-based unsupervised classification of symmetry-protected non-Hermitian topological phases. This algorithm distinguishes topological differences among non-Hermitian Hamiltonians with symmetries, and constructs, in an unsupervised manner, a topological periodic table for non-Hermitian systems. Additionally, it can account for the boundary effects, enabling the exploration of open-boundary effects on the topological phase diagram. These results introduce an unsupervised approach for classifying symmetry-protected non-Hermitian topological phases without omission and provide valuable guidance for the development of theories and experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20882v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Long, Haoran Xue, Baile Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic space-time crystalline order in a hybrid Josephson junction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05797</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05797v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We demonstrate the emergence of an intrinsic space-time crystalline order in a long ferromagnetic $\varphi_{0}$ Josephson junction on a topological insulator without any external periodic modulation. The presence of the exchange and Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interactions in a ferromagnetic layer with broken inversion symmetry internally modulates the critical current due to the coupling between the magnetic moment and the Josephson phase. This breaks the time translation symmetry, leading to the appearance of the space-time crystalline pattern in the spatiotemporal dependence of the in-plane current, which oscillates with almost twice the ferromagnetic resonance frequency. In the limit where the critical current is not modulated internally, the space-time crystalline order does not occur. In this case, only when an external parametric modulation is applied, the system exhibits a typical classical discrete space-time crystalline order that oscillates at half of the modulation frequency. Considering the still-pending problem of experimental detection, we demonstrate that a recently developed magnetometry device, which visualizes the supercurrent flow at the nanoscale, can be used to detect space-time crystalline patterns in hybrid Josephson junctions experimentally.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05797v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/kxkc-4gs4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 184507 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>M. Nashaat, J. Teki\'c, Yu. M. Shukrinov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of the Mott phase in excitonic double layers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13026</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13026v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the stability of excitonic Mott phases in the presence of a periodic potential and a non-local exciton-exciton interaction. The non-local interaction is treated in a mean-field approximation, while the local repulsion of the excitons is treated in a hopping expansion. The convergence of the latter is the criterion for the stability of the Mott phase with respect to quantum and thermal fluctuations. This hybrid approach enables us to establish a phase diagram for a bosonic Mott to superfluid transition. Our results could be useful to interpret recent experiments on electron-hole crystals in van der Waals heterostructures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13026v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physleta.2025.131139</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Lett. A 565, 131139 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>K. Ziegler, R. Ya. Kezerashvili</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signatures of Majorana bound states in scanning gate microscopy of hybrid nanowires</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14562</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14562v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We theoretically study scanning gate microscopy of a superconductor-proximitized semiconducting wire focusing on the potential for detection of Majorana bound states. We exploit the possibility to create a local potential perturbation by the scanning gate tip which allows controllable modification of the spatial distribution of the Majorana modes, which is translated into changes in their energy structure. When the tip scans across the system, it effectively divides the wire into two parts with controllable lengths, in which two pairs of Majorana states are created when the system is in the topological regime. For strong values of the tip potential, the pairs are decoupled, and the presence of Majorana states can be detected via local tunneling spectroscopy that resolves the energy splittings resulting from the Majorana states wave functions overlap. Importantly, as the system is probed spatially via the tip, this technique can distinguish Majorana bound states from quasi-Majorana states localized on smooth potential barriers. We demonstrate that for weaker tip potentials, the two neighboring Majorana states hybridize, opening pronounced anticrossings in the energy spectra which are reflected in local conductance maps and which result in non-zero non-local conductance features. Finally, we demonstrate that the scanning gate microscopy technique can be used to discriminate between the trivial and topological nature of the zero-bias conductance peak in disordered wires.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14562v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/bc9x-lswp</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 195422 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>S. Maji, M. P. Nowak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin correlations in La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ superconducting thin films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03178</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.03178v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The discovery of ambient-pressure superconductivity with $T_{c,\text{onset}} &gt; 40$ K in {\LNO} (LNO) thin films grown on the SrLaAlO$_4$ (SLAO) substrate with compressive ($\varepsilon\approx-2\%$) epitaxial strain provides a unique platform for investigating the superconducting mechanisms in nickelate superconductors. Here, we use resonant inelastic X-ray scattering (RIXS) to unveil the dispersive spin excitations in the LNO/SLAO superconducting thin film and establish the strain dependence of the electronic and spin excitations in LNO thin films with strain ranging from $\varepsilon\approx-2\%$ to $+1.9\%$. Compared with the bulk crystal, the LNO/SLAO thin film (with $\varepsilon\approx-2\%$) exhibits similar $dd$ excitations and spin dynamics with larger bandwidth. By contrast, tensile-strained LNO/SrTiO$_3$ ($\varepsilon \approx +1.9\%$) exhibits a marked suppression of both the spin excitations and the Ni 3{\dz}-derived $dd$ excitations. The strain dependence of the spin excitations reflects significant changes in the interlayer exchange coupling $J_z$, and the diminishing $dd$ excitations in tensile-strained samples indicate weaker Ni 3{\dz}-O 2$p_{z}$ hybridization. This strain evolution of the spin excitations and $J_z$ is attributed to the strain-tuned $c$-axis Ni-O-Ni bond angle $\varphi$, which controls the Ni 3{\dz}-O 2$p_{z}$ hybridization. Since superconductivity is observed only in films grown on SLAO, and spin correlations are enhanced along with the emergence of superconductivity, our results identify $\varphi$ as a key structural lever controlling $J_z$ and provide direct spectroscopic support for interlayer spin-fluctuation-mediated pairing scenarios in bilayer nickelates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.03178v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hengyang Zhong, Bo Hao, Zhijia Zhang, Anni Chen, Yuan Wei, Ruixian Liu, Xinru Huang, Chunyi Li, Wenting Zhang, Chang Liu, Xiao-Sheng Ni, Marli dos Reis Cantarino, Kurt Kummer, Nicholas Brookes, Kun Cao, Yuefeng Nie, Thorsten Schmitt, Xingye Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic phase diagram of magnetocaloric TmFeO$_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17291v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Neutron diffraction experiments of TmFeO$_3$ single crystals were performed in the external magnetic fields. The field along $c$-axis increases temperature of spin-reorientation transition $T_{SR}$ from phase ${\Gamma}4$ to ${\Gamma}2$. Application of the field along $b$-axis led to the decrease of $T_{SR}$ and to the formation of new phases. Based on the temperature and field dependence of the Bragg reflection intensity, the configuration of magnetically induced phases was proposed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17291v5</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. I. Tkachenko, P. Fabrykiewicz, A. K. Ovsianikov, M. Meven, O. V. Usmanov, I. A. Zobkalo, K. A. Shaykhutdinov, K. Yu. Terentjev, S. V. Semenov, E. Ressouche, K. Beauvois</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact Chiral Symmetries of 3+1D Hamiltonian Lattice Fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07708</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.07708v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct Hamiltonian models on a 3+1d cubic lattice for a single Weyl fermion and for a single Weyl doublet protected by exact (as opposed to emergent) chiral symmetries. In the former, we find a not-on-site, non-compact chiral symmetry which can be viewed as a Hamiltonian analog of the Ginsparg-Wilson symmetry in Euclidean lattice models of Weyl fermions. In the latter, we combine an on-site $U(1)$ symmetry with a not-on-site $U(1)$ symmetry, which together generate the $SU(2)$ flavor symmetry of the doublet at low energies, while in the UV they generate an algebra known in integrability as the Onsager algebra. This latter model is in fact the celebrated magnetic Weyl semimetal which is known to have a chiral anomaly from the action of $U(1)$ and crystalline translation, that gives rise to an anomalous Hall response - however reinterpreted in our language, it has two exact $U(1)$ symmetries that gives rise to the global $SU(2)$ anomaly which protects the gaplessness even when crystalline translations are broken. We also construct an exact symmetry-protected single Dirac cone in 2+1d with the $U(1) \rtimes T$ parity anomaly. Our constructions evade both old and recently-proven no-go theorems by using not-on-siteness in a crucial way, showing our results are sharp.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.07708v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Gioia, Ryan Thorngren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Optimally Accurate Lanczos Algorithm in the Matrix Product State Representation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.21786v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We improve the convergence of the Lanczos algorithm using the matrix product state representation. As an alternative to the density matrix renormalization group (DMRG), the Lanczos algorithm avoids local minima and can directly find multiple low-lying eigenstates. However, its performance and accuracy are affected by the truncation required to maintain the efficiency of the tensor network representation. In this work, we propose the modified thick-block Lanczos method to enhance the convergence of the Lanczos algorithm with MPS representation. We benchmark our method on one-dimensional instances of the Fermi-Hubbard model and the Heisenberg model in an external field, using numerical experiments targeting the first five lowest eigenstates. Across these tests, our approach attains the best possible accuracy permitted by the given bond dimension. This work establishes the Lanczos method as a reliable and accurate framework for finding multiple low-lying states within a tensor-network representation</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.21786v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Wang, Zhangyu Yang, Xingyao Wu, Christian B. Mendl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond kagome: $p$-bands in kagome metals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00796</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00796v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We review recent studies on quantum materials where transition-metal atoms give rise to $d$-bands typical of kagome metals. Using examples from several material families - AV$_3$Sb$_5$, FeGe, RV$_6$Sn$_6$, and LaRu$_3$Si$_2$ - we argue that $p$-bands contributed by elements beyond the kagome network also play a crucial role in the electronic instabilities, including the charge-density-waves and superconductivity in kagome metals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00796v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/qute.202500336</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Adv. Quant. Tech. 8, e2500336 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alexander A. Tsirlin, Ece Uykur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ordered buckling structures in a twisted crimped tube</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21065</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21065v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: When a ribbon or tube is twisted far enough it forms buckles and wrinkles. Its new geometry can be strikingly ordered, or hopelessly disordered. Here we study this process in a tube with hybrid boundary conditions: one end a cylinder, and the other end crimped flat like a ribbon, so that the sample resembles a toothpaste tube. The resulting irregular structures and mechanical responses can be dramatically different from those of a ribbon. However, when we form two creases in the tube prior to twisting, we obtain an ordered structure composed of repeating triangular facets oriented at varying angles, and a more elastic torque response, reminiscent of the creased helicoid structure of a twisted ribbon. We measure how the torque and structural evolution depend on parameters such as material thickness and the twist angle. When only part of the tube is pre-creased, the ordered structures are confined to this segment. Surprisingly, in some tubes made from thicker sheets, an ordered structure forms without pre-creasing. This study provides insights into controlling the buckling of thin shells, offering a potential pathway for designing ordered structures in soft materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21065v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pan Dong, Nathan C. Keim, Joseph D. Paulsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Signatures of Magnetic Phase Transitions with Majorana Fermions through Local Observables and Quantum Information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.11731</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.11731v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The one-dimensional (1D) $J_1-J_2$ quantum spin model can be viewed as a strong-coupling analogue of the Schrieffer-Su-Heeger model with two inequivalent alternating Ising couplings along the wire, associated to the physics of resonating valence bonds. Similar to the quantum Ising model, which differently presents a long-range N\' eel ordered phase, this model also maps onto a p-wave superconducting wire which shows a topological phase transition with the emergence of low-energy Majorana fermions. We show how signatures of the topological phase transition for the p-wave superconducting wire, i.e. a half Skyrmion, are revealed through local (short-range) spin observables and their derivatives related to the capacitance of the pairing fermion model. Then, we present an edge correspondence through the edge spin susceptibility in the $J_1-J_2$ model revealing that the topological phase transition is a metal of Majorana fermions. We justify that the spin magnetization at an edge at very small transverse magnetic field is a good marker of the topological invariant and of Majorana zero modes. We identify a correspondence between the quantum information of resonating valence bonds and the charge fluctuations in a p-wave superconductor through our method "the bipartite fluctuations". Physical properties of this 1D model are in fact robust when including additional interactions, which is optimistic for practical applications e.g. in quantum circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.11731v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karyn Le Hur, Fan Yang, Magali Korolev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anderson-skin dualism: A boundary-dependent effect in non-Hermitian disordered coupled systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05013v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report a novel localization phenomenon that emerges in non-Hermitian and quasiperiodic coupled systems, which we dub ``Anderson-Skin (AS) dualism". The emergence of AS dualism is due to the fact that non-Hermitian topological systems provide non-trivial topological transport channels for disordered systems, causing the originally localized Anderson modes to transform into skin modes, i.e., the localized states within the point gap regions have dual characteristics of localization under periodic boundary condition (PBC) and skin effects under open boundary conditions (OBC). As an example, we analytically prove the 1D AS dualism through the transfer matrix method. Moreover, by discussing many-body interacting systems, we confirm that AS dualism is universal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05013v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/vz12-2qn3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, L201108 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shan-Zhong Li, Linhu Li, Shi-Liang Zhu, Zhi Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interaction-enhanced quantum to classical transport crossover temperature in a Luttinger liquid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05356</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05356v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Strange metals are highly entangled gapless states of matter that exhibit anomalous transport, such as linear in temperature resistivity, over more than a decade of temperature. Why a single power law should be so robust is an open question. We propose a scenario in which interactions enhance the domain of certain scattering regimes, effectively suppressing other ``would-be regimes." We test this proposal in a one-dimensional Luttinger liquid coupled to a one-dimensional acoustic phonon. We use the memory matrix formalism to calculate the dc electrical and thermal conductivities at low and high temperatures, relative to the Debye cutoff on phonon frequencies, in both the ``clean" (umklapp scattering) and ``dirty" (disorder scattering) limits. We find the crossover temperature separating the low and high temperature regimes to be interaction-dependent, with repulsive interactions substantially increasing it, generally by more than an order of magnitude. This provides a concrete illustration for how interactions can extend a single transport regime over a wider temperature range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05356v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yen-Wen Lu, Michael Mulligan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-chirality-dependent modulation of topological gap, Chern number, and valley-polarization in monolayer kagome lattice Cr3Se4</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09884v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Kagome materials exhibit unique electronic properties, such as the quantum anomalous Hall effect. The control of Chern numbers is critical for quantum device manipulation, but existing research has mainly focused on collinear magnetization while neglecting chiral spin textures. Through first-principles calculations and tight-binding modeling of monolayer Cr3Se4, this study reveals spin-chirality-dependent control of topological gaps, Chern numbers, and valley polarization in kagome materials. The results demonstrate that the azimuthal angle has no observable effect. For collinear magnetization (\k{appa} = 0) or spin-chirality \k{appa} = -1, the topological bandgap decreases as the spin orientation approaches the in-plane direction. Conversely, increasing the polar angle enhances the bandgap for \k{appa} = 1. In the breathing kagome lattice, the degeneracy between K and K' valleys is lifted. As the gap undergoes sequential closure and reopening in the two valleys, the structural asymmetry and spin-chirality allow for controlled tuning of the topological gap, Chern number, and valley polarization. Moreover, the emergence of a topological Hall effect is is also demonstrated. These findings provide strategies for controlling topological states and advancing applications in quantum devices and valleytronic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09884v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenzhe Zhou, Guibo Zheng, Yating Li, Aolin Li, Fangping Ouyang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermally Activated Snap-through Transitions Controlled by Tunable Metastability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14658</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14658v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The effects of thermal fluctuations on the morphology of two-dimensional materials are hard to harness. We propose that a geometrically constrained graphene nanoribbon (GNR) can exhibit thermally activated snap-through transitions with a predictable and controllable transition rate constant. The energetics and kinetics of such transitions can be fully captured by combining enhanced sampling methods and generalized transition state theory. Using well-tempered metadynamics, we determine the free energy landscape and a pair of asymmetric transition pathways of the GNR system. Notably, generalized transition state theory accurately captures how the transition rate constant responds to temperature and the tunable free energy landscape of our system. This work offers a theoretical framework for elastic metastability, introduces rare event methods into thermalized nanomechanical systems, and provides potential applications in designing nanoscale thermal switches and thermal actuators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14658v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Renjie Zhao, Yiquan Zhang, Chenglin Luo, Yihang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superpotentials, flat bands and the role of Quantum Geometry for the superfluid stiffness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15604</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15604v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Enhancing superconductivity through material design is a central goal in quantum materials research. Moire engineering, where twisting stacked layers creates long-wavelength modulations and flat bands, has shown how electronic correlations can be amplified and eventually used to raise the superconducting critical temperature Tc. Yet this approach is largely confined to van der Waals materials and offers limited tunability. Here we explore a moire-inspired alternative: imposing artificial superpotentials on otherwise homogeneous systems to engineer flat electronic minibands. Whether such superlattice potentials can truly enhance superconductivity and sustain a finite superfluid stiffness remains, however, an open question. Our calculations show that a periodic superpotential imposed to a 2D system can indeed enhance superconductivity by reconstructing the electronic bands and creating regions of large density of states, leading to a substantial increase of Tc. In contrast to conventional flat band systems, where the superfluid stiffness arises solely from quantum geometry through the quantum metric, a modulated system inherits kinetic energy from the filled minibands below the Fermi level. This inherited component coexists with a positive quantum geometric contribution, yielding a finite and robust stiffness even when the upper band becomes nearly flat. The resulting superconducting state remains coherent and resilient against weak to moderate disorder. Our findings demonstrate that engineered superpotentials offer a tunable route to enhance superconductivity beyond twist based moire systems, unifying flat band amplification of pairing with preserved phase stiffness. They further highlight the central role of quantum geometry in shaping collective electronic phenomena and point to superlattice design as a promising platform for next-generation superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15604v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Bauch, F. Lombardi, G. Seibold</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-Orbit Coupling Effect on the Seebeck Coefficient in Dirac Electron Systems in $\alpha$-(BETS)$_2$I$_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07349v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Seebeck coefficient, $S=L_{12}/(TL_{11})$, which is proportional to a ratio of the thermoelectric conductivity $L_{12}$ to the electric conductivity $L_{11}$ with $T$ being temperature is examined for two-dimensional Dirac electrons in the three-quarter filled organic conductor, $\alpha$-(BETS)$_2$I$_3$, [BETS = BEDT-TSeF = bis(ethylenedithio)tetraselenafulvalene] at ambient pressure.Using a tight-binding model obtained with the first-principles relativistic density-functional theory method [Tsumuraya and Suzumura, Eur. Phys. J. B 94, 17 (2021)], we calculate $S$ in the presence of the impurity and electron--phonon scatterings. We show that $S_x &lt; 0$ and $S_y &gt;0$ at high temperatures, where $S_x$ ($S_y$) denotes $S$ perpendicular (parallel) to the molecular stacking axis. There is a sign change of $S_y$ with increasing $T$. We find that, at low temperatures the absolute value of $S$ is enhanced by the spin-orbit coupling. The Seebeck coefficient is examined by dividing it into components of the conduction and valence bands; we find that the electron and hole contributions compete with each other. Such $T$ dependence of $S$ is clarified using the spectral conductivity, which determines $L_{12}$ and $L_{11}$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07349v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/9htn-m1pp</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 195414(1-11) (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yoshikazu Suzumura, Takao Tsumuraya, Masao Ogata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large Chern-Number Quantum Anomalous Hall Effect from Canted Antiferromagnetic Order in $d$-Electron System on Kagome Lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10976</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.10976v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Electrons of $d$-symmetry interacting with a localized non-collinear antiferromagnetic spin order on a kagome lattice are considered. Even in the absence of an external magnetic field, spin-orbit coupling or relativistic effects, the spin texture produces a non-trivial intrinsic Berry curvature. This opens the route for a quantum anomalous Hall effect in the $d$-system. For spin orders with an out-of-plane component, the scalar spin chirality is finite, and the integration of the Berry curvature over the Brillouin zone may yield integer Hall conductivities in units of $e^2/h$. This canted configuration gives rise to the maximal possible Chern number, $C=\pm 5$ when the Fermi level is within nontrivial gap. The effect is best understood for -- but not limited to -- isotropic $d$-electron hopping and degenerate $d$-levels. In this case, analytic expressions are available and point to a topological origin for the manifestation of the maximal $C$. Numerical calculations show that these findings are robust to some anisotropy in the hopping integrals and to moderate splittings of the $d$ levels. The $C=\pm 5$ plateau can be split into Chern peaks with smaller integers by varying the onsite energies. The topological phase transition between Hall plateaus of opposite $C$ can be driven by flipping the out-of-plane component of the spin order, alluding to the potential of this system to quantum information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.10976v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Waquar Ahmed, Steffen Schaeffer, Pierre Lombardo, Roland Hayn, Imam Makhfudz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Soliton Formation as a Dark-State Phase Transition in a Dissipative Superfluid Josephson Junction Chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25707</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25707v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We identify and characterize a first-order dark-state phase transition between a discrete dark soliton and a uniform superfluid in a Bose-Hubbard chain with a single lossy site. Using classical-field (truncated-Wigner) simulations together with a Bogoliubov stability analysis, we show that the dark-state nature of the soliton suppresses fluctuations and shifts the critical point relative to the comparable phenomenon of optical bistability in driven-dissipative Kerr resonators. We then demonstrate that this mechanism quantitatively captures the bistability phase boundary observed in the experiment of R. Labouvie et al. [Phys. Rev. Lett. 116, 235302 (2016)], resolving substantial discrepancies in prior modeling efforts. Our results reveal how driving, dissipation and quantum coherence can interact to induce nonequilibrium phase transitions in ultra-cold atomic gases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25707v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robbe Ceulemans, Samuel E. Begg, Matthew J. Davis, Michiel Wouters</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Valley-dependent topological interface states in biased armchair nanoribbons in single-layer graphene for transport applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05653</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05653v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For nanoscale single-layer graphene-based devices, valley-dependent topological physics may be exploited in device design. To demonstrate the point, we investigate an electrical bias-controlled, topological kind discontinuity in valley polarization, in a two-segment armchair nanoribbon of single-layer graphene, where the discontinuity is created at the interface by applying opposite in-plane, transverse electrical biases to the two segments. In particular, using an efficient tight-binding theoretical formulation, we explicitly obtain energy eigenvalues and probability distributions of discontinuity-induced, interface-confined electron eigenstates, in a reference configuration. Moreover, implications of the confinement for electron transport are explored. A configurational variation is introduced to transform the eigenstates into transport-active, quasi-localized ones. Such states are shown to result in Fano "anti-resonances" in transmission spectra. The resilience of the quasi-localized states and their associated Fano fingerprints is presented with respect to configurational fluctuations. Last, a proof-of-concept electron energy band-stop filter is illustrated, highlighting the potential of the foregoing confinement and, more broadly, valley-dependent topological physics in designing nanoscale single-layer graphene devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05653v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zheng-Han Huang, Jing-Yuan Lai, Yu-Shu G. Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thickness dependent rare earth segregation in magnetron deposited NdCo$_{4.6}$ thin films studied by Xray reflectivity and Hard Xray photoemission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23852v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Magnetic anisotropy in disordered rare-earth-transition metals (RE-TM) compounds arises from RE atoms occupying asymmetric environments within the TM lattice. However, the underlying mechanism that promotes such environments remains not fully understood. In this study, we investigate amorphous NdCo$_{4.6}$ thin films deposited by magnetron sputtering, where the magnetic anisotropy evolves with thickness from in-plane to out-of-plane orientation above 40 nm. X-ray reflectivity measurements revealed the progressive formation of an additional layer between the 3 nm Si capping layer and the NdCo film with increasing film thickness. To probe the composition and distribution of Co and Nd near the surface, Hard X-ray Photoemission Spectroscopy (HAXPES) was performed on films ranging from 5 nm to 65 nm in thickness using incident photon energies of 7, 19, and 13 keV. These correspond to inelastic electron mean free paths of 7.2-12.3 nm in cobalt. The cobalt atomic concentration, deduced from HAXPES at the Nd 3d and Co 2p excitations, was consistently below the nominal value and varied with both thickness and photon energy. This indicates segregation of RE atoms at the film surface, which becomes more pronounced with increasing thickness. Background analysis of the Co 2p and Nd 3d peaks supports this conclusion. The thickness of the Nd segregated layer is estimated in 2-3 nm. These findings demonstrate that incorporating neodymium into the cobalt lattice incurs an energy cost which is associated with strain due to the volume mismatch between the two elements. Reducing this strain energy promotes anisotropic atomic environments for Nd, thereby explaining the emergence of perpendicular anisotropy and its dependence on film thickness in these RE-TM compounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23852v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. D\'iaz, J. Rodr\'iguez-Fern\'andez, J. Rubio-Zuazo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resonating-valence-bond superconductor from small Fermi surface in twisted bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26801</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26801v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Mechanism of superconductivity in twisted bilayer graphene (TBG) remains one of the central problems in correlated moir\'e materials. The most intriguing question is about the nature of the normal state: is the Cooper pair formed from small Fermi surface or large Fermi surface? In this work we point out the possibility of a symmetric pseudogap metal with small hole pockets, dubbed as second Fermi liquid (sFL). In the sFL phase at $\nu=-2-x$, there is a two-component picture: two electrons mainly localize at each AA site and form a paired singlet due to anti-Hund's coupling mediated by the optical phonon, while additional holes doped into the AA sites form small Fermi surfaces. The sFL phase corresponds to an intrinsically strongly interacting fixed point and is topologically distinct to the conventional Fermi liquid. We develop a unified framework to describe both a renormalized FL phase and an sFL phase. We propose that the TBG superconductor emerges from the sFL phase, but is close to the transition toward the FL phase under increasing hole doping. In the superconductor, pairing of local moments is shared to the mobile carriers and a smaller superconducting gap with nodal $p_x$ symmetry is opened on the small hole pockets. This work provides, to our knowledge, the first unified theory that explains both the pseudogap metal above $T_c$ and the two-gap nematic superconductivity below it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26801v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jing-Yu Zhao, Ya-Hui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for spontaneous breaking of a continuous symmetry at a non-conformal quantum critical point in one dimension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09097v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we present evidence for the spontaneous breaking of a continuous symmetry in a nearest-neighbour interacting spin-1 chain tuned to a quantum critical point at $T=0$ between two XY quasi-long-range order phases differing by the spontaneous breaking of a $\mathbb{Z}_2$ symmetry. Despite the one-dimensional nature of the system, which typically prevents such a continuous symmetry breaking due to the Hohenberg-Mermin-Wagner theorem, the presence of a Berry phase term in the quantum model allows us to observe, using matrix product state methods, a finite perpendicular magnetization. Moreover, the quasi-long-range decay of the correlation function becomes truly long-range order, and the dynamical structure factor displays a characteristic Bragg peak together with sharp gapless modes. Our results imply the quantum phase transition has an anomalous dimension of $\eta \simeq 1$ together with the dynamical critical exponent $z\simeq 3/2$, known from the Kardar-Parisi-Zhang universality class in one dimension. We perform a perturbative renormalization group calculation about the upper critical dimension $d_c=2$ that we could close at second loop order. We find an interacting fixed point with critical exponents distinct from the Ising ones. Together, our findings suggest the nature of the fixed point to be non-perturbative. We propose a field-theory that we believe to improve the quantitative results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09097v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Flores-Calder\'on, M. Z\"undel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-Dependent Oxidation and Scale Evolution of a Wrought Co/Ni-based Superalloy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09678v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding how protective oxide scales evolve over time is necessary for improving the long term resistance of superalloys. This work investigates the time-dependent oxidation behavior of an ingot-processable Co/Ni-based superalloy oxidized in air at $800~^\circ\mathrm{C}$ for $20$, $100$, and $1000~\mathrm{h}$ . Mass-gain and white-light interferometry measurements quantified oxidation kinetics, surface roughness, and spallation, while high-resolution STEM-EDX characterized oxide morphology and nanoscale elemental partitioning. Atom probe tomography captured the key transition regions between the chromia and alumina scales, and X-ray diffraction was used to identify a gradual transition from NiO and (Ni,Co)-spinel phases to a compact, dual phase chromia and alumina-rich scale. The oxidation rate evolved from near-linear to parabolic behavior with time, consistent with diffusion-controlled growth once a continuous Cr$_2$O$_3$/$\alpha$-Al$_2$O$_3$ scale formed. These observations help link kinetics, structure and chemistry, showing how an originally porous spinel layer transforms into a dense, adherent chromia + alumina scale that provides long-term protection in wrought Co/Ni-based superalloys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09678v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cameron. Crabb, Zachary. T. Kloenne, Samuel. R. Rogers, Chi-Hang. D. Kwok, Mark. C. Hardy, Michelle. S. Conroy, David. Dye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TasVisAn and InsPy -- Python Packages for Triple-Axis Spectrometer Data Visualization, Analysis, Instrument Resolution Calculation, and Convolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18216</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18216v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Experimental data collected from a triple-axis spectrometer (TAS) are typically analysed by considering the instrument resolution, as the resolution of a TAS instrument is often complex and significantly influences the measured results. Two Python packages, TasVisAn and InsPy, have been developed to visualize and analyse data from TAS instruments - particularly from the cold-neutron TAS Sika and the thermal-neutron TAS Taipan at the Australian Centre for Neutron Scattering. TasVisAn offers a range of functions, including data importing, reduction, plotting, contour mapping, convolution fitting, and more, for data collected on TAS instruments, especially on Sika and Taipan. It also supports data reduction of the current trendy multi-analyser and multiplexing TAS instruments, including the multiplexing mode of Sika. Besides, it includes scan simulation and batch file validation tools for both Taipan and Sika, assisting users in designing and planning experiments in advance. InsPy is a general-purpose Python package designed to calculate the four-dimensional (4D) instrument resolution in momentum-energy space for any TAS instrument. Combined with InsPy, TasVisAn supports both instrument resolution calculation and resolution-convoluted data fitting. Its flexible external data import feature further allows TasVisAn to be adapted for the visualization and convolution analysis of inelastic neutron scattering data across various TAS instruments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18216v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1107/S1600576725008180</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Appl. Crystallogr. Volume 58, Page 1-14, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Guochu Deng, Garry J. McIntyre</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutron Reflectometry by Gradient Descent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.06924v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Neutron reflectometry (NR) is a powerful technique to probe surfaces and interfaces. NR is inherently an indirect measurement technique, access to the physical quantities of interest (layer thickness, scattering length density, roughness), necessitate the solution of an inverse modelling problem, that is inefficient for large amounts of data or complex multiplayer structures (e.g. lithium batteries / electrodes). Recently, surrogate machine learning models have been proposed as an alternative to existing optimisation routines. Although such approaches have been successful, physical intuition is lost when replacing governing equations with fast neural networks. Instead, we propose a novel and efficient approach; to optimise reflectivity data analysis by performing gradient descent on the forward reflection model itself. Herein, automatic differentiation techniques are used to evaluate exact gradients of the error function with respect to the parameters of interest. Access to these quantities enables users of neutron reflectometry to harness a host of powerful modern optimisation and inference techniques that remain thus far unexploited in the context of neutron reflectometry. This paper presents two benchmark case studies; demonstrating state-of-the-art performance on a thick oxide quartz film, and robust co-fitting performance in the high complexity regime of organic LED multilayer devices. Additionally, we provide an open-source library of differentiable reflectometry kernels in the python programming language so that gradient based approaches can readily be applied to other NR datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.06924v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Max D. Champneys, Andrew J. Parnell, Philipp Gutfreund, Maximilian W. A. Skoda, . Patrick A. Fairclough, Timothy J. Rogers, Stephanie L. Burg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Average Winding Number for Determinantal Curves associated with 2-Matrix Models in the Class AIII</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06669</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06669v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: To classify one-dimensional disordered quantum systems with chiral symmetry, we analyse the winding number of the determinant of a parametrized non-Hermitian random matrix field over the unit circle modelling the off-diagonal block of a disordered chiral Hamiltonian. The associated partition function is computed explicitly for a broad class of additive two-matrix models extending beyond the Ginibre Unitary Ensemble. In the large-dimension limit, we derive an asymptotic expansion of the average winding number whose leading term exhibits universal features, up to the tail behaviour of the underlying random matrix ensemble, and identify a new correction term absent in the previously studied Ginibre case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06669v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mathieu Yahiaoui, Mario Kieburg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
