<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 05:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the apparent violation of the Mott relation in a noncentrosymmetric kagome ferromagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00173</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00173v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In magnetic topological materials, time-reversal symmetry breaking gives rise to topological point and line nodes with distinctive signatures in the anomalous Hall and anomalous Nernst conductivity that satisfy the well-known Mott relation. However, this relationship can fail for doping-dependent transport measurements of materials with complex magnetism, topology, and electronic correlations. In this work, we present transport measurements of the correlated topological metal UCoAl doped with Ru, which appear to violate the Mott relation. We develop a model that captures the evolution of Stoner magnetism and topological Weyl points as a function of doping. Using this model, we show how the correlated flat band in this material pins the Weyl points to the Fermi energy, and demonstrate how this explains the unusual doping-dependent behavior of the anomalous Hall and anomalous Nernst conductivities in this material, while the Mott relation is in fact satisfied at each doping level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00173v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Kostroun, Tomoya Asaba, Sean M. Thomas, Eric D. Bauer, Sergey Y. Savrasov, Filip Ronning, Vsevolod Ivanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Purely even harmonic Josephson current due to crossed pair transmission across strongly spin-polarized materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00177</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00177v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We revisit the problem of the second harmonic generation in the current-phase relation across ferromagnetic bilayers placed between BCS superconductors. In particular, we consider a strongly spin-polarized metallic ferromagnet coupled to two superconducting leads via thin spin-active (left) and non-spin-active (right) insulating layers. The system is examined in the framework of the quasiclassical Green$^\prime$s function formalism, both in the ballistic (Eilenberger) and the diffusive (Usadel) limit. Strong spin polarization allows for neglecting short-range mixed-spin correlations, and the Josephson supercurrent across the ferromagnet is fully mediated by long-range equal-spin triplet correlations. Using a diagrammatic technique for ballistic propagators introduced in Refs. [1-3], we describe the relevant Andreev processes responsible for the effective conversion of two spin-singlet Cooper pairs in the superconductor into two $\uparrow\uparrow$ and $\downarrow\downarrow$ pairs in the ferromagnet. Contrary to the naive picture of direct conversion, we show that the lowest order process involves four Cooper pairs in the superconductor, among which three are incoming, and one is outgoing, giving rise to net charge transport of 4e across the non-spin-active interface. The self-consistent numerical treatment of the diffusive junction, typically more relevant in experiments, confirms this picture quantitatively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00177v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niklas L. Schulz, Danilo Nikoli\'c, Matthias Eschrig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resonant Dyakonov-Shur Magnetoplasmons in Graphene Terahertz Photodetectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00180v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Graphene plasmons confine incident terahertz fields far below the diffraction limit and, when hosted by a gate-defined Fabry-Perot cavity, enable electrically tunable, frequency-selective photodetectors. In a magnetic field, these plasmons hybridize with the cyclotron motion to form magnetoplasmons, offering a platform for fundamental studies and for nonreciprocal, spectrally selective, ultrasensitive terahertz photonics. However, implementing magnetoplasmon-assisted resonant transistors at terahertz frequencies has remained challenging so far. Here we use gate-dependent, on-chip terahertz photocurrent spectroscopy combined with a perpendicular magnetic field to resolve and probe the evolution of resonant magnetoplasmons in antenna-coupled monolayer and bilayer graphene TeraFETs. In monolayer graphene the dispersion reflects the Dirac nature of the carriers, exhibiting a non-monotonic density dependence due to the interplay of plasma resonance and cyclotron motion, with an inflection point at maximal plasmon-cyclotron coupling. In contrast, in bilayer graphene we recover and map a magnetoplasmon dispersion consistent with the conventional Schr\"odinger-type picture. These results establish graphene TeraFET devices as a robust on-chip platform for resonant magnetoplasmonics at terahertz frequencies, enabling magnetically programmable, frequency-selective photonics and opening avenues toward photodetectors with enhanced sensitivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00180v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan A. Delgado-Notario, Cedric Bray, Elsa Perez-Martin, Ben Benhamou-Bui, Namrata Saha, Sahil Parvez, Christophe. Consejo, Guillaume Sigu, Salah Benlemqwanssa, Laurent Bonnet, Takashi Taniguchi, Kenji Watanabe, Jos\'e M. Caridad, Sergey S. Krishtopenko, Yahya M. Meziani, Benoit Jouault, J\'er\'emie Torres, Sandra Ruffenach, Fr\'ed\'eric Teppe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust semiclassical magnetization plateau in the kagome lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00223</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00223v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Inspired by recent observations of the $1/3$ magnetization plateau in kagome-based magnets, we investigate the $J_1-J_2$ Heisenberg model on the kagome lattice under the influence of an external magnetic field. Although the classical ground state at zero field depends on the sign of $J_2$, we find a robust $1/3$ semiclassical magnetization plateau in both cases. The mechanism that stabilizes this plateau is analogous to that observed in the triangular lattice, where quantum fluctuations select a collinear state from the degenerate classical manifold. We calculate the plateau width, which shows a weak dependence on $J_2$, using nonlinear spin-wave theory. Additionally, we find that a straightforward approach based on linear spin-wave yields quantitatively accurate results even for $S=1/2$. Furthermore, we identify a magnetization jump at the saturation field when $J_2=0$; this jump is related to the presence of a flat band and disappears for $J_2 \neq 0$. Our study demonstrates that a semiclassical approach effectively captures the $1/3$ plateau in the kagome lattice and serves as a valuable tool for interpreting experimental and numerical results alike.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00223v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel Capelo, Eric C. Andrade</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetosynthesis effect on the structure and ground state of Cu$^{2+}$-based antiferromagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00253v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Subtle synthetic variables can have an outsizes influence on the crystal structure and magnetic properties of a material, particularly those of quantum materials. In this work, we investigate the impact of synthesis under a magnetic field (magnetosynthesis) on the crystal structure and magnetic properties of several Cu$^{2+}$ ($S=1/2$) based materials with antiferromagnetic interactions and varying levels of magnetic frustration, from simple antiferromagnets to a quantum spin liquid. We employ small (0.09 - 0.37 T) magnetic fields applied during low-temperature hydrothermal or evaporative synthesis of the simple antiferromagnet CuCl$_2\cdot$2H$_2$O, the canted antiferromagnet (Cu,Zn)$_3$Cl$_4$(OH)$_2\cdot$2H$_2$O, the frustrated and canted antiferromagnet atacamite Cu$_2$(OH)$_3$Cl, and the highly frustrated quantum spin liquid herbertsmithite Cu$_3$Zn(OH)$_6$Cl$_2$. We found that (Cu,Zn)$_3$Cl$_4$(OH)$_2\cdot$2H$_2$O experiences structural changes well above its magnetic transition. Atacamite Cu$_2$(OH)$_3$Cl synthesized under a 0.19 T field experiences a 0.15 K (~3%) decrease in its N\'eel transition temperature and a significant strengthening of its antiferromagnetic interactions, suggesting that magnetosynthesis can influence the ground state of moderately frustrated materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00253v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Micaela E. Primer, Anna A. Berseneva, Ayesha Ulde, Wenhao Sun, Rebecca W. Smaha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpretable Graph Neural Networks for Classifying Structure and Magnetism in Delafossite Compounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00292v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Delafossites (ABC2, where A and B are metals and C is a chalcogen) are a versatile family of quantum materials and layered oxides/chalcogenides whose properties are highly sensitive to atomic composition and stacking geometry. Their broad chemical tunability makes them an ideal platform for large-scale combinatorial exploration and high-throughput computational screening with desirable quantum properties. In this work, we employ a Concept Whitening Graph Neural Network, a gray-box AI model, to classify delafossite structures by stacking sequence and magnetic states. By aligning learned representations with human-interpretable physical concepts, this gray-box approach enables both accurate prediction and insight into the structural and chemical features driving magnetic behavior. The magnetic-ordering models achieved validation accuracies exceeding 80 percent, with a further slight uptick observed in the model incorporating the largest number of concepts. Concept alignment analysis revealed measurable learning across nine physically meaningful descriptors, with coefficients of determination ranging from approximately 0.6 for the d-shell valence-electron concepts to 0.4-0.5 for the magnetic coupling parameters. Furthermore, we mapped the concept importances onto the material graph representation, elucidating interpretable physical trends and the progression of stable concept-aligned regions across training. These results demonstrate the potential of interpretable graph-based learning to capture the underlying physics of complex materials systems and provide an interpretable framework for accelerating the discovery and understanding of delafossites and related crystalline materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00292v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jovin Ryan Joseph, Do Hoon Kiem, Sinchul Yeom, Mina Yoon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dual instability of superconductivity from oxygen defects in La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_{7+\delta}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00301v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We uncover a dual mechanism by which oxygen defects suppress superconductivity in the bilayer nickelate La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_{7+\delta}$ using density functional theory, dynamical mean-field theory, and functional renormalization group analysis. Apical vacancies and interbilayer interstitials emerge as the dominant low-energy defect species and are further stabilized by orthorhombic domain walls. These two defect classes drive the electronic structure in opposing directions. Vacancy-induced disorder generates local magnetic moments and promotes Anderson localization at moderate concentrations, whereas periodic interstitial ordering yields a coherent but weakly correlated metallic background that fails to support superconductivity. These findings highlight the decisive role of oxygen defects in shaping the superconducting and provide microscopic guidance for improving superconductivity through controlled defect engineering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00301v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peiheng Jiang, Jie Li, Yu-Han Cao, Xiaodong Cao, Zhicheng Zhong, Yi Lu, Qiang-Hua Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classification of coherent peaks in two-terminal quantum devices into normal and anomalous Kondo peaks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00330v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Coherent peaks arising in the differential conductance of quantum dot (QD) and quantum point contact (QPC) devices are classified into two categories, normal and anomalous Kondo peaks, according to the underlying spin dynamics and the form of the scaling function to which the scaled temperature-dependent linear conductance collapses. The zero-bias peaks (ZBPs) observed in QPCs and in the triplet state of the even sector of quantum dot single-electron transistors (QDSETs) are identified as normal Kondo peaks, formed by spin dynamics involving spin exchange, a symbolic characteristic of the Kondo effect. For these ZBPs, the scaling temperature coincides with half the full width at half maximum (FWHM). In contrast, the ZBP observed in the odd sector of QDSETs and all finite-bias coherent peaks, including the coherent side peaks of QPCs and the split ZBP in the singlet state of the QDSET even sector, are identified as anomalous Kondo peaks, because they arise from spin dynamics without spin exchange, and their scaling temperature does not coincide with half the FWHM. To support these findings, we reproduce gate-voltage-dependent differential conductance line shapes measured in the odd sector of a QDSET, demonstrating that its ZBP originates from a combination of two coherent side peaks explicitly observed in QPCs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00330v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jongbae Hong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Band inversion transition in HgTe nanowire grown along the [001] direction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00334</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00334v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The low-energy effective Hamiltonian of a cylindrical HgTe nanowire grown along the [001] crystallographic direction is constructed by using the perturbation theory. Both the anisotropic term and the bulk inversion asymmetry term of the Kane model are taken into account. Although the anisotropic term has converted the crossing between the $E_{1}$ and $H_{1}$ subbands into an anticrossing at $k_{z}R\!=\!0$, the gap-closing-and-reopening transition in the subband structure can still occur at the wave vectors $k_{z}R\!\approx\!\pm0.24$ for critical nanowire radius $R\!\approx\!3.45$ nm. The bulk inversion asymmetry does not contribute to the low-energy effective Hamiltonian, i.e., there is no spin splitting in the $E_{1}$, $H_{1}$, and $H_{2}$ subbands for a [001] oriented cylindrical nanowire.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00334v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rui Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent Anomalous and Topological Hall Responses in an Epitaxial Ferromagnetic Weyl Nodal-Line metal Fe5Si3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00340</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00340v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The interplay between real and reciprocal space topology yields intrinsically linked transport phenomena in magnetic Weyl systems, wherein the broken time-reversal symmetry, strong Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction, and pronounced uniaxial anisotropy stabilize the momentum-space Berry-curvature monopoles (Weyl nodes) and real-space chiral spin textures. We present a combined first-principles and experimental study of epitaxial Fe5Si3 thin films, establishing them as a magnetic Weyl nodal-line material. First-principles Density Functional Theory (DFT) calculations unambiguously reveal that Fe5Si3 hosts a topologically nontrivial electronic structure containing six pairs of Weyl nodes at or near the Fermi level, accompanied by pronounced Berry curvature at high-symmetry points of the Brillouin Zone. High-quality epitaxial films exhibit robust ferromagnetism with a Curie temperature of ~370 K and strong magneto crystalline anisotropy. The magneto transport measurements on epitaxial films reveal the corresponding Berry curvature-driven responses, including a significantly large intrinsic anomalous Hall conductivity of 504 S/cm and a high anomalous Hall angle of 5.5%, which is in good agreement with DFT calculations. A negative and non-saturating longitudinal magnetoresistance is observed, consistent with a chiral-anomaly contribution from Weyl fermions near the Fermi level (EF). Furthermore, a substantial topological Hall resistivity of 1.6 {\mu}{\Omega} cm robust across a wide temperature range, indicating the possibility of robust chiral spin textures in the thin-film geometry. These combined theoretical and experimental results establish Fe5Si3 as a unique, low-cost, centrosymmetric magnetic Weyl nodal-line material, providing a versatile platform for exploring coupled real and reciprocal space topologies in topological spintronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00340v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shubhashish Pati, Sonali Srotaswini Pradhan, Abhay Pandey, Nikita Sharma, Nanhe Kumar Gupta, Nakul Kumar, Nidhi Shukla, Saurav Singh, Vidhi Jain,  Mitali, V. Kanchana, Sujeet Chaudhary</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantized nonlinear transport and its breakdown in Fermi gases with Berry curvature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00356</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00356v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantized transport not only exist in gapped topological states but also in metallic states. Recently, Kane proposed a quantized nonlinear conductance in ballistic metals whose value is determined by the Euler characteristic of the Fermi sea [Phys. Rev. Lett. 128, 076801 (2022)]. In this paper, we consider two-dimensional noninteracting fermionic systems whose Fermi surface has nonvanishing Berry curvature. We find that the Berry curvature at the Fermi surface does not affect the quantized nonlinear transport for translationally invariant systems. When spatial inhomogeneity is introduced, such quantization breaks down due to the combined effect of Berry curvature and the gradient of local potential. Such breakdown of quantization can be observed in trapped ultracold atoms with topological bands.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00356v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fan Yang, Xingyu Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Precise computation of universal corner entanglement entropy at 2+1 dimension: From Ising to Gaussian quantum critical points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00382</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00382v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Computing the subleading logarithmic term in the entanglement entropy (EE) of (2+1)d quantum many-body systems remains a significant challenge, despite its critical role in revealing universal information about quantum states and quantum critical points (QCPs). Capitalizing on recent algorithmic advances that enable the stable calculation of EE as an exponential observable, we develop a {\it bubble basis} projector quantum Monte Carlo (QMC) algorithm to precisely and efficiently compute the universal corner EE along a parameter trajectory connecting the Ising and Gaussian QCPs; where in the latter case there exists an analytic value to benchmark with. Our approach eliminates the dominant area-law term directly within the QMC sampling, thereby promoting the coveted subleading logarithmic term to the leading contribution. We apply this technique to calculate the EE in a (2+1)d square-lattice transverse-field Ising model augmented with a four-body interaction, tracing a path from the Ising to the Gaussian QCPs and then to the first-order transition. The consistent values obtained for the universal corner EE along the path validate the reliability and precision of our approach for extracting challenging entanglement properties. These results establish the long-sought connection between the universal values of an exactly solvable limit and those of a strongly correlated regime at (2+1)d.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00382v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ben Lee-Yeung Ngai, Justin Tim-Lok Chau, Junchen Rong, Yuan Da Liao, Zi Yang Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Altermagnetic boosting of chiral phonons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00388</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00388v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Chirality characterizes the asymmetry between a structure and its mirror image and underlies a wide range of chiral functionalities. In crystallographically chiral materials, phonons with non-zero linear momentum $\textbf{k}$ can acquire a $k$-induced longitudinal magnetization, giving rise to chiral phonons. Helical spin order, with its proper screw-type configuration, breaks all mirror symmetries and therefore carries magnetic chirality. Such helical spins also generate non-relativistic spin splitting for any quasiparticle excitations propagating along the screw axis. To explore the possible connection between chiral phonons and magnetic chirality, we investigated the crystallographically polar and chiral compound (Mn,Ni)$_3$TeO$_6$, which hosts three distinct states: a paramagnetic state, a helical spin state with magnetic chirality, and a collinear spin state without magnetic chirality. We find an approximately tenfold enhancement of chiral-phonon coupling in the helical spin state along the screw axis, compared with both the paramagnetic and collinear spin states. These results identify a new route to amplify chiral phonons through an altermagnetic effect arising from the broken parity-time symmetry in helical spins. %from non-relativistic spin splitting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00388v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Okamoto, C. Y. Mou, H. Y. Huang, G. Channagowdra, C. Won, K. Du, X. Fang, E. V. Komleva, C. T. Chen, S. V. Streltsov, A. Fujimori, S-W. Cheong, D. J. Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wafer-Scale Single-Crystalline Monolayer Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00394</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00394v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Producing large-area single-crystalline graphene is key to realizing its full potential in advanced applications, including twistronics. Yet, controlling graphene growth kinetics to avoid grain boundaries or multilayer growth remains challenging. Here, we demonstrate single-crystalline graphene free from multilayer domains via one-step delamination of epitaxial graphene from silicon carbide (SiC). This is enabled by a specific surface reconstruction of 4H-SiC(0001) achieved in our growth conditions. High crystalline quality is confirmed by the observation of the half-integer quantum Hall effect -- the hallmark of monolayer graphene -- in near cm-sized crystals. The scalability of our process, explored with 4''-wafers, represents an advance toward large-scale integration of high-performance graphene applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00394v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johanna Huhtasaari, Joyal Jain Palakulam, Awse Salha, Per Hyldgaard, Elsebeth Schr\"oder, Magnus H{\aa}rdensson Berntsen, Oscar Tjernberg, Manasi Shah, Rodrigo Martinez-Duarte, Hans He, Johannes Hofmann, Thilo Bauch, Naveen Shetty, Samuel Lara-Avila</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiterminal Ballistic Josephson Effect in Monocrystalline Gold</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00409v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report on the realization of a planar, quasi-ballistic Josephson junction array using a Au micron-sized single-crystal. The system exhibits a nonlocal, multiterminal Josephson effect, where the supercurrent between any two superconducting leads is governed by the phase coherence across the entire crystal. Key evidence includes a non-monotonic dependence of the critical current on junction length and magnetic interference patterns with periods corresponding to the shared normal-metal area. Nonlocal transport measurements further confirm that the supercurrent between two electrodes depends on the phase configuration of all the others. Our results, supported by a developed theoretical model, establish a platform for exploring complex superconducting phenomena in multiterminal ballistic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00409v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. B. Polevoy, G. A. Bobkov, D. S. Kalashnikov, A. G. Shishkin, I. V. Trofimov, A. M. Bobkov, M. A. Tarkhov, I. V. Bobkova, V. S. Stolyarov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theory of planar quasi-ballistic Josephson junctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00411</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00411v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a theoretical framework for planar quasi-ballistic Josephson junctions, where multiple superconducting leads are coupled through a large, nearly ballistic normal metal crystal. Our approach, based on quasiclassical Eilenberger equations, accounts for the dominant role of electron reflections from the crystal surfaces or single impurities, a mechanism distinct from both purely ballistic and diffusive limits. We calculate the critical current between superconducting leads for various geometries, examining its dependence on temperature and magnetic field. Crucially, we demonstrate that in multi-terminal setups, the junctions are not independent but form a strongly coupled system. The theory successfully explains key experimental observations from a companion work, including a non-monotonic dependence of the critical current on the interlayer length, providing a foundation for designing and understanding complex multi-terminal Josephson systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00411v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. A. Bobkov, I. V. Bobkova, A. M. Bobkov, K. B. Polevoy, V. S. Stolyarov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Rapid Thermal Chemical Vapor Deposition System for Fast Synthesis of Epitaxial Graphene Under Ambient Pressure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00447</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00447v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Graphene has emerged as a promising material for next-generation electronic and thermal devices owing to its exceptional charge transport and thermal conductivity. However, high-quality samples are predominantly obtained via mechanical exfoliation from graphite crystals, a process that inherently lacks scalability. Despite extensive efforts toward large-area synthesis, cost-effective approaches for producing high-quality, large-area, single-crystalline graphene with fast turnaround time remain limited. Here, we report the design, fabrication, and performance benchmarking of a rapid thermal chemical vapor deposition (RTCVD) system capable of synthesizing epitaxial monolayer graphene under atmospheric pressure. The entire growth process, from sample loading to unloading, is achieved within $25$ minutes with a temperature ramp rate exceeding $23^\circ\mathrm{C}/s$. Growth at atmospheric pressure eliminates the need for vacuum components, thereby reducing both system complexity and operational costs. The structural and electronic quality of epitaxial graphene is comprehensively characterized using Raman spectroscopy, selected area electron diffraction (SAED), and magnetotransport measurements, which reveal signatures of quantum Hall effect in synthesized graphene samples. Furthermore, we demonstrate van der Waals epitaxial growth of palladium (Pd) thin films on graphene transferred to Si/SiO$_{2}$ substrates, establishing its single-crystalline nature over a large area and its potential as a versatile platform for subsequent heteroepitaxial growth.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00447v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shikhar Kumar Gupta, Meet Ghelani, Pragna Datta, Subhalakshmi Guha, Shivesh Yadav, Nilesh Kulkarni, Maheshwar Gokhale, Bhagyashree Chalke, Devendra Buddhikot, Naveen Paneri, Lavudya Devendar, Arnab Bhattacharya, Shouvik Chatterjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterizing topology at nonzero temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00464v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We compare different methods for characterizing topology at nonzero temperatures, as applied to one-dimensional inversion-symmetric fermionic chains and focusing on the Su-Schrieffer-Heeger model with nearest- and next-nearest-neighbor hopping. Whilst the ensemble geometric phase, a mixed-state generalization of the Zak phase remains well defined at nonzero temperature, the modulus of the corresponding expectation value vanishes in the thermodynamic limit, limiting its practical use. To develop a diagnostic that is suitable also for very large systems, we introduce local density operators acting on neighboring sites, which distinguish topological phases by comparing their expectation values. The topological phase is identified from the relative magnitude of these expectation values, which only requires measuring two local expectation values at nonzero temperature, together with one additional nonlocal expectation value when next-nearest-neighbor hopping is included. In addition, we generalize the local chiral marker to mixed Gaussian states, fully determined by its single-particle correlation matrix, with a nonzero purity gap in their effective single-particle Hamiltonian. The presence of a purity gap ensures that the correlation matrix can be adiabatically flattened to an effective projector. Evaluating the chiral marker with respect to the band-flattened correlation matrix yields a real space topological invariant that coincides with the winding number in the zero temperature limit. The ensemble geometric phase, the local density operators, and the local chiral marker, provide complementary schemes to identify and measure topological phases of the Su-Schrieffer-Heeger chain beyond pure states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00464v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julia D. Hannukainen, Nigel R. Cooper</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Near-flat-band-driven violation of Pauli limit in heavy fermion superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00486</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00486v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Heavy-fermion superconductors often display upper critical fields that exceed the conventional Pauli paramagnetic limit, indicating that strong correlations and hybridized quasiparticle bands play an essential role in the paramagnetic pair-breaking process. Within the two-dimensional Kondo-Heisenberg model, we perform a self-consistent mean-field analysis of spin-singlet s-, extended-s-, and d-wave pairing under Zeeman fields, and compute the critical field Bc, the transition temperature Tc, and the Clogston-Chandrasekhar ratio rCC. We find that rCC increases sharply as the conduction filling approaches half filling. This enhancement arises from the weakly dispersive region of the lower hybridized band, where the strongly reduced Fermi velocity diminishes the normal-state paramagnetic energy and stabilizes superconductivity. At fixed filling, the distinct JH dependences among the three pairing channels reflect the sensitivity of Pauli limiting to both band curvature and the structure of the order parameter. These results provide microscopic evidence that proximity to a near-flat hybridized band offers a robust route to enhanced Pauli-limiting fields in heavy-fermion superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00486v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan-Xiao Wang, Yin Zhong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dressing composite fermions with artificial intelligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00527v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent variational studies have demonstrated that the strongly correlated ground states of the fractional quantum Hall (FQH) effect can be captured using machine learning approaches starting from no prior knowledge of the underlying physics. We introduce a complementary framework that instead starts from Jain's composite-fermion (CF) wavefunctions, which accurately describe FQH states as weakly interacting states of CFs at fillings $\nu = n/(2pn+1)$ in an idealized limit. As we move away from this idealized limit to one more in line with experimental reality, we expect CFs to become dressed much like the electrons of a noninteracting system, which are dressed by neutral excitations as interaction is turned on adiabatically, as in Landau's Fermi-liquid theory. We model this dressing using a Feynman-Cohen-style backflow approach, implemented through symmetry-preserving neural networks-a framework we refer to as CF-Flow. CF-Flow achieves competitive accuracy with substantially greater computational efficiency and scales to systems of $\gtrsim 26$ electrons. At fillings $\nu = 1/3$ and $2/5$, as a function of Landau-level mixing strength, CF-Flow produces ground-state energies with low local-energy variance that are nearly indistinguishable from those obtained using the fixed-phase diffusion Monte Carlo (fp-DMC) method, even though the latter constrains the wavefunction phase to that of the lowest Landau level-thereby providing insight into why fp-DMC has been successful in giving an accurate quantitative account of several experiments. Finally, the symmetry-preserving architecture of CF-Flow enables access to excited states and computation of the transport gap at $\nu = 1/3$, where we find, unexpectedly, that it decays exponentially toward a finite value in the limit of large Landau-level mixing, suggesting a first-order transition from the FQH liquid to a non-FQH state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00527v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mytraya Gattu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-wave emission with current-controlled frequency by a PMA-based spin-Hall oscillator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00593v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spin-torque and spin-Hall oscillators (SHOs) have emerged as promising candidates for building blocks in neuromorphic computing due to their ability to synchronize mutually, a process that can be mediated by propagating spin waves. We demonstrate a SHO that takes advantage of a low-damping magnetic garnet with dominant perpendicular magnetic anisotropy (PMA), namely gallium-substituted yttrium-iron-garnet (Ga:YIG). In-plane magnetized Ga:YIG allows for the operation at a high efficiency level while also enabling resonant spin-wave emission. A nonlinear self-localization of the excitation is avoided by exploiting the positive nonlinear frequency shift, which facilitates a current-controlled frequency of the emitted spin waves. Via micro-focused Brillouin light scattering spectroscopy, we investigate the properties of the local auto-oscillation and its spin-wave emission. Multiple modes are excited and compete internally, with two propagating modes detected up to distances larger than \SI{10}{\micro\meter}. Their frequencies combine to an extended frequency bandwidth of approximately \SI{1.6}{\giga\hertz}. The experimentally observed two-mode system and its transition to a single mode at higher currents are reproduced via micromagnetic simulations, which account for spatial variation of the PMA arising due to the microstructures on Ga:YIG. Our results propose a promising platform for hosting SHOs, interconnected via propagating spin waves with particular relevance to neuromorphic computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00593v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Moritz Bechberger, David Breitbach, Abbas Koujok, Bj\"orn Heinz, Carsten Dubs, Abbass Hamadeh, Philipp Pirro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Carrier localization and dynamics in In$_{0.10}$Ga$_{0.90}$N: the impact of alloying and Si doping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00603v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Alloying and doping are crucial for enhancing the electronic and optical properties of semiconductors while simultaneously introducing disorder. This report explores the effects of alloying and Si (0.5 at.\%) doping on In$_{0.10}$Ga$_{0.90}$N thin films that were grown by metal-organic vapor phase epitaxy. Post-growth X-ray diffraction measurements indicate that Si doping does not affect the lattice parameters and screw dislocations but significantly increases the edge dislocation density. Temperature-dependent time-resolved photoluminescence spectroscopy shows that Si-doped In$_{0.10}$Ga$_{0.90}$N exhibits higher photoluminescence intensity, blue-shifted peaks, narrower emission linewidths, and quenching of lower energy sidebands when compared to pristine In$_{0.10}$Ga$_{0.90}$N. The peak energies of the most dominant feature, the donor-bound exciton, for both samples show an $S$-shape behavior indicating the presence of disorder. Although doping improves luminescence, it also introduces deeper localized states. This suggests that impurity-induced disorder outweighs compositional fluctuations, as confirmed by higher disorder parameters and Stokes shifts. Thus, the Si doping leads to increased localization, reducing nonradiative recombination channels while enhancing radiative processes. The deeper states in the doped sample confirm improved carrier confinement, and their saturation leads to early thermalization, thereby lowering the red-blue shift transition from 165 K to about 50 K. Even though the high doping level makes Si-doped In$_{0.10}$Ga$_{0.90}$N a degenerate system, it exhibits enhanced luminescence properties. These findings shed light on the impact of silicon doping on charge transport in InGaN alloys for optoelectronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00603v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ongeziwe Mpatani, Dominik Muth, Anton Kr\"uger, Rajdeep Adhikari, Alberta Bonanni, Marina Gerhard, Hilary Masenda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of Electrical Contacts on Transition Metal Dichalcogenides-Based Acoustoelectric and Acousto-Photoelectric Devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00606</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00606v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the impact of electrical contact barriers in hybrid WSe$_2$-LiNbO$_3$-based acoustoelectric and acousto-photoelectric devices using a combination of scanning photocurrent and acousto-electric current spectroscopy. Static scanning photocurrent measurements provide a qualitative measure of the band-bending and spatial distribution of the Schottky barrier between semiconducting WSe$_2$ and gold electrodes whereas the surface acoustic wave-induced acousto-electric current reveals the height of the tunnelling barrier created by the van der Waals gap between the multilayered WSe$_2$ flake and the gold electrodes in addition to the Schottky barrier. The combination of both techniques shows a ten-fold increase in the photocurrent by the acoustic wave. Moreover, the observed spatial redistribution of the current is attributed to the interplay between the contact properties at the source and drain electrodes and the charge carrier dynamics induced by the surface acoustic wave. The ratio of acoustic wavelength to the electrical channel length is found to impact the SAW-induced charge carrier transport. For a channel length shorter than one acoustic wavelength, carriers undergo a seesaw-like motion which changes to charge conveyance for channel lengths comparable or exceeding the acoustic wavelength.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00606v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acsaelm.5c01446</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ACS Applied Electronic Materials 7, 9717-9728 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Mayer, Felix M. Ehring, Clemens Strobl, Matthias Wei{\ss}, Ursula Wurstbauer, Hubert J. Krenner, Emeline D. S. Nysten</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-resolved Mott crossover and entanglement in the half-filled Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00613</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00613v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study interaction-driven crossover from a correlated metallic state to Mott-insulating state on the half-filled 3x3 square cluster using exact diagonalization in the S=1/2 and S=3/2 sectors. Using complementary diagnostics such as order parameters, principal component analysis (PCA) of correlation matrices and quantum geometry, we obtain a unified, data-driven characterization of the crossover. All three diagnostics consistently identify a broad crossover centered in the weak-to-intermediate coupling regime U~2-6; charge gaps open rapidly, double occupancy suppresses, local moments form, entanglement is significantly reduced, PCA concentrates variance into a few dominant modes and the distance matrices reveals rapid wavefunction reorganization. Our multi-pronged approach establishes the Mott crossover as a smooth but well defined reorganization of electronic correlations with pronounced spin-sector dependence in finite systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00613v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Md Fahad Equbal, M. A. H. Ahsan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electric Polarization from Nonpolar Phonons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00628v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Born effective charge (BEC), a fundamental quantity in lattice dynamics and ferroelectric theory, provides a quantitative measure of linear polarization response to ionic displacements. However, it does not account for higher-order effects, which can play a significant role in certain materials, such as fluorite HfO$_2$. In this letter, we extend the BEC framework by introducing the concept of second-order dynamical charge and mode effective charge. Using first-principles calculations, we demonstrate that specific combinations of nonpolar phonon modes in many oxides can induce substantial second-order polarizations, reaching magnitudes comparable to those of intrinsically polar modes. Through a symmetry-based analysis of the charge density, we elucidate the microscopic origin of these effects, tracing them to variations in bond covalency and local electronic rearrangements. We also demonstrate large second-order mode effective charge in well-studied perovskites such as SrTiO$_3$, highlighting the generality of these phenomena. Our results reveal a previously unrecognized mechanism that drives polarization in crystalline solids, offering new insights into the design principles of next-generation ferroelectric, piezoelectric and multifunctional materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00628v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seongjoo Jung, Turan Birol</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling of a Mutual-Information Distance in One-dimensional Quantum Spin Chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00649</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00649v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a geometric scaling relation that characterizes the local scale behavior of correlations using the informational distance $d_E = K_0/\sqrt{I}$, where $I$ is the mutual information. We define a geometric conversion factor, $G \equiv \partial_r d_E$, which quantifies the local scale. We show that $G$ relates directly to $I$ via $G \propto I^{\kappa}$. For systems with power-law correlations $I(r) \sim r^{-X}$, the metric scaling exponent is $\kappa = 1/X - 1/2$. A key consequence is that the geometric scale $G$ is uniform (position-independent) if and only if $\kappa = 0$, which occurs precisely at $X = 2$. This identifies $X = 2$ as the unique condition for a uniform and metric informational distance. We validate this relation using DMRG simulations of the 1D XXZ chain and exact results for the XX model. We demonstrate two falsifiable diagnostics: (i) $G(r)$ is flat in the bulk at criticality ($X \approx 2$) but varies strongly when gapped; (ii) a coordinate-agnostic slope test of $\log G$ versus $\log I$ at the XX benchmark ($X = 2$) yields $\kappa \simeq 0$. This approach provides a coordinate-independent method for identifying scaling regimes that helps to reduce ambiguity from non-universal amplitudes and from the fitting choices in standard power-law analyses, and defines a simple post-processing pipeline that can be applied directly to numerical or experimental mutual-information data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00649v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Beau Leighton-Trudel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlocal Josephson diode effect in minimal Kitaev chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00664</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00664v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the emergence of the nonlocal Josephson effect in a system composed of three laterally coupled minimal Kitaev chains and exploit it to realize the nonlocal Josephson diode effect. We find that an imbalance between crossed Andreev reflections and electron cotunneling in the middle Kitaev chain gives rise to an asymmetric $2\pi$-periodic phase-dependent Andreev spectrum, controlled by the superconducting phases across the left and right junctions. We then show that the asymmetric Andreev spectrum, formed by hybridized Andreev bound states at the left and right junctions, enables a supercurrent across one junction via the phase difference at the other junction, thereby signaling the nonlocal Josephson effect. Notably, these nonlocal Josephson supercurrents exhibit distinct positive and negative critical currents, demonstrating the realization of the nonlocal Josephson diode effect with highly tunable polarity and efficiencies exceeding $50\%$. The nonlocal Josephson diode effect requires breaking local time-reversal and local charge-conjugation symmetries, with the latter being unique to minimal Kitaev chains. Our results establish minimal Kitaev chains as a highly controllable platform for engineering nonlocal Josephson phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00664v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jorge Cayao, Masatoshi Sato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Dimensionally Consistent Size-Strain Plot Method for Crystallite Size and Microstrain Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00689</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00689v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: X-ray diffraction (XRD) peak broadening analysis remains a cornerstone for quantifying crystallite size and lattice microstrain in materials. Among various approaches, the Size Strain Plot (SSP) method is widely employed for its conceptual simplicity and ease of use. However, this study reveals that the equation most commonly applied in SSP analysis is dimensionally inconsistent, a critical flaw that has gone largely unnoticed and replicated across decades of materials research. This pervasive error raises concerns about the validity of a significant body of published microstructural data. By tracing the historical origin of the misformulated equation, we demonstrate how a seemingly minor oversight evolved into a widely accepted standard practice within the field. We then present a dimensionally consistent formulation that restores physical meaning and analytical reliability to the SSP method. The corrected framework re-establishes the SSP approach as a robust and physically valid tool for XRD-based microstructural characterization. \en</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00689v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jallcom.2025.185324</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Alloys and Compounds 1048, 185324 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Anand Pal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First-principles calculations of elasto-optical properties of $R$Te$_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00726v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rare-earth tritellurides ($R$Te$_3$) exhibit complex charge-density-wave (CDW) phases intertwined with lattice symmetry, offering a platform to explore unconventional symmetry breaking in correlated materials. Elasto-optical probing, which detects strain-induced changes in birefringence, provides a non-invasive approach to visualize anisotropy and emergent order in these quasi-two-dimensional systems. However, the magnitude and symmetry of the expected optical response remain poorly quantified, hindering experimental interpretation. Here, we perform first-principles calculations of the elastic, dielectric, and piezo-optical tensors of NdTe$_3$ to establish a quantitative framework for strain-induced optical anisotropy. These results establish a quantitative link between lattice strain and optical response in $R$Te$_3$, providing a predictive framework for probing symmetry-breaking states via elasto-birefringence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00726v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kuiqing Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bi-altermagnetism unveiled by sublattice-specific circular dichroism in resonant inelastic X-ray scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00737</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00737v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An altermagnet is a recently identified class of magnets that exhibit a zero net magnetic moment but break symmetry under the combined operations of parity and time reversal. It typically consists of two magnetic sites of opposite spins related by rotation within the unit cell. Here, we use circular dichroism (CD) in resonant inelastic X-ray scattering (RIXS) to identify a new form of altermagnetism, namely bi-altermagnetism, in the correlated insulator Fe2Mo3O8, which comprises two altermagnetic sublattices: one with alternating quasi-octahedral Fe environments and the other with alternating tetrahedral Fe environments. We experimentally revealed the emergence of CD in an achiral, zero-magnetization system, thereby probing mirror-symmetry breaking associated with altermagnetic order. Notably, the CD appeared at sublattice-specific excitations of the octahedral and tetrahedral sites, indicating symmetry breaking in both altermagnetic sublattices. Calculations based on a model with the bi-altermagnetic order along the c axis successfully reproduce the observed CD. Our findings provide compelling evidence for bi-altermagnetism in Fe2Mo3O8, and showcase the use of RIXS-CD as a probe of magnetic sublattices in systems with zero net magnetization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00737v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Channagowdra, A. Singh, H. Y. Huang, M. Furo, Bin Gao, Pengcheng Dai, C. T. Chen, J. Kunes, A. Fujimori, S-W. Cheong, A. Hariki, D. J. Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for itinerant electron-local moment interaction in Li-doped $\alpha$-MnTe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00747v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We use inelastic neutron scattering to study the impact of Li doping on the semiconducting altermagnet $\alpha$-MnTe. Introducing Li results in a spin reorientation from in-plane to out-of-plane and increases the density of itinerant carriers. While the spin waves in Li-doped $\alpha$-MnTe remain largely Heisenberg-like, there is significant spin wave broadening across the entire Brillouin zone, signaling enhanced magnon damping induced by itinerant carriers. By extracting the local dynamic susceptibility and applying the total moment sum rule, we find that both undoped and Li-doped $\alpha$-MnTe exhibit the full expected Mn$^{2+}$ local moment of $\approx5.9~\mu_\mathrm{B}$ with $S=5/2$. These results demonstrate that Li-doped $\alpha$-MnTe hosts robust local-moment magnetism whose interactions are mediated via Ruderman-Kittel-Kasuya-Yosida-type interactions, highlighting the importance of itinerant carriers in magneto-transport and spin dynamic properties of altermagnets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00747v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tingjun Zhang, Steven J. Gomez Alvarado, Sijie Xu, Travis J. Williams, Xiaoping Wang, Junhong He, Matthew B. Stone, Colin Sarkis, Feng Ye, Zhaoyu Liu, Jinyulin Li, Aparna Jayakumar, Zehao Wang, Yaofeng Xie, Ching-Wu Chu, Liangzi Deng, Emilia Morosan, Pengcheng Dai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of individual vortex penetration in a coplanar superconducting resonator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00790</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00790v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate the detection and control of individual Abrikosov vortices in superconducting microwave resonators. $\lambda/4$ resonators with a narrowed region near the grounded end acting as a vortex trap were fabricated and studied using microwave transmission spectroscopy at millikelvin temperatures. Sharp stepwise drops in resonance frequency are detected as a function of increasing external magnetic field, attributed to the entry of individual Abrikosov vortices in the narrow region. This interpretation is confirmed by NV center magnetometry revealing discrete vortex entry events on increasing field. Our results establish a method to investigate and manipulate the states of Abrikosov vortices with microwaves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00790v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kirill Shulga, Shunsuke Nishimura, Pavel A. Volkov, Ryota Hasegawa, Miu Hirano, Takeyuki Tsuji, Takayuki Iwasaki, Mutsuko Hatano, Kento Sasaki, Kensuke Kobayashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vortex configuration dependent equilibrium and non-equilibrium states in two-dimensional quantum turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00800</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00800v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we analyze the evolution of four vortex configurations, namely, dipole, plasma, cluster, and lattice, using the two-dimensional mean-field Gross-Pitaevskii equation, focusing on their dynamical decay and approach to the equilibrium. Our analysis reveals that the cluster vortex configuration reaches equilibrium more rapidly than the others, while the dipole, plasma, and lattice configurations exhibit persistent non-equilibrium behavior, tending toward non-thermal fixed points. Specifically, the cluster configuration follows Kolmogorov-like scaling ($\varepsilon^{i}(k)\sim k^{-5/3}$) in the incompressible spectrum, while the other configurations follow Vinen-like scaling ($\varepsilon^{i}(k)\sim k^{-1}$). In the compressible spectrum, the cluster case exhibits a $k$ scaling, indicating full mode equilibration, while for the other configurations, the modes thermalize only above a critical wave number. Additionally, the transfer function for the cluster configuration displays a Gaussian distribution, typical of equilibrium states, while the other configurations exhibit skewed Gaussian or exponential distributions, indicative of their non-equilibrium nature. Finally, the particle number spectra show that the cluster case follows dynamical scaling closer to equilibrium, while the dipole, plasma, and lattice configurations evolve towards non-thermal fixed points. Our findings provide new insights into the dynamics of vortex configurations and their approach to equilibrium or non-equilibrium states, offering guidance for future studies on quantum turbulence and its control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00800v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shawan K. Jha, Makoto Tsubota, Pankaj K. Mishra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Fabrication of Graphene/Perovskite Oxide Hybrid Heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00815</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00815v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hybrid heterostructures composed of graphene and perovskite oxides provide a promising platform for exploiting synergetic interfacial functionalities. Conventional fabrication methods of the hybrid heterostructures rely on transferring graphene grown on metallic substrates-- a process that is time-consuming, labor-intensive, and prone to introducing numerous defects. In this study, we present a universal, catalyst-free method for the direct growth of graphene on insulating substrates by employing three different perovskite oxide substrates (SrTiO$_3$, LaAlO$_3$, and (La$_{0.18}$Sr$_{0.82}$)(Al$_{0.59}$Ta$_{0.41}$)O$_3$) using atmospheric chemical vapor deposition. Comprehensive characterization via Raman spectroscopy, X-ray spectroscopy, scanning probe microscopy, and electron microscopy confirmed the formation of a uniform, continuous monolayer graphene on all substrates. We identified that growth temperature critically governs graphene quality, as excessive active species may lead to secondary nucleation and the formation of multilayer graphene. Notably, all substrates shared the same optimal growth conditions. Low-temperature Raman spectroscopy and scanning tunneling microscopy of the graphene/SrTiO$_3$ hybrid heterostructure revealed cooperative phenomena, including substrate-induced lattice-phonon and electron-phonon coupling. Our work establishes a reproducible, transfer-free fabrication route for graphene/perovskite oxide hybrid heterostructures and provides empirical support for the universal growth of graphene on insulating substrates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00815v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yeongju Choi (Department of Physics, Sungkyunkwan University), Seungjin Lee (Department of Energy Science, Sungkyunkwan University), Dongwon Shin (Department of Physics, Sungkyunkwan University, Center for Advanced Materials and Manufacturing, The University of Tennessee), Sukhoon Sim (Department of Physics, Sungkyunkwan University), Min-Hyoung Jung (Department of Energy Science, Sungkyunkwan University), Dirk Wulferding (Department of Physics and Astronomy, Sejong University), Minjae Kim (Department of Physics, Sungkyunkwan University), Jaesik Eom (Department of Physics, Sungkyunkwan University), Myeesha Mostafa (Department of Physics and Astronomy, The University of Tennessee, Center for Advanced Materials and Manufacturing, The University of Tennessee), Wonhee Ko (Department of Physics and Astronomy, The University of Tennessee, Center for Advanced Materials and Manufacturing, The University of Tennessee), SeungNam Cha (Department of Physics, Sungkyunkwan University), Jungseek Hwang (Department of Physics, Sungkyunkwan University), Hu Young Jeong (Graduate School of Semiconductor Materials and Devices Engineering, Ulsan National Institute of Science and Technology), Ki Kang Kim (Department of Energy Science, Sungkyunkwan University), Woo Seok Choi (Department of Physics, Sungkyunkwan University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Helical Edge Transport in the \nu = 0 Quantum Hall Ferromagnetic State of an Organic Dirac Fermion System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00816</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00816v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We experimentally confirm the \nu = 0 quantum Hall ferromagnetic (QHF) state, accompanied by helical edge states, in the layered organic Dirac-fermion system \alpha-(ET)2I3 by demonstrating helical edge transport in multilayers. The saturation of interlayer magnetoresistance (MR) in the high-magnetic-field quantum limit does not scale with the sample cross-sectional area and appears when the magnetic field is oriented along the side surface. The in-plane MR exhibits a similar angle dependence, whereas this feature disappears in the Corbino geometry where no edge channels are present. These results are consistent with helical edge transport in the multilayer QHF state. They also rule out the possibility that the observed angle-dependent MR arises from the chiral magnetic effect expected for a 3D Dirac or Weyl semimetal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00816v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Toshihito Osada, Mitsuyuki Sato, Takako Konoike, Woun Kang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Screened topological plasmons in graphene plasmonic crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00845</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00845v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study topological effects in an one-dimensional plasmonic crystal formed by the screened acoustic plasmons emerging in a periodically modulated graphene sheet, placed on top of a metallic substrate. To this end, we develop the theory of quantization of screened plasmons, as appropriate for lossless graphene described by a Drude conductivity. By analyzing the resulting band structure, we show that the crystal sustains nontrivial topological bands, with quantized geometric phase. We further show that in a finite, open system, edge states appear within the band gap, which undergo a topological phase transition and merge with bulk states as the modulation increases. Our work provides a robust theoretical framework for the study of band structure and topology of layered media, and extends the possibilities for engineering two-dimensional materials with external modulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00845v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andr\'e Oct\'avio Soares, Christos Tserkezis, N. M. R. Peres</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stacking-Induced Large-Chern-Number Quantum Anomalous Hall Phases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00863</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00863v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the interaction between quantum anomalous Hall (QAH) phases hosted by two atomically thin hexagonal lattices and demonstrate the emergence of topological phases with large Chern numbers. Interlayer coupling between two graphene-like lattices produces band crossings, while relative sliding preserves gapless Dirac points located at generic, low-symmetry $\mathbf{k}$ points. The introduction of Haldane-type complex next-nearest-neighbor hoppings gaps these Dirac points, breaks time-reversal symmetry, and generates a sequence of quantum anomalous Hall phases. Depending on the phase angles $\phi_1$ and $\phi_2$ associated with the two layers, the system exhibits QAH states with Chern numbers $|C|&gt;2$. The nontrivial bulk topology is verified by the presence of the corresponding number of chiral edge modes in ribbon geometries. These high-Chern-number phases originate from the enhanced twisting of the valence-band manifold induced by interlayer stacking.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00863v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. Minh Lam, V. Nam Do</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electric-field driven flat bands in the distorted sawtooth chain via the Katsura-Nagaosa-Balatsky mechanism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00900</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00900v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate flat magnonic bands in a generalized sawtooth-chain
  model in which three sets of exchange parameters (symmetric
  Heisenberg exchange, axial Ising anisotropy, and antisymmetric
  Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya (DM) exchange) are assigned independently to
  each side of the triangular plaquette. If the effective
  Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya (DM) interaction parameters are generated
  via the Katsura-Nagaosa-Balatsky (KNB) mechanism of
  magnetoelectricity, they become explicit functions of the
  electric-field magnitude and direction, as well as of the lattice
  geometry, which in the present casen is characterized by two bond
  angles. We focus on the situation in which these two angles are
  unequal, corresponding to a distortion of the triangular
  plaquette. Several electric-field induced flat-band scenarios in
  the distorted sawtooth chain are analyzed, and expressions are
  derived for the electric-field strength required to drive the
  one-magnon excitations into a flat-band regime when the field is
  aligned along the lattice bonds. The saturation field and its
  dependence on the distortion angle are also examined. Finally, we
  establish a mapping between the flat-band solutions for a general
  DM interaction and its specific KNB-induced form.
  \\~
  \emph{This article is dedicated to the memory of Johannes Richter.}</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00900v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vadim Ohanyan, Lusik Amiraghyan, Michael Sekania, Marcus Kollar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Field-Tunable Quantum Metric in Few-Layer Phosphorene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00914</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00914v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The quantum metric -- which quantifies the distance between quantum states -- is a fundamental component of the quantum geometric tensor, playing a crucial role in a wide range of physical phenomena. Its direct detection and control remains a challenge, requiring suitable material candidates. In this work, we present the emergence of a tunable quantum metric in a versatile two-dimensional material platform, namely, few-layer phosphorene. Using ab-initio-derived models, we show how electric fields can be used to substantially enhance the quantum metric as well as the associated quantum weight. Furthermore, we present a layer-dependent evolution of the quantum metric and its interplay with the electric field in this material. Our results establish few-layer phosphorene as a promising platform for exploring control over the quantum metric and the resulting metric responses in real materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00914v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Md Afsar Reja, Arka Bandyopadhyay, Awadhesh Narayan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exchange-Correlation Functionals in 2D Materials: Applications, Challenges, and Limitations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00921</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00921v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The rapid development of two-dimensional (2D) materials has reshaped modern nanoscience, offering properties that differ fundamentally from their bulk counterparts. As experimental discovery accelerates, the need for reliable computational techniques has become increas- ingly important. Within the framework of density functional theory, this review explores the critical role of exchange-correlation functionals in predicting key material properties such as structural, optoelectronic, magnetic, and thermal. We examine the challenges posed by quantum confinement, anisotropic screening, and van der Waals interactions, which conventional functionals often fail to describe. Advanced approaches, including meta-GGA, hybrid functionals, and many-body perturbation theory (e.g., GW and Bethe-Salpeter equation), are assessed for their improved accuracy in capturing electronic structure and excitonic effects. We further discuss the non-universality of functionals across different 2D material families and the emerging role of machine learning to enhance computational efficiency. Finally, the review outlines current limitations and emerging strategies, providing a roadmap for advancing exchange-correlation functionals and beyond, to enable the practical design and application of 2D materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00921v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahsan Javed, Mahvish Shaheen, Muhammad Shahbaz, M. Sufyan Ramzan, Rafi Ullah, Wei Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charge state equilibration of nitrogen-vacancy center ensembles in diamond: The role of electron tunneling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00952</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00952v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The charge state stability of nitrogen-vacancy (NV) centers critically affects their application as quantum sensors and qubits. Understanding charge state conversion and equilibration is critical not only for NV centers in diamond but also for defects and impurities in wide-bandgap materials in general. The mechanisms by which these centers change charge state upon optical or electronic excitation without the presence of mobile carriers remain unclear, potentially affecting the performance of applications ranging from phosphors to power electronics. Here, we elucidate this issue for the case of photoionization of NV center ensembles. Using pump-probe spectroscopy, we ionize negatively charged NV centers and monitor the recovery of $\NVm$ on timescales of up to several seconds. We find that the recovery rate depends strongly on the concentration of surrounding nitrogen donors. Remarkably, the equilibration dynamics exhibit no discernible dependence on temperature, ruling out thermally activated processes. The multiphonon-assisted electron tunneling model, supported by density-functional calculations, explains the measurements and identifies tunneling as the equilibration mechanism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00952v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Audrius Alkauskas, Chris G. Van de Walle, Lukas Razinkovas, Ronald Ulbricht</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of hidden altermagnetism in Cs$_{1-\delta}$V$_2$Te$_2$O</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00972v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Altermagnets are characterized by anisotropic band/spin splittings in momentum space, dictated by their spin-space group symmetries. However, the real-space modulations of altermagnetism are often neglected and have not been explored experimentally. Here we combine neutron diffraction, angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES), spin-resolved ARPES and density functional theory to demonstrate that Cs$_{1-\delta}$V$_2$Te$_2$O realizes a spatially modulated form of altermagnetism, i.e., hidden altermagnetism. Such a state in Cs$_{1-\delta}$V$_2$Te$_2$O results from its G-type antiferromagnetism and two-dimensional electronic states, allowing for the development of spatially alternating altermagnetic layers, whose local spin polarizations are directly verified by spin-resolved ARPES measurements. Our experimental discovery of hidden altermagnetism broadens the scope of unconventional magnetism and opens routes to exploring emergent phenomena from real-space modulations of altermagnetic order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00972v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guowei Yang, Ruihan Chen, Changchao Liu, Jing Li, Ze Pan, Liwei Deng, Naifu Zheng, Yu Tang, Hao Zheng, Weifan Zhu, Yifu Xu, Xin Ma, Xiaoping Wang, Shengtao Cui, Zhe Sun, Zhengtai Liu, Mao Ye, Chao Cao, Ming Shi, Lunhui Hu, Qihang Liu, Shan Qiao, Guanghan Cao, Yu Song, Yang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic clusters in the paramagnetic phase of a high-temperature ferromagnetic metal-organic framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00980</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00980v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Owing to their exceptional chemical and electronic tunability, metal-organic frameworks can be designed to develop magnetic ground states making a range of applications feasible, from magnetic gas separation to the implementation of lightweight, rare-earth free permanent magnets. However, the typically weak exchange interactions mediated by the diamagnetic organic ligands result in ordering temperatures confined to the cryogenic limit. The itinerant magnetic ground state realized in the chromium-based framework Cr(tri)$_{2}$(CF$_{3}$SO$_{3}$)$_{0.33}$ (Htri, $1H$-$1$,$2$,$3$-triazole) is a remarkable exception to this trend, showing a robust ferromagnetic behavior almost at ambient conditions. Here, we use dc SQUID magnetometry, nuclear magnetic resonance, and ferromagnetic resonance to study the magnetic state realized in this material. We highlight several thermally-activated relaxation mechanisms for the nuclear magnetization due to the tendency of electrons towards localization at low temperatures as well as the rotational dynamics of the charge-balancing triflate ions confined within the pores. Most interestingly, we report the development within the paramagnetic regime of mesoscopic magnetic correlated clusters whose slow dynamics in the MHz range are tracked by the nuclear moments, in agreement with the highly unconventional nature of the magnetic transition detected by dc SQUID magnetometry. We discuss the similarity between the clustered phase in the paramagnetic phase and the magnetoelectronic phase segregation leading to colossal magnetoresistance in manganites and cobaltites. These results demonstrate that high-temperature magnetic metal-organic frameworks can serve as a versatile platform for exploring correlated electron phenomena in low-density, chemically tunable materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00980v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giacomo Prando, Benjamin Costarella, Matthew S. Dickson, Ryan A. Murphy, Jesse G. Park, Gianrico Lamura, Giuseppe Allodi, Cristian Aloisi, A\"eto Apaix, Maria Cristina Mozzati, T. David Harris, Jeffrey R. Long, Pietro Carretta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Second-Order Jahn-Teller Distortions and Dynamic Lattice Polarizability as the Origin of Broadband Emission in Bi3+-Doped Cs2SnCl6</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00988</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00988v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Lead-free vacancy-ordered perovskites (VOHPs) such as Cs2SnCl6 have emerged as promising materials for optoelectronic applications but typically suffer from wide band gaps and low photoluminescence quantum yields (PLQY). In this work, the electronic origins of broadband blue emission in Bi3+-doped Cs2SnCl6 are elucidated by combining density functional theory (DFT) calculations and ab initio molecular dynamics simulations. The study systematically explores the spatial configurations of Bi3+ dopants and Cl- vacancies, assessing their impact on structural and electronic properties. Results demonstrate that the formation of square pyramidal BiCl5(2-) units serves as efficient exciton traps, fundamentally enabling strong luminescence in an otherwise non-emitting host. The Bi3+ 6s2 lone pair in an asymmetric coordination environment drives second-order Jahn-Teller distortions, creating a highly polarizable local lattice. This softness, in contrast to the rigid SnCl6(2-) framework, produces heterogeneous distributions of bond lengths, bond angles, and band edges around dopant sites. Defect-induced states strongly localize charge carriers, while coupling to vibrational modes at 300 K dynamically broadens the band edges, accounting for the large Stokes shift and broadband photoluminescence. These results establish lone-pair-driven Jahn-Teller distortions and lattice heterogeneity as key design principles for efficient luminescence in lead-free perovskites.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00988v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shruti Prasad, Pabitra Kumar Nayak, Dibyajyoti Ghosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of superconducting pairs in the two-dimensional Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01124</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01124v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The frequency structure of the superconducting correlations in cuprates gives insights on the pairing mechanism. Here we present an exhaustive study of this problem in the two-dimensional Hubbard model with cellular dynamical mean-field theory. To this end, we systematically quantify the dependence on doping and interaction strength of the superconducting gap, of the frequency scales where pairing occurs, and of their relative contribution to pairing. We find pair-forming alternating with pair-breaking processes as a function of frequency, providing new evidence that pairing can arise in principle from both low- and high-frequency processes. However, we find that the high-frequency pair-forming processes are outweighed by pair-breaking ones. Hence, the net contribution to pairing comes only from the low-frequency pair-forming processes, a result that underscores their key role in the pairing mechanism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01124v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Sordi, E. M. O'Callaghan, C. Walsh, M. Charlebois, P. S\'emon, A. -M. S. Tremblay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single Color Center Spin Coherence revealed in Optically Detected Magnetic Resonance of an Ensemble of Silicon Vacancies in SiC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01144</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01144v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a quantitative theory for simulating optically detected magnetic resonance (ODMR) measurements of optically-active spin centers using steady-state Lindblad equations. We apply the theory to an experimental ODMR spectrum associated with the negatively-charged silicon vacancy V2 center in 6H-SiC, showing that spin Hamiltonian parameters, optical transition rates, and even coherence times may be extracted, with values consistent with recent literature. Notably the $T_2$ spin coherence time is measurable, not just the $T_2^*$ dephasing time. Furthermore, we simulate the ODMR spectra of a V2 center in isotopically-purified 6H-SiC, and predict an order-of-magnitude narrowing of some, but not all spectral lines compared with natural abundance samples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01144v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David A. Fehr, Hannes Kraus, Corey J. Cochrane, Michael E. Flatt\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast track to the overdoped regime of superconducting YBa2Cu3O7-{\delta} thin films via electrochemical oxidation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01146v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High temperature superconductors, especially YBa$_2$Cu$_3$O$_{7-\delta}$ (YBCO), are considered a key enabling technology towards a clean energy future. Hole doping in YBCO is a prerequisite for the emergence of its unchallenged superconducting properties. Up to now, research was focused on the under- and optimally doped region, due to practical limitations in reaching the overdoped state, despite being highly interesting from fundamental and applied aspects as competing orders vanish and critical current densities are expected to peak. Here, we deploy for the first time an electrochemical method to access the mostly uncharted overdoped region. We demonstrate precise control over the bulk oxygen concentration in YBCO thin films across the full off-stoichiometry window (0$\le{\delta}\le$1) using electrochemical oxidation combined with in situ XRD and electrical measurements. Resulting high doping states and critical current densities are confirmed using a multi modal approach, including x-ray diffraction, electrical, Hall and magnetic characterization. Thus, this work opens a promising pathway based on electrochemical oxidation towards electronically clean, oxygen overdoped cuprate superconductors and therefore will assist to further push the critical current density to its intrinsic limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01146v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Stangl (Univ. Grenoble Alpes, CNRS, Grenoble INP, Institut N\'eel, Grenoble, France, TU Wien, Atominstitut, Vienna, Austria, Univ. Grenoble Alpes, CNRS, Grenoble INP, LMGP, Grenoble, France), Aiswarya Kethamkuzhi (Institut de Ci\`encia de Materials de Barcelona), Herv\'e Roussel (Univ. Grenoble Alpes, CNRS, Grenoble INP, LMGP, Grenoble, France), Cornelia Pop (Institut de Ci\`encia de Materials de Barcelona), Xavier Obradors (Institut de Ci\`encia de Materials de Barcelona), Teresa Puig (Institut de Ci\`encia de Materials de Barcelona), M\'onica Burriel (Univ. Grenoble Alpes, CNRS, Grenoble INP, LMGP, Grenoble, France), Arnaud Badel (Univ. Grenoble Alpes, CNRS, Grenoble INP, G2ELab - Institut N\'eel, Grenoble, France)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial structure and magnetism of a spin-orbit entangled spin-1 coherent spin center: the manganese neutral acceptor in a III-V semiconductor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01158v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A Mn dopant in a III-V semiconductor produces a highly-entangled, coherent triplet ground state not fully captured by single-determinant theories of electron structure. We directly construct an analytic form for its ground-state wavefunction, finding surprising spin-charge correlations not revealed by semiclassical calculations. Spin-correlated circulating currents associated with the dopant yield remarkably large magnetic fringe fields of $\sim$1$\,\mu$T at distances of $\sim 10$~nm from Mn in GaAs, potentially detectable by NV-diamond magnetometry while the dopant spin coherently precesses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01158v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julian Zanon, Michael E. Flatt\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Role of Quantum Geometry in the Competition between Higgs Mode and Quasiparticles in Third-Harmonic Generation of Superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01200v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Collective modes in superconductors, such as the Higgs mode, offer deep insights into the nature of condensates. Third-harmonic generation (THG) is a primary tool for probing the Higgs mode, but its signal competes with that of quasiparticle excitations depending on impurity scattering rates. In particular, in the clean regime the standard BCS theory generally predicts the dominance of quasiparticle contributions. Here, we propose and demonstrate that the quantum geometry of electronic bands can be a key mechanism governing this competition. By developing a formalism that explicitly incorporates the quantum metric, and applying it to a tunable model of a dispersive-band superconductor, we show that the quantum metric can dramatically amplify the nonlinear light-Higgs coupling by several orders of magnitude. Our results establish that a large quantum metric can cause the Higgs mode to dominate the THG response, resolving the puzzle of Higgs and quasiparticle competition in the clean regime and identifying band geometry as a crucial ingredient for designing and understanding the nonlinear response of superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01200v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chang-geun Oh, Haruki Watanabe, Naoto Tsuji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microscopic origin of the spin-splitting in altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01206v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Altermagnets, characterized by spin-split bands without net magnetization, have recently emerged as a promising platform for spintronics. However, their microscopic mechanisms remain elusive, often relying on abstract group theory. In this work, we present an intuitive and pedagogical framework to understand the origin of spin splitting in altermagnets. We identify two essential ingredients: (1) alternating spin-polarized wavefunction localization on sublattices, and (2) broken translational symmetry caused by distortions in non-magnetic ion cages. We discuss a minimal model Hamiltonian based on an atomic exchange-driven spin splitting and anisotropic hopping that captures these effects and reproduces the hallmark features of altermagnetic band structures, including nodal spin degeneracies and large spin splittings. Our model is further validated by ab initio calculations on MnF2. By demystifying the microscopic origins of altermagnetism, our work bridges symmetry analysis and material realizations, shedding light on practical designs of altermagnetic spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01206v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.cap.2025.07.004</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Current Applied Physics,Volume 79,2025,Pages 29-33</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Suyoung Lee, Minjae Kim, Changyoung Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Competing Lattice and Defect Dynamics Govern Terahertz-Induced Ferroelectricity in Quantum Paraelectric SrTiO$_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01253v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Intense terahertz (THz) pulses induce transient inversion-symmetry breaking in quantum paraelectric SrTiO$_3$, yet the underlying mechanism remains controversial. Using fields up to $\sim$1.1 MV/cm, we reveal spatially inhomogeneous THz-field-induced second harmonic generation (TFISH) governed by competing lattice and defect dynamics. Short-lived coherent antiferrodistortive (AFD) modes suppress dipole correlations within $\sim$5 ps, while heavily damped soft/AFD modes and a defect-induced low-frequency mode ($\sim$0.1-0.3 THz) jointly prevent long-range ferroelectric coherence in oxygen-vacancy-rich regions. Collective modes manifested by oscillatory TFISH components exhibit softening followed by hardening below a critical temperature $T^*\simeq$28 K, confirming transient ferroelectric order where defects are sparse. These results reconcile conflicting interpretations, establish defect-mediated competition as a central regulator of light-induced ferroelectricity, and open routes to ultrafast control of quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01253v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Cheng, K. Hu, S. Yang, Yan Liang, Jiandi Zhang, J. Qi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inductive van der Waals Force between Two Quantum Loops</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01263</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01263v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the van der Waals-London force, which is typically associated with fluctuating dipoles in atoms, in a mesoscopic circuit consisting of two inductively coupled superconducting loops. We investigate the ``inductive" van der Waals-London interaction using both semiclassical and quantum electrodynamic (QED) approaches. The semiclassical model predicts a repulsive interaction due to anticorrelated current fluctuations. In contrast, the QED framework, which incorporates virtual photon exchange, reveals a predominantly attractive force. A key contribution comes from a state-independent two-photon exchange, which is absent in the semiclassical description and undetectable by spectroscopy. Our study introduces a new experimental platform for measuring the van der Waals force between individual artificial atoms via controlled mesoscopic circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01263v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kicheon Kang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Nagaoka ferromagnetism accompanied by flavor-selective Mott states in an SU($N$) Fermi-Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01264</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01264v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the ferromagnetic instability in an SU($N$) Fermi-Hubbard model on the hypercubic lattice. Combining dynamical mean-field theory with continuous-time quantum Monte Carlo simulations, we find that, in the strong-coupling regime at low temperatures, ferromagnetically ordered (FM) states develop away from the commensurate fillings. In the particle-doped SU($3$) system near one-third filling, the FM state is accompanied by a spontaneous flavor-selective Mott state, where two of the three flavors are Mott insulating while the remaining flavor is metallic. Since particles in the metallic flavor can almost freely move on the lattice without correlation effects, the ordered state is stabilized by the kinetic-energy gain of the doped particles. This is similar to the generalized Nagaoka ferromagnetism discussed in the one-hole-doped system at one-third filling. In the SU($4$) case, we find that six distinct types of FM states appear as the particle density varies. The results uncover the nature of the FM state in the SU($N$) Fermi-Hubbard systems and highlight the rich magnetic behavior enabled by enlarged internal symmetries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01264v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juntaro Fujii, Kazuki Yamamoto, Akihisa Koga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological superconductivity and superconducting diode effect mediated via unconventional magnet and Ising spin-orbit coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01266v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a theoretical framework in which a one-dimensional (1D) tight-binding model incorporating unconventional magnetic order together with Rashba and Ising spin-orbit couplings are considered to realize two key phenomena in condensed matter systems: topological superconductivity and the superconducting diode effect (SDE). We first elucidate the underlying band topology of the normal-state Hamiltonian and subsequently introduce an on-site attractive Hubbard interaction. Performing a a self-consistent mean-field analysis, we establish superconducting order parameters in both the conventional Bardeen-Cooper-Schrieffer (BCS) and finite-momentum Fulde-Ferrell-Larkin-Ovchinnikov (FFLO) pairing channels. Intriguingly, both pairing states can support topological superconductivity, characterized by a nontrivial winding number, and lead to the emergence of four zero-energy Majorana modes localized at the ends of the 1D chain. The FFLO state further gives rise to an intrinsic field-free SDE, manifested as a nonreciprocal supercurrent and quantified by the diode efficiency $\eta$. Notably, our model yields a large diode efficiency $\eta \sim 65\%$, highlighting its potential for realising topological superconductivity and highly efficient superconducting devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01266v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amartya Pal, Debashish Mondal, Tanay Nag, Arijit Saha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extraordinary cation-replace-cation antisite defect predominate in Bi2SeO5</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01284v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As a newly identified single-crystalline van der Waals dielectric with a high dielectric constant, Bi2SeO5 plays a pivotal role in advancing 2D electronic devices. In this work, we systematically investigate the defect properties of Bi2SeO5 using first-principles calculations based on a hybrid functional. Although Bi2SeO5 is a chemically ternary compound, each constituent element occupies several crystallographically nonequivalent sites, rendering its defect chemistry highly complex. Due to the anomalous +4 cationic valence state of Se, the defect formation energies of same main group anion antisite defects (SeO and OSe) are prohibitively high, and their concentrations can therefore be neglected. In contrast, the extraordinary cation-cation antisite defects BiSe and SeBi emerge as the dominant defects. The pronounced variability in the formation energies of the six types of VO defects demonstrates that identical defect types located on nonequivalent atomic sites can exhibit markedly different properties. Under O-rich and Se/Bi-poor conditions, Bi2SeO5 shows relatively robust p-type behavior. Conversely, under O-poor and Se/Bi-rich conditions, or at intermediate O, Se, and Bi partial pressures, Bi2SeO5 behaves as an intrinsic semiconductor or displays very weak n-type conductivity due to strong donor-acceptor compensation. This study provides theoretical insights to guide the design and development of high-performance Bi2SeO5-based electronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01284v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen-Min Dai, Feifan Bian, Yafeng Zhang, Jiaqi Chen, Zenghua Cai, Menglin Huang, Chunlan Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Floquet Chern Insulators and Radiation-Induced Zero Resistance in Irradiated Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01346</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01346v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent advances in optics and time-resolved techniques have facilitated the exploration of new states of matter under nonequilibrium conditions. Here, we predict that irradiated graphene can host two novel nonequilibrium steady states of matter with zero resistance when exposed to circularly polarized light: (i) Floquet Chern insulators and (ii) a radiation-induced zero-resistance state with spontaneous formation of an inhomogeneous current distribution. Specifically, we calculate nonequilibrium anomalous Hall and longitudinal conductivities to map the nonequilibrium phase diagram of irradiated graphene as a function of the driving frequency and the electric-field strength of circularly polarized light. As a result, Floquet Chern insulators are found to occur at high driving frequencies above the graphene band width. By contrast, at low driving frequencies below the graphene band width, the nonequilibrium anomalous Hall conductivity deviates from the expected quantized values, and the nonequilibrium longitudinal conductivity exhibits highly irregular behavior, including negative resistance. It is predicted that the thermodynamically unstable negative resistance will trigger a catastrophic breakdown, inducing a zero-resistance state with spontaneous formation of an inhomogeneous current distribution, similar to the radiation-induced zero-resistance state observed in quantum Hall systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01346v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Youngjae Kim, Kwon Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of a Zero-Field Josephson Diode Effect in a Helimagnet Josephson Junction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01379</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01379v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cr$_{1/3}$NbS$_{2}$ is a transition metal dichalcogenide that is also a chiral helimagnet, and so lacks inversion symmetry and has non-zero Berry curvature in position and momentum space. It is well known that the combination of broken time-reversal symmetry and broken inversion symmetry can generate non-reciprocal phenomena, but the interplay between these kinds of systems and superconductivity is not well known. We present Josephson junctions fabricated from Cr$_{1/3}$NbS$_{2}$ that give magnetic diffraction patterns with asymmetry in both the magnetic field and the critical current. The non-reciprocity in positive critical current and negative critical current, generally called the Josephson diode effect, has an efficiency of up to $\eta=20\%$ in some parts of the magnetic diffraction pattern and persists even at zero applied field. We propose that pinned Abrikosov vortices are a main mechanism for the asymmetric magnetic field response in this system, and that the non-zero spin chirality of the Cr$_{1/3}$NbS$_{2}$ causes the diode effect. Simulations of magnetic diffraction patterns from Josephson junctions with vortices present show offsets from zero-field consistent with observations, while simulations of chiral spin structures with an out-of-plane canting show a diode effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01379v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Beach, Mostafa Tanhayi Ahari, Younghyuk Kim, Kannan Lu, Gregory MacDougall, Matthew Gilbert, Nadya Mason</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Questioning the cuprate paradigm - absence of superfluid density loss in several overdoped cuprates I</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01395</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01395v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is long established that overdoped cuprate superconductors experience a loss of superfluid density (SFD) with increasing doping, p, along with the decline in T_c. Such behavior is unconventional and suggests a depletion of the condensate by increasing pairbreaking or the growth of a second non-pairing channel. This led to a recent suggestion that the condensate arises from an incoherent charge channel which progressively gives way with overdoping to a second, coherent non-pairing channel. Contra these ideas, we report analysis of the field-dependent electronic specific heat of several cuprates from which we find no apparent loss of SFD with overdoping. The SFD per CuO_2 plaquette is found to rise progressively with overdoping from p towards (1+p), undiminished and much the same as the Hall number, thus implying that all available carriers contribute to the condensate. We suggest this could be the underlying intrinsic behavior for all cuprates. Our samples include (Y,Ca)Ba_2Cu_3O_{7-\delta}, Bi_2Sr_2CaCu_2O_{8+\delta}, La_{2-x}Sr_xCuO_4 and Tl_2Ba_2CuO_6, with the latter being the only exception. Our results signal a possible return to a more conventional picture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01395v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. L. Tallon, J. G. Storey, J. W. Loram, Jianlin Luo, C. Bernhard, I. Kokanovic, J. R. Cooper</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unusual electronic ordering in the pseudogap phase of underdoped cuprate superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01402v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The pseudogap phase of the underdoped cuprate superconductors harbours diverse manifestations of different ordered electronic-states, and then these ordered electronic-states coexist or compete with superconductivity. Here starting from the microscopic electron propagator, the nature of the ordered electronic-states in the pseudogap phase is investigated within the $T$-matrix approach. This $T$-matrix is derived in terms of the inverse of matrix for various kinds of a single impurity, and then is used to evaluate the local density of states (LDOS) by the involvement of all the quasiparticle excitations and scattering processes. It is shown that a number of the anomalous properties in the underdoped cuprate superconductors is directly correlated to the opening of the normal-state pseudogap: (i) the structure of the microscopic octet scattering model generated by the normal-state pseudogap is essentially the same both in the superconducting (SC)-state and pseudogap phase, which naturally leads to that the quasiparticle scattering interference octet phenomenology observed in the SC-state exists in the pseudogap phase; (ii) however, the spectral weight at around the antinodal region in the SC-state is gapped out completely by both the SC gap and normal-state pseudogap, while it in the pseudogap phase is suppressed partially by the normal-state pseudogap, this directly leads to that the non-dispersive checkerboard charge ordering with a finite wave vector ${\bf Q}$ appears in the pseudogap phase only. The theory therefore also shows that the electronic-states affected by the normal-state pseudogap exhibit the LDOS modulation spectrum organization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01402v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiang Li, Minghuan Zeng, Yu Lan, Huaiming Guo, Shiping Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Field-free diode effects in one-dimensional superconductor: a complex interplay between Fulde-Ferrell pairing and altermagnetism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01415v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the emergence of nonreciprocal dissipationless supercurrents in one-dimension manifested through the superconducting diode effect (SDE) and the Josephson diode effect (JDE) in the absence of any external magnetic field, where inversion symmetry (IS) and time-reversal symmetry (TRS) can be intrinsically broken by spin-orbit coupling (SOC), and altermagnetism (AM), respectively. We investigate Ising and Rashba SOC separately in two models where two-component AM, assembled with crystallographic angle, can lead to qualitatively similar indirect band-gap closing and non-reciprocal supercurrent in a Fulde-Ferrell (FF) superconductor. Interestingly, in the absence of the above SOCs, SDE persists and the sign of efficiency can be altered by tuning the angle only. Parallel spin components with complementary momentum functions, ensuring the breaking of IS and TRS, can induce SDE in the presence of FF pairing. Continuing the analysis in the context of JDE, we explore the interplay between SOCs and AM with the p-wave and Fulde-Ferrell superconductivity in three different setups. The bulk bands contributes to the non-reciprocity in the case of p-wave superconductivity while JDE is dominated by Andreev bound states for FF superconductivity. Importantly, JDE continues to exist due to finite momentum Cooper pair even without AM and SOC unlike the p-wave superconductivity. The sign of JD efficiency can be tuned with angle for p-wave superconductivity while absence of such sign reversal is a hallmark signature of FF superconductivity. Similar to SDE, parallel spin components in conjunction with p-wave superconductivity can lead to JDE that can also be mediated by only FF pairing in the absence of SOC and AM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01415v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>SVS Sai Ruthvik, Tanay Nag</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disorder Suppression of Charge Density Wave in the Honeycomb Holstein Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01487</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01487v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The formation of charge-density-wave order in Dirac fermion systems via electron-phonon coupling represents a significant topic in condensed matter physics. In this work, we investigate this phenomenon within the Holstein model on the honeycomb lattice, with a specific focus on the effect of disorder. While the interplay between electron-electron interactions and disorder has long been a central theme in the field, recent attention has increasingly turned to the combined influence of disorder and electron-phonon coupling. Using determinant quantum Monte Carlo simulations, we concentrate on the phase transitions of charge-density-wave order on the honeycomb lattice. Disorder is introduced through the random hopping of electrons in the system, which can localize electrons via the Anderson effect. Our primary result is that disorder suppresses the charge-density-wave phase, and the interplay between disorder and electron-phonon interactions extends the phase area. We also determine the transition temperature \(\beta_c\) to the ordered phase as a function of the electron-phonon coupling. Additionally, we observed a suppression of electron kinetic energy and dc conductivity under disorder, highlighting the role of Anderson localization in the degradation of electronic transport. These findings offer significant theoretical insight into the stability and critical phenomena of correlated phases in disordered two-dimensional systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01487v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guangchao Li, Lifei Zhang, Tianxing Ma, Qionglin Dai, Lufeng Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interatomic spin-orbit interaction in a $p$-orbital helical atomic chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01504</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01504v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We derive the interatomic spin-orbit interaction (SOI) from a helical atomic chain composed of $p$-orbitals with intra-atomic SOI, which exhibits a helical state--a potential origin of the chiral-induced spin selectivity (CISS) effect. In this model, a strong crystal field in the tangential direction of the helix leads to the formation of energetically separated $\sigma$- and $\pi$-bands. In the second-order process, a spin in the $\sigma$-orbital virtually hops to the $\pi$-orbital, flips its direction due to intra-atomic SOI, and then hops back to the $\sigma$-orbital in the neighboring atom due to the misalignment of $p$-orbitals along the helix. This process induces an interatomic SOI in the $\sigma$-band, which takes the form of a Rashba-type SOI generated by an electric field normal to the helical axis. The magnitude of the SOI is proportional to the curvature, the hopping energy, the intra-atomic SOI energy, and inversely proportional to the crystal field strength. The second-order process also induces long-range second-nearest-neighbor hoppings. We analytically derive the spin-split band structure in the zero-torsion limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01504v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjs/s11734-025-02065-1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. Spec. Top. (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Takemitsu Kato, Yasuhiro Utsumi, Ora Entin-Wohlman, Amnon Aharony</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defect-Limited Efficiency of Pnictogen Chalcohalide Solar Cells</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01531</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01531v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Pnictogen chalcohalides (MChX) have recently emerged as promising nontoxic and environmentally friendly photovoltaic absorbers, combining strong light absorption coefficients with favorable low-temperature synthesis conditions. Despite these advantages and reported optimized morphologies, device efficiencies remain below 10%, far from their ideal radiative limit. To uncover the origin of these performance losses, we present a systematic and fully consistent first-principles investigation of the defect chemistry across the Bi-based chalcohalide family. Our results reveal a complex defect landscape dominated by chalcogen vacancies of low formation energy, which act as deep nonradiative recombination centers. Despite their moderate charge-carrier capture coefficients, the high equilibrium concentrations of these defects reduce the theoretical maximum efficiencies by 6% in BiSeI and by 10% in BiSeBr. In contrast, sulfur vacancies in BiSI and BiSBr are comparatively benign, presenting smaller capture coefficients due to weaker electron-phonon coupling. Interestingly, despite its huge nonradiative charge-carrier recombination rate, BiSeI presents the best conversion efficiency among all four compounds owing to its most suitable bandgap for outdoor photovoltaic applications. Our findings identify defect chemistry as a critical bottleneck in MChX solar cells and proposes chalcogen-rich synthesis conditions and targeted anion substitutions as effective strategies for mitigation of detrimental vacancies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01531v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cibr\'an L\'opez, Se\'an R. Kavanagh, Pol Ben\'itez, Edgardo Saucedo, Aron Walsh, David O. Scanlon, Claudio Cazorla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eu-assisted enhancement of photoresponse in MBE-grown CdO/Si photodetectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01548</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01548v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Doping cadmium oxide with rare earth (RE) elements is a way to control the band gap and enhance carrier concentration and mobility. This work presents how one of REs, europium, impacts performance of CdO/Si diode. The samples were grown using plasma-assisted molecular beam epitaxy. Doping level was modified by changing the temperature of the effusion cell with Eu and therefore flux of Eu particles. Different dopant concentrations were confirmed by secondary ion mass spectrometry. Atomic force microscopy images revealed a grain-like surface structure of the samples with grain size increasing after rapid thermal processing (RTP). Raman spectroscopy showed that introducing Eu changes vibrational properties of CdO through intraionic anharmonicity reduction. Kelvin probe method revealed upward band bending caused by oxygen adsorption during RTP. Electrical measurements confirmed that rectifying junctions were manufactured and that they are able to produce photocurrent in the spectral range of 450-1150 nm without external voltage bias. Introducing Eu into CdO was found to increase e.g. rectifying factor and responsivity. The results show that doping CdO with Eu is a way to enhance performance of the presented zero-power-consumption photodetectors, making it a promising material for future applications in optoelectronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01548v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Igor Perlikowski, Eunika Zielony, Abinash Adhikari, Rafa{\l} Jakie{\l}a, Sergij Chusnutdinow, Ewa Popko, Ewa Prze\'zdziecka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Origin of Bright Quantum Emissions with High Debye-Waller factor in Silicon Nitride</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01569</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01569v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Silicon nitride has emerged as a promising photonic platform for integrated single-photon sources, yet the microscopic origin of the recently observed bright quantum emissions remains unclear. Using hybrid density functional theory, we show that the negatively charged N$_\text{Si}$V$_\text{N}$ center (NV$^{-}$) in the C$_{1h}$ configuration exhibits a linearly polarized zero-phonon line (ZPL) at 2.46 eV, with a radiative lifetime of 9.01 ns and a high Debye-Waller (DW) factor of 33%. We further find that the C$_{1h}$ configuration is prone to a pseudo-Jahn-Teller distortion, yielding two symmetrically equivalent defect structures that emit bright, linearly polarized ZPL at 1.80 eV with a lifetime of 10.17 ns and an increased DW factor of 41%. These nitrogen-vacancy-related defects explain the origins of visible quantum emissions, paving the way for deterministic and monolithically integrated silicon-nitride quantum photonics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01569v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shibu Meher, Manoj Dey, Abhishek Kumar Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-Space Spectral Approach to Orbital Magnetization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01575</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01575v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a real-space spectral method for computing the orbital magnetization of crystals. Starting from the commutator form of the orbital magnetization operator, we formulate an energy-resolved spectral function that is amenable to exact Chebyshev polynomial expansions and yields the total magnetization upon integration up to the Fermi level. This avoids the need for computing eigenstates and ground-state projects, providing an efficient numerical framework that is applicable to very large systems even in the presence of disorder and temperature. Our approach is benchmarked on the Haldane model, finding results that are in excellent agreement with the modern $k$-space formulation of orbital magnetization. Leveraging this technique, we extend our study to systems with uncorrelated disorder and point defects, and further show that the bulk Chern number can be directly obtained from the magnetization spectral density. These results open a promising route to investigate orbital responses and topological transitions in real-space models of quantum materials with realistic complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01575v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin J. U. Vidarte, Henrique P. Veiga, Jo\~ao M. Viana Parente Lopes, Ramon Cardias, Aires Ferreira, Tarik P. Cysne, Tatiana G. Rappoport</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Manipulating fractional Shapiro steps in twisted cuprate Josephson junctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01586</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01586v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High$-$quality Josephson junctions made of twisted cuprate superconductors offer unprecedented opportunities in addressing fundamental problems and realizing next$-$generation superconducting devices at relatively high temperatures. Whether or not the twisted cuprates possess high$-$temperature topological superconductivity remains an outstanding issue. Here, we tackle this problem via an in$-$depth study of the key predicted feature $--$ half$-$integer Shapiro steps. We show that half$-$integer Shapiro steps do occur in samples at a twist angle of 45$^\circ$ but are unstable with thermal cycling. Interestingly, fractional steps can be introduced by training the sample with a small magnetic field or annealing with a large electrical current, attesting to a tunable current$-$phase relation (CPR) in twisted cuprates. We extend the current annealing to realize fractional steps with odd denominators too. Furthermore, half$-$integer steps can be induced in the regime that is well beyond the expectation of topological superconductivity, favoring an alternative mechanism involving trapped vortices. Our results not only caution the direct association of half$-$integer Shapiro steps with the exotic mechanism but also open a distinct pathway toward a Josephson junction with electrically tunable CPR at high temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01586v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuying Zhu, Heng Wang, Ding Zhang, Qi-Kun Xue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electric polarization driven by non-collinear spin alignment investigated by first principles calculations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01615v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an approach for first principles investigations on the spin driven electric polarization in type II multiferroics. We propose a
  parametrization of the polarization with the parameters calculated
  using the Korringa-Kohn-Rostoker Green function (KKR-GF) formalism. Within this approach the induced electric polarization of a unit cell is represented in terms of three-site parameters. Those antisymmetric with respect to spin permutation are seen as an ab-initio based counter-part to the phenomenological parameters used within the inverse-Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya-interaction (DMI) model. Due to their relativistic origin, these parameters are responsible for the electric polarization induced in the presence of a non-collinear spin alignment in materials with a centrosymmetric crystal structure. Beyond to this, our approach gives direct access to the element- or site-resolved electric polarization. To demonstrate the capability of the approach, we consider several examples of the so-called type II multiferroics, for which the magneto-electric effect is observed either as a consequence of an applied magnetic field (we use Cr$_2$O$_3$ as a prototype), or as a result of a phase transition to a spin-spiral magnetic state, as for instance in MnI$_2$, CuCrO$_2$ and AgCrO$_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01615v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergiy Mankovsky, Svitlana Polesya, Jan Minar, Hubert Ebert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First-principles screening of materials with extreme effective masses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01631v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The effective mass of charge carriers is a fundamental descriptor of the electronic structure of materials, and can be used to assess performance in electronics applications, or to screen for thermoelectrics and transparent conductors. Here, we perform a high-throughput computational screening of approximately 20,000 experimentally known three-dimensional stoichiometric inorganics obtained from the Materials Cloud 3D structure database. By combining density-functional theory calculations and maximally localized Wannier functions, we are able to compute the full conductivity effective mass tensor for electrons and holes from the Boltzmann transport equation in the constant relaxation-time approximation. This approach captures the effects of band non-parabolicity, anisotropy, and valley multiplicity that would be neglected by standard parabolic fittings. The screening identifies a curated set of candidates exhibiting extreme electronic properties, from ultra-low to ultra-large effective masses, these latter associated with flat-band physics. We validate the workflow by recovering established high-mobility semiconductors and highlight promising novel candidates. Furthermore, we classify materials by their mass anisotropy and discuss the physical limits of defining a conductivity effective mass in narrow-gap regimes at room temperature. The resulting dataset provides a systematic roadmap to search for high-performance materials in novel chemical spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01631v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Szymon B{\l}azucki, Junfeng Qiao, Nicola Marzari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distinguish the Orientation of Sliding Ferroelectricity by Second-Harmonic Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01635</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01635v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As the emerging ferroelectric (FE) materials, the ultrathin two-dimensional (2D) sliding ferroelectrics without phase-matching bottleneck, usually exhibit the pronounced second harmonic generation (SHG) responses. Despite the structural polarity of sliding ferroelectrics can be precisely detected via SHG characterizations, distinguishing the orientations of sliding ferroelectricity based on SHG responses has rarely been realized, as SHG intensities for upward and downward polarization states are supposed to be same. In current work, combining computational simulations and experimental characterizations, the orientation of sliding ferroelectricity is demonstrated to be readily distinguishable via SHG responses in 2D SnP2S6 (SnP2Se6), a new sliding FE material. Specifically, owing to the unique symmetry operation within FE-SnP2S6 (SnP2Se6), the intersection between \c{hi}xxx and \c{hi}yyy SHG susceptibility coefficients with opposite signs leads to the effective rotation of SHG polar directions upon switching of sliding ferroelectricity. Moreover, the remarkable dependence of SHG polar directions on the orientation of sliding ferroelectricity is further validated by experimental characterizations performed on SnP2S6 crystal in a single FE domain structural form. This work opens up the avenue for in-situ detecting the ferroelectricity orientation of 2D sliding ferroelectrics based on SHG nonlinear optical responses, and also demonstrates the controllable optical nonlinearly for new "slidetronics" applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01635v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fengfeng Ye, Qiankun Li, Zhuocheng Lu, Xinfeng Chen, Yang Li, Hua Wang, Lu You, Gaoyang Gou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasistatic response for nonequilibrium processes: evaluating the Berry potential and curvature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01654</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01654v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate how introducing slow, time-dependent perturbations to a steady, nonequilibrium process alters the expected (excess) values of important observables, such as the dynamical activity and entropy flux. When we make a cyclic thermodynamic transformation, the excesses are described in terms of a (geometric) Berry phase with corresponding Berry potential and Berry curvature quantifying the response. Focussing on Markov jump processes, we show how a non-zero Berry curvature leads to a breakdown of the thermodynamic Maxwell relations and of the Clausius heat theorem. We also present a variant of the Aharonov-Bohm effect in which the parameters follow a curve with vanishing Berry curvature, but the system still experiences a nonzero Berry phase. Finally, we identify (sufficient) no-localization conditions in terms of mean first-passage times under which the corresponding Berry potentials and curvatures vanish at absolute zero, extending, for arbitrary driving, e.g. the case of vanishing heat capacity as for the Nernst postulate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01654v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aaron Beyen, Faezeh Khodabandehlou, Christian Maes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Floquet-induced $p_x+ip_y$ bosonic pair condensate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01674</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01674v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study, we propose a dynamical pairing mechanism other than the pair-wise interactions. Starting from a two-dimensional hard-core boson model with periodically modulated hopping amplitude, we derive an effective Floquet Hamiltonian with three-site interactions that are responsible for unconventional pairing between adjacent bosons. By performing a density matrix renormalization group study on this three-site interacting Hamiltonian, we reveal a bosonic pair condensate with $p_x+ ip_y$ symmetry, while the single-particle Bose-Einstein condensate is completely depleted. The experimental implementations of the proposed model on polar molecular systems and superconducting quantum circuit have also been discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01674v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhizhen Chen, Jiale Huang, Mingpu Qin, Zi Cai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distinct Modulation Behavior of Superconducting Coherence Peaks Associated with Sign-Reversal Gaps in FeTe$_{0.55}$Se$_{0.45}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01703</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01703v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using high-resolution scanning tunneling microscopy, we reveal two distinct types of superconducting (SC) gap modulations in bulk superconductor FeTe$_{0.55}$Se$_{0.45}$. By analyzing the phase relation between modulations at positive and negative bias, we identify in-phase (particle-hole asymmetric) and anti-phase (particle-hole symmetric) oscillations, corresponding to sign-reversing and sign-preserving scattering processes, respectively. The observed features are consistent with predictions from pair-breaking scattering interference (PBSI) theory and are distinguishable from other alternative mechanisms such as pair density waves. Our results provide compelling evidence that PBSI is the dominant mechanism behind the SC gap modulations in FeTe$_{0.55}$Se$_{0.45}$, offering new insights into the role of impurity scattering in iron-based superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01703v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiyong Hou, Zhiyuan Shang, Wen Duan, Wei Xie, Huan Yang, Hai-Hu Wen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atomic-scale Origin of Interfacial Dzyaloshinskii--Moriya Interaction in Pt/Fe/Au</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01724</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01724v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent results show remarkable interfacial--Dzyaloshinskii--Moriya interaction (i-DMI) in magnetic heterostructures composed of relatively thick Fe thin films ($\gg 1$ nm). To investigate its origin, we present a thorough magnetic characterization of the SiO$_2$/${}^{57}\mathrm{Fe}$($t$)/Au and SiO$_2$/Pt/${}^{57}\mathrm{Fe}$($t$)/Au heterostructures ($t = 1.6$ - $2.2$ nm). An i-DMI constant of $D_s^{\mathrm{Pt}} = 0.43\,\mathrm{mJ\,m^{-2}}$ is extracted for the Pt/Fe/Au system, as probed by wavevector-resolved Brillouin light scattering spectroscopy. Ferromagnetic resonance and conversion electron M\"ossbauer spectroscopy indicate that significant surface anisotropy is present in Pt/Fe/Au, and that an interfacial Fe fraction ($\sim18$) exhibits tilted magnetization ($\sim25^\circ$ out of plane) and an enhanced hyperfine field, correlating with the stronger i-DMI.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01724v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emanuele Longo, Gianluca Gubbiotti, Matteo Belli, Claudia Wiemer, Mario Alia, M. Fanciulli, Roberto Mantovan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transition Metal Dichalcogenide 1T$'$-MoTe$_2$ Nanoscale Films as Spin Pumping Platforms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01743v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) have emerged as a promising class of materials for spintronics, with the aim of promoting efficient spin-charge conversion (SCC) in TMD/ferromagnet (FM)-based devices. The MoTe$_2$ semimetal with distorted orthorhombic crystal structure in the 1T$'$ phase has gathered particular attention due to its high spin-orbit coupling and reconfigurability as a type-II Weyl semimetal close to room temperature. Here, we report on the role of chemically grown 1T$'$-MoTe$_2$ thin films in inducing SCC in 1T$'$-MoTe$_2$/FM heterostructures as measured at room temperature. Ferromagnetic resonance (FMR) and electrically detected spin-pumping FMR measurements performed on 1T$'$-MoTe$_2$/Co/Au and 1T$'$-MoTe$_2$/Au/Co/Au heterostructures reveal a spin-mixing conductance value of up to $\sim1.6 \times 10^{20}~\mathrm{m^{-2}}$ and a spin Hall angle of $1.7\%$. These findings position MoTe$_2$ thin films as a competitive spin-charge conversion option compared to other functional materials (e.g., heavy metals, topological insulators), highlighting their potential for future applications in spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01743v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emanuele Longo, Pinakapani Tummala, M. Belli, Alessio Lamperti, Christian Martella, Alessandro Molle, Marco Fanciulli, Roberto Mantovan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exciton-Polariton hybrid skin-topological states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01768</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01768v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The non Hermitian skin effect, where bulk states accumulate at system boundaries, challenges the conventional bulk boundary correspondence. Here we propose a scheme to realize hybrid skin topological states in exciton polariton honeycomb lattices by introducing sublattice dependent gain and loss. This non Hermiticity couples with the intrinsic topological edge modes, leading to relocalization of edge states. We show two distinct regimes: hybrid skin Chern states with switchable localization controlled by TE TM splitting , and hybrid skin antichiral states which preserves the spin polarized property. Our results bridge polariton spin physics and non-Hermitian topology, opening routes toward controllable non reciprocal and spin polarized transport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01768v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruiqi Bao, R. Banerjee, S. Mandal, Huawen Xu, Shiji Li, Junfeng Gao, Timothy C. H. Liew</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum dynamics of monitored free fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01772</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01772v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore, both analytically and numerically, the quantum dynamics of a many-body free-fermion system subjected to local density measurements. We begin by extending the mapping to the nonlinear sigma-model (NLSM) field theory for the case of finite evolution time $T$ and different classes of initial states, which lead to different NLSM boundary conditions. The analytical formalism is then used to study how quantum correlations gradually develop, with increasing $T$, from those determined by the initial state towards their steady-state form. The analytical results are confirmed by numerical simulations for several types of initial states. We further consider the long-time limit, when the system in $d+1$ space-time dimensions becomes quasi-one-dimensional, and analyze the scaling of the ``localization'' time (which is simultaneously the purification time and the charge-sharpening time for this class of problems). The analytical predictions for scaling properties are fully confirmed by numerical simulations in a $d=2$ model around the measurement-induced phase transition. We use this dynamical approach to determine numerically the measurement-induced transition point and the associated correlation-length critical exponent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01772v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Igor Poboiko, Alexander D. Mirlin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\mathbb{Z}_2$ Vortex Crystal Candidate in the Triangular $S=1/2$ Quantum Antiferromagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01793</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01793v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The prospect of merging the paradigms of geometric frustration on a triangular lattice and bond anisotropies in the strong spin-orbit coupling limit holds tremendous promise in the ongoing hunt for exotic quantum materials. Here we identify a new candidate system to realize such physics, the organic quantum antiferromagnet (CD$_3$ND$_3$)$_2$NaRuCl$_6$. We report a combination of thermodynamic, magneto-elastic and neutron scattering experiments on single-crystals to determine the phase diagram in axial magnetic fields $\mathbf{H \parallel c}$ and propose a minimal model Hamiltonian. (CD$_3$ND$_3$)$_2$NaRuCl$_6$ displays an ideal triangular arrangement of Ru$^{3+}$ ions adopting the spin-orbital entangled $j_{\rm eff} = 1/2$ state. It hosts residual magnetic order below $T_{\rm N} = 0.23$ K and a highly unusual $H-T$ phase diagram including three different incommensurate states. Spin-waves in the high-field polarized regime are well described by a Heisenberg-like triangular lattice Hamiltonian with a potential sub-leading bond dependent anisotropy term. We discuss possible candidate magnetic structures in the various observed phases and propose two mechanisms that could explain the field-dependent incommensurability, requiring either a small ferromagnetic Kitaev term or a tiny magneto-elastic $J-J'$ isosceles distortion driven by pseudospin-lattice coupling. We argue that the multi-$\mathbf{q}$ ground state in zero magnetic field is a prime candidate for hosting the $\mathbb{Z}_2$ vortex crystal proposed on the triangular Heisenberg-Kitaev model. (CD$_3$ND$_3$)$_2$NaRuCl$_6$ is the first member in an extended family of quantum triangular lattice magnets, providing a new playground to study the interplay of geometric frustration and spin-orbit effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01793v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Nagl, K. Yu. Povarov, B. Duncan, C. N\"appi, D. Khalyavin, P. Manuel, F. Orlandi, J. Sourd, B. V. Schwarze, F. Husstedt, S. A. Zvyagin, O. Zaharko, P. Steffens, A. Hiess, D. Allan, S. Barnett, Z. Yan, S. Gvasaliya, A. Zheludev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous Eigenstates of a Doped Hole in the Ising Antiferromagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01815</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01815v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The problem of a mobile hole doped into an antiferromagnet Mott insulator is believed to underly the rich physics of several paradigmatic strongly correlated electron systems, ranging from heavy fermions to high-Tc superconductivity. Arguably the simplest incarnation of this problem corresponds to a doped Ising antiferromagnet, a problem widely considered essentially solved since almost 60 years by a popular yet approximate mapping to a single-particle problem on the Bethe lattice. Here we show that, despite its deceptive simplicity, the local spectrum of a single hole in a classical Ising-N\'eel state contains a series of anomalous, long-lived states that go beyond the well-known ladder-like spectrum with excited energies spaced as $J^{2/3} t^{1/3}$. The anomalous states we find through exact diagonalization and within the self-avoiding path approximation have excitation energies scaling approximately linear with $J$ and lead to a series of avoided crossings with the more pronounced ladder spectrum. By also computing different local, rotational spectra we explain the origin of the anomalous states as rooted in an approximate emergent local $C_3$ symmetry of the problem. From their direct spectral signatures we further conclude that these states lead to anomalously slow thermalization behavior -- hence representing a new type of quantum many-body scar state, potentially related to many-body scars predicted in lattice gauge theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01815v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Piotr Wrzosek, Krzysztof Wohlfeld, Eugene A. Demler, Annabelle Bohrdt, Fabian Grusdt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fabrication and Properties of NbN/NbNx/NbN and Nb/NbNx/Nb Josephson Junctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01826</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01826v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Increasing integration scale of superconductor electronics (SCE) requires employing kinetic inductors and self-shunted Josephson junctions (JJs) for miniaturizing inductors and JJs. We have been developing a ten-superconductor-layer planarized fabrication process with NbN kinetic inductors and searching for suitable self-shunted JJs to potentially replace high Josephson critical current density, Jc, Nb/Al-AlOx/Nb junctions. We report on the fabrication and electrical properties of NbN/NbNx/NbN junctions produced by reactive sputtering in Ar+N2 mixture on 200-mm wafers at 200 oC and incorporated into a planarized process with two Nb ground planes and Nb wiring layer. Here NbN is a stoichiometric nitride with superconducting critical temperature Tc =15 K and NbNx is a high resistivity, nonsuperconducting nitride deposited using a higher nitrogen partial pressure than for the NbN electrodes. For comparison, we co-fabricated Nb/NbNx/Nb JJs using the same NbNx barriers deposited at 20 oC. We varied the NbNx barrier thickness from 5 nm to 20 nm, resulting in the range of Jc from about 1 mA/um^2 down to ~10 uA/um^2, and extracted coherence length of 3 nm and 4 nm in NbNx deposited, respectively at 20 oC and 200 oC. Both types of JJs are well described by resistively and capacitively shunted junction model without any excess current. We found the Jc of NbN/NbNx/NbN JJs to be somewhat lower than of Nb/NbNx/Nb JJs with the same barrier thickness, despite a much higher Tc and energy gap of NbN than of Nb electrodes. IcRn products up to ~ 0.5 mV were obtained for JJs with Jc~ 0.6 mA/um^2. Jc(T) dependences have been measured.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01826v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergey K. Tolpygo (Lincoln Laboratory, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Lexington, MA), Ravi Rastogi (Lincoln Laboratory, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Lexington, MA), David Kim (Lincoln Laboratory, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Lexington, MA), Terence J. Weir (Lincoln Laboratory, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Lexington, MA), Neel Parmar (Lincoln Laboratory, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Lexington, MA), Evan B. Golden (Lincoln Laboratory, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Lexington, MA)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Order in Deep State</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01863</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01863v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Topologically ordered states are among the most interesting quantum phases of matter that host emergent quasi-particles having fractional charge and obeying fractional quantum statistics. Theoretical study of such states is however challenging owing to their strong-coupling nature that prevents conventional mean-field treatment. Here, we demonstrate that an attention-based deep neural network provides an expressive variational wavefunction that discovers fractional Chern insulator ground states purely through energy minimization without prior knowledge and achieves remarkable accuracy. We introduce an efficient method to extract ground state topological degeneracy -- a hallmark of topological order -- from a single optimized real-space wavefunction in translation-invariant systems by decomposing it into different many-body momentum sectors. Our results establish neural network variational Monte Carlo as a versatile tool for discovering strongly correlated topological phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01863v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmed Abouelkomsan, Max Geier, Liang Fu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Refining Heuristic Predictors of Fractional Chern Insulators using Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01873v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop an interpretable, data-driven framework to quantify how single-particle band geometry governs the stability of fractional Chern insulators (FCIs). Using large-scale exact diagonalization, we evaluate an FCI metric that yields a continuous spectral measure of FCI stability across parameter space. We then train Kolmogorov-Arnold networks (KANs) -- a recently developed interpretable neural architecture -- to regress this metric from two band-geometric descriptors: the trace violation $T$ and the Berry curvature fluctuations $\sigma_B$. Applied to spinless fermions at filling $\nu=1/3$ in models on the checkerboard and kagome lattices, our approach yields compact analytical formulas that predict FCI stability with over $&gt;80 \%$ accuracy in both regression and classification tasks, and remain reliable even in data-scarce regimes. The learned relations reveal model-dependent trends, clarifying the limits of Landau-level-mimicking heuristics. Our framework provides a general method for extracting simple, phenomenological "laws" that connect many-body phase stability to chosen physical descriptors, enabling rapid hypothesis formation and targeted design of quantum phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01873v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oriol Mayn\'e i Comas, Andr\'e Grossi Fonseca, Sachin Vaidya, Marin Solja\v{c}i\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On-chip high-order parametric downconversion in the excitonic Mott insulator Nb$_3$Cl$_8$ for programmable multiphoton entangled states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01874</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01874v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spontaneous parametric downconversion (SPDC) and four-wave mixing in $\chi^{(2)}$ and $\chi^{(3)}$ media underpin most entangled-photon sources, but direct generation of higher-order entangled multiphoton states by $n$-th order parametric downconversion remains extremely challenging because conventional materials exhibit tiny high-order nonlinearities. Here we show that single-layer Nb$_3$Cl$_8$, an excitonic Mott insulator on a breathing Kagome lattice, supports exceptionally large nonlinear susceptibilities up to seventh order. Many-body GW--Bethe--Salpeter and time-dependent BSE / Kadanoff--Baym simulations yield resonant $\chi^{(2)}$--$\chi^{(7)}$ for monolayer Nb$_3$Cl$_8$, with $|\chi^{(4)}|$ and $|\chi^{(5)}|$ surpassing values in prototypical transition metal dichalcogenides by 5--9 orders of magnitude. We trace this enhancement to flat bands and strongly bound Frenkel excitons with ferroelectrically aligned out-of-plane dipoles. Building on experimentally demonstrated 1$\times N$ integrated beam splitters with arbitrary power ratios, we propose an on-chip architecture where each output arm hosts an Nb$_3$Cl$_8$ patch, optionally gated by graphene to tune the complex $n$-photon amplitudes. Using the ab-initio $\chi^{(3)}$ and $\chi^{(4)}$ values, we predict that three-photon GHZ$_3$ and four-photon cluster-state sources in this platform can achieve $n$-photon generation rates up to $\sim 10^8$ and $\sim 10^6$ times larger, respectively, than silica-fiber- and MoS$_2$-based implementations with comparable geometry. We derive the quantum Hamiltonian and explicit $n$-photon generation rates for this platform, and show how suitable interferometric networks enable electrically and spectrally tunable GHZ, $W$, and cluster states based on genuine high-order nonlinear processes in a 2D excitonic Mott insulator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01874v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dmitry Skachkov, Dirk R. Englund, Michael N. Leuenberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collapse of the superconducting order parameter in Ising superconductors with Rashba spin-orbit coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01910</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01910v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ising superconductors have attracted quite some attention recently, due to their resilience against magnetic fields way beyond the Pauli-paramagnetic limit. Their protection against external magnetic field relies on strong Ising spin-orbit coupling, which originates from in-plane inversion symmetry breaking. Due to the heavy atom nature of Ising SCs, a smaller but sizable Rashba SOC could be present through gating or interfacial effects. Here, we consider the effect of Rashba SOC in a two valley model of Ising superconductors with an attractive $s$-wave interaction. We show that Rashba SOC gives a critical magnetic field, above which the superconducting order parameter collapses at low temperatures. This effect, however, disappears at high temperatures. Our findings demonstrate that the low- and high temperature physics of Ising SCs is quantitatively and qualitatively different in our two-valley model, and may lead to new ways to determine the strength of the Rashba SOC in Ising SCs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01910v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. S. Harms, M. Hein, W. Belzig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Admittance and critical current of nonreciprocal Josephson junctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01955</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01955v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the nonequilibrium current response in diffusive superconductor-normal-metal-superconductor junctions subjected to a low-frequency AC voltage. Using a kinetic description based on the adiabatic motion of Andreev bound states, we derive a general expression for the admittance of a junction under a DC phase bias, formulated entirely in terms of the phase-dependent density of states induced by the proximity effect. A numerical solution of the full nonlinear Usadel equations that describe the dynamics of the junction is presented. The obtained results for the admittance and the Josephson current-phase relation apply to two-dimensional planar junctions with Rashba spin-orbit coupling and an in-plane Zeeman field, as well as to Josephson junctions formed with topological insulator surface states as the normal layer. The frequency dependence of the admittance captures the crossover between the hydrodynamic and collisionless regimes, distinguished by the relation between the drive frequency and the inelastic relaxation rate in the normal region.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01955v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tony Liu, Alex Levchenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Braided QM and Majorana qubits at third root of unity: a color Heisenberg-Lie (super)algebra framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00809v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce color Heisenberg-Lie (super)algebras graded by the abelian groups $Z_3^2$, $Z_2^p\times Z_3^2$ for $p=1,2,3$, and investigate the properties of their associated multi-particle quantum paraoscillators. In the Rittenberg-Wyler's color Lie (super)algebras framework the above abelian groups are the simplest ones which induce mixed brackets interpolating commutators and anticommutators. These mixed brackets allow to accommodate two types of parastatistics: one based on the permutation group (beyond bosons and fermions in any space dimension) and an anyonic parastatistics based on the braid group. In both such cases the two broad classes of paraparticles are given by parabosons and parafermions. Mixed-bracket parafermions are created by nilpotent operators; they satisfy a generalized Pauli exclusion principle leading to roots-of-unity truncations in their multi-particle energy spectrum (braided Majorana qubits and their Gentile-type parastatistics are recovered in this color Lie superalgebra setting). Mixed-bracket parabosons do not admit truncations of the spectrum; the minimal detectable signature of their parastatistics is encoded in the measurable probability density of two indistinguishable parabosonic oscillators in a given energy eigenstate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00809v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhanna Kuznetsova, Francesco Toppan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact quantum dynamics of Fermi--Hubbard systems using the Gaussian phase-space representation with diffusion gauges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00987</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.00987v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We use the Gaussian Phase-Space Representation to solve the real-time dynamic of interacting fermions in 1D, 2D, and 3D systems. The method is exact up to a spiking point, which represents a limit on the practical simulation time. The spiking can be delayed, and the practical simulation time extended, by adjusting the gauges of the representation, resulting in different equivalent stochastic differential equations. Here, we work on the so-called diffusion gauge and propose an algorithm to find efficiently new implementations of the noise terms. Compared with our initial results [F. Rousse \textit{et al.} 2024, J. Phys. A: Math. Theor. \textbf{57}, 015303], the new method achieves a significantly longer practical simulation time and can be applied to significantly larger systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.00987v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F Rousse, M Fasi, A Dmytryshyn, M Gulliksson, J F Corney, M Ogren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lorentz violation and momentum-space geometric phases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01156</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01156v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Geometric phases can manifest when a relativistic quantum particle moves cyclically along a loop in parameter space. The phase can be affected by the presence of a background field and can be accompanied by nontrivial topological features. The appearance of adiabatic geometric phases in momentum space is demonstrated for a Lorentz-violating Weyl fermion, where the role of the background is played by the coefficients for Lorentz violation. As explicit examples, the Berry curvature and the first Chern number are derived for two cases with large Lorentz violation, one incorporating CPT violation and one preserving CPT symmetry. Some alternative topological invariants are also obtained. In certain scenarios with large Lorentz violation, the physical vacuum is associated with a topological phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01156v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alan Kostelecky, Ralf Lehnert, Marco Schreck, Babak Seradjeh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of thermal annealing and film thickness on the structural and optical properties of indium-tin-oxide thin films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01441</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01441v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Indium-tin oxide (ITO) has been leveraged as a crucial functional layer in the optoelectronic frameworks, such as non-volatile color display thin films based on the ITO/phase-change material (PCM)/ITO/reflective metal multilayer structures on a silicon substrate. In addition to non-volatile color tuning by PCMs, phase transition of ITO may pose a substantial impact on display performances. Yet, a comprehensive colormap of ITO thin films as functions of annealing temperature and film thickness is missing. In this work, we systematically investigate properties of ITO films based on X-ray diffraction, spectroscopic ellipsometry and ultraviolet-visible spectrophotometry measurements. We provide a colormap of the ITO/platinum/silicon structure in terms of the annealing temperature (150-350 {\deg}C) and thickness (5-100 nm) for the non-volatile color display, and we observe strong color changes under 250 {\deg}C annealing treatment for the 50-nm and 100-nm-thick ITO films. We suggest that the intrinsic change in colors of the ITO functional thin-film layers should also be taken into account, when the PCM-based reconfigurable color devices are used in practice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01441v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ding Xu, Wen Zhou, Yuxin Du, Junying Zhang, Wei Zhang, Jiangjing Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antibunching in locally driven dissipative Lieb lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01645</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01645v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In Lieb lattices, geometric frustration and destructive interference of hopping cancels the occupation of certain sites, leading to flat-band physics. Here, we show numerically how, in the driven-dissipative Bose-Hubbard (DDBH) model arranged into Lieb lattices and related geometries, specific localised driving schemes can repurpose this interference to generate enhanced antibunching via a mechanism similar to the so-called unconventional photon blockade. Stochastic simulations using the positive-P method allow us to calculate occupations and second order correlations exactly for extended lattices. We use this to optimise the parameters for the possible observation of this effect in polariton micropillar experiments. This work demonstrates the possibility of using localised driving and interference effects to generate non-trivial quantum correlations in open quantum lattice systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01645v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex Ferrier, Micha{\l} Matuszewski, Piotr Deuar, Marzena H. Szyma\'nska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The algebraic spin liquid in the SU(6) Heisenberg model on the kagome lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09713</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09713v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explore the Dirac spin liquid (DSL) as a candidate for the ground state of the Mott insulating phase of fermions with six flavors on the Kagome lattice, particularly focusing on realizations using $^{173}$Yb atoms in optical lattices. Using mean-field theory and variational Monte Carlo simulations, we demonstrate that the Dirac spin liquid (DSL) has the lowest variational energy among SU(6) symmetry-preserving trial wave functions with a periodicity of a 12-site unit cell, as well as uniform chiral states with larger unit cells. It remains a local minimum even when small second-nearest neighbor and ring exchange interactions are introduced. To characterize the DSL, we calculate the static and dynamic structure factor of the Gutzwiller projected wavefunction and compare it with mean-field calculations. The static structure factor shows triangular-shaped plateaus around the $\mathrm{K}$ points in the extended Brillouin zone, with small peaks at the corners of these plateaus. The dynamical structure factor consists of a gapless continuum of fractionalized excitations. Our study also presents several complementary results, including bounds for the ground state energy, methods for calculating three-site ring exchange expectations in the projective mean field, the boundary of ferromagnetic states, and the non-topological nature of flat bands in the DSL band structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09713v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.144437</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 144437 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>D\'aniel V\"or\"os, Kr\'anitz P\'eter, Karlo Penc</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A resonant valence bond spin liquid in the dilute limit of doped frustrated Mott insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03372</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03372v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Ideas about resonant valence bond liquids and spin-charge separation have led to key concepts in physics such as quantum spin liquids, emergent gauge symmetries, topological order, and fractionalisation. Despite extensive efforts to demonstrate the existence of a resonant valence bond phase in the Hubbard model that originally motivated the concept, a definitive realisation has yet to be achieved. Here we present a solution to this long-standing problem by uncovering a resonant valence bond phase exhibiting spin-charge separation in realistic Hamiltonians. We show analytically that this ground state emerges in the dilute-doping limit of a half-filled Mott insulator on corner-sharing tetrahedral lattices with frustrated hopping, in the absence of exchange interactions. We confirm numerically that the results extend to finite exchange interactions, finite-sized systems and finite dopant density. Although much attention has been devoted to the emergence of unconventional states from geometrically frustrated interactions, our work demonstrates that kinetic energy frustration in doped Mott insulators may be essential for stabilising robust, topologically ordered states in real materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03372v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41567-025-02923-8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature Physics 21, 1211-1216 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Cecilie Glittum, Antonio \v{S}trkalj, Dharmalingam Prabhakaran, Paul A. Goddard, Cristian D. Batista, Claudio Castelnovo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconductivity and charge-density-wave in the Holstein model on the Penrose Lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18050</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.18050v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The exotic quantum states emerging in the quasicrystal (QC) have attracted extensive interest because of various properties absent in the crystal. In this paper, we systematically study the Holstein model at half filling on a prototypical structure of QC, namely rhombic Penrose lattice, aiming at investigating the superconductivity (SC) and other intertwined ordering arising from the interplay between quasiperiodicity and electron-phonon ({\it e}-ph) interaction. Through unbiased sign-problem-free determinant quantum Monte Carlo simulations, we reveal the salient features of the ground-state phase diagram. Distinct from the results on bipartite periodic lattices at half filling, SC is dominant in a large parameter regime on the Penrose lattice. When {\it e}-ph coupling is sufficiently strong, charge-density-wave order appears and strongly suppresses the SC. The strongest SC emerges at intermediate {\it e}-ph coupling strength and pronounced pairing fluctuation exists above the SC transition temperature. The strong pairing originates from the cooperative effects of unique lattice structure and macroscopically degenerate confined states at Fermi energy which uniquely exist on the Penrose lattice. Moreover, we demonstrate the forbidden ladders substantially suppress the phase coherence of SC. Our unbiased numerical results suggest that Penrose lattice is a potential platform to realize strong SC pairing, providing a promising avenue to searching for relatively high-$T_c$ SC dominantly induced by {\it e}-ph coupling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.18050v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.134.206001</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 134, 206001 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lu Liu, Zi-Xiang Li, Fan Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polarons and bipolarons in Rydberg-dressed extended Bose-Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06275</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06275v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Impurities immersed in hard-core Bose gases offer exciting opportunities to explore polaron and bipolaron physics. We investigate the ground state properties of a single and a pair of impurities throughout the superfluid and insulating (charge density wave) phases of the bosonic environment. In the superfluid phase, the impurity exhibits polaron-like behavior, forming a dressed quasiparticle. In contrast, in the insulating phase, the impurity regains its particle-like character, moving through a potential landscape shaped by the charge density wave order. Moreover, we show that two impurities can form a bound state even in the absence of an explicit impurity-impurity coupling. We establish the stability of this bound state within both the superfluid and insulating phases. Our results offer valuable insights for ongoing lattice polaron experiments with ultracold gases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06275v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. A. Dom\'inguez-Castro, L. Santos, L. A. Pe\~na Ardila</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancement of spin Hall angle by an order of magnitude via Cu intercalation in MoS$_2$/CoFeB heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18582</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18582v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) are a novel class of quantum materials with significant potential in spintronics, optoelectronics, valleytronics, and opto-valleytronics. TMDs exhibit strong spin-orbit coupling, enabling efficient spin-charge interconversion, which makes them ideal candidates for spin-orbit torque-driven spintronic devices. In this study, we investigated the spin-to-charge conversion through ferromagnetic resonance in MoS$_2$/Cu/CoFeB heterostructures with varying Cu spacer thicknesses. The conversion efficiency, quantified by the spin Hall angle, was enhanced by an order of magnitude due to Cu intercalation. Magneto-optic Kerr effect microscopy confirmed that Cu did not significantly modify the magnetic domains, indicating its effectiveness in decoupling MoS$_2$ from CoFeB. This decoupling preserves the spin-orbit coupling (SOC) of MoS$_2$ by mitigating the exchange interaction with CoFeB, as proximity to localized magnetization can alter the electronic structure and SOC. First-principles calculations revealed that Cu intercalation notably enhances the spin Berry curvature and spin Hall conductivity, contributing to the increased spin Hall angle. This study demonstrates that interface engineering of ferromagnet/TMD-based heterostructures can achieve higher spin-to-charge conversion efficiencies, paving the way for advancements in spintronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18582v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhisek Mishra, Pritam Das, Rupalipriyadarsini Chhatoi, Soubhagya Dash, Shubhransu Sahoo, Kshitij Singh Rathore, Pil-Ryung Cha, Seung-Cheol Lee, Satadeep Bhattacharjee, Subhankar Bedanta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral Bifurcation and Anomalous Supercurrent in Dissipative Topological Insulator-based Josephson Junctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09397</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09397v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The interplay between topological protection and dissipation constitutes a critical frontier in the realization of hybrid quantum devices. Here, we investigate the transport signatures in a dissipative topological insulator-based Josephson junction, a platform that directly probes the competition between quantum coherence and loss. We model dissipation by coupling a `lossy' metallic lead to the junction, described effectively by a non-Hermitian Hamiltonian derived using the Lindblad formalism. We observe that the junction exhibits an asymmetric complex Andreev spectrum, where the imaginary energy component imposes a finite lifetime on the quasi-bound states. Furthermore, beyond specific phase intervals, the real component of the spectrum bifurcates: one branch merges with the continuum, while the other penetrates just below the superconducting gap. Crucially, the characteristic zero-energy crossing shifts away from $\phi=\pi$ and acquires a non-zero imaginary component; consequently, the associated Majorana bound states acquire a finite lifetime, signaling a loss of robustness against dissipation. Finally, this spectral asymmetry drives an anomalous supercurrent, manifested as a non-vanishing current at zero phase difference. Our results reveal how dissipation fundamentally reshapes superconducting transport in topological junctions, opening new directions for dissipation-engineered quantum devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09397v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ardamon Sten, Paramita Dutta, Sudeep Kumar Ghosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constructing a variational ground state of matter fermions coupled to a vison pair in Kitaev's honeycomb model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15113</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15113v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a new method to construct simple and explicit variational approximations for the ground state of Kitaev's honeycomb model with a non-trivial Z2 flux configuration consisting of a pair of visons on neighbouring plaquettes. The method consists of retaining only the largest singular values of the generator of the transformation between the vison-pair and flux-free ground states. We compare physical quantities calculated using the approximate state to those obtained by extrapolating results of exact diagonalisation of finite lattices, finding them to be in very good agreement. We discuss ways to extend the method to more complicated flux configurations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15113v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Grace, A. Principi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\mathbb{Z}_2$ Vortex Crystals in Tetrahedral Antiferromagnets: Fractional Charges and Topological Magnons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.06008</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.06008v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report the formation of a $\mathbb{Z}_2$ vortex crystal in the tetrahedral antiferromagnetic order on a triangular lattice. The noncoplanar tetrahedral state consists of four sublattices with spins oriented along the faces of a tetrahedron in spin space. The long-range order characterized by a $\mathbb{Z}_2$ topology arises due to the Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction and appears at zero temperature and without external fields. Each vortex carries a half-integer electric charge relative to the uniform background in itinerant magnets, enabling the emergence of anyonic excitations. Its magnetic excitations include magnetically active gyrotropic and breathing modes, which -- under an external magnetic field -- carry nontrivial Chern numbers that stabilize chiral magnon edge states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.06008v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomoki Hirosawa, Alexander Mook, Maria Azhar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Band topology and dynamic multiferroicity induced from dynamical Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interactions in centrosymmetric lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06529</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06529v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a theory of a dynamical Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction (dDMI) in centrosymmetric crystals by generally considering the vibration of both cations and anions. It gives rise to an antisymmetric spin-lattice coupling, inducing magnon-phonon hybridized topological excitations. Moreover, we find that this dDMI naturally exhibits a magnetoelectric feature, leading to the presence of dynamic multiferroicity with finite toroidal moment distribution in the momentum space. By comparing toroidal moments with band skyrmion structure, we reveal the intrinsic connection between band topology and dynamic multiferroicity through the dDMI.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06529v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bowen Ma, Z. D. Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colloidal nanoparticles in liquid crystals: Bulk properties, biaxiality and untwisting in cholesterics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01417</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.01417v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the effects of colloidal nanoparticles (NPs) in liquid crystal samples in the dilute limit, in a Landau--de Gennes theoretical framework. The effects of the suspended NPs are captured by a homogenized energy, as outlined in~\cite{canevari2020design}. For spatially homogeneous samples, we explicitly compute the critical points and minimizers of the modified Landau--de Gennes energy and show that the presence of NP eliminates the first-order isotropic-nematic phase transition, stabilises elusive biaxial phases over some temperature ranges and that the symmetry of the NP boundary conditions or surface treatments dictates the bulk equilibrium phase at high temperatures. We also numerically demonstrate structural transitions from twisted helical director profiles to untwisted director profiles in cholesteric-filled channel geometries, driven by the collective effects of the NPs and increasing temperature. These transitions are reversible upon lowering the temperature in sufficiently large domains, where thermal hysteresis can also be observed. This behaviour opens interesting avenues for tuning the optical properties of confined, nano-doped cholesteric systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.01417v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prabakaran Rajamanickam, Fatimah Almutari, Apala Majumdar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonadiabatic Origin of Quantum-Metric Effects via Momentum-Space Metric Tensor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.06439</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.06439v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We reveal a fundamental geometric structure of momentum space arising from the nonadiabatic evolution of Bloch electrons. By extending semiclassical wave packet theory to incorporate nonadiabatic effects, we introduce a momentum-space metric tensor -- the nonadiabatic metric. This metric gives rise to two velocity corrections, dubbed geometric and geodesic velocities, providing a unified and intuitive framework for understanding nonlinear and nonadiabatic transport phenomena beyond Berry phase effects. Furthermore, we show that the nonadiabatic metric endows momentum space with a curved geometry, recasting wave packet dynamics as forced geodesic motion. In this picture, the metric defines distances, the Berry connection acts as a gauge potential, band dispersion serves as a scalar potential, and the toroidal topology of the Brillouin zone imposes periodic boundary conditions. When the nonadiabatic metric is constant, it reduces to an effective mass, allowing electrons to behave as massive particles in flat bands. In a flat Chern band with harmonic attractive interactions, the two-body wave functions mirror the Landau-level wave functions on a torus.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.06439v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yafei Ren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum state transfer and maximal entanglement between distant qubits using a minimal quasicrystal pump</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.00854</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.00854v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Coherent quantum state transfer over macroscopic distances between non-neighboring elements in quantum circuits is a crucial component to increase connectivity and simplify quantum information processing. To facilitate such transfers, an efficient and easily controllable quantum pump would be highly beneficial. In this work, we demonstrate such a quantum pump based on a one-dimensional quasicrystal Fibonacci chain~(FC). In particular, we utilize the unique properties of quasicrystals to pump the edge-localized winding states between the two distant ends of the chain by only minimal manipulation of the FC at its end points. We establish the necessary conditions for successful state transfer within a fully time-dependent picture and also demonstrate robustness of the transfer protocol against disorder. We then couple external qubits to each end of the FC and establish highly adaptable functionality as a quantum bus with both on-demand switching of the qubit states and generation of maximally entangled Bell states between the qubits. Thanks to the minimal control parameters, the setup is well-suited for implementation across diverse experimental platforms, thus establishing quasicrystals as an efficient platform for versatile quantum information processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.00854v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/8zys-w2v4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 205427 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Arnob Kumar Ghosh, Rub\'en Seoane Souto, Vahid Azimi-Mousolou, Annica M. Black-Schaffer, Patric Holmvall</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proximity effect and p-wave superconductivity in s-wave superconductor/helimagnet heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05479</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05479v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is known that in contrast to homogeneous ferromagnetism helical magnetism is compatible with superconductivity and causes only weak suppressive effect on superconducting critical temperature. Despite this fact it induces p-wave triplet superconducting correlations in homogeneous superconducting systems with intrinsic helical magnetism. The combination of these two facts indicates a high potential for the application of such systems in disspationless spintronics. For this reason here we investigate the proximity effect in atomically thin superconductor/helical (conical) magnet heterostructures (SC/HM). It is shown that in SC/HM heterostructures the strength of the proximity effect and, in particular, amplitude of p-wave triplet superconductivity and the degree of superconductivity suppression are complex functions of the magnet exchange field and filling factors of the magnet and the superconductor. Further we demonstrate that $p$-wave correlations ensure transport spin supercurrent flow in the SC/HM heterostructure with conical magnets and unveil the physical relationship between the transport spin supercurrent, degree of the magnet conicity and internal structure of p-wave correlations in the momentum space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05479v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/pmg9-sqyd</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 184515 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>G. A. Bobkov, A. V. Kornev, A. M. Bobkov, I. V. Bobkova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Projective Representations, Bogomolov Multiplier, and Their Applications in Physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12515</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.12515v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a pedagogical review of projective representations of finite groups and their physical applications in quantum many-body systems. Some of our physical results are new. We begin with a self-contained introduction to projective representations, highlighting the role of group cohomology, representation theory, and classification of irreducible projective representations. We then focus on a special subset of cohomology classes, known as the Bogomolov multiplier, which consists of cocycles that are symmetric on commuting pairs but remain nontrivial in group cohomology. Such cocycles have important physical implications: they characterize (1+1)D SPT phases that cannot be detected by string order parameters and give rise, upon gauging, to distinct gapped phases with completely broken non-invertible $\mathrm{Rep}(G)$ symmetry. We construct explicit lattice models for these phases and demonstrate how they are distinguished by the fusion rules of local order parameters. We show that a pair of completely broken $\mathrm{Rep}(G)$ SSB phases host nontrivial interface modes at their domain walls. As an example, we construct a lattice model where the ground state degeneracy on a ring increases from 32 without interfaces to 56 with interfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.12515v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryohei Kobayashi, Haruki Watanabe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin and thermal current scaling at a $Y$-junction of XX spin chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10267v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the boundary phase diagram and the low-temperature heat and magnetization transport at a $Y$-junction of XX spin chains. Depending on the magnetization axis anisotropy between the magnetic exchange interactions at the junction, the system exhibits two different strong-coupling regimes at low energies/temperatures, similar to the overscreened (topological) four- and to the two-channel Kondo fixed points. Using renormalization group arguments combined with boundary conformal field theory methods, we show the instability of the former under any XY-type anisotropy at the junction. We analyze the low-temperature spin and the heat conductances. We find evidence of spin fractionalization of the elementary excitations at the four-channel Kondo fixed point by means of the magnetic Wiedemann-Franz law. We caution that the instability under XY anisotropy may hinder the detection of the phenomenology related to the four-channel Kondo effect, therefore requiring careful control in experimental realizations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10267v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/9pvr-329m</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 205121 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Domenico Giuliano, Francesco Buccheri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radio-frequency charge detection on graphene electron-hole double quantum dots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12061v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: High-fidelity detection of charge transitions in quantum dots (QDs) is a key ingredient in solid state quantum computation. We demonstrate high-bandwidth radio-frequency charge detection in bilayer graphene quantum dots (QDs) using a capacitively coupled quantum point contact (QPC). The device design suppresses screening effects and enables sensitive QPC-based charge readout. The QPC is arranged to maximize the readout contrast between two neighboring, coupled electron and hole QDs. We apply the readout scheme to a single-particle electron-hole double QD and demonstrate time-resolved detection of charge states as well as magnetic field dependent tunneling rates. This promises a high-fidelity readout scheme for individual spin and valley states, which is important for the operation of spin, valley or spin-valley qubits in bilayer graphene.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12061v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katrin Hecker, Samuel M\"oller, Hubert Dulisch, \c{S}iyar Duman, Leon Stecher, Lucca Valerius, Tobias Deu{\ss}en, Saketh Ravuri, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Florian Libisch, Christian Volk, Christoph Stampfer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Phase Diagram of Generalized SSH Models with Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12373v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate interacting Su-Schrieffer-Heeger (SSH) chains with two- and three-site unit cells using density matrix renormalization group (DMRG) simulations. By selecting appropriate filling fractions and sweeping across interaction strength \( J_z \) and dimerization \( \delta \), we map out their phase diagrams and identify transition lines via entanglement entropy and magnetization measurements. In the two-site model, we observe the emergence of an interaction-induced antiferromagnetic intermediate phase between the topologically trivial and non-trivial regimes, as well as a critical region at negative \( J_z \) with suppressed magnetization and finite-size scaling of entanglement entropy. In contrast, the three-site model lacks an intermediate phase and exhibits asymmetric edge localization and antiferromagnetic ordering in both positive and negative \( J_z \) regimes. We further examine the response of edge states to Ising perturbations. In the two-site model, zero-energy edge modes are topologically protected and remain robust up to a finite interaction strength. However, in the three-site model, where the edge states reside at finite energy, this protection breaks down. Despite this, the edge-localized nature of these states survives in the form of polarized modes whose spatial profiles reflect the non-interacting limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12373v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxiao Hang, Stephan Haas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Quantum Tsallis Entropy to Strange Metals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13362v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a unified framework connecting quantum Tsallis statistics to electronic transport in strongly interacting systems. Starting from R\'enyi and Tsallis entropies, we construct a quantum Tsallis distribution that reduces to the conventional Fermi--Dirac distribution when $q=1$. For $q$ slightly deviating from unity, the correction term in the occupation function can be mapped to a $q$-deformed Schwarzian action, corresponding to soft reparametrization modes. Coupling these soft modes to electrons via the Fermi Golden Rule yields a modified scattering rate, which reproduces conventional Fermi-liquid behavior at low temperatures and linear-in-temperature resistivity at high temperatures. Using the memory matrix formalism, we analyze magnetotransport, finding a linear-in-field magnetoresistance and a Hall angle consistent with Anderson's two-lifetime scenario. At sufficiently low temperatures, both magnetoresistance and Hall response smoothly recover Fermi-liquid quadratic behaviors. This approach provides a controlled interpolation between Fermi-liquid and non-Fermi-liquid regimes, quantitatively linking $q$-deformation, soft-mode dynamics, and experimentally measurable transport coefficients in strange metals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13362v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xian-Hui Ge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Power-Law Spectra and Asymptotic $\omega/T$ Scaling in the Orbital-Selective Mott Phase of a Three-Orbital Hubbard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23758</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23758v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum materials whose properties lie beyond the celebrated Landau Fermi-liquid paradigm have been observed for decades across diverse material platforms. Finding microscopic lattice models for metallic states that exhibit such peculiar behavior remains a major theoretical challenge, as these features often originate from strong quantum fluctuations in strongly interacting electron systems. Here we investigate a three-orbital Hubbard model at a high-symmetry point that hosts a transition from a metallic to an orbital-selective Mott (OSM) phase. Employing single-site dynamical mean-field theory combined with full-density-matrix numerical renormalization group, we chart the $T-U$ phase diagram and obtain high-resolution real-frequency dynamics. In the OSM regime we find asymptotically scale-invariant (power-law) single-particle spectra and asymptotic $\omega/T$ scaling in both charge and spin channels, spanning several decades in frequency and temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23758v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabian Eickhoff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Suppression of quantized heat flow by the dielectric response of a compressible strip at the quantum Hall edge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22459</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22459v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a unified perturbative framework for energy transport along a chiral quantum Hall edge coupled to a disordered, compressible strip. Treating the strip as a generic linear response environment characterized by its retarded susceptibility, we obtain leading corrections to both the heat flux carried by the edge plasmon and to its spectrum. Two generic regimes emerge: (i) a gapped, local dielectric response with finite-range coupling, producing a negative correction to the quantized heat flux that scales as T^4 at low temperatures together with a convex cubic shift of the plasmon dispersion; and (ii) a hydrodynamic (diffusive) response with relaxation, yielding a crossover from T^4 to T^{3/2} scaling and a change of sign in the correction. We further introduce a microscopic dipolar model in which the edge couples electrostatically to localized dipole moments inside a wide compressible strip. This long-range interaction amplifies the nonlocal dielectric back-action and generates new suppression laws, T^3 or even T^2 for smooth disorder profiles, together with a universal ratio connecting spectral curvature to thermal response. Across all regimes, the total heat flux remains quantized: the apparent deficit of the plasmon contribution reflects reversible heat drag into the compressible strip rather than a breakdown of quantization. The framework thus provides a coherent and quantitatively plausible explanation of the "missing heat flux" anomaly and unifies the thermal and spectral signatures of quantum Hall edge dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22459v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eugene V. Sukhorukov, Adrien Tom\`a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limitations on Activation of High Dose Ge implant in beta-Ga2O3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19674</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19674v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Among ultrawide bandgap semiconductors, beta-Ga2O3 is particularly promising for high power and frequency applications. For devices, n-type concentrations above 10^19 cm^-3 are required. Ge is a promising alternative n-type dopant with an ionic radius similar to Ga. Homoepitaxial 010 beta-Ga2O3 films were implanted with Ge to form 50 and 100 nm box concentration of 3*10^19 cm^-3 and 5*10^19 cm^-3, with damage ranging from 1.2 to 2.0 displacement per atom. For lower damage implants, optimized anneals in ultrahigh purity N2 at 950-1000 C for 5-10 minutes resulted in Rs of 600-700 omega/sqr, mobilities of 60-70 cm^2/Vs, and Ge activation of up to 40%. For higher damage implants, activation dropped to 23% with similar mobilities. Ge diffusion, measured by second ion mass spectrometry, showed formation of a Ge "clustering peak" with a concentration exceeding the initial implant following anneals in N2 or O2 at 950-1000 C. Beyond this peak, minimal Ge diffusion occurred for N2 anneals at 950 C, but at 1050 C non-Fickian diffusion extended to &gt;200 nm. Electrical activation data suggests that clustered Ge is electrically inactive. To understand Ge clustering, several samples were characterized by synchrotron x-ray diffraction. Second-phase precipitates were observed in as-implanted samples which then fully dissoved after furnace annealing in N2 at 1050 C. Diffraction peaks suggest these implant-induced precipitates may be related to a high pressure Pa-3 phase of GeO2, and may evolve during anneals to explain the Ge clustering. Ultimately, we believe Ge clustering limits activation of implanted Ge at high concentrations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19674v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tianhai Luo, Katie R. Gann, Cameron A. Gorsak, Ming-Chiang Chang, Prescott E Evans, Thaddeus J Asel, Hari P Nair, R. B. van Dover, Michael O. Thompson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dichroism from Chiral Thermoelectric Probes: Generalized Sum Rules for Orbital and Heat Magnetizations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21599</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21599v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a unified framework that relates orbital and heat magnetizations to experimentally accessible excitation spectra, through thermoelectric probes and generalized sum rules. By analyzing zero-temperature transport coefficients and applying Kramers-Kronig relations, we derive spectral representations of magnetization densities from thermoelectric correlation functions. Excitation rates under chiral thermoelectric drives then naturally emerge as direct probes of these Kubo-type correlators, placing orbital and heat magnetizations on equal footing with the topological Chern number. As a direct consequence of our formalism, we introduce a hierarchical construction that organizes orbital and heat magnetizations into distinct physical contributions accessible through sum rules, and also derive real-space markers of these magnetizations. From an experimental standpoint, we propose concrete implementations of thermoelectric dichroic measurements in quantum-engineered platforms based on modulated strain fields. These results establish thermoelectric dichroic measurements as a versatile route to access and disentangle fundamental ground-state properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21599v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Baptiste Bermond, Lucila Peralta Gavensky, Ana\"is Defossez, Nathan Goldman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observing the spatial and temporal evolution of exciton wave functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.23001</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.23001v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Excitons, the correlated electron-hole pairs governing optical and transport properties in organic semiconductors, have long resisted direct experimental access to their full quantum-mechanical wave functions. Here, we use femtosecond time-resolved photoemission orbital tomography (trPOT), combining high-harmonic probe pulses with time- and momentum-resolved photoelectron spectroscopy, to directly image the momentum-space distribution and ultrafast dynamics of excitons in $\alpha$-sexithiophene thin films. We introduce a quantitative model that enables reconstruction of the exciton wave function in real space, including both its spatial extent and its internal phase structure. The reconstructed wave function reveals coherent delocalization across approximately three molecular units and exhibits a characteristic phase modulation, consistent with ab initio calculations within the framework of many-body perturbation theory. Time-resolved measurements further show a $\sim 20$\% contraction of the exciton radius within 400 fs, providing direct evidence of self-trapping driven by exciton-phonon coupling. These results establish trPOT as a general and experimentally accessible approach for resolving exciton wave functions -- with spatial, phase, and temporal sensitivity -- in a broad class of molecular and low-dimensional materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.23001v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcel Theilen, Siegfried Kaidisch, Monja Stettner, Sarah Zajusch, Eric Fackelman, Alexa Adamkiewicz, Robert Wallauer, Andreas Windischbacher, Christian S. Kern, Michael G. Ramsey, Fran\c{c}ois C. Bocquet, Serguei Soubatch, F. Stefan Tautz, Ulrich H\"ofer, Peter Puschnig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Mode Lens for Momentum Microscopy and XPEEM: Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10104v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The strong electric field between the sample and the extractor is the core of cathode lenses and a pivotal determinant of high resolution. Nevertheless, fields in the range of 3-8 kV/mm can be a source of complications. Local field enhancement at sharp edges or microscopic protrusions of cleaved samples may result in field emission or flashovers. Moreover, slow background electrons are drawn into the microscope column, where they contribute to space charge effects. A novel front lens configuration, optimized through ray-tracing simulations, significantly reduces the field at the sample and allows even for zero field or retarding field, which serves to suppress space charge effects. One or several annular electrodes, situated in a concentric position relative to the extractor, serve to form an additional lens within the gap between the sample and the extractor. The refractory power of this lens, and consequently the field at the sample surface, can be modified by adjusting the potentials of the annular electrodes. The imaging properties and aberrations of this gap lens have been investigated with regard to momentum imaging and XPEEM. The study encompasses the energy range from the few-eV level for laser-ARPES to 6 keV, for hard X-ray ARPES. The additional converging lens situated in close proximity to the sample exhibits a reduced field curvature of the k-image in the backfocal plane. This allows for the acquisition of larger fields of view in both momentum and real-space imaging.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10104v2</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Olena Tkach, Gerd Schoenhense</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stabilizing Non-Abelian Topological Order against Heralded Noise via Local Lindbladian Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21402v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: An important open question for the current generation of highly controllable quantum devices is understanding which phases can be realized as stable steady-states under local quantum dynamics. In this work, we show how robust steady-state phases with both Abelian and non-Abelian mixed-state topological order can be stabilized, in two spatial dimensions (2d), against generic ``heralded" noise using active dynamics that incorporate measurement and feedback, modeled as a \emph{fully local} Lindblad master equation. These topologically ordered steady states are two-way connected to pure topologically ordered ground states using local quantum channels, and preserve quantum information for a time that is exponentially large in the system size. Specifically, we present explicit constructions of families of local Lindbladians for both Abelian ($\mathbb{Z}_2$) and non-Abelian ($D_4$) topological order whose steady-states host mixed-state topological order when the noise is below a threshold strength. As the noise strength is increased, these models exhibit first-order transitions to intermediate mixed state phases where they encode robust classical memories, followed by (first-order) transitions to a trivial steady state at high noise rates. When the noise is imperfectly heralded, steady-state order disappears but our active dynamics significantly enhances the lifetime of the encoded logical information. To carry out the numerical simulations for the non-Abelian $D_4$ case, we introduce a generalized stabilizer tableau formalism that permits efficient simulation of the non-Abelian Lindbladian dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21402v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/zf7y-hxtq</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PRX Quantum 6, 030363 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sanket Chirame, Abhinav Prem, Sarang Gopalakrishnan, Fiona J. Burnell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistics of Abelian topological excitations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07653</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07653v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we develop a novel theory that generalizes the concept of anyon statistics to Abelian topological excitations of any dimension. We axiomatize excitations as a selected collection of states and operators satisfying the configuration axiom and the locality axiom, purely based on many-body quantum mechanics. Upon these axioms, we define a rigorous and self-contained theory of statistics using only basic algebra and can be implemented on a computer. While our theory is developed independently, the results align with existing physical theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07653v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanyu Xue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Irrational CFTs from coupled anyon chains with non-invertible symmetries?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14280</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14280v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Irrational CFTs in 1+1d with a discrete spectrum and no conserved currents other than the stress-tensor are expected to be generic, unsolvable by standard methods, and hard to construct explicitly. We introduce a lattice model that realizes a candidate for such a CFT as a conformal phase of matter without fine-tuning. The model is constructed by coupling $N\geq3$ golden anyon chains together, preserving $N$ copies of the Fibonacci non-invertible symmetry. We use the MPS/DMRG approach to study this model numerically, which allows us to calculate the corresponding conformal data, obtaining hints of its irrationality. Along the way, we characterize the phase diagram for $N=2$ coupled chains where we identify a weakly first-order phase transition as well as critical points that we are able to identify with known rational CFTs, except for one case. We also provide an extensive list of rational CFTs with $1&lt;c&lt;2.1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14280v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ant\'onio Antunes, Junchen Rong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extending fusion rules with finite subgroups: For a general understanding of quotient or gauging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.08639v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct the $Z_{N}$ symmetry extended fusion ring of bulk and chiral theories and the corresponding modular partition functions with nonanomalous subgroup $Z_{n}(\subset Z_{N})$. The chiral fusion ring provides fundamental data for the $Z_{N}$ graded symmetry topological field theories and also provides algebraic data of smeared boundary conformal field theories describing zero modes of the extended models. For more general multicomponent or coupled systems, we also obtain a new series of extended theories. By applying the folding trick, their partition functions correspond to charged or gapped domain walls or massless renormalization group flows preserving quotient group structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.08639v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoshiki Fukusumi, Shinichiro Yahagi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heralded Emission Detection in InAs/ZnSe Quantum Dot Solids Using Time-Correlated Photons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11704</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11704v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Harnessing quantum correlations between photons is an emerging frontier in optical spectroscopy, yet experimental demonstrations have largely remained limited to molecular systems at room temperature. Here, we investigate heralded emission detection (HED) under continuous-wave entangled-photon excitation of near-infrared (NIR)-emitting colloidal III-V quantum dot (QD) solids at low temperatures. We demonstrate the advantages of superconducting nanowire single-photon detectors (SNSPDs) for high time resolution ($\sim$72 ps) and large-area NIR avalanche photodiodes (APDs) for high emission count rates ($\sim$2000 cps). Second-order photon-correlation analysis reveals exciton lifetimes and fine-structure energy splittings. These results establish NIR colloidal QDs as a bright, tunable model system for quantum-light spectroscopy and highlight their compatibility with optical cavities as a further experimental control parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11704v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chieh Tsao, Xiang Li, Alex Hinkle, Yifan Chen, Elvar Oskarsson, Uri Banin, Hendrik Utzat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Orders from Reflection Positive Frustration-free Hamiltonians</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20662</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20662v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We establish a framework with reflection positivity as the first principle for establishing the boundary theory of topologically ordered quantum spin systems. For any reflection positive frustration-free Hamiltonian, We proved that the local topological quantum order (LTQO) condition of ground states on a disk holds if and only if the ground state on the sphere is non-degenerate. Furthermore, we show that the Osterwalder-Schrader reconstruction produces the boundary local net of operator algebras from the local ground states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20662v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhengwei Liu, Zishuo Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
