<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 04:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>XDXD: End-to-end crystal structure determination with low resolution X-ray diffraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17936</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.17936v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Determining crystal structures from X-ray diffraction data is fundamental across diverse scientific fields, yet remains a significant challenge when data is limited to low resolution. While recent deep learning models have made breakthroughs in solving the crystallographic phase problem, the resulting low-resolution electron density maps are often ambiguous and difficult to interpret. To overcome this critical bottleneck, we introduce XDXD, to our knowledge, the first end-to-end deep learning framework to determine a complete atomic model directly from low-resolution single-crystal X-ray diffraction data. Our diffusion-based generative model bypasses the need for manual map interpretation, producing chemically plausible crystal structures conditioned on the diffraction pattern. We demonstrate that XDXD achieves a 70.4\% match rate for structures with data limited to 2.0~\AA{} resolution, with a root-mean-square error (RMSE) below 0.05. Evaluated on a benchmark of 24,000 experimental structures, our model proves to be robust and accurate. Furthermore, a case study on small peptides highlights the model's potential for extension to more complex systems, paving the way for automated structure solution in previously intractable cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.17936v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiale Zhao, Cong Liu, Yuxuan Zhang, Chengyue Gong, Zhenyi Zhang, Shifeng Jin, Zhenyu Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Highly efficient quantum Stirling engine using multilayer Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.18086v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, quantum Stirling engines based on monolayer, AB-stacked bilayer, and ABC-stacked trilayer graphene under perpendicular magnetic fields are analyzed. Performance maps of the useful work \((\eta W)\) reveal a robust optimum at low magnetic fields and moderately low temperatures, with all stackings capable of reaching Carnot efficiency under suitable configurations. The AB bilayer achieves this across the broadest parameter window while sustaining finite work, the monolayer exhibits highly constrained regimes, and the trilayer shows smoother trends with sizable \(\eta W\). These results identify multilayer graphene, particularly the AB bilayer, as a promising platform for efficient Stirling engines, while also highlighting the versatility of the monolayer in realizing all four operational regimes of the Stirling cycle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.18086v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bastian Castorene, Francisco J. Pe\~na, Eric Suarez, Caio Lewenkopf, Martin HvE Groves, Natalia Cort\'es, Patricio Vargas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Hidden Symmetry and Altermagnetism with Sub-Picometer Sensitivity via Nonlinear Transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18144</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.18144v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: X-ray and neutron diffraction are foundational tools for determining crystal structures, but their resolution limits can lead to misassignments, especially in materials with subtle distortions or competing phases. Here, we demonstrate the use of nonlinear transport as a complementary approach to uncover hidden crystal symmetries, using the strongly correlated Ca$_3$Ru$_2$O$_7$ as a case study. Below 48 K (T$_S$), where the magnetic moments of the antiferromagnetic phase reorient from the a- to the b-axis, leading to a pseudogap opening, our measurements, with support of DFT, reveal a previously overlooked lower-symmetry phase. This is manifested by the emergence of longitudinal nonlinear resistance (NLR) along the b-axis below T$_S$, providing direct evidence of combined translational and time-reversal symmetry breaking. This response also suggests a transformation from a conventional antiferromagnet into an altermagnet. The lower-symmetry phase arises from a subtle lattice distortion (~0.1 pm) associated with the magnetic transition at T$_S$, below the detection limit of conventional diffraction. Moreover, this NLR below T$_S$ is accompanied by a nonlinear Hall effect, both of which are enhanced by the large quantum metric associated with Weyl chains near the Fermi surface. Our findings demonstrate nonlinear transport as a sensitive probe of hidden symmetry breaking and altermagnetism, complementing and extending beyond the reach of traditional diffraction and spectroscopic techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.18144v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subin Mali, Yufei Zhao, Yu Wang, Saugata Sarker, Yangyang Chen, Zixuan Li, Jun Zhu, Ying Liu, Venkatraman Gopalan, Binghai Yan, Zhiqiang Mao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Altermon: a magnetic-field-free parity protected qubit based on a narrow altermagnet Josephson junction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18145</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.18145v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Altermagnets provide a new route to engineer superconducting circuits without magnetic fields. We theoretically study the Andreev bound state (ABS) spectrum of a finite-width altrmagnet-based Josephson junction and show how the $d$-wave altermagnetic symmetry and geometric confinement shape its low-energy excitations. We find a clear distinction between the two $d$-wave symmetries: $d_{x^2-y^2}$ order produces spin splitting, whereas $d_{xy}$ order preserves spin degeneracy and exhibits splitting of the ABS spectrum induced by intermode hybridization. Leveraging these novel features, we propose applying a transverse electric field to tune the system and realize a magnetic-field-free, parity-protected superconducting qubit that we call altermon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.18145v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sakineh Vosoughi-nia, Micha{\l} P. Nowak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anisotropic-Strain Control of The Magnetic Structure in Mn\textsubscript{3}GaN</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.18174v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A first principles study is conducted to explore the changes in the magnetic structure of Mn\textsubscript{3}GaN under anisotropic biaxial strain. Mn\textsubscript{3}GaN is an antiperovskite with a structure similar to that of an ideal cubic perovskite. Several manganese nitride antiperovskites including Mn\textsubscript{3}GaN were reported to have a frustrated noncollinear antiferromagnetic structure. Successful electric switching of its magnetic structure has been reported. Furthermore, despite a cubic lattice symmetry, the magnetic symmetry is rhombohedral, allowing a piezomagnetic response. Tensile biaxial strain has been shown to produce a net magnetic moment by inducing in-plane spin canting. Compressive biaxial strain has been used to induce a spin-polarized ferro- or ferrimagnetic phase. In this study, anisotropic strain in the (001) plane is applied, outlining a magnetic phase diagram that can predict the properties when growing Mn\textsubscript{3}GaN thin films on noncubic substrates. The lattice vectors along the a and b crystallographic axes are strained by -5\% to 5\% in percentwise increments in all permutations. An extensive phase diagram is mapped, revealing multiple combinations of strain applied to the two lattice vectors that result in a ferro- or ferrimagnetic transition. Unlike previous results, not only strictly compressive strain on both lattice vectors, but combinations of tensile and compressive strain, as well as uniaxial strain, are seen producing the magnetic phase transitions. Furthermore, while biquadratic strain was seen producing a net moment in the [110] direction under tensile strain and [\bar{1}\bar{1}0] under compressive strain, anisotropic strain allows tuning the direction of the net magnetization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.18174v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roman Malyshev, Ingeborg-Helene Svenum, Sverre M. Selbach, Thomas Tybell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>All-Electrical Self-Switching of van der Waals Chiral Antiferromagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18272</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.18272v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Antiferromagnets have garnered significant attention due to their negligible stray field and ultrafast magnetic dynamics, which are promising for high-density and ultrafast spintronic applications. Their dual functionality as both spin sources and information carriers could enable all-electrical self-induced switching of antiferromagnetic order, offering great potential for ultra-compact spintronic devices. However, related progress is still elusive. Here, we report the deterministic switching of chiral antiferromagnetic orders induced by charge current at zero external magnetic field in the van der Waals (vdW) magnetically intercalated transition metal dichalcogenide CoTa3S6. This system exhibits strong interactions between cobalt atom magnetic moment lattice and itinerant electrons within the metallic layers, as demonstrated by temperature-dependent angle-resolved photoemission, scanning tunneling spectroscopy, and topological Nernst effect measurements. Notably, the itinerant-localization interactions lead to current-induced chiral spin orbit torques as well as Ruderman-Kittel-Kasuya-Yosida (RKKY) exchange torques that interact with the localized magnetic moments, facilitating all-electrical switching of the chiral magnetic order in the CoTa3S6 flake. Our work opens a promising avenue for manipulating antiferromagnetic orders by delicately engineering the synergistic interactions between magnetic moments and itinerant electrons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.18272v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junlin Xiong, Jiawei Jiang, Yanwei Cui, Han Gao, Ji Zhou, Zijia Liu, KuiKui Zhang, Shaobo Cheng, Kehui Wu, Sang-Wook Cheong, Kai Chang, Zhongkai Liu, Hongxin Yang, Shi-Jun Liang, Bin Cheng, Feng Miao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Floquet engineering enabled by charge density wave transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18323</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.18323v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Floquet engineering has emerged as a powerful approach for dynamically tailoring the electronic structures of quantum materials through time-periodic light fields generated by ultrafast laser pulses. The light fields can transiently dress Bloch electrons, creating novel electronic states inaccessible in equilibrium. While such temporal modulation provides dynamic control, spatially periodic modulations, such as those arising from charge density wave (CDW) order, can also dramatically reconstruct the band structure through real-space symmetry breaking. The interplay between these two distinct forms of modulation-temporal and spatial-opens a new frontier in electronic-phase-dependent Floquet engineering. Here we demonstrate this concept experimentally in the prototypical CDW material 1T-TiSe$_2$. Using time- and angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (TrARPES) with mid-infrared pumping, we observe a striking pump-induced instantaneous downshift of the valence band maximum (VBM), which is in sharp contrast to the subsequent upward shift on picosecond timescale associated with CDW melting. Most remarkably, the light-induced VBM downshift is observed exclusively in the CDW phase and only when the pump pulse is present, reaching maximum when pumping near resonance with the CDW gap. These observations unequivocally reveal the critical role of CDW in the Floquet engineering of TiSe$_2$. Our work demonstrates how time-periodic drives can synergistically couple to spatially periodic modulations to create non-equilibrium electronic states, establishing a new paradigm for Floquet engineering enabled by spontaneous symmetry breaking.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.18323v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fei Wang, Xuanxi Cai, Teng Xiao, Changhua Bao, Haoyuan Zhong, Wanying Chen, Tianyun Lin, Tianshuang Sheng, Xiao Tang, Hongyun Zhang, Pu Yu, Zhiyuan Sun, Shuyun Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KVASIR: A backscattering neutron spectrometer for hard condensed matter at ESS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.18415v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the instrument concept for KVASIR, a backscattering indirect time-of-flight neutron spectrometer for the European Spallation Source (ESS). KVASIR will probe low lying excitations of single crystal hard condensed matter that many advanced technologies rely upon. The instrument is simultaneously optimized for high resolution of energy-and momentum transfer, while ensuring perturbation by high magnetic fields. Detailed ray tracing simulations, considering the true geometry and aberrations of the analyser configuration have been performed. The proposed concept has room for polarisation analysis and extreme sample environments. Inelastic neutron scattering studies of single crystal hard condensed matter, with a particular focus on quantum, at yet unseen spatial and dynamic precision under extreme conditions are hereby enabled.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.18415v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amalie F. Davidsen, Kristine M. L. Krighaar, Pascale P. Deen, and Kim Lefmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ideal Nodal-Sphere Semimetal in the Three-Dimensional Boron Allotrope CT-B$_{24}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18426</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.18426v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nodal-sphere semimetals (NSSMs), featuring spherical band degeneracies in momentum space, constitute a fascinating class of topological materials. However, their realization in real materials is severely hampered by discrete crystallographic symmetry constraints, often resulting in gapped ``pseudo'' nodal spheres. Here, combining first-principles calculations and symmetry analysis, we predict a new three-dimensional boron allotrope, CT-B$_{24}$, as a nearly ideal NSSM. Its structural stability is systematically confirmed by phonon calculations, \textit{ab initio} molecular dynamics simulations at 600~K, and elastic constant analysis. Notably, the electronic structure of CT-B$_{24}$ exhibits two bands crossing linearly near the Fermi level, forming a quasi-nodal sphere around the $\Gamma$ point. The maximum energy gap is merely 0.008~meV, which is two orders of magnitude smaller than the gaps reported in previous pseudo-NSSMs. Furthermore, the (001) surface hosts pronounced drumhead-like surface states located outside the projected nodal sphere, providing distinct signatures detectable by angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES). The nodal sphere also demonstrates remarkable robustness and tunability under external strain, driving a topological phase transition from an NSSM to a Dirac semimetal and finally to a trivial insulator. Our work not only presents a superior material platform for exploring nodal-sphere physics but also suggests potential for strain-tunable topological devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.18426v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao-jing Gao, Yanfeng Ge, Yan Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric control of the moire twist angle in heterobilayer flakes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18694</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.18694v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate a finite twist-angle stabilization mechanism in lattice-mismatched 2D heterobilayers, which results from the geometric alignment between the flake edges and its moire pattern. Using atomistic simulations of graphene on hexagonal boron nitride flakes with diameters of up to $\sim 2500${\AA}, we identify robust metastable angles at $\sim 0.61^\circ$ for armchair and $\sim1.89^\circ$ for zigzag-edged flakes, tunable via in-plane heterostrain. This locking mechanism, which relies on energy barriers that are an order of magnitude larger than those of nearby metastable twist angles, provides a geometric route to precision twist-angle control of two-dimensional heterostructures and to understand the self-orientation of macroscopic flakes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.18694v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prathap Kumar Jharapla, Nicolas Leconte, Zhiren He, Guru Khalsa, Jeil Jung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fermi arcs for generic nodal points hosting monopoles or dipoles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.18785v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fermi arcs represent the surface states at the boundary of a three-dimensional topological semimetal with the vacuum, illustrating the notion of bulk-boundary correspondence playing out in real materials. Their special character is tied up with the topological charges carried by the nodes of the semimetal in the momentum space, where two or more bands cross. In fact, they are constrained to begin and end on the perimeters of the projections of the Fermi surfaces of the bands tangentially, signalling their mixing with the bulk states. The number of Fermi arcs grazing onto the tangents of the outermost projection about a given node also reflects the magnitude of the charge at the node (equalling the Berry-curvature monopole), revealing the intrinsic topology of the underlying bandstructure, which can be visualised in experiments like ARPES. Here we take upon the task of unambiguously characterising the analytical structure of these states for generic nodal points, (1) whose degeneracy might be twofold or multifold; and (2) the associated bands might exhibit isotropic or anisotropic, linear- or nonlinear-in-momentum dispersion. Moreover, we also address the question of whether we should get any Fermi arcs at all for topological nodes carrying zero values of monopoles, but representing ideal dipoles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.18785v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ipsita Mandal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiscale transitional flow in anisotropic nanoparticle suspensions revealed by time-resolved x-ray scatter microscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18444</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.18444v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Complex fluids transition from laminar to transitory flow above a critical control parameter, akin to their Newtonian counterparts. In a continuum mechanics sense, fluid elements follow the ensuing complex trajectories, giving rise to secondary flows in terms of macroscopic vortices and patterns thereof. However, if we replace idealized fluid elements with actual anisotropic nanoparticles, would their trajectories still reveal the same spatiotemporal behavior as the macroscopic flow field? This question is fundamental for complex fluids, where fully developed turbulence is suppressed by high viscosities and where understanding particle-flow coupling is central to transport, processing, and structure formation. To address this question, we develop small-angle x-ray scatter microscopy of unprecedented temporal resolution combined with polarized light imaging, thereby bridging seven orders of magnitude in lengtscales. Proof-of-principle is demonstrated on a classical stability problem, Taylor-Couette flow, of platelet-like graphene oxide nanoparticle and rod-like cellulose nanocrystal suspensions. The analysis shows hitherto hidden, markedly different multiscale dynamics underlying flow stability; while the platelet-like particles follow the wavy motion of the macroscopic, secondary flow field, the rod-like particles exhibit high-frequency motion that is uncorrelated with the vortex instabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.18444v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kesavan Sekar, Viney Ghai, Reza Ghanbari, Marko Bek, Marianne Liebi, Aleksandar Matic, Ann E. Terry, Kim Nyg{\aa}rd, Roland K\'ad\'ar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unraveling Intertwined Orders in the Strongly Correlated Kagome Metal CsCr3Sb5</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06778</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06778v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: While correlated phenomena of flat bands have been extensively studied in twisted systems, the ordered states that emerge from interactions in the intrinsic flat bands of kagome lattice materials remain largely unexplored. The newly discovered kagome metal CsCr3Sb5 offers a unique and rich platform for this research, as its multi-orbital flat bands at the Fermi surface result in a complex interplay of pressurized superconductivity, antiferromagnetism, a structural phase transition, and density wave orders. Here, using ultrafast optical techniques, we provide strong spectroscopic evidence for a charge density wave transition in CsCr3Sb5, resolving previous ambiguities. Crucially, we identify rotational symmetry breaking that manifests as a three-state Potts-type nematicity. Our elastoresistance measurements directly demonstrate the electronic origin of this order, as the rotational-symmetry-breaking E2g component of the elastoresistance shows a divergent behaviour around the transition temperature. This exotic nematicity results from the lifting of degeneracy of the multi-orbital flat bands, akin to phenomena seen in certain iron-based superconductors. Our study pioneers the investigation of ultrafast dynamics in flat-band systems at the Fermi surface, offering new insights into the interactions between multiple elementary excitations in strongly correlated systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06778v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liangyang Liu, Yidian Li, Hengxin Tan, Yi Liu, Kuanglv Sun, Ying Shi, Yuxin Zhai, Hao Lin, Guanghan Cao, Xianhui Chen, Tao Wu, Binghai Yan, Guang-Ming Zhang, Luyi Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hamiltonian parameter inference from resonant inelastic x-ray scattering with active learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16021</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.16021v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Identifying model Hamiltonians is a vital step toward creating predictive models of materials. Here, we combine Bayesian optimization with the EDRIXS numerical package to infer Hamiltonian parameters from resonant inelastic X-ray scattering (RIXS) spectra within the single atom approximation. To evaluate the efficacy of our method, we test it on experimental RIXS spectra of NiPS3, NiCl2, Ca3LiOsO6, and Fe2O3, and demonstrate that it can reproduce results obtained from hand-fitted parameters to a precision similar to expert human analysis while providing a more systematic mapping of parameter space. Our work provides a key first step toward solving the inverse scattering problem to extract effective multi-orbital models from information-dense RIXS measurements, which can be applied to a host of quantum materials. We also propose atomic model parameter sets for two materials, Ca3LiOsO6 and Fe2O3, that were previously missing from the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.16021v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marton K. Lajer, Xin Dai, Kipton Barros, Matthew R. Carbone, S. Johnston, M. P. M. Dean</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Floquet-engineered moire quasicrystal patterns of ultracold Bose gases in twisted bilayer optical lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.21093v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the formation of moir\'e quasicrystal patterns in Bose gases confined in twisted bilayer optical lattices via Floquet-engineered intralayer atomic interactions. Dynamical evolutions of the inverse participation ratio and the density wave amplitude reveal the stage for the emergence of moir\'e quasicrystal patterns, whose symmetry can be easily manipulated by the modulation frequencies and amplitudes. Reducing the frequencies and increasing the amplitudes can both facilitate lattice symmetry breaking and the subsequent emergence of rotational symmetry. Notably, a twelve-fold quasicrystal pattern emerges under specific parameters, closely resembling the moir\'e quasicrystal in twisted bilayer graphene. The momentum-space distributions also exhibit high rotational symmetry, which is consistent with the real-space patterns at specific evolution times. Our findings establish a new quantum platform for exploring quasicrystals and their symmetry properties in ultracold bosonic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.21093v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhenze Fan, Juan Wang, Yan Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature Dependence of the Momentum-Resolved Static Spin Susceptibility in a Mott-Proximate Cuprate Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16884v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents the temperature dependence of the static spin susceptibility at $\mathbf{q} = (\pi, \pi)$ and $\mathbf{q} = (\pi, 0)$ in a Mott-proximate cuprate model with an antinodal pseudogap -- a model system for high-temperature superconducting (HTSC) cuprates.
  The results show the susceptibility onset temperature tracks the critical temperature ($T_c$) of HTSCs with a comparable scale across the electron filling factor. Also, as the electron filling decreases and the chemical potential approaches the antinodal van Hove region, the susceptibility at $\mathbf{q}=(\pi,0)$ -- the axial particle-hole response -- grows markedly.
  The emergence of cuprate superconductivity correlates with a suppression of low-energy antinodal spin response and associated particle-hole excitations, which would otherwise dephase $d$-wave pairing, commonly attributed to spin fluctuations. In this context, the pseudogap partially suppresses antinodal spectral weight near $\omega = 0$, thereby reducing the low-$\omega$ particle-hole phase space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16884v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keishichiro Tanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Protocols for Creating Anyons and Defects via Gauging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.04181</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.04181v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Creating and manipulating anyons and symmetry defects in topological phases, especially those with a non-Abelian character, constitutes a primitive for topological quantum computation. We provide a physical protocol for implementing the ribbon operators of non-Abelian anyons and symmetry defects. We utilize dualities, in particular the Kramers-Wannier or gauging map, which have previously been used to construct topologically ordered ground states by relating them to simpler states. In this work, ribbon operators are implemented by applying a gauging procedure to a lower-dimensional region of such states. This protocol uses sequential unitary circuits or, in certain cases, constant-depth adaptive circuits. We showcase this for anyons and defects in the $\mathbb{Z}_3$ toric code and $S_3$ quantum double. The general applicability of our method is demonstrated by deriving unitary expressions for ribbon operators of various (twisted) quantum doubles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.04181v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/q2c6-nd6r</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Anasuya Lyons, Chiu Fan Bowen Lo, Nathanan Tantivasadakarn, Ashvin Vishwanath, Ruben Verresen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trapped-ion quantum simulation of the Fermi-Hubbard model as a lattice gauge theory using hardware-aware native gates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07778</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07778v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Fermi-Hubbard model (FHM) is a simple yet rich model of strongly interacting electrons with complex dynamics and a variety of emerging quantum phases. These properties make it a compelling target for digital quantum simulation. Trotterization-based quantum simulations have shown promise, but implementations on current hardware are limited by noise, necessitating error mitigation techniques like circuit optimization and post-selection. A mapping of the FHM to a Z2 LGT was recently proposed that restricts the dynamics to a subspace protected by additional symmetries, and its ability for post-selection error mitigation was verified through noisy classical simulations. In this work, we propose and demonstrate a suite of algorithm-hardware co-design strategies on a trapped-ion quantum computer, targeting two key aspects of NISQ-era quantum simulation: circuit compilation and error mitigation. In particular, a novel combination of iteratively preconditioned gradient descent (IPG) and subsystem von Neumann Entropy compression reduces the 2-qubit gate count of FHM quantum simulation by 35%, consequently doubling the number of simulatable Trotter steps when used in tandem with error mitigation based on conserved symmetries, debiasing and sharpening techniques. Our work demonstrates the value of algorithm-hardware co-design to operate digital quantum simulators at the threshold of maximum circuit depths allowed by current hardware, and is broadly generalizable to strongly correlated systems in quantum chemistry and materials science.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07778v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dhruv Srinivasan, Alex Beyer, Daiwei Zhu, Pranav Srikanth, Spencer Churchill, Kushagra Mehta, Sashank Kaushik Sridhar, Kushal Chakrabarti, David W. Steuerman, Nikhil Chopra, Avik Dutt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Competing color superconductivity and color Kondo effect in quark matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11617</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.11617v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The competition between bulk color superconductivity and the localized screening of a heavy quark impurity, analogous to the Kondo effect, leads to a rich spectrum of phenomena in dense quark matter. We investigate this competition at the edge of a superconducting quark bulk, where both the superconducting gap and the Kondo scale are dynamically generated in a tractable toy model. Utilizing the exact Bethe Ansatz method, we elucidate the resulting boundary physics. We identify distinct regimes characterized by either multi-particle Kondo screening or an unscreened local moment. Crucially, we also uncover a novel intermediate phase featuring impurity screening through a single-particle bound state formed within the superconducting gap. The toy model presented in this work highlights the complex interplay between dynamically generated bulk properties and boundary impurities in extreme QCD environments, offering potential insights into phenomena occurring in heavy-ion collisions and compact stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.11617v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pradip Kattel, Abay Zhakenov, Natan Andrei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
