<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 04:00:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Haerter-Shastry kinetic magnetism and metallicity in the triangular Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.18954v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The fermionic Hubbard model, when combined with the ingredient of frustration, associated with the breaking of particle-hole symmetry, harbors a rich phase diagram. Aspects of theoretical findings associated with the nature of magnetism and metallicity, in a diverse set of parameter regimes, are now being actively investigated in triangular Hubbard cold atom and solid-state (moir\'e) based emulators. Building on the theoretical work of Haerter and Shastry [Phys. Rev. Lett. 95,087202 (2005)], we explore the impact of kinetically frustrated magnetism, a phenomenon where antiferromagnetic order emerges without any underlying magnetic interactions, at finite hole density. We numerically study the infinite-$U$ triangular Hubbard model using the density matrix renormalization group algorithm and estimate the extent of stability of the kinetically induced $120^{\circ}$ antiferromagnetic state to hole doping. Beyond the Haerter-Shastry regime, we find an intermediate phase with multimer (involving multiple correlated spins) stripes that eventually gives way to a paramagnet. We also find evidence of gapless charge excitations (metallicity) throughout the phase diagram for finite hole density. We discuss the implications at large, but finite and realistic values of $U/t$, and investigate whether kinetic magnetism and superexchange collaborate or compete.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.18954v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sogoud Sherif, Prakash Sharma, Aman Kumar, Hitesh J. Changlani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sliding Disassembly of van der Waals Heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19064</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19064v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many recent advances in our understanding of two-dimensional (2D) electron systems stem from van der Waals (vdW) heterostructures. The assembly process relies on the weak bonding across interfaces between layered vdW compounds, making it possible to construct exceptionally clean heterostructures from chemically and structurally distinct materials - a challenging task for traditional thin-film growth techniques. Here we demonstrate an additional, dynamic degree of freedom afforded by vdW interfaces, wherein we use microstructured polymer stamps to disassemble and reconfigure vdW heterostructures by sliding. We apply this technique to alter the dielectric environment of monolayer graphene, perform scanning tunneling microscopy on semiconducting and air-sensitive monolayers, and manipulate strain-sensitive moir\'e materials. Together these demonstrations suggest a new paradigm for assembling and dynamically modifying van der Waals heterostructures, with the potential to reveal new insights into 2D electron systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19064v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jordan Pack, Karl V. Falb, Sanat Ghosh, Xuehao Wu, Keng Tou Chu, Florie Mesple, Ellis Thompson, Zhuquan Zhang, Carolin Gold, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Dmitri N. Basov, A. N. Pasupathy, Matthew Yankowitz, Cory R. Dean, Aravind Devarakonda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calculating the Luttinger liquid parameter for an interacting Kitaev chain quantum simulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19189</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19189v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we introduce a solid-state platform for building quantum simulators using implanted spin centers in solid-state materials. We build upon the proposal for an $S=1$ chain of spin centers coupled through the magnetic dipole-dipole interaction and subjected to an external magnetic field as a quantum simulator for critical floating phases. We introduce another magnetic field and map the system to the interacting Kitaev chain. This setup, tunable through the applied fields and the orientation of the spin centers within the crystal, exhibits a variety of rich quantum behavior which notably includes floating phases, a $Z_2$ symmetry-breaking phase, and lines of both Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless (BKT) and Pokrovsky-Talapov transitions. Furthermore, we employ several novel methods to calculate the Luttinger liquid parameter in our model with incommensurate correlations. We find that these methods provide a route to identify BKT transitions with less computational resources than utilizing entanglement entropy and central charge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19189v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Troy Losey, Jin Zhang, S. -W. Tsai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mapping the twist angle dependence of quasi-Brillouin zones in doubly aligned graphene/BN heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19369</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19369v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: When monolayer graphene is crystallographically aligned to hexagonal boron nitride (BN), a moir\'e superlattice is formed, producing characteristic satellite Dirac peaks in the electronic band structure. Aligning a second BN layer to graphene creates two coexisting moir\'e patterns, which can interfere to produce periodic, quasi-periodic or non-periodic superlattices, depending on their relative alignment. Here, we investigate one of the simplest realizations of such a double-moir\'e structure, graphene encapsulated between two BN layers, using dynamically rotatable van der Waals heterostructures. Our setup allows \textit{in situ} control of the top BN alignment while keeping the bottom BN fixed. By systematically mapping the charge transport as a function of BN angular alignment, we identify the simultaneous signatures of the original moir\'es, super-moir\'es, and a third set of features corresponding to quasi-Brillouin zones (qBZ) formed when the system's periodicity becomes ill-defined. Comparing our measurements with theoretical models, we provide the first experimental mapping of the qBZs as a function of angular alignment. Our results establish a direct experimental link between moir\'e interference and qBZ formation, opening new avenues for engineering electronic structures in multi-aligned 2D heterostructures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19369v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jorge Vallejo Bustamante, Viet-Hung Nguyen, Liam S. Farrar, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Dominique Mailly, Jean-Christophe Charlier, Rebeca Ribeiro-Palau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lattice Unitarity: Saturated Collisional Resistivity of Strongly Interacting Metals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19395</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19395v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the interaction-induced resistivity of ultracold fermions in a three-dimensional optical lattice. In situ observations of transport dynamics enable the determination of real and imaginary conductivity (or resistivity). In the strongly interacting metallic regime, we observe a striking saturation of the current-dissipation rate to a value independent of the interaction strength. This behavior is quantitatively captured by a dissipation model that uses a renormalized two-body scattering matrix. The highest observed dissipation rates approach, but do not reach, the unitarity bound on two-body scattering in the lattice, owing to momentum dispersion. We further measure the temperature dependence of resistivity in the strongly interacting limit and compare it to the predicted asymptotic behaviors. These results provide a clear microscopic understanding of bounded resistivity of low-density metals, thus providing a useful benchmark for studies of strongly correlated atomic and electronic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19395v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Frank Corapi, Robyn T. Learn, Benjamin Driesen, Antoine Lefebvre, Xavier Leyronas, Fr\'ed\'eric Chevy, Cora J. Fujiwara, Joseph H. Thywissen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pairing Symmetry Crossover from $d$-wave to $s_{\pm}$-wave in a Bilayer Nickelate Driven by Hund's Coupling and Crystal Field Splitting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19406v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The pairing symmetry of the recently discovered bilayer nickelate superconductor La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ is a subject of intense debate in condensed matter physics, with the two leading theoretical candidates being a sign-reversing $s_{\pm}$-wave and a $d$-wave state. To investigate its ground-state properties in the intermediate coupling regime which is critical for real materials, we construct a two-orbital bilayer Hubbard model and employ the constrained-path quantum Monte Carlo method for large-scale simulations. By systematically calculating ground-state pairing correlation functions across parameter spaces, we map its pairing symmetry phase diagram. We find that an increasing Hund's coupling selectively enhances the interlayer $s_{\pm}$-wave pairing while suppressing the intralayer $d$-wave pairing. Similarly, a larger crystal field splitting drives a transition from $d$-wave- to $s_{\pm}$-wave-dominant states. Further analysis reveals that the strength of the intralayer $d$-wave pairing is strongly correlated with the $(\pi, \pi)$ antiferromagnetic spin fluctuations, which are in turn effectively suppressed by a large crystal field splitting, thereby weakening the $d$-wave pairing channel. Additionally, the dominant pairing symmetry transition region roughly overlaps with the inversion of orbital occupancy response to Hubbard $U$, suggesting an intrinsic link between pairing competition and orbital physics. Our results indicate that, within the parameter regime relevant to the actual material, the $s_{\pm}$-wave is the most probable pairing symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19406v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yicheng Xiong, Yanmei Cai, Tianxing Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lattice-reflection symmetry in tensor-network renormalization group with entanglement filtering in two and three dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19428v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Tensor-network renormalization group (TNRG) is an efficient real-space renormalization group method for studying the criticality in both classical and quantum lattice systems. Exploiting symmetries of a system in a TNRG algorithm can simplify the implementation of the algorithm and can help produce correct tensor RG flows. Although a general framework for considering a global on-site symmetry has been established, it is still unclear how to incorporate a lattice symmetry like rotation or reflection in TNRG. As a first step for lattice symmetries, we propose a method to incorporate the lattice-reflection symmetry in the context of a TNRG with entanglement filtering in both two and three dimensions (2D and 3D). To achieve this, we write down a general definition of lattice-reflection symmetry in tensor-network language. Then, we introduce a transposition trick for exploiting and imposing the lattice-reflection symmetry in two basic TNRG operators: projective truncations and entanglement filtering. Using the transposition trick, the detailed algorithms of the TNRG map in both 2D and 3D are laid out, where the lattice-reflection symmetry is preserved and imposed. Finally, we demonstrate how to construct the linearization of the TNRG maps in a given lattice-reflection sector, with the help of which it becomes possible to extract scaling dimensions in each sector separately. Our work paves the way for understanding the lattice-rotation symmetry in TNRG.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19428v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinliang Lyu, Naoki Kawashima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Practical algorithm for simulating thermal pure quantum states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19504</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19504v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The development of novel quantum many-body computational algorithms relies on robust benchmarking. However, generating such benchmarks is often hindered by the massive computational resources required for exact diagonalization or quantum Monte Carlo simulations, particularly at finite temperatures. In this work, we propose a new algorithm for obtaining thermal pure quantum states, which allows efficient computation of both mechanical and thermodynamic properties at finite temperatures. We implement this algorithm in our open-source C++ template library, Physica. Combining the improved algorithm with state-of-the-art software engineering, our implementation achieves high performance and numerical stability. As an example, we demonstrate that for the $4 \times 4$ Hubbard model, our method runs approximately $10^3$ times faster than $\mathcal{H}\Phi$ 3.5.2. Moreover, the accessible temperature range is extended down to $\beta = 32$ across arbitrary doping levels. These advances significantly push forward the frontiers of benchmarking for quantum many-body systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19504v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Bo He, Yun-Tong Yang, Hong-Gang Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic nonlinear Hall effect beyond Bloch geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19515</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19515v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The theory of the intrinsic Hall effect, both linear and nonlinear, is rooted in a geometry which is defined in the Bloch-vector parameter space; the formal expressions are mostly derived from semiclassical concepts. When disorder and interaction are considered there is no Bloch vector to speak of; one needs a more general quantum geometry, defined in a different parameter space. Such higher-level geometrical formulation of the intrinsic Hall effect provides very compact expressions, which have the additional virtue -- in the Bloch special case -- of yielding the known results in a straightforward way: the logic is not concealed by the algebra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19515v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raffaele Resta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Applied electric and magnetic field effects on the bandgap formation and antiferromagnetic ordering in AA-stacked Bilayer Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19526v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study, we consider a two-layer graphene structure stacked in the AA form and exposed to the influence of two different electric fields applied to different layers. The graphene layers are also subjected to an external magnetic field perpendicular to the planes of the layers. We investigate the possible effects of the applied in-plane fields and the magnetic field on excitonic pairing, antiferromagnetic order, and the chemical potential. Simultaneously, we analyze the effects of the interlayer Coulomb interaction potential on the physical properties of the considered system. We demonstrate that the application of planar electric fields leads to the formation of an unusually large bandgap in the electronic band structure, which is not typical for AA-stacked bilayer graphene. We discuss various values of the applied electric field potentials and show their influence on the electronic band structure of the system. Additionally, we identify the existence of a critical value of the magnetic field above which Wigner crystallization-like effect is present for the electrons, also affecting the excitonic gap in one spin channel. The results obtained in this study could be important for applications of AA-stacked bilayer graphene as a large band-gap material.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19526v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physe.2025.116235</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physica E: Low-dimensional Systems and Nanostructures, 171, 116235 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>V. Apinyan, T. Kope\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atomic displacements drive flat band formation and lateral electron and hole separation in near-60 degree twisted MoSe2/WSe2 bilayers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19596</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19596v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Transition metal dichalcogenide (TMD) bilayers with an interlayer twist exhibit a moire super-period, whose effects can manifest in both structural and electronic properties. Atomic displacements can lead to reconstruction into domains of aligned stacking, and flat bands can form that may host correlated electron states. In heterobilayers angular mismatch is nearly unavoidable, so understanding the consequences of an interlayer twist is essential. Using ab initio density functional theory, we find that in near-60 degree twisted MoSe2/WSe2 bilayers valence and conduction band flat bands emerge at ~3 degree twist. Despite relatively limited reconstruction at these angles, atomic displacement creates a polarization gradient that forms a confining potential, localizing and laterally separating electrons and holes within the moire supercell. Excitons formed from flat band electrons and holes should therefore have not only the out-of-plane dipole moment familiar from MoSe2/WSe2 interlayer excitons, but an in-plane dipole moment as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19596v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Madeleine Phillips, C. Stephen Hellberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct visualization of gate-tunable flat bands in twisted double bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19632</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19632v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The symmetry-broken correlated states in twisted double bilayer graphene (TDBG) can be tuned via several external knobs, including twist angle, displacement field, and carrier density. However, a direct, momentum-resolved characterization of how these parameters reshape the flat-band structure remains limited. In this study, we employ micro focused angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy to investigate the flat-band dispersion of TDBG at a twist angle of 1.6, systematically varying the displacement field and carrier density via electrostatic gating. We directly observe multiple flat moir'e minibands near charge neutrality, including a flat remote valence band residing below the low-energy flat-band manifold. Furthermore, the dominant Coulomb repulsive energy over the flat- band bandwidth suggests favorable conditions for the emergence of interaction-driven correlated phenomena in TDBG. These findings establish that the formation and evolution of flat bands in TDBG arises from the interplay between the electron filling and the displacement field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19632v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Souvik Sasmal (Department of Physics, Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, USA), Ryan Muzzio (Department of Physics, Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, USA), Ahmed Khalifa (Department of Physics, Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, USA), Paulina Majchrzak (Department of Applied Physics, Stanford University, Stanford, CA, USA), Alfred J. H. Jones (Department of Physics and Astronomy, Aarhus University, Aarhus C, Denmark), I-Hsuan Kao (Department of Physics, Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, USA), Kenji Watanabe (Research Center for Electronic and Optical Materials, National Institute for Materials Science, Tsukuba, Japan), Takashi Taniguchi (Research Center for Materials Nanoarchitectonics, National Institute for Materials Science, Tsukuba, Japan), Simranjeet Singh (Department of Physics, Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, USA), Eli Rotenberg (Advanced Light Source, E. O. Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, Berkeley, CA, USA), Aaron Bostwick (Advanced Light Source, E. O. Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, Berkeley, CA, USA), Chris Jozwiak (Advanced Light Source, E. O. Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, Berkeley, CA, USA), S{\o}ren Ulstrup (Department of Physics and Astronomy, Aarhus University, Aarhus C, Denmark), Shubhayu Chatterjee (Department of Physics, Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, USA), Jyoti Katoch (Department of Physics, Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, USA)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dara: Automated multiple-hypothesis phase identification and refinement from powder X-ray diffraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19667v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Powder X-ray diffraction (XRD) is a foundational technique for characterizing crystalline materials. However, the reliable interpretation of XRD patterns, particularly in multiphase systems, remains a manual and expertise-demanding task. As a characterization method that only provides structural information, multiple reference phases can often be fit to a single pattern, leading to potential misinterpretation when alternative solutions are overlooked. To ease humans' efforts and address the challenge, we introduce Dara (Data-driven Automated Rietveld Analysis), a framework designed to automate the robust identification and refinement of multiple phases from powder XRD data. Dara performs an exhaustive tree search over all plausible phase combinations within a given chemical space and validates each hypothesis using a robust Rietveld refinement routine (BGMN). Key features include structural database filtering, automatic clustering of isostructural phases during tree expansion, peak-matching-based scoring to identify promising phases for refinement. When ambiguity exists, Dara generates multiple hypothesis which can then be decided between by human experts or with further characteriztion tools. By enhancing the reliability and accuracy of phase identification, Dara enables scalable analysis of realistic complex XRD patterns and provides a foundation for integration into multimodal characterization workflows, moving toward fully self-driving materials discovery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19667v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxing Fei, Matthew J. McDermott, Christopher L. Rom, Shilong Wang, Gerbrand Ceder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-Locked Helical Currents and Pure Spin Pumping in Altermagnetic Nanotubes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19700</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19700v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that rolling a two-dimensional altermagnet into a nanotube turns it into a spin-programmable chiral nanosolenoid with two reciprocal, SOC-free functionalities. (i) Direct: injecting a single-spin-polarized current produces a steady helical current whose handedness is locked to the spin orientation, yielding opposite axial magnetic fields for opposite spins. (ii) Inverse: a time-varying axial flux Phi(t) induces a circumferential Faraday field E_theta = -(dPhi/dt)/(2 pi R) that drives equal-magnitude, opposite-sign axial charge currents in the two spin channels, Iz^up = - Iz^down, thereby pumping a pure spin current Is = (hbar/2e)(Iz^up - Iz^down) with zero net charge flow. Both effects arise from the interplay between momentum-odd spin polarization inherent to altermagnets and the screw symmetry of the rolled geometry, and persist in the complete absence of spin-orbit coupling. Using V2Se2O as a prototype, first-principles calculations reveal spin-dependent chiral wave functions near both the conduction- and valence-band edges. These results establish a nonrelativistic route toward compact spin-controlled flux generators and charge-neutral spin injectors in light-element materials without static magnetic bias.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19700v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Chen, Linyang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature-invariant magneto-optical Kerr effect in a noncollinear antiferromagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19709</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19709v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The anomalous Hall effect and magneto-optical Kerr effect have traditionally been associated with ferromagnets, but recent studies reveal their presence in noncollinear antiferromagnets due to nonzero Berry curvature despite negligible net magnetization. However, Hall measurements often show strong temperature dependence caused by extrinsic scattering, complicating quantitative analysis, and temperature invariance of the Kerr effect remains unconfirmed. Here we employ epitaxial, stoichiometric Mn3NiN single crystal films and perform polar Kerr measurements at an infrared 1550 nm telecommunication wavelength, demonstrating a spontaneous Kerr signal that remains stable within a few percent across a 200 Kelvin range below the N\'eel temperature. This temperature-invariant Kerr effect contrasts with the strongly temperature-dependent Hall effect and confirms the intrinsic nature of Berry curvature in these materials. Our findings establish infrared Kerr effect as a reliable, local probe of Berry curvature in noncollinear antiferromagnets, facilitating quantitative characterization and advancing antiferromagnetic spintronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19709v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Camron Farhang, Weihang Lu, Yuchuan Yao, Pratap Pal, Shaofeng Han, Jian-Guo Zheng, Hua Chen, Chang-Beom Eom, Jing Xia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Point-contact Andreev reflection spectroscopy of layered superconductors with device-integrated diamond anvil cells</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19736v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Superconductors that can be mechanically exfoliated are an interesting platform for exploring superconducting properties tuned by layer thickness. These layered superconductors are also expected to exhibit sensitivity to applied pressure. While pressure has been demonstrated to be an effective way of tuning bulk superconductors, analogous studies on superconducting thin flakes have been limited due to technical challenges. In particular, spectroscopic measurements under pressure remain insufficiently explored. In this work, we functionalized the diamond anvil cell technique for point-contact Andreev reflection spectroscopy (PCAR) measurement on thin-flake materials under pressure, offering the opportunity to obtain spectroscopic information on superconductivity. To validate the feasibility of this method, we have conducted PCAR measurements on iron-selenide thin flakes to extract temperature-dependent superconducting gap values under ambient and high pressure. Combine with the proven magnetotransport capability, our method provides a conceptually simple tool for a detailed examination of thin-flake superconductors under pressure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19736v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0285454</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Rev. Sci. Instrum. 96, 103902 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Che-hsuan Ku, Omargeldi Atanov, King Yau Yip, Wenyan Wang, Siu Tung Lam, Jiayu Zeng, Wei Zhang, Zheyu Wang, Lingfei Wang, Tsz Fung Poon, Rolf Lortz, Swee K. Goh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two parameter scaling of conductance in quantum Hall effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19739</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19739v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: After a brief survey of theoretical concepts for the two-parameter scaling theory in the integer quantum Hall effect regime, a comprehensive set of early, recent and new experimental results on constructing scaling diagrams for conductance in 2D semiconductor structures, as well as in graphene is displayed. A comparative analysis of scaling diagrams obtained from experimental data with calculated ones is carried out.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19739v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yurii G. Arapov, Svetlana V. Gudina, Vladimir N. Neverov, Nikita S. Sandakov, Nina G. Shelushinina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Soft Mode Origin of Charge Ordering in Superconducting Kagome CsV$_3$Sb$_5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19790</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19790v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Charge-density-wave (CDW) order and superconductivity coexist in the kagome metals AV$_3$Sb$_5$ (A=K, Cs, Rb), raising fundamental questions about the mechanisms driving their intertwined phases. Here we combine high-resolution inelastic X-ray scattering with first-principles calculations to uncover the origin of CDW formation in CsV$_3$Sb$_5$. Guided by structure factor analysis, we identify a soft phonon mode along the reciprocal M-L direction, with the strongest effect at the L point, where the elastic scattering intensity also grows most rapidly upon cooling. First-principles calculations incorporating lattice anharmonicity and electron-phonon coupling reproduce these observations and establish a soft-mode instability at the L point as the driving mechanism of CDW formation. Despite the weakly first-order character of the transition, our results unambiguously demonstrate that the CDW in CsV$_3$Sb$_5$ originates from a softened phonon, clarifying its microscopic origin and highlighting the central role of lattice dynamics in kagome metals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19790v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philippa Helen McGuinness, Fabian Henssler, Manex Alkorta, Mark Joachim Graf von Westarp, Artem Korshunov, Alexei Bosak, Daisuke Ishikawa, Alfred Q. R. Baron, Michael Merz, Amir-Abbas Haghighirad, Maia G. Vergniory, Sofia-Michaela Souliou, Rolf Heid, Ion Errea, Matthieu Le Tacon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hexa-Graphyne: A Transparent and Semimetallic 2D Carbon Allotrope with Distinct Optical Properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19795v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Herein, we conduct a comprehensive investigation of Hexa-graphyne (HXGY), a planar carbon allotrope formed by distorted hexagonal and rectangular rings incorporating sp and sp$^2$-hybridized carbon atoms. First-principles calculations confirm its energetic, dynamical and thermal stability (up to at least 1000 K). Regarding its band structure, this material exhibits a semimetallic nature. It exhibits high mechanical compliance, with a Young's modulus approximately 13 times lower and a Poisson's ratio nearly 4 times higher than those of graphene. The optical response is marked by strong ultraviolet absorption, high infrared reflectivity, and pronounced transparency in the visible-light range. Raman and infrared spectra exhibit sharp and well-separated peaks, providing a clear signature of acetylenic linkage stretching vibrations. Nanoribbon structures derived from HXGY show distinct electronic behaviors depending on the edge termination type and width. These findings highlight the HXGY potential for nanoelectronic and optoelectronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19795v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jhionathan de Lima, Cristiano Francisco Woellner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative measurement of magnetic dichroic signals at sub-nanometer to atomic scale resolution conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19115</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19115v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: When aiming for atomic resolution electron magnetic circular dichroism (EMCD) in STEM mode, the high convergence angle of the electron probe can lead to unforeseen artefacts and strong reductions of the signal to noise ratio (SNR) in the measurement of magnetic magnitudes. In this work, the EMCD signal is measured in STEM mode at semi-convergence angles ranging from \alpha=\ 2-10\ mrad\ using iron samples with high structural perfection. We observe that the relative EMCD signal remains very similar for all convergence angles, which is in good agreement with simulations. The improvement in the signal-to-noise ratio as compared to earlier works is due to better crystalline quality of the Fe sample, high control of the sample orientation, better control over sample thickness, and factors such as higher beam current and the use of a fast and sensitive hybrid-pixel electron detector. One of the key factors to remove experimental ambivalences is the use of an acquisition geometry where the two conjugate EMCD spectra are acquired simultaneously. Furthermore the high crystalline quality Fe sample enables the acquisition of statistical entities of spectra at the same sample orientation, which in turn results in high SNR EMCD signals. We obtain high SNR EMCD signals for all semi convergence angles and could measure the orbital to spin magnetic moment ratio ml/ms with high precision. We observed that at high convergence angles, the ml/ms ratio gets sensitive to minute changes in sample orientation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19115v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sharath Kumar Manjeshwar Sathyanath, Anna L. Ravensburg, Vassilios Kapaklis, Jan Rusz, Bj\"orgvin Hj\"orvarsson, Klaus Leifer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoherence of a dissipative Brownian charged magneto-anharmonic oscillator: an information theoretic approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19317v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the decoherence of an anisotropic anharmonic oscillator in a magnetic field, coupled to a bath of harmonic oscillators at high and low temperatures. We solve the anharmonic oscillator problem using perturbative techniques and derive the non-Markovian master equation in the weak coupling limit. The anharmonicity parameter {\alpha} enhances decoherence due to the deconfining effect of anharmonicity. The oscillatory nature of the time evolution of heating function indicates information backflow. The von-Neumann entropy is also calculated for the system, which increases with {\alpha}, consistent with the deconfining effect noted in the decoherence analysis. We have also proposed a cold ion experimental set up for testing our theoretical predictions. The study is of relevance to the domain of quantum technology where decoherence significantly affects the performance of a quantum computer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19317v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suraka Bhattacharjee, Koushik Mandal, Supurna Sinha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mechanism of the electrochemical hydrogenation of graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19505</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19505v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The electrochemical hydrogenation of graphene induces a robust and reversible conductor-insulator transition, of strong interest in logic-and-memory applications. However, its mechanism remains unknown. Here we show that it proceeds as a reduction reaction in which proton adsorption competes with the formation of H2 molecules via an Eley-Rideal process. Graphene's electrochemical hydrogenation is up to $10^6$ times faster than alternative hydrogenation methods and is fully reversible via the oxidative desorption of protons. We demonstrate that the proton reduction rate in defect-free graphene can be enhanced by an order of magnitude by the introduction of nanoscale corrugations in its lattice, and that the substitution of protons for deuterons results both in lower potentials for the hydrogenation process and in a more stable compound. Our results pave the way to investigating the chemisorption of ions in 2D materials at high electric fields, opening a new avenue to control these materials' electronic properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19505v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Y. -C. Soong, H. Li, Y. Fu, J. Tong, S. Huang, X. Zhang, E. Griffin, E. Hoenig, M. Alhashmi, Y. Li, D. Bahamon, J. Zhong, A. Summerfield, R. N. Costa Filho, C. Sevik, R. Gorbachev, E. C. Neyts, L. F. Vega, F. M. Peeters, M. Lozada-Hidalgo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Twisted superconducting quantum diodes: Towards anharmonicity and high fidelity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19627</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19627v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: As quantum technologies advance, a fundamental challenge is mitigating noise and backscattering in superconducting circuits to achieve scalable, high-fidelity operations. Conventional superconducting components lack directionality, causing energy loss and decoherence. Superconducting diodes, that allow dissipationless current in one direction and resistive flow in the other, offer a potential remedy, yet their efficiency and quantum integration remain limited. Here, we realize a quantum diode in twisted NbSe2 bilayers under in-plane and out-of-plane magnetic fields. A mere 1 degree twist yields an efficiency enhancement over pristine devices, reaching 27.6 percent. Quantum simulations reveal that this intermediate efficiency, well below 100 percent ideal, is both experimentally practical and optimal for preserving qubit anharmonicity and stabilizing two-level systems. These findings show that maximal rectification is not always beneficial for quantum information, establishing a new principle for designing the fundamental properties of twisted superconductors towards low-power, high-fidelity quantum circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19627v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Han Zhong, Denis Kochan, Igor Zutic, Yingying Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atomic-superfluid heat engines controlled by twisted light</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19821</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19821v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We theoretically propose a quantum heat engine using a setup consisting of a ring-trapped Bose-Einstein condensate placed in a Fabry--P\'erot cavity where the optical fields carry orbital angular momentum. We first show that the cavity-enhanced light-atom coupling leads to the emergence of polaritonic modes, whose character can be reversibly switched between photonlike and phononlike by detuning sweeps allowing work extraction governed by distinct reservoirs. We investigate the dependence of the engine efficiency on the orbital angular momentum. Beyond ideality, we discuss finite-time scenarios based on shortcuts to adiabaticity such that the efficiency retains its ideal-operation value, despite finite-time challenges. Finally, for lower values of the orbital angular momentum, we describe an alternate scheme for operating quantum heat engines based on the adiabatic elimination of a mechanical mode. Our analysis identifies orbital angular momentum as an experimentally-accessible control knob that can reconfigure the performance of such quantum heat engines as desired.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19821v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aritra Ghosh, Nilamoni Daloi, M. Bhattacharya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct imaging and control of Berry curvature in noncollinear antiferromagnetic single-crystal thin films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.02990v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The discovery of the intrinsic anomalous Hall effect (AHE) in noncollinear antiferromagnets where transverse Hall voltage emerges without magnetic field, has opened a plethora of promising opportunities in antiferromagnetic devices. The key challenges limiting their full potential are (1) high-quality epitaxial thin-film growth and (2) the understanding of Berry curvature domain physics. Here, we focus on a noncollinear antiperovskite antiferromagnet Mn3NiN as a model system, successfully grown as a single-crystal epitaxial thin film. Combining multiple experiments supported by theoretical calculations, we probe the Berry curvature associated with antiferromagnetic {\Gamma}4g domains in Mn3NiN and its strong connection to an AHE. We directly image the intrinsic Berry curvature with high-resolution Sagnac microscopy, controlling spatial distribution and dynamics by varying temperature and applied magnetic fields. We discover that the {\Gamma}4g domains are switchable near the N\'eel transition, but become frozen and unresponsive to external stimuli at low temperature. This behavior enables the tuning of Berry-curvature driven AHE and magneto-optic Kerr effect responses through controlled experimental conditions. Our findings provide critical advancement of the fundamental understanding and wide tunability of Berry curvature in noncollinear antiferromagnets important for realization in potential spintronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.02990v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuchuan Yao, Pratap Pal, Camron Farhang, Weihang Lu, Mohamed Elekhtiar, Paul Lenharth, Neil G. Campbell, Gautam Gurung, Roger D. Johnson, Pascal Manuel, Mark S. Rzchowski, Evgeny Y. Tsymbal, Jing Xia, Chang-Beom Eom</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent Kitaev materials in synthetic Fermi-Hubbard bilayers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.15755v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the emergence of bond-directional spin-spin interactions in a synthetic Fermi-Hubbard bilayer that can be realized with ultracold fermions in Raman optical lattices. The model exploits synthetic dimensions to couple two honeycomb layers, each corresponding to a different hyperfine atomic state, via Raman-assisted tunneling and, moreover, via an inter-layer Hubbard repulsion due to the cold-atom scattering. In the strong-coupling regime at half filling, we derive effective spin Hamiltonians for the kinetic exchange featuring Kitaev, Heisenberg, off-diagonal exchange ($\Gamma$-couplings), as well as tunable Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interactions. We identify specific configurations that generate both ferromagnetic and antiferromagnetic Kitaev couplings with various perturbations of relevance to Kitaev materials, providing a tunable platform that can explore how quantum spin liquids emerge from itinerant fermion systems. We analyze the Fermi-liquid and Mott-insulating phases, highlighting a correspondence between Dirac and Majorana quasi-particles, with possible phase transitions thereof. In an extreme anisotropic limit, we show that the model reduces to an inter-layer ribbon in a quasi-1D ladder, allowing for a numerical study of the correlated ground state using matrix product states. We find a transition from a symmetry-protected topological insulator to a Kitaev-like regime characterized by nonlocal string order. Our results establish that cold-atom quantum simulators based on Raman optical lattices can be a playground for extended Kitaev models, bridging itinerant fermionic systems and spin-liquid physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.15755v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Gonz\'alez-Cuadra, Alejandro Bermudez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A versatile setup for symmetry-resolved ultrafast dynamics of quantum materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04855</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.04855v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Correlated phenomena occur in quantum materials because of the delicate interplay between internal degrees of freedom, leading to multiple symmetry-broken quantum phases. Resolving the structure of these phases is a key challenge, often requiring facilities equipped with x-ray free-electron lasers and electron sources that may not be readily accessible to the average user. Table-top sources that offer alternative means are therefore needed. In this work, we present an all-optical, table-top setup that enables symmetry-resolved studies using linear and nonlinear spectroscopies. We demonstrate the versatility of the setup with chosen examples that underscore the importance of tracking symmetries and showcase the strengths of the setup, which offers a large tunable parameter space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.04855v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0279973</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Review of Scientific Instruments 96, 103903 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Khalid M. Siddiqui, Hanna Strojecka, Thomas H. Meyland, Nitesh Khatiwada, Nikolaj Klinkby, Daniel Perez-Salinas, Simon E. Wall</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial correlations of charge density wave order across the transition in 2H-NbSe2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02991v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Charge density waves (CDWs) involve coupled amplitude and phase degrees of freedom, but direct access to local amplitude correlations remains experimentally challenging. Here, we report cryogenic four-dimensional scanning transmission electron microscopy (4D-STEM) measurements of CDW ordering in a 2H-NbSe2 flake of 24 nm thickness, enabled by liquid helium-based cooling. By mapping the spatial distribution of CDW superlattice intensities at nanometer-scale resolution and analyzing their autocorrelations, we extract the temperature-dependent correlation length associated with the local amplitude of the CDW order parameter, independent of global phase coherence. Our results reveal that a finite local CDW amplitude is already established well above the transition temperature. When the system is cooled below the transition temperature down to 20 K, the correlation length extends to nearly 110 nm, and the local CDW amplitude is found to strongly anticorrelate with the local strain field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02991v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seokjo Hong, Jaewhan Oh, Jemin Park, Woohyun Cho, Soyoung Lee, Colin Ophus, Yeongkwan Kim, Heejun Yang, SungBin Lee, Yongsoo Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Fractionalization to Chiral Topological Superconductivity in a Flat Chern Band</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.10938</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.10938v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that interacting electrons in a flat Chern band can form, in addition to fractional Chern insulators, a chiral $f$-wave topological superconductor that hosts neutral Majorana fermion edge modes. Superconductivity emerges from an interaction-induced metallic state that exhibits anomalous Hall effect, as observed in rhombohedral graphene and near the $\nu=\frac{2}{3}$ fractional Chern insulator in twisted transition metal dichalcogenides.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.10938v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniele Guerci, Ahmed Abouelkomsan, Liang Fu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunneling conductance in superconducting junctions with $p$-wave unconventional magnets breaking time-reversal symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13372</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13372v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A new type of magnet called $p$-wave unconventional magnet is proposed, stimulated by the discovery of altermagnet. We study the tunneling conductance of $p$-wave unconventional magnet/superconductor junctions by adopting the effective Hamiltonian of $p$-wave unconventional magnets with time-reversal symmetry breaking, suggested in Ref [arXiv: 2309.01607 (2024)]. The tunneling conductance shows an asymmetric behavior with respect to bias voltage in the helical $p$-wave superconductor junctions. It is caused by the missing of helical edge states contributing to the charge conductance owing to the momentum-dependent spin-split feature of the Fermi surface in $p$-wave unconventional magnets. In chiral $d$ and $p$-wave superconductor junctions, the resulting spin-resolved tunneling conductance takes a different value for spin sectors due to the time-reversal symmetry breaking in superconductors. Our results qualitatively reproduce the results based on the simplified Hamiltonian in Ref [J.\ Phys.\ Soc.\ Jpn.\ \textbf{93}, 114703 (2024)], where only the odd function of the exchange coupling of $p$-wave unconventional magnets is taken into account, which gives the shift of the Fermi surface and preserves the time-reversal symmetry similar to the spin-orbit coupling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13372v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuri Fukaya, Keiji Yada, Yukio Tanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Closely competing valence bond crystal orders in the ground state of the spin-$\frac{1}{2}$ antiferromagnetic Heisenberg model on the pyrochlore lattice: a large scale unrestricted variational study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13746v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The spin-$\frac{1}{2}$ antiferromagnetic Heisenberg model on the pyrochlore lattice(PAFH) is arguably the most well known strongly frustrated quantum magnet in three spatial dimension. However, due to the rapid scaling of Hilbert space with the linear size of such a three dimensional system, the nature of its ground state in the thermodynamic limit remains elusive. Here we apply a recently developed powerful algorithm to perform large scale unrestricted variational optimization of the ground state of the spin-$\frac{1}{2}$ PAFH from the resonating valence bond(RVB) theory perspective. We find a candidate ground state of the system that features a maximally resonating valence bond crystal(VBC) pattern with $2\vec{a}_{1}\times2\vec{a}_{2}\times2\vec{a}_{3}$ periodicity. There are at least four levels of hierarchical structure in such a VBC state, with the first and the second level of hierarchy related to the breaking of the inversion and the translational symmetry. Intriguingly, we find that within the RVB framework such a maximally resonating VBC state is almost degenerate with a recently proposed VBC state that is obtained from dressing hard hexagon covering of the pyrochlore lattice, although they have very different structures. We also find that further symmetry breaking will occur in the dressed hard hexagon VBC state under unrestricted optimization, which results in strong disparity in $\langle \hat{\mathbf{S}}^{2}_{u} \rangle$ for up and down tetrahedrons as we observe in the maximally resonating VBC state. We show that the maximally resonating VBC state found here will be favored by a tiny next-neighboring exchange coupling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13746v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rong Cheng, Tao Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General Many-Body Perturbation Framework for Moir\'e Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19764</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19764v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Moir\'e superlattices host a rich variety of correlated topological states, including interaction-driven integer and fractional Chern insulators. A common approach to study interacting ground states at integer fillings is the Hartree-Fock mean-field method. However, this method neglects dynamical correlations, which often leads to an overestimation of spontaneous symmetry breaking and fails to provide quantitative descriptions of single-particle excitations. This work introduces a general many-body perturbation framework for moir\'e systems, combining all-band Hartree-Fock calculations with random phase approximation (RPA) correlation energies and $GW$ quasiparticle corrections. We apply this framework to hexagonal boron nitride aligned rhombohedral pentalayer graphene and magic-angle twisted bilayer graphene. We show that incorporating RPA correlation energy and $GW$ self-energy corrections yields phase diagrams and single-particle spectra that quantitatively align with experimental measurements. Our versatile framework provides a systematic beyond-mean-field approach applicable to generic moir\'e systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19764v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Lu, Yuanfan Yang, Zhongqing Guo, Jianpeng Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay of competing bond-order and loop-current fluctuations as a possible mechanism for superconductivity in kagome metals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00134v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The pairing symmetry and underlying mechanism for superconducting state of AV${}_3$Sb${}_5$ (A=K, Rb, Cs) kagome metal has been a topic of intense investigation. In this work, we consider an 8-band minimal model, which includes V, and the two types of Sb, both within and above/below the kagome plane. This model captures the Fermi surface pocket with significant in-plane Sb contribution near the zone center, and also has the two types of van Hove singularities (VHS), one of which has a strong out of plane Sb weight. By including V-V and V-planar Sb nearest-neighbor Coulomb interactions, we obtain the susceptibilities for fluctuating bond-order and loop-current in both charge and spin channels, and examine the resulting superconducting instabilities. In particular, we find that the time-reversal odd (even) charge-loop-current (charge bond-order) fluctuations favor unconventional (conventional) pairing symmetry such as $s_{+-}$ and $d+id$ ($s_{++}$). Recent experimental works have highlighted the presence of $s$-wave pairing with two distinct gaps, one isotropic and one anisotropic. We discuss how this scenario may be compatible with either $s_{++}$ or $s_{+-}$ pairing, with an isotropic gap on the pocket dominated by in-plane Sb, but a highly anisotropic gap on V-dominated bands.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00134v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Asimpunya Mitra, Daniel J. Schultz, Yong Baek Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
