<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 05:00:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Light-induced Asymmetric Pseudogap below T$_\text{c}$ in cuprates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20768</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20768v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To this day, high-temperature cuprate superconductors remain an unparalleled platform for studying the competition and coexistence of emergent, static and dynamic, quantum phases of matter exhibiting high transition temperature non-s-wave superconductivity, non-Fermi liquid transport and a still enigmatic pseudogap regime. However, how superconductivity emerges alongside and competes with the pseudogap regime remains an open question. Here, we present a high-resolution, time- and angle-resolved photoemission study of the near-antinodal region of optimally-doped Bi$_2$Sr$_2$CaCu$_2$O$_{8+\delta}$. For a sufficiently high excitation fluence, we disrupt superconductivity and drive a transient change from a symmetric superconducting-like to an asymmetric pseudogap-like density of states, for electronic temperatures well below the equilibrium superconducting critical temperature. Conversely, when the superconductivity is fully restored, the pseudogap is suppressed, as signaled by a fully particle-hole symmetric density of states. A unique aspect of our experiments is that the pseudogap coexists with superconducting features at intermediate times or at intermediate fluence. Our findings challenge the paradigm that superconductivity emerges by establishing phase coherence in the pseudogap. Instead, our experimental results, supported by phenomenological theory, demonstrate that the two states compete, and that the low-temperature ground state of the cuprates originates from a competition between superconducting and pseudogap states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20768v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Armanno, O. Gingras, F. Goto, J. -M. Parent, A. Longa, A. Jabed, B. Frimpong, R. D. Zhong, J. Schneeloch, G. D. Gu, G. Jargot, H. Ibrahim, F. Legare, B. J. Siwick, N. Gauthier, A. Georges, A. J. Millis, F. Boschini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hund-projected Kanamori model: an effective description of Hund's metals near the Mott insulating regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20788</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20788v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hund's coupling plays a decisive role in shaping electron correlations of multi-orbital systems, giving rise to a class of materials--Hund's metals--that combine local-moment physics with metallic transport. Here we derive an effective low-energy description of such a system near the Mott insulating regime, starting from the multi-orbital Hubbard-Kanamori Hamiltonian and projecting onto the high-spin manifold favored by Hund's first rule. The resulting Hund-projected Kanamori model captures the interplay between carrier motion and magnetic correlations in the presence of strong Hund's coupling. In the undoped limit, the model reduces to a spin-$N/2$ Heisenberg system with suppressed quantum fluctuations, approaching the classical limit for realistic five-band configurations. Upon doping, carrier motion couples strongly to the spin background and drives ferromagnetic correlations through a Hund-enhanced kinetic mechanism analogous to, but much stronger than, Nagaoka ferromagnetism. Owing to its reduced sign problem, the model can be addressed with advanced path-integral methods to determine quasiparticle structure and effective interactions between carriers-quantities that are challenging to obtain with other methods. This framework establishes a microscopic bridge between the Kanamori model and the emergent magnetic and transport phenomena characteristic of Hund's metals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20788v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johan Carlstr\"om</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hardware Acceleration of Frustrated Lattice Systems using Convolutional Restricted Boltzmann Machine</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20911v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Geometric frustration gives rise to emergent quantum phenomena and exotic phases of matter. While Monte Carlo methods are traditionally used to simulate such systems, their sampling efficiency is limited by the complexity of interactions and ground-state properties. Restricted Boltzmann Machines (RBMs), a class of probabilistic neural networks, offer improved sampling by incorporating machine learning techniques. However, fully-connected bipartite RBMs are inefficient for representing physical lattices with sparse interactions. To address this, we implement Convolutional Restricted Boltzmann Machines (CRBMs) that leverage translational symmetry inherent to lattices. Using the classical Shastry-Sutherland (SS) Ising lattice, we demonstrate (i) CRBM formulation that captures SS interactions, and (ii) digital hardware accelerator to enhance sampling performance. We simulate lattices with up to 324 spins, recovering all known phases of the SS Ising model, including the long range ordered fractional plateau. Our hardware characterizes spin behavior at critical points and within spin liquid phases. This implementation achieves a speedup of 3 to 5 orders of magnitude (33 ns to 120 ms) over GPU-based implementations. Moreover, the time-to-solution is within two orders of magnitude of quantum annealers, while offering superior scalability, room-temperature operation and reprogrammability. This work paves a pathway for scalable digital hardware that embeds physical symmetries to enable large scale simulations of material systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20911v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pratik Brahma, Junghoon Han, Tamzid Razzaque, Saavan Patel, Sayeef Salahuddin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ion Jump Motion as the Background for Muon Diffusion in Battery Materials Research Using $\mu$SR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21013v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is shown by numerical simulations of muon spin relaxation ($\mu$SR) spectra and analysis of these using the Kubo-Toyabe relaxation function $G_z^{\rm KT}(t)$ that the anomalous peak in the fluctuation rate $\nu_{\rm KT}$ around a specific temperature $T^*$ and associated decrease of the linewidth $\Delta_{\rm KT}$ above $T^*$, often observed in the previous $\mu$SR studies on ion diffusion, originate from the sharp increase in the ion jump rate $\nu_{\rm i}$ against that of the muon $\nu_\mu$ with increasing temperature. This indicates that a more detailed reanalysis of the vintage data using the "extended" Kubo-Toyabe relaxation function $G_z^{\rm EA}(t)$ incorporating the jump motion of both ions and implanted muon (which was also used to simulate the $\mu$SR spectra) is useful for the proper evaluation of $\nu_{\rm i}$ and $\nu_\mu$. Meanwhile, it also suggests that the $\mu$SR results showing no such anomaly convey little information on ion diffusion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21013v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryosuke Kadono</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing magnetic-field-induced multipolar ordering through field-angle-resolved magnetostriction and thermal expansion in PrIr$_2$Zn$_{20}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21039</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21039v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We performed field-angle-resolved magnetostriction and thermal-expansion measurements on PrIr$_2$Zn$_{20}$, a cubic non-Kramers compound exhibiting antiferroquadrupolar order below $T_{\rm Q}=0.125$ K. Thermal expansion exhibits two qualitatively different anomalies under magnetic fields applied along the $[001]$ direction, providing experimental support for the existence of an intermediate A phase previously reported. Furthermore, comparison between the experimental results and theoretical modeling indicates a strong anisotropic coupling of the $O_{20}$ quadrupolar moment, which plays a key role in stabilizing the A phase. These findings demonstrate that multipolar states in non-Kramers systems can be effectively tuned by magnetic-field orientation, providing insights into the anisotropic nature of quadrupolar interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21039v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naoki Okamoto, Yohei Kono, Takahiro Onimaru, Keisuke T. Matsumoto, Kazumasa Hattori, Shunichiro Kittaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Edge-state transport in gapped bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21049</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21049v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate electronic transport in gapped bilayer graphene (gBLG) devices. For certain edge terminations -typically a combination of zigzag, armchair, and bearded types - we observe edge state conduction within the band gap, which is opened by a potential bias between the two layers. The edge states can generate a non-local resistance, in line with recent experiments [1]. Band structure calculations of gBLG nanoribbons corroborate the existence of the edge states, whose edge localization can be switched by tuning the electron energy. Their existence strongly depends on the edge termination and does not originate from a topological bulk-boundary correspondence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21049v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jes\'us Arturo S\'anchez-S\'anchez, Thomas Stegmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerated Discovery of Crystalline Materials with Record Ultralow Lattice Thermal Conductivity via a Universal Descriptor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21172</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21172v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ultralow glass-like lattice thermal conductivity in crystalline materials is crucial for enhancing energy conversion efficiency in thermoelectrics and thermal insulators. We introduce a universal descriptor for thermal conductivity that relies only on the atomic number in the primitive cell and the sound velocity, enabling fast and scalable materials screening. Coupled with high-throughput workflows and universal machine learning potentials, we identify the candidate materials with ultralow thermal conductivity from over 25, 000 materials. We further validate this approach by experimentally confirming record-low thermal conductivity values of 0.15-0.16 W/m/K from 170 to 400 K in the halide metal CsAg2I3. Combining inelastic neutron scattering with first-principles calculations, we attribute the ultralow thermal conductivity to the intrinsically small sound velocity, strong anharmonicity, and structural complexity. Our work illustrates how a universal descriptor, combined with high-throughput screening, machine-learning potential and experiment, enables the efficient discovery of materials with ultralow thermal conductivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21172v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xingchen Shen, Jiongzhi Zheng, Michael Marek Koza, Petr Levinsky, Jiri Hejtmanek, Philippe Boullay, Bernard Raveau, Jinghui Wang, Jun Li, Pierric Lemoine, Christophe Candolfi, Emmanuel Guilmeau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Giant critical current peak induced by pressure in kagome superconductor RbV$_{3}$Sb$_{5}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21195v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Superconductivity can coexist or compete with other orders such as magnetism or density waves. Optimizing superconductivity requires identifying competing orders that may disrupt Cooper pair coherence. Here, we use the self-field critical current ($I_{\rm c,sf}$) to probe pressure-tuned superconductivity in the kagome superconductor RbV$_3$Sb$_5$. As pressure destabilizes the charge-density wave (CDW) state, $I_{\rm c,sf}$ drastically enhances, peaking near the critical pressure where the CDW state is completely suppressed at zero temperature. Surprisingly, a weaker $I_{\rm c,sf}$ peak emerges within the CDW phase. Near the pressure of the weaker peak, the superconducting phase transition temperature shifts from an increasing trend with pressure to a near plateau. Our analysis suggests the possibility of a sudden change in the CDW pattern or a Lifshitz transition, highlighting the need for microscopic examinations of the CDW state for understanding the pressure evolution of superconductivity in RbV$_3$Sb$_5$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21195v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lingfei Wang, Wenyan Wang, Tsz Fung Poon, Zheyu Wang, Chun Wai Tsang, Xinyou Liu, Shanmin Wang, Kwing To Lai, Wei Zhang, Jeffery L. Tallon, Youichi Yamakawa, Hiroshi Kontani, Rina Tazai, Swee K. Goh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coupled Structural and Electronic Requirements in Alpha-FASnI3 Imposed by the Sn(II) Lone Pair</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21254</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21254v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Alpha-Formamidinium-tin-iodide (alpha-FASnI3) is a leading candidate for lead-free photovoltaic applications, adopting a nearly cubic structure at room temperature, but its stability remains limited by oxidation-driven degradation. Reliable first-principles modelling of the photovoltaic alpha-phase is further complicated by inconsistent structural models and levels of theory in the literature. Here, we identify the structural and electronic requirements needed for a physically sound description of alpha-FASnI3, whose behaviour is governed by a pseudo-Jahn-Teller (PJT) instability arising from the stereochemically active Sn(II) lone pair.
  Using 0 K relaxations, cross-code hybrid-functional benchmarks, and finite-temperature ab initio molecular dynamics, we show that a 4x4x4 supercell with randomly oriented FA+ cations is the smallest model that removes macroscopic dipoles, preserves cubic symmetry, recovers local octahedral tilts, and captures the characteristic PJT-driven Sn off-centering. Accurate band edges and a reliable band gap require a PBE0-level hybrid functional with spin-orbit coupling to treat Sn relativistic effects, together with nonlocal dispersion (rVV10) to capture the enhanced Sn-I covalency. Finite-temperature simulations reveal that Sn off-centering remains local, &lt;111&gt;-oriented, and robust against thermal fluctuations, and that reproducing the experimental 300 K band gap requires a 6x6x6 supercell. These results define the essential ingredients for reliable modelling of alpha-FASnI3 and provide a rigorous foundation for studying lone-pair-driven physics in tin halide perovskites.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21254v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mridhula Venkatanarayanan, Vladislav Slama, Madhubanti Mukherjee, Andrea Vezzosi, Ursula Rothlisberger, Virginia Carnevali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery and recovery of crystalline materials with property-conditioned transformers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21299</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21299v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Generative models have recently shown great promise for accelerating the design and discovery of new functional materials. Conditional generation enhances this capacity by allowing inverse design, where specific desired properties can be requested during the generation process. However, conditioning of transformer-based approaches, in particular, is constrained by discrete tokenisation schemes and the risk of catastrophic forgetting during fine-tuning. This work introduces CrystaLLM-{\pi} (property injection), a conditional autoregressive framework that integrates continuous property representations directly into the transformer's attention mechanism. Two architectures, Property-Key-Value (PKV) Prefix attention and PKV Residual attention, are presented. These methods bypass inefficient sequence-level tokenisation and preserve foundational knowledge from unsupervised pre-training on Crystallographic Information Files (CIFs) as textual input. We establish the efficacy of these mechanisms through systematic robustness studies and evaluate the framework's versatility across two distinct tasks. First, for structure recovery, the model processes high-dimensional, heterogeneous X-ray diffraction patterns, achieving structural accuracy competitive with specialised models and demonstrating applications to experimental structure recovery and polymorph differentiation. Second, for materials discovery, the model is fine-tuned on a specialised photovoltaic dataset to generate novel, stable candidates validated by Density Functional Theory (DFT). It implicitly learns to target optimal band gap regions for high photovoltaic efficiency, demonstrating a capability to map complex structure-property relationships. CrystaLLM-{\pi} provides a unified, flexible, and computationally efficient framework for inverse materials design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21299v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cyprien Bone, Matthew Walker, Kuangdai Leng, Luis M. Antunes, Ricardo Grau-Crespo, Amil Aligayev, Javier Dominguez, Keith T. Butler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling Micrometer-Range Spin-Wave Transport in Artificial Spin Ice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21308</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21308v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Artificial spin ice (ASI) systems exhibit fascinating phenomena, such as frustration and the formation of magnetic monopole states, and Dirac strings. However, exploring the wave phenomena in these systems is elusive due to the weak dipolar coupling that governs their interactions. In this study, we demonstrate coherent spin-wave propagation in an hybrid ASI system, which is based on a multilayered ferromagnetic thin film with perpendicular magnetic anisotropy and in-plane magnetized nanoelements embedded within it. We show that this system enables spin-wave transmission over a one-micrometer distance via exchange-mediated coupling between subsystems and evanescent spin-wave tunneling through the out-of-plane magnetized parts. This system overcomes the limitations of purely dipolar interactions in standard ASIs while preserving their fundamental properties. Thus, it provides a platform for studying spin-wave phenomena in frustrated ASI systems and paves the way for exploiting them in analog signal processing with spin waves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21308v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Syamlal Sankaran Kunnath, Mateusz Zelent, Pawel Gruszecki, Maciej Krawczyk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stabilization of Tetragonal Phase and Aluminum-Doping Effect in a Bilayer Nickelate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21315v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent studies suggest that the tetragonal phase of the Ruddlesden-Popper (RP) bilayer nickelate, La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ or La$_2$PrNi$_2$O$_7$, which is stabilized under high pressures, is responsible for high-temperature superconductivity (HTSC). In this context, realization of the tetragonal phase at ambient pressure could be a rational step to achieve the goal of ambient-pressure HTSC in the nickelate system. By employing the concept of Goldschmidt tolerance factor, we succeed in stabilizing the tetragonal phase by aluminum doping together with post annealing under moderately high oxygen pressure. X-ray and neutron diffractions verify the tetragonal $I4/mmm$ structure for the post-annealed samples La$_3$Ni$_{2-x}$Al$_x$O$_{7-\delta}$ (0.3 $\leq x \leq$ 0.5). The Al-doped samples, including the tetragonal ones, show semiconducting properties, carry localized magnetic moments, and exhibit spin-glass-like behaviors at low temperatures, all of which can be explained in terms of charge carrier localization. Furthermore, high-pressure resistance measurements on post-annealed samples reveal that even a low Al doping ($x$ = 0.05) suppresses superconductivity almost completely. This work gives information about the effect of nonmagnetic impurity on metallicity as well as superconductivity in bilayer nickelates, which would contribute to understanding the superconducting mechanism in RP nickelates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21315v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jia-Yi Lu, Yi-Qiang Lin, Kai-Xin Ye, Xin-Yu Zhao, Jia-Xin Li, Ya-Nan Zhang, Hao Li, Bai-Jiang Lv, Hui-Qiu Yuan, Guang-Han Cao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large longitudinal and anomalous transverse Magneto-thermoelectric effect in kagome antiferromagnet FeGe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21361</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21361v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Topological Kagome magnets, characterized by nontrivial electronic band structures featuring flat band, Dirac cone and van Hove singularities, provide a new avenue for the realization of thermoelectric devices. Unlike the conventional longitudinal Seebeck effect, transverse thermoelectric (TE) effects like the Nernst effect have attracted growing interest due to their unique transverse geometry and potential advantages. Here, we report the observation of a significant transverse thermoelectric conductivity alpha A_zx of 15 A K-1m-1 at low temperatures, together with a pronounced anomalous Nernst effect in the Kagome antiferromagnet FeGe, which exhibits a charge density wave inside the antiferromagnetic (AFM) state. This value is the highest record among known AFM materials. Furthermore, the thermopower at 14 T increases by 102-104% around the canted-AFM (CAFM) transition temperature, Tcant, comparable to that of the well-known AFM thermoelectric materials. These effects are attributed to large Berry curvature arising from the non-collinear spin texture in FeGe, highlighting its potential for enhancing thermoelectric performance and its candidacy for magneto-TE applications in Kagome antiferromagnetic materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21361v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiajun Ma, Rong Chen, Yazhou Li, Chenfei Shi, Yantao Cao, YuWei Zhang, Jiaxing Liao, Yunfei Han, Guangxi Wen, Jialu Wang, Hanjie Guo, Jianhui Dai, Chenguang Fu, Jin-Ke Bao, Yan Sun, Zhu-An Xu, Yuke Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Torsion-induced Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction in helical magnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21400</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21400v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It has been shown that in magnets possessing an inversion center in the absence of deformations, a torsion-induced Dzyaloshinsky-Moriya interaction (tiDMI) can arise. A microscopic mechanism for this interaction is described, involving the transfer of angular momentum to the lattice upon electron reflection from the magnet's boundary. An estimate of the tiDMI constant is provided. It is demonstrated that tiDMI can lift the chiral degeneracy in helimagnets, and a way for experimentally observing this effect is proposed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21400v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. A. Kuznetsov, A. A. Fraerman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Size optimization for observeing Majorana fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21423</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21423v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Majorana fermions (zero modes) are predicted to emerge in nanowire-superconductor heterostructures. This theoretical prediction typically relies on an oversimplified model, where both the nanowire and the superconductor are idealized as one-dimensional systems. In reality, heterostructures have finite sizes that deviate from this idealization-and as a result, smoking-gun evidence confirming the existence of these zero modes remains elusive. Here, we investigate the finite-size effects of both the nanowire and the superconductor, and optimize their sizes to ensure that only one Majorana fermion exists at each end of the heterostructure. It is discovered that the optimal transverse sizes of the nanowire are less than 100nm in width and approximately 1nm in thickness. For the superconductor layer, its optimal thickness (a key aspect of its size) must exceed its coherence length. We also present the optimal sizes of the two types of materials used in the experiment in a quantitative manner. Notably, the identified optimal thickness of the superconductor (Al films, $\sim$1000nm)--a critical size parameter--is two orders of magnitude larger than the thickness of Al films currently utilized in experimental devices (e.g., InSb-Al and InAs-Al heterostructures). Our findings could explain why Majorana fermions have not been observed in current experiments, and offer guidance for the size selection of heterostructures to implement Majorana fermions in future studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21423v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guo-Jian Qiao, Zhi-Lei Zhang, Xin Yue, C. P. Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antiferromagnetism and Kekul\'e valence bond order in the honeycomb optical Su-Schrieffer-Heeger-Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21440</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21440v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The precise role of e-ph coupling in graphene and related materials on a honeycomb lattice is not yet fully understood, despite extensive research on these systems. Here, we perform sign-problem-free determinant quantum Monte Carlo (DQMC) simulations of the optical Su-Schrieffer-Heeger (oSSH)-Hubbard model on the honeycomb lattice, focusing on the parameters relevant to graphene. Performing finite-size scaling analyzes, we obtain the model's ground state phase diagram, which includes the semi-metal (SM), Kekul\'e Valence Bond Solid (KVBS), and anti-ferromagnetic (AFM) phases, as well as indications of a small KVBS/AFM coexistence region. We find that a weak to moderate Hubbard repulsion, tuned toward the SM-AFM critical value in the pure honeycomb Hubbard model, enhances KVBS correlations and can even stabilize the KVBS phase. Estimating the effective parameters for graphene places it in the SM region of the phase diagram, but near the SM-KVBS phase boundary. Notably, we predict that increasing either the on-site Hubbard repulsion or the e-ph coupling strength drives graphene toward the KVBS phase rather than the AFM phase, highlighting a synergistic effect that can be exploited to further control the remarkable properties of graphene and related materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21440v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sohan Malkaruge Costa, Benjamin Cohen-Stead, Steven Johnston</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of interacting bosons in a two-leg ring ladder with artificial magnetic flux and ac-driven modulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21445v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the nonequilibrium dynamics of interacting bosons in a two-leg ring ladder pierced by an artificial magnetic flux, where the particles are initially localized in the central sites of both rings, and the ac-driven local energy shifts are applied to the remaining lattice sites. Within the mean-field approximation, we demonstrate the emergence of nonlinear self-trapping for strong interparticle interactions, and characterize the distinct excitation regimes in the absence of the inter-ring tunneling. The artificial magnetic flux typically introduces Peierls phase factors, which induces complex-valued hopping amplitudes and leads to directed net particle currents along the chains. By further incorporating the finite inter-ring coupling and biased intra-ring hopping, we reveal that the tuning of the drive frequency and Peierls phase allows the precise control over both the intensity and direction of particle currents, which facilitates the transition between chiral and antichiral dynamics. These findings offer insights into the coherent manipulation of matter-wave transports in closed-loop lattice configurations and the exploration of nonequilibrium synthetic quantum systems in related fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21445v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Q. Lai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enabling the bulk photovoltaic effect in centrosymmetric materials through an external electric field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21458</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21458v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a practical approach to electrically tuning the nonlinear photoresponse of two-dimensional semiconductors by explicitly incorporating a static out-of-plane electric field into the electronic ground state prior to optical excitation, as a gate bias. The method is implemented by dressing a Wannier-interpolated Hamiltonian with the field through its position matrix elements, which allows the gate bias to modify orbital hybridization and band dispersion beyond perturbative treatments. Within the independent-particle approximation, the resulting second-order (shift) conductivity is evaluated for both centrosymmetric and non-centrosymmetric layered systems. Applied to MoS$_2$, the approach captures the emergence of a finite shift current in centrosymmetric bilayers and the tunability of intrinsic responses in polar structures. The shift conductivity rises linearly at small fields and saturates at higher intensities, reflecting the competition between the growing shift vector and the weakening interband coupling as resonant transitions move away from high-symmetry valleys. A Taylor expansion of the field-dressed conductivity connects this behavior to the third-order optical response, revealing a unified picture of field-induced nonlinearities. These results establish field dressing of Wannier Hamiltonians as a practical route to model and predict nonlinear photocurrents in layered materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21458v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guilherme J. Inacio, Juan Jos\'e Esteve-Paredes, Maur\'icio F. C. Martins Quintela, Wendel S. Paz, Juan Jos\'e Palacios</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charge carrier relaxation dynamics in the one-dimensional Kondo lattice model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21539v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A generic question in the field of ultrafast dynamics is concerned with the relaxation dynamics and the subsequent thermalization of optically excited charge carriers. Among several possible relaxation channels available in a solid-state system, we focus on the coupling to magnetic excitations. In this paper, we study the real-time dynamics of a paradigmatic model, the Kondo lattice model in one dimension. We conduct a comprehensive study of the relaxation processes by evaluating the spin polarization of the conduction electron, the local spin-spin correlation between localized and conduction electrons, and the electronic momentum distribution. While in the well-studied cases of one or two charge carriers in a ferromagnetic background, no thermalization occurs, we demonstrate that the stationary state is compatible with thermalization if either the electronic filling is finite or the magnetic background is in the singlet sector. Our real-time simulations using the time-dependent Lanczos method are corroborated by a direct comparison with finite-temperature expectation values and an analysis of the spectrum in terms of the gap ratio.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21539v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arturo Perez-Romero, Mica Schwarm, Fabian Heidrich-Meisner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetries of excitons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21540</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21540v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Excitons, bound electron-hole pairs, are responsible for strong optical resonances near the bandgap in low-dimensional materials and wide-bandgap insulators. Although current ab initio methods can accurately determine exciton energies and eigenstates, their symmetries have been much less explored. In this work, we employ standard group-theory methods to analyse the transformation properties of excitonic states, obtained by solving the BSE, under crystal symmetry operations. We develop an approach to assign irreducible-representation labels to excitonic states, providing a state-of-the-art framework for analysing their symmetries and selection rules (including, for example, the case of exciton-phonon coupling). Complementary to the symmetry classification, we introduce the concept of total crystal angular momentum for excitons in the presence of rotational symmetries, allowing the derivation of conservation laws. Furthermore, we demonstrate how these symmetry properties can be exploited to greatly enhance the computational efficiency of exciton calculations with the BSE. We apply our methodology to three prototypical systems to understand the role of symmetries in different contexts: (i) For LiF, we present the symmetry analysis of the entire excitonic dispersion and examine the selection rules for optical absorption. (ii) In the calculation of resonant Raman spectra of monolayer MoSe2, we demonstrate how the conservation of total crystal angular momentum governs exciton-phonon interactions, leading to the observed resonant enhancement. (iii) In bulk hBN, we analyze the role of symmetries for the coupling of finite-momentum excitons to finite-momentum phonons and their manifestation in the phonon-assisted luminescence spectra. This work establishes a general and robust framework for understanding the symmetry properties of excitons in crystals, providing a foundation for future studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21540v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muralidhar Nalabothula, Davide Sangalli, Fulvio Paleari, Sven Reichardt, Ludger Wirtz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phonon-tunable THz magnonic emission in multiferroic heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21596</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21596v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Collective excitations such as magnons and polar phonons provide natural access to the terahertz (THz) regime, but efficient generation and tunability remain elusive. Multiferroic BiFeO3 combines both orders at room temperature, offering a unique platform for narrowband THz emission. Here, we achieve efficient sub-bandgap optical rectification of coupled phonon-polaritons near 2 THz in bare epitaxial thin films. In Pt/BiFeO3 bilayers, we demonstrate that coupling the electromagnon branch with ultrafast strain waves, optically generated in Pt layers with various thicknesses, can produce tunable and narrowband emission between 0.4-0.8 THz. These results uncover the intertwined role of phonons, magnons, and magneto-acoustic dynamics in antiferromagnetic multiferroics, and establish these hybrid platforms as versatile engineered narrowband THz sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21596v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sylvain Massabeau, Amr Abdelsamie, Florian Godel, Filip Miljevic, Noela Rezi, Pascale Gemeiner, Karim Bouzehouane, Thomas Buttiens, Sukhdeep Dhillon, Thomas Maroutian, Jean-Marie George, Henri Jaffres, Brahim Dkhil, Stephane Fusil, Vincent Garcia, Romain Lebrun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unconventional orders in the maple-leaf ferro-antiferromagnetic Heisenberg model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21598v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by the search for unconventional orders in frustrated quantum magnets, we present a multi-method investigation into the nature of the quantum phase diagram of the spin-$1/2$ Heisenberg model on the maple-leaf lattice with three symmetry-inequivalent nearest-neighbor interactions. It has been argued that the parameter regime with antiferromagnetic couplings on hexagons $J_h$ and ferromagnetic couplings on triangles $J_t$ and dimer $J_d$ bonds, is potentially host to a cornucopia of emergent phases with unconventional orders. Our analysis indeed identifies an extended region where any conventional dipolar magnetic order is absent. A hexagonal singlet state is found in the region around $J_{d}=J_{t}=0$, while a dimerized hexagonal singlet order of a lattice nematic character appears proximate to the phase boundary with the c$120^\circ$ antiferromagnetic order. Interestingly, upon traversing the bulk of the paramagnetic (PM) region, we find a variety of distinct correlation profiles, which are qualitatively different from those of the hexagonal singlet and dimerized hexagonal singlet orders but feature no appreciable spin-nematic response, while the boundary with the ferromagnetic phase shows evidence of spin-nematic order. This PM region is thus likely host to an ensemble of nonmagnetic phases which could putatively include quantum spin liquids. Our phase diagram is built from a complementary application of state-of-the-art implementations of the cluster mean-field and pseudo-fermion functional renormalization group approaches, together with an unconstrained Luttinger-Tisza treatment of the model providing insights from the semi-classical limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21598v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lasse Gresista, Dominik Kiese, Simon Trebst, Yasir Iqbal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dichroism from Thermoelectric Chiral Drives: Generalized Sum Rules for Orbital and Heat Magnetizations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21599</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21599v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a unified framework that relates orbital and heat magnetizations to experimentally accessible excitation spectra, through thermoelectric probes and generalized sum rules. By analyzing zero-temperature transport coefficients and applying Kramers-Kronig relations, we derive spectral representations of magnetization densities from thermoelectric correlation functions. Excitation rates under thermoelectric chiral drives then naturally emerge as direct probes of these Kubo-type correlators, placing orbital and heat magnetizations on equal footing with the topological Chern number. As a direct consequence of our formalism, we introduce a hierarchical construction that organizes orbital and heat magnetizations into distinct physical contributions accessible through sum rules, and also derive real-space markers of these magnetizations. From an experimental standpoint, we propose concrete implementations of thermoelectric dichroic measurements in quantum-engineered platforms based on modulated strain fields. These results establish thermoelectric dichroic measurements as a versatile route to access and disentangle fundamental ground-state properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21599v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Baptiste Bermond, Lucila Peralta Gavensky, Ana\"is Defossez, Nathan Goldman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Edge-Dependent Superconductivity in Twisted Bismuth Bilayers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21657v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Twisted bilayers offer a compelling and, at times, confounding platform for the engineering of new twistronic materials. Whereas standard studies almost exclusively focus on the explicit enigma that is presented by twist-angles, perhaps better epitomized by the related phenomena that have been observed in twisted bilayer graphene, functional devices necessarily face a fundamental concern: boundary heterogeneity in their structures. In this study, we address this concern by strictly investigating the electronic properties of twisted bismuth bilayers at the flake's edges and the vibrational properties of the flake. Twisted flakes exhibit continuous variations of these properties, away from the bulk, as we herein report using ab initio density functional theory, by systematically mapping the drastic evolution of band topology, electronic density of states, and possible superconductivity. Our work reveals a dramatic, non-fortuitous consequence of the structural disorder at the edges of the flakes: an enhanced electronic density of states at the Fermi level. This enhancement reaches a maximum of 10 times that of perfect-crystalline bismuth. Given that the superconducting critical temperature, Tc, is exponentially dependent on the electronic density of states at the Fermi level, this substantial structural variation immediately suggests a powerful mechanism for vastly increasing Tc. We also identify the twist-angle as a new critical parameter in designing novel engineering devices with topologically enhanced properties. Our results provide a necessary theoretical framework for interpreting new data for the upcoming generation of twistronic heterogeneous materials, and pave the way to search for atomic disordered metastable structures that could lead to enhanced superconducting transition temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21657v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Isa\'ias Rodr\'iguez, Renela M. Valladares, Alexander Valladares, David Hinojosa-Romero, Flor B. Quiroga, Ariel A. Valladares</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the generalized Keffer form of the Dzyaloshinskii constant: its consequences for the spin, momentum and polarization evolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21672</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21672v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Different analytical features of the Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction are related to different contribution to the Dzyaloshinskii constant in the microscopic Hamiltonian. Consequences appear in the macroscopic Landau--Lifshitz--Gilbert equation. It leads to various phenomena. Three contributions to the Dzyaloshinskii constant are reviewed and combined in the generalized Keffer form of the Dzyaloshinskii constant. Macroscopic consequences of these three mechanisms are well-known, but further possible generalizations of the Keffer form of the Dzyaloshinskii constant are suggested. Consequences for the spin evolution equations, the momentum balance equations, and polarization evolution equations are considered. Some analog of the Keffer form is suggested for the exchange integral in symmetric Heisenberg Hamiltonian demonstrating the nontrivial contribution of the ligands in this regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21672v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pavel A. Andreev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mean-field Modelling of Moir\'e Materials: A User's Guide with Selected Applications to Twisted Bilayer Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21683</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21683v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We review the theoretical modelling of moir\'e materials, focusing on various aspects of magic-angle twisted bilayer graphene (MA-TBG) viewed through the lens of Hartree-Fock mean-field theory. We first provide an elementary introduction to the continuum modelling of moir\'e bandstructures, and explain how interactions are incorporated to study correlated states. We then discuss how to implement mean-field simulations of ground state structure and collective excitations in this setting. With this background established, we rationalize the power of mean-field approximations in MA-TBG, by discussing the idealized "chiral-flat" strong-coupling limit, in which ground states at electron densities commensurate with the moir\'e superlattice are exactly captured by mean-field ans\"atze. We then illustrate the phenomenological shortcomings of this limit, leading us naturally into a discussion of the intermediate-coupling incommensurate Kekul\'e spiral (IKS) order and its origins in ever-present heterostrain. IKS and its placement within an expanded Hartree-Fock manifold form our first "case study". Our second case study involves time-dependence, and focuses on the collective modes of various broken-symmetry insulators in MA-TBG. As a third and final case study, we return to the strong-coupling picture, which can be stabilized by aligning MA-TBG to an hBN substrate. In this limit, we show how mean field theory can be adapted to the translationally non-invariant setting in order to quantitatively study the energetics of domain walls in orbital Chern insulating states. We close with a discussion of extensions and further applications. Used either as a standalone reference or alongside the accompanying open-source code, this review should enable readers with a basic knowledge of band theory and many-body physics to systematically build and analyze detailed models of generic moir\'e systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21683v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yves H. Kwan, Ziwei Wang, Glenn Wagner, Nick Bultinck, Steven H. Simon, Siddharth A. Parameswaran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical topology of chiral and nonreciprocal state transfers in a non-Hermitian quantum system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.03026</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.03026v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The fundamental concept underlying topological phenomena posits the geometric phase associated with eigenstates. In contrast to this prevailing notion, theoretical studies on time-varying Hamiltonians allow for a new type of topological phenomenon, known as topological dynamics, where the evolution process allows a hidden topological invariant associated with continuous flows. To validate this conjecture, we study topological chiral and nonreciprocal dynamics by encircling the exceptional points (EPs) of non-Hermitian Hamiltonians in a trapped ion system. These dynamics are topologically robust against external perturbations even in the presence dissipation-induced nonadiabatic processes. Our findings indicate that they are protected by dynamical vorticity -- an emerging topological invariant associated with the energy dispersion of non-Hermitian band structures in a parallel transported eigenbasis. The symmetry breaking and other key features of topological dynamics are directly observed through quantum state tomography. Our results mark a significant step towards exploring topological properties of open quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.03026v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pengfei Lu, Yang Liu, Qifeng Lao, Teng Liu, Xinxin Rao, Ji Bian, Hao Wu, Feng Zhu, Le Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The effects of decoherence on Fermi's golden rule</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21238</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21238v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fermi's golden rule which describes the transition rates between two electronic levels under external stimulations is used ubiquitously in different fields of physics. The original Fermi's golden rule was derived from perturbative time-dependent Schr\"{o}dinger's equation without the direct contribution by decoherence effect. However, as a result of recent developments of quantum computing and ultra fast carrier dynamics, the decoherence becomes a prominent topic in fundamental research.Here, by using the non-adiabatic molecular dynamics which goes beyond the time-dependent Schr\"{o}dinger's equation by introducing decoherence, we study the effect of decoherence on Fermi's golden rule for the fixed basis and the adiabatic basis, respectively. We find that when the decoherence time becomes short, there is a significant deviation from the Fermi's golden rule for both bases. By using monolayer $\mathrm{WS_2}$ as an example, we investigate the decoherence effect in the carrier transitions induced by the electron-phonon coupling with first-principle method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21238v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Caihong Zheng, Fan Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic and extrinsic photogalvanic effects in twisted bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.15005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.15005v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The chiral lattice structure of twisted bilayer graphene with D6 symmetry allows for intrinsic photogalvanic effects only at off-normal incidence, while additional extrinsic effects are known to be induced by a substrate or a gate potential. In this work, we first compute the intrinsic effects and show they reverse sign at the magic angle, revealing a band inversion at the {\Gamma} point. We next consider different extrinsic effects, showing how they can be used to track the strengths of the substrate coupling or displacement field. We also show that the approximate particle-hole symmetry implies stringent constraints on the chemical potential dependence of all photocurrents. A detailed comparison of intrinsic vs. extrinsic photocurrents therefore reveals a wealth of information about the band structure and can also serve as a benchmark to constrain the symmetry breaking patterns of correlated states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.15005v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fernando Pe\~naranda, Hector Ochoa, Fernando de Juan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic structure of UTe$_2$ under pressure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04292v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A heavy-fermion paramagnet UTe$_2$ has been a strong candidate for a spin-triplet superconductor. Experiments on UTe$_2$ under pressure have been vigorously conducted, and rich phase diagrams have been suggested. Multiple superconducting phases exist in the pressure region of $0 \leq P &lt; 1.8 \mathrm{\;GPa}$, and an antiferromagnetic ordered state is observed in the high pressure region $P &gt; 1.8 \mathrm{\;GPa}$. However, under pressure, the underlying electronic structure in the normal state has not been clarified, although knowledge of electronic structures is essential for studying magnetic and superconducting states. As an indispensable step toward understanding the phase diagram of UTe$_2$, we study the electronic structure under hydrostatic and uniaxial stresses based on the density functional theory with and without employing structural optimization. It is shown that the low-energy band structure and Fermi surfaces are not sensitive to pressure for parameters where itinerant $f$-electrons are not essential. However, we find a significant pressure dependence for a certain Coulomb interaction $U$ of the GGA+$U$ calculation, where the large weight of $f$-electrons appears at the Fermi level. An increase in the density of states at the Fermi level is observed under pressure, which is attributed to compressive stress along the [010] crystallographic axis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04292v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Makoto Shimizu, Youichi Yanase</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ab initio study of orbital-selective superconductivity in $\gamma$-BiPd</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14734v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the superconducting (SC) properties of experimentally realised $\gamma$-BiPd by solving the anisotropic Migdal-Eliashberg equations in conjunction with {\it ab initio} relativistic calculations of the electron and phonon band structures as well as electron-phonon coupling (EPC) matrix elements. Our study reveals that $\gamma$-BiPd possesses a complex Fermi surface (FS), consisting of two electron pockets and one hole pocket, each characterised by distinct atomic orbitals. Our key finding is that the superconductivity in $\gamma$-BiPd is primarily orbital-selective, arising from Bi $p$-orbitals, and distributed anisotropically on the FS, although contribution from Pd $d$-orbitals, particularly on the hole pocket, is also discernable. While our results show an anisotropic nature of the {\bf k}-dependent SC gap $\Delta_{\bf k}$ and EPC strength $\lambda_{\bf k}$ across the FS, calculated superconducting quasiparticle density of states $N_S$ spectra exhibit a U-shaped gap and $\Delta_{\bf k}$ distribution forms a single peak, being consistent with the spin-singlet $s$-wave superconductivity observed in this material. The calculated $T_c$ is $\sim$2.0 K, agreeing in order of magnitude with the experimental value of 3.3 K in $\gamma$-BiPd thin films. The predicted EPC-enhanced Sommerfeld coefficient $\gamma_n$ of $0.141$ mJ/K$^2$cm$^3$ is similar to the experimental $\gamma_n$ value ($0.119$ mJ/K$^2$cm$^3$) of the isoelectronic and isostructural Bi(Pd$_{0.5}$Pt$_{0.5}$) alloy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14734v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sonu Prasad Keshri, Guang-Yu Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic injection photocurrents in valley polarized states of twisted bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09703</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09703v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Magic-angle twisted bilayer graphene displays a complex phase diagram as a function of flat band filling, featuring compressibility cascade transitions and a variety of competing ground states with broken spin, valley and point group symmetries. Recent THz photocurrent spectroscopy experiments have shown a dependence on the filling which is not consistent with the simplest cascade picture of sequential filling of equivalent flat bands. In this work, we show that when time-reversal symmetry is broken due to valley polarization, a magnetic injection photocurrent develops which can be used to distinguish different spin-valley polarization scenarios. Using the topological heavy fermion model we compute both shift and injection currents as a function of filling and argue that current experiments can be used to determine the spontaneous valley polarization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09703v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fernando Pe\~naranda, H\'ector Ochoa, Fernando de Juan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critical spin fluctuations across the superconducting dome in La$_{2-x}$Sr$_{x}$CuO$_4$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13600</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13600v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Overdoped cuprate superconductors are strange metals above their superconducting transition temperature. In such materials, the electrical resistivity has a strong linear dependence on temperature ($T$) and electrical current is not carried by electron quasiparticles as in conventional metals. Here we demonstrate that the strange metal behaviour co-exists with strongly temperature-dependent critical spin fluctuations showing dynamical scaling across the cuprate phase diagram. Our neutron scattering observations and the strange metal behaviour are consistent with a spin density wave quantum phase transition in a metal with spatial disorder in the tuning parameter. Numerical computations using a theory of spin density waves in a disordered metal yield an extended `Griffiths phase' with scaling properties in agreement with experimental observations. Thus we establish that low-energy spin excitations and spatial disorder are central to the strange metal behaviour.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13600v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacopo Radaelli, Oliver J. Lipscombe, Mengze Zhu, J. Ross Stewart, Aavishkar A. Patel, Subir Sachdev, Stephen M. Hayden</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Charge Density Waves in two-dimensional NbSe2 with Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13675</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.13675v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Niobium diselenide (NbSe$_2$) has garnered significant attention due to the coexistence of superconductivity and charge density waves (CDWs) down to the monolayer limit. However, realistic modeling of CDWs-capturing effects such as layer number, twist angle, and strain-remains challenging due to the high computational cost of first-principles methods. Here, we develop a physically informed workflow for training machine-learning interatomic potentials (MLIPs) based on the E(3)-equivariant Allegro architecture, tailored to capture the subtle structural and dynamical signatures of CDWs in mono- and bilayer NbSe$_2$.We find that while CDW lattice distortions are relatively easy to learn, modeling vibrational properties remains more challenging. It requires targeted dataset design and careful hyperparameter tuning, pushing the boundaries and testing the extensibility of current MLIP frameworks. Our MLIPs enable reliable simulations of commensurate and incommensurate CDW phases, including their sensitivity to dimensionality and stacking, as well as CDW dynamics, phonons, and transition temperatures estimated via the stochastic self-consistent harmonic approximation. This work opens new possibilities for studying and tuning CDWs in NbSe$_2$ and other two-dimensional systems, with implications for electron-phonon coupling, superconductivity, and advanced materials design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.13675v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Norma Rivano, Francesco Libbi, Chuin Wei Tan, Christopher Cheung, Jose Lado, Arash Mostofi, Philip Kim, Johannes Lischner, Adolfo O. Fumega, Boris Kozinsky, Zachary A. H. Goodwin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crossover of Superconductivity across the antiferromagnetic end point in FeSe$_{\rm 1-x}$S$_{\rm x}$ under pressure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04156</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.04156v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Temperature-pressure ($T$-$P$) phase diagrams of FeSe$_{\rm 1-x}$S$_{\rm x}$ were investigated by the measurements of dc magnetization ($M$) and electrical resistivity ($\rho$) under pressure, using single crystal specimens with $x$=0.04, 0.08 and 0.13. For all specimens, the $M$($T$) curves under pressure near the end point of the antiferromagnetic (AFM) phase are found to show a two-step diamagnetic response, which can be described as the sum of two diamagnetic components $M_1$($T$) and $M_2$($T$), indicating that two superconducting (SC) phases with different $T_{\rm c}$ values coexist within a pressure range of $\Delta$$P$$\sim$1 GPa. Moreover, the pressure dependence of the amplitudes of $M_1$($T$) and $M_2$($T$) indicates a continuous transfer of the volume fraction between the two SC phases. These behaviors suggest that a crossover of superconductivity occurs in conjunction with the emergence of AFM phase and imply that the SC phases inside and outside the AFM phase could have different origins.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.04156v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kiyotaka Miyoshi, Takanobu Nakatani, Yumi Yamamoto, Takumi Maeda, Daichi Izuhara, Ikumi Matsushima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-dimensional $J_1$-$J_2$ clock model: Enhanced symmetries, emergent orders, and Landau-incompatible transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.05194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.05194v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive study on the frustrated $J_1$-$J_2$ classical $q$-state clock model with even $q&gt;4$ on a two-dimensional square lattice, revealing a rich ensemble of phases driven by competing interactions. In the unfrustrated regime ($J_1&gt;2J_2$), the model reproduces the standard clock model phenomenology: a low-temperature $\mathbb{Z}_q$-broken ferromagnet, an intermediate XY-like critical quasi-long-range-ordered (QLRO) phase with emergent $U(1)$ symmetry, and a high-temperature paramagnet. For $J_1&lt;2J_2$, frustration stabilizes five distinct regimes: the disordered paramagnet, a stripe-ordered phase breaking $\mathbb{Z}_q\times\mathbb{Z}_2$ symmetry, two $\mathbb{Z}_2$-broken nematic phases (one with and one without QLRO), and an exotic stripe phase with emergent discrete $\mathbb{Z}_q$ spin degrees of freedom prohibited in the microscopic Hamiltonian. Remarkably, this seemingly forbidden $\mathbb{Z}_q$ order emerges via a relevant operator in the infrared long-wavelength limit, rather than from an irrelevant perturbation, highlighting a non-standard route to emergence. Using large-scale corner transfer matrix renormalization group calculations, complemented by classical Monte Carlo simulations, we map the complete phase diagram and identify Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless, Ising, first-order, and unconventional Landau-incompatible transitions between different phases. Finally, we propose an effective field-theoretic framework that encompasses these emergent orders and their interwoven transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.05194v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vishnu Pulloor Kuttanikkad, Abhishodh Prakash, Rajesh Narayanan, Titas Chanda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unconventional Fractional Phases in Multi-Band Vortexable Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07790</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07790v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this Letter, we study topological flat bands with distinct features that deviate from conventional Landau level behavior. We show that even in the ideal quantum geometry limit, moire flat band systems can exhibit physical phenomena fundamentally different from Landau levels without lattices. In particular, we find new fractional quantum Hall states emerging from multi-band vortexable systems, where multiple exactly flat bands appear at the Fermi energy. While the set of bands as a whole exhibits ideal quantum geometry, individual bands separately lose vortexability, and thus making them very different from a stack of Landau levels. At certain filling fractions, we find fractional states whose Hall conductivity deviates from the filling factor. Through careful numerical and analytical studies, we rule out all known mechanisms--such as fractional quantum Hall crystals or separate filling of trivial and topological bands--as possible explanations. Leveraging the exact solvability of vortexable systems, we use analytic Bloch wavefunctions to uncover the origin of these new fractional states, which arises from the commensurability between the moire unit cell and the magnetic unit cell of an emergent effective magnetic field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07790v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/jmk4-46tj</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 216501 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Siddhartha Sarkar, Xiaohan Wan, Ang-Kun Wu, Shi-Zeng Lin, Kai Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comment on "Electric conductivity of graphene: Kubo model versus a nonlocal quantum field theory model (arXiv:2403.02279v3)"</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.10792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.10792v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently, Rodriguez-Lopez, Wang, and Antezza [Phys. Rev. B v.111, 115428 (2025)] compared the theoretical descriptions of electric conductivity of graphene given by the Kubo model and quantum field theory in terms of the polarization tensor. According to this article, in the spatially nonlocal case, the quantum field theoretical description contains ``hard inconsistencies". By modifying the equality, which relates the conductivity and polarization expressions, the predictions of quantum field theory were revised and brought in agreement with those following from the nonrelativistic Kubo model. Here, it is shown that this modification violates the requirement of gauge invariance and, thus, is unacceptable. By comparing both theoretical approaches, we demonstrate that all the results obtained within quantum field theory are physically well justified whereas an application of the modified expression for the conductivity of graphene leads to the consequences of nonphysical character.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.10792v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Bordag, N. Khusnutdinov, G. L. Klimchitskaya, V. M. Mostepanenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Double Supersolid Phase in a Bosonic t-J-V Model with Rydberg Atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16820</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16820v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent advances in Rydberg tweezer arrays bring novel opportunities for programmable quantum simulations beyond previous capabilities. In this work, we investigate a bosonic t-J-V model currently realized with Rydberg atoms. Through large-scale quantum Monte Carlo simulations, we uncover an emergent double supersolid (DSS) phase with the coexistence of two superfluids and crystalline order. Tunable long-range tunneling and repulsive hole-hole interactions enable a rich phase diagram featuring a double superfluid phase, a DSS phase, and an antiferromagnetic insulator. Intriguingly, within the DSS regime we observe an unconventional thermal enhancement of crystalline order. Our results establish the bosonic t-J-V model as a promising and experimentally accessible platform for exploring exotic quantum phases in Rydberg atom arrays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16820v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kuangjie Chen, Yang Qi, Zheng Yan, Xiaopeng Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From localized 4f electrons to anisotropic exchange interactions in ferromagnetic CeRh6Ge4</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03508</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03508v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: CeRh6Ge4 is a cerium-based ferromagnetic material exhibiting a quantum critical behavior under pressure. We derive effective exchange interactions, using the framework of density functional theory combined with dynamical mean-field theory. Our results reveal that the nearest-neighbor ferromagnetic interaction along the c axis is isotropic in spin space, leading to a formation of spin chains. On the other hand, the inter-chain coupling is highly anisotropic: The in-plane moment weakly interacts ferromagnetically in the a--b plane to stabilize the ferromagnetic state, whereas the z-component couples antiferromagnetically, contributing to its destabilization. The magnetic anisotropy of the interchain interactions as well as of the local 4f wavefunctions characterizes the magnetic properties underlying the ferromagnetic transition and the quantum critical behavior in CeRh6Ge4.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03508v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s43246-025-00998-7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Commun. Mater. 6, 269 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shoichiro Itokazu, Akimitsu Kirikoshi, Harald O. Jeschke, Junya Otsuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multifractality in high-dimensional graphs induced by correlated radial disorder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15551v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a class of models containing robust and analytically demonstrable multifractality induced by disorder correlations. Specifically, we investigate the statistics of eigenstates of disordered tight-binding models on two classes of rooted, high-dimensional graphs -- trees and hypercubes -- with a form of strong disorder correlations we term `radial disorder'. In this model, site energies on all sites equidistant from a chosen root are identical, while those at different distances are independent random variables (or their analogue for a deterministic but incommensurate potential, a case of which is also considered). Analytical arguments, supplemented by numerical results, are used to establish that this setting hosts robust and unusual multifractal states. The distribution of multifractality, as encoded in the inverse participation ratios (IPRs), is shown to be exceptionally broad. This leads to a qualitative difference in scaling with system size between the mean and typical IPRs, with the latter the appropriate quantity to characterise the multifractality. The existence of this multifractality is shown to be underpinned by an emergent fragmentation of the graphs into effective one-dimensional chains, which themselves exhibit conventional Anderson localisation. The interplay between the exponential localisation of states on these chains, and the exponential growth of the number of sites with distance from the root, is the origin of the observed multifractality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15551v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/5vqd-v4b8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review B 112, 184202 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>David E. Logan, Sthitadhi Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Mott quantum criticality in a modified periodic Anderson model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00225v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Mott quantum criticality is a central theme in correlated electron physics, observed in systems featuring both continuous zero-temperature transitions and those with finite-temperature critical endpoints. Within dynamical mean-field theory (DMFT), the paradigmatic single-band Hubbard model (SBHM) displays such criticality only above a finite-temperature endpoint. In contrast, the modified periodic Anderson model (MPAM) is a rare example known to host a surface of genuinely continuous Mott quantum critical points (QCPs) at zero temperature. Using DMFT with the numerical renormalization group as an impurity solver, we investigate the finite-temperature, real-frequency properties of the MPAM. Our central finding is the emergence of quantum critical scaling in the electrical resistivity, with critical exponents $z_{\text{met}} = 0.76$ and $z_{\text{ins}} = 0.66$ on the metallic and insulating sides, respectively. These values fall within the range reported for the SBHM, suggesting that both transitions are governed by a common universality class. We further substantiate the presence of local quantum criticality by demonstrating robust $\omega/T$ scaling in single- and two-particle correlation functions. Finally, we identify novel transport signatures in the optical conductivity, where the distinct evolution of two isosbestic points serves as a unique fingerprint of the QCP. These results establish the MPAM as a canonical model for investigating genuine Mott quantum criticality and support the existence of a universal framework for this fundamental phenomenon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00225v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sujan K. K., N. S. Vidhyadhiraja</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magneto-optical Kerr-effect measurements under pulsed magnetic fields over 40 T using a compact sample fixture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07383</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07383v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The magnetic field is one of the most fundamental control parameters in materials science. A pulsed magnetic-field apparatus can generate high magnetic fields that are inaccessible by conventional DC-field magnets. One important issue is that measurement techniques compatible with pulsed fields are rather limited due to short pulse duration and large electromagnetic or mechanical noise originating from field pulses. The magneto-optical Kerr effect (MOKE), the change in the state of light polarization upon reflection from magnetic materials, has the potential to become a powerful tool for investigation of magnetic properties of a wide range of materials including non-transparent materials or thin films in pulsed fields. Nevertheless, since the MOKE response is typically very small, MOKE measurements under pulsed fields are quite challenging. Here, we present a new method to measure polar MOKE under high pulsed magnetic fields of 2-ms pulse width. The keys of this new technique are a ferrule-based compact sample-fiber fixture and a phase-resolved numerical lock-in analysis, combined with the high-resolution optical apparatus based on an all-fiber loop-less Sagnac interferometer. We succeeded in measuring MOKE signals from various ferromagnetic or ferrimagnetic samples above 40 T and down to 77 K, significantly extending the limits of previously reported pulse-field MOKE measurements. Our apparatus is simple enough to be compatible with larger-scale experiments in pulse-field facilities, thus becoming a new promising tool to optically investigate material properties in pulsed fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07383v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Atsutoshi Ikeda, Sota Nakamura, Soichiro Yamane, Kosuke Noda, Akihiko Ikeda, Shingo Yonezawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$C_{3}$-Symmetry-induced Antisymmetric Planar Hall effect and Magnetoresistance in Single-Crystalline Ferromagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02319v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The planar Hall effect (PHE) is typically symmetric under magnetic field reversal, as required by the Onsager reciprocity relations. Recent advances have identified the antisymmetric PHE (under magnetic field reversal) as an intriguing extension in magnetic systems. While new mechanisms have been proposed, the role of conventional anisotropic magnetoresistance (AMR) in this phenomenon remains unclear. Here, we report the experimental discovery of an antisymmetric (with respect to both magnetic field and magnetization) PHE and magnetoresistance in single-crystal $Co_{30}Pt_{70}$ (111) thin films with $C_{3}$ rotational symmetry and perpendicular magnetic anisotropy (PMA). We demonstrate that both antisymmetric effects arise naturally from the intrinsic fourth-rank AMR tensor inherent to C3-symmetric planes, assisted by PMA. Our findings link conventional AMR to antisymmetric galvanomagnetic responses, offering new insights into symmetry-governed transport in crystalline ferromagnets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02319v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>W. J. Qin, B. Yang, Y. Z. Tian, B. W. Zheng, K. Y. Wang, B. Y. Huang, Y. B. Yang, W. Q. Zou, D. Wu, P. Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crystal Growth and Physical Properties of Orthorhombic Kagome Lattice Magnets $R$Fe$_6$Ge$_6$ ($R$=Y, Tb, Dy)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17398</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17398v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Kagome magnets represent a promising class of materials that exhibit intriguing electronic and magnetic properties, and they have recently garnered significant attention. While most kagome-lattice compounds are hexagonal, we report here single-crystal growth and physical property measurements of $R$Fe$_6$Ge$_6$ ($R$ = Y, Dy, Tb) compounds, which crystallize in an orthorhombic structure. The structure can be derived from a hexagonal prototype $R$Fe$_3$Ge$_2$ by replacing every other $R$ atom with a covalent Ge$_2$ dimer. Ordering of these dimers renders the structure orthorhombic, slightly distorts the kagome net, and makes the three Fe sites formally inequivalent. The iron and rare-earth sublattices order independently. Fe moments order above 400 K, forming ferromagnetic kagome planes stacked antiferromagnetically, while rare-earth moments order below 9 K. TbFe$_6$Ge$_6$ exhibits a single magnetic ordering transition associated with the Tb atoms, whereas DyFe$_6$Ge$_6$ shows two distinct magnetic phase transitions, strongly influenced by crystal electric field effects on the Dy$^{3+}$ ions. Density functional theory (DFT) calculations indicate that the ferromagnetic ordering of the Fe planes is driven by a high density of states at the Fermi energy. They also reveal three dramatically different structural energy scales: $R$ and Ge$_2$ form alternating 1D chains perpendicular to the kagome planes, and violating this alternation incurs a large energy cost. Aligning these chains is less costly, and achieving a two-dimensional order of anti-aligned chains requires very little energy. These compounds represent a unique class of materials, offering new opportunities to investigate the interplay between the distinct crystal lattice geometry and the underlying electronic and magnetic properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17398v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhijeet Nayak, Sk Jamaluddin, Fan Wu, Emily Rapp, Resham Babu Regmi, Mohamed El Gazzah, Bence G. M\'arkus, L\'aszl\'o Forr\'o, Madhav P. Ghimire, Allen Oliver, Kateryna Foyevtsova, Igor I. Mazin, Nirmal J. Ghimire</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Floquet-engineered Valley Topology with Anisotropic Response in 1T'-WSe$_2$ and Janus WSeTe monolayers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17661</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17661v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Valley topology has emerged as a key concept for realizing new classes of quantum states. Here, we investigate Floquet-engineered topological phase transitions in anisotropic 1T'-WSe$_2$ and its Janus derivative WSeTe monolayers, which exhibit valley-degenerate and valley-polarized characteristics, respectively. In 1T'-WSe$_2$, a single topological-phase-transition (TPT) occurs from the quantum-spin-Hall state (QSH) to the quantum anomalous Hall (QAH) state, involving one spin channel at both valleys simultaneously. In contrast, Janus WSeTe undergoes a two-stage Floquet-driven TPT that occurs within a single valley and sequentially involves two spin components. The intermediate phase manifests as a valley-polarized QAH (vp-QAH) state with a finite valley Chern number, while the final phase evolves into a high-Chern-number QAH state with distinct valley gaps. Furthermore, an in-plane anisotropic response of the TPTs is predicted under oblique light incidence, reflecting the intrinsic low-symmetry nature of the lattice. These findings provide a comprehensive understanding of Floquet-engineered valley-based topological properties and offer guidance for designing light-controllable valleytronic and topological devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17661v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhe Li, Haijun Cao, Lijuan Li, Huixia Fu, Mengxue Guan, Sheng Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crystal Orbital Guided Iteration to Atomic Orbitals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19725</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19725v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Atomic orbitals underpin our understanding of electronic structure, providing intuitive descriptions of bonding, charge transfer, magnetism, and correlation effects. Despite their utility, an atomic basis that is adaptable, strictly localized on atomic centers, and enables accurate tight-binding interpolation has remained elusive. Here, we introduce Crystal Orbital Guided Iteration To atomic-Orbitals (COGITO), a framework that constructs an optimal atomic orbital basis by identifying and resolving key mathematical obstacles inherent to nonorthogonal bases--particularly uncontrolled orbital mixing, and the fixed-overlap constraint between orbitals. We demonstrate that COGITO enables tight-binding models as accurate as MLWF-based approaches, while preserving the ability of tight-binding parameters to represent the projected atomic basis--an essential feature lost in schemes that enforce orbital orthogonality or maximal localization. By creating accurate and chemically interpretable models of electronic structure, COGITO reveals the orbital-resolved covalent bonds and charge transfer that is encoded in the Kohn-Sham wavefunctions of DFT. Our method thus offers a powerful tool for any physics- or chemistry-based application that relies on a faithful description of local electronic structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19725v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emily Oliphant, Emmanouil Kioupakis, Wenhao Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral Riemann Surface Topology of Gapped Non-Hermitian Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18616</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18616v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show topological configurations of the complex-valued spectra in gapped non-Hermitian systems. These arise when the distinctive EPs in the energy Riemann surfaces of such models are annihilated after threading them across the boundary of the Brillouin zone. This results in a non-trivially closed branch cut that is protected by an energy gap in the spectrum. Their presence or absence establishes topologically distinct configurations for fully non-degenerate systems and tuning between them requires a closing of the gap, forming exceptional point degeneracies. We provide an outlook toward experimental realizations in metasurfaces and single-photon interferometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18616v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton Montag, Alexander Felski, Flore K. Kunst</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reweighted Time-Evolving Block Decimation for Improved Quantum Dynamics Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08730</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08730v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a simple yet significant improvement to the time-evolving block decimation (TEBD) tensor network algorithm for simulating the time dynamics of strongly correlated one-dimensional (1D) mixed quantum states. The efficiency of 1D tensor network methods stems from using a product of matrices to express either: the coefficients of a wavefunction, yielding a matrix product state (MPS); or the expectation values of a density matrix, yielding a matrix product density operator (MPDO). To avoid exponential computational costs, TEBD truncates the matrix dimension while simulating the time evolution. However, when truncating a MPDO, TEBD does not favor the likely more important low-weight expectation values, such as $\langle c_i^\dagger c_j \rangle$, over the exponentially many high-weight expectation values, such as $\langle c_{i_1}^\dagger c^\dagger_{i_2} \cdots c_{i_n} \rangle$ of weight $n$, despite the critical importance of the low-weight expectation values. Motivated by this shortcoming, we propose a reweighted TEBD (rTEBD) algorithm that deprioritizes high-weight expectation values by a factor of $\gamma^{-n}$ during the truncation. This simple modification (which only requires reweighting certain matrices by a factor of $\gamma$ in the MPDO) makes rTEBD significantly more accurate than the TEBD time-dependent simulation of an MPDO, and competive with and sometimes better than TEBD using MPS. Furthermore, by prioritizing low-weight expectation values, rTEBD preserves conserved quantities to high precision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08730v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sayak Guha Roy, Kevin Slagle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergence of Cascading Flat Bands in Breathing Superlattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.04759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.04759v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Flat bands have become a pillar of modern condensed matter physics and photonics owing to the vanishing group velocity and diverging density of states. Here, we present a paradigmatic scheme to construct arbitrary flat bands on demand by introducing a new type breathing superlattice, where both the number and spectral positions of isolated flat bands can be continuously tailored by simply controlling the breathing strength. Microscopically, the momentum-independent interband scatterings near the band edge protect them robust against weak intra-cell disorder. By dimensional reduction, we establish a duality between the one-dimensional (1D) breathing superlattice and the 2D Harper-Hofstadter model, where cascade flat bands naturally emerge as the different orders of Landau levels in the weak magnetic flux limit. As a proof of concept, photonic flat bands at optical frequencies are experimentally demonstrated with all-dielectric photonic crystal slabs. Finally, we generalize our scheme to 2D systems to realize partial and omnidirectional flat bands, and discuss the achievement of high-quality factors. Our findings shed new light on the manipulation of flat bands with high band flatness and large usable bandwidth, paving the way for the development of advanced optical devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.04759v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/g4zp-k7s9</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Moru Song, Jingyu Hu, Lina Shi,  YongliangZhang, Kai Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complexity transitions in chaotic quantum systems: Nonstabilizerness, entanglement, and fractal dimension in SYK and random matrix models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09707</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.09707v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Complex quantum systems -- composed of many, interacting particles -- are intrinsically difficult to model. When a quantum many-body system is subject to disorder, it can undergo transitions to regimes with varying non-ergodic and localized behavior, which can significantly reduce the number of relevant basis states. It remains an open question whether such transitions are also directly related to an abrupt change in the system's complexity. In this work, we study the transition from chaotic to integrable phases in several paradigmatic models, the power-law random banded matrix model, the Rosenzweig--Porter model, and a hybrid SYK+Ising model, comparing three complementary complexity markers -- fractal dimension, von Neumann entanglement entropy, and stabilizer R\'enyi entropy. For all three markers, finite-size scaling reveals sharp transitions between high- and low-complexity regimes, which, however, can occur at different critical points. As a consequence, while in the ergodic and localized regimes the markers align, they diverge significantly in the presence of an intermediate fractal phase. Additionally, our analysis reveals that the stabilizer R\'enyi entropy is more sensitive to underlying many-body symmetries, such as fermion parity and time reversal, than the other markers. As our results show, different markers capture complementary facets of complexity, making it necessary to combine them to obtain a comprehensive diagnosis of phase transitions. The divergence between different complexity markers also has significant consequences for the classical simulability of chaotic many-body systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.09707v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gopal Chandra Santra, Alex Windey, Soumik Bandyopadhyay, Andrea Legramandi, Philipp Hauke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Chiral Edge Dynamics of a Kitaev Honeycomb on a Trapped Ion Processor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08939</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08939v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Kitaev's honeycomb model is a paradigmatic exactly solvable system hosting a quantum spin liquid with non-Abelian anyons and topologically protected edge modes, offering a platform for fault-tolerant quantum computation. However, real candidate Kitaev materials invariably include complex secondary interactions that obscure the realization of spin-liquid behavior and demand novel quantum computational approaches for efficient simulation. Here we report quantum simulations of a 22-site Kitaev honeycomb lattice on a trapped-ion quantum processor, without and with non-integrable Heisenberg interactions that are present in real materials. We develop efficient quantum circuits for ground-state preparation, achieving high accuracy with energy errors equivalent to an effective temperature of 0.2 (in units of the Kitaev interactions), consistent with the experimentally relevant spin-liquid regime. Starting from these states, we apply controlled perturbations and measure time-dependent spin correlations along the system's edge. In the non-Abelian phase, we observe chiral edge dynamics consistent with a non-zero Chern number, a hallmark of topological order, which vanishes upon transition to the Abelian toric code phase. Extending to the non-integrable Kitaev-Heisenberg model, we find that weak Heisenberg interactions preserve chiral edge dynamics, while stronger couplings suppress them, signaling the breakdown of topological protection. Our work demonstrates a viable route for probing dynamical signatures of topological order in quantum spin liquids using programmable quantum hardware, opening new pathways for quantum simulation of strongly correlated materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08939v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ammar Ali, Joe Gibbs, Keerthi Kumaran, Varadharajan Muruganandam, Bo Xiao, Paul Kairys, G\'abor Hal\'asz, Arnab Banerjee, Phillip C. Lotshaw</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tsunami Solitons Emerging from Superconducting Gap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18311</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.18311v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a classical integrable system exhibiting tsunami-like solitons with a rocky-desert-like disordered stationary background. One of the Lax operators describing this system is interpretable as a Bogoliubov--de Gennes Hamiltonian in parity-mixed superconductors. The family of integrable equations is generated from this seed operator using Krichever's method, whose pure $s$-wave limit includes the coupled Schr\"odinger--Boussinesq hierarchy applied to plasma physics. A linearly unstable finite background with a superconducting gap supports the tsunami-soliton solution, where the propagation of the step structure turns back at a certain moment, accompanied with the oscillation on the opposite side. In addition, the equation allows inhomogeneous stationary solutions with an arbitrary number of bumps at arbitrary positions, which we term \textit{the Korteweg--de Vries (KdV) rocks}. In the Zakharov--Shabat scheme, the tsunami solitons are created from the Bogoliubov quasiparticles in the energy gap and the KdV rocks from normal electrons/holes. The unexpected large space of stationary solutions originates from the non-coprime Lax pair and the multivalued Baker--Akhiezer functions on the Riemann surface, formulated in terms of higher-rank holomorphic bundles by Krichever and Novikov. Furthermore, the concept of \textit{isodispersive phases} is introduced to characterize quasiperiodic multi-tsunami backgrounds and consider their classification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.18311v4</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.7566/JPSJ.94.123001</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. 94, 123001 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Daisuke A. Takahashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability theory of flat band solitons in nonlinear wave systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05671</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05671v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We establish a sharp criterion for the stability of a class of compactly supported, homogeneous density``minimal compact solitons'' or MCS states, of the time-dependent discrete nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation on a multi-lattice, $\mathbb L$ ($\mathbb L$-DNLS). MCS states arise for multi-lattices where a nearest neighbor Laplace-type operator on $\mathbb L$ has a flat band. Our stability criterion is in terms of the explicit form of the nonlinearity and the projection of distinguished vectors onto the flat band eigenspace. We apply our general results to MCS states of DNLS for the diamond, Kagom{\'e} and checkerboard lattices. In lattices where MCS states are unstable, we demonstrate how to engineer the nonlinearity to stabilize small amplitude MCS states. Finally, via systematic numerical computations, we put our analytical results in the context of global bifurcation diagrams.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05671v2</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheng Shi, Ross Parker, Panayotis G. Kevrekides, Michael I. Weinstein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
