<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 01:30:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Geometry of Altermagnetic Magnons Probed by Light</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02781v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnons with momentum-dependent chirality are a key signature of altermagnets. We identify bicircular light as a smoking-gun optical probe for chiral altermagnetic magnons, selectively targeting their quantum geometry induced by an alteration of magnonic chirality. We show that in $d$-wave altermagnets, under a canting magnetic field, the altermagnetic magnons realize a nontrivial quantum geometry, resulting in an enhancement of the nonlinear second-order light-magnon interactions. We find that the scattering of bicircular pulses probes the present magnon quantum geometry, even if the magnonic topology is trivial. Hence, our findings establish bicircular Raman response as an optical effect of choice to identify altermagnetic magnons. As such, we propose a universal experimental protocol to distinguish altermagnets from antiferromagnets by detecting their magnon chirality patterns with light, independently of the underlying magnon topology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02781v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rundong Yuan, Wojciech J. Jankowski, Ka Shen, Robert-Jan Slager</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dichotomy of flat bands in the van der Waals ferromagnet Fe$_5$GeTe$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03029</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03029v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum materials with bands of narrow bandwidth near the Fermi level represent a promising platform for exploring a diverse range of fascinating physical phenomena, as the high density of states within the small energy window often enables the emergence of many-body physics. On one hand, flat bands can arise from strong Coulomb interactions that localize atomic orbitals. On the other hand, quantum destructive interference can quench the electronic kinetic energy. Although both have a narrow bandwidth, the two types of flat bands should exhibit very distinct spectral properties arising from their distinctive origins. So far, the two types of flat bands have only been realized in very different material settings and chemical environments, preventing a direct comparison. Here, we report the observation of the two types of flat bands within the same material system--an above-room-temperature van der Waals ferromagnet, Fe$_{5-x}$GeTe$_2$, distinguishable by a switchable iron site order. The contrasting nature of the flat bands is also identified by the remarkably distinctive temperature-evolution of the spectral features, indicating that one arises from electron correlations in the Fe(1) site-disordered phase, while the other geometrical frustration in the Fe(1) site-ordered phase. Our results therefore provide a direct juxtaposition of the distinct formation mechanism of flat bands in quantum materials, and an avenue for understanding the distinctive roles flat bands play in the presence of magnetism, topology, and lattice geometrical frustration, utilizing sublattice ordering as a key control parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03029v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Han Wu, Jianwei Huang, Chaowei Hu, Lei Chen, Yiqing Hao, Yue Shi, Paul Malinowski, Yucheng Guo, Bo Gyu Jang, Jian-Xin Zhu, Andrew F. May, Siqi Wang, Xiang Chen, Yaofeng Xie, Bin Gao, Yichen Zhang, Ziqin Yue, Zheng Ren, Makoto Hashimoto, Donghui Lu, Alexei Fedorov, Sung-Kwan Mo, Junichiro Kono, Yu He, Robert J. Birgeneau, Pengcheng Dai, Xiaodong Xu, Huibo Cao, Qimiao Si, Jiun-Haw Chu, Ming Yi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of Embedded Topology in a Trivial Bulk via Projective Crystal Symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03033v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Bulk-boundary correspondence is the foundational principle of topological physics, first established in the quantum Hall effect, where a $D$-dimensional topologically nontrivial bulk gives rise to $(D-1)$-dimensional boundary states. The advent of higher-order topology has generalized this principle to a hierarchical chain, enabling topological states to appear at $(D-2)$ or even lower-dimensional boundaries. To date, all known realizations of topological systems must require a topologically nontrivial bulk to initiate the chain of action for bulk-boundary correspondence. Here, in an acoustic crystal platform, we experimentally demonstrate an exception to this paradigm--embedded topology in a trivial bulk--where the bulk-boundary correspondence originates from a trivial bulk. Rather than relying on global symmetries, we employ projective crystal symmetry, which induces nontrivial topology not at the outset in the $D$-dimensional bulk, but midway through the correspondence hierarchy in lower-dimensional boundaries. We further realize a three-dimensional system exhibiting embedded topology that supports zero-dimensional topological states, achieving the longest possible chain of action for such an unconventional bulk-boundary correspondence in physical space. Our work experimentally establishes a new form of bulk-boundary correspondence initiated from a trivial bulk, opening additional degrees of freedom for the design of robust topological devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03033v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hau Tian Teo, Yang Long, Hong-yu Zou, Kailin Song, Haoran Xue, Yong Ge, Shou-qi Yuan, Hong-xiang Sun, Baile Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dielectric Substrate Dependence of Thermoelectric Transport in BLG-GaAs-BLG Heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03035</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03035v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We theoretically study the thermoelectric transport S in a double-layer bilayer graphene (BLG-GaAs-BLG) system on dielectric substrates (h-BN, Al2O3, HfO2). Electrons interact with GaAs acoustic phonons via both the deformation potential (acDP) and piezoelectric (acPE) scattering. Results show that piezoelectric scattering dominates the total transport, especially at low carrier density and high dielectric constant. Substrate dielectric constant significantly influences thermopower S, and the thermopower of the materials is in the order of HfO2 &gt; Al2O3 &gt; h-BN. When densities on two BLG layers are unequal, the contribution from acDP scattering Sd decreases (increases) at low (high) densities versus equal densities, while acPE scattering Sg remains stable, making S largely Sg-dependent. Increasing interlayer distance d enhances S, while higher temperature boosts Sd (notably at low densities) with minimal effect on Sg. These insights and substrate-dependent trends demonstrate substrate engineering as a key parameter for optimizing BLG thermoelectric devices</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03035v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vo Van Tai, Truong Van Tuan, Tran Trong Tai, Le Tri Dat, Nguyen Duy Vy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic ordering driven by flat band nesting in a van der Waals magnet Fe5GeTe2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03116</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03116v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Solid-state systems with flat electronic bands have a theoretical propensity to form electronic orders such as superconductivity and charge-density waves. However, for many flat-band systems such as Kagome and Clover lattices, the flat bands do not naturally appear at the Fermi level, hence not driving the low-energy electronic ordering. Here we demonstrate the concurrent formation of flat bands at the Fermi level and a $\sqrt{3} \times \sqrt{3}\, R30^\circ$ charge order in a van der Waals magnet Fe5GeTe2 using high-resolution angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy. This charge order is manifested by clear band structure folding below 100 K, yet the band folding is limited to 30 meV below the Fermi level where the flat bands reside. The nesting vector in the reciprocal space connects segments of Fermi surfaces where pronounced flat bands are discovered. Taken together with calculations of the Lindhard response function, our results establish Fe5GeTe2 as a model system where flat bands promote inter-band nesting and electronic ordering. The appearance of the flat band at the Fermi level is reminiscent of the Kondo lattice effect, yet we point out that the flat bands may originate from the abundance of vacancies in the Fe(1) sublattice, where the vacancies induce flat dispersions via destructive charge or spin interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03116v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiang Gao, Gabriele Berruto, Khanh Duy Nguyen, Chaowei Hu, Haoran Lin, Beomjoon Goh, Bo Gyu Jang, Xiaodong Xu, Peter Littlewood, Jiun-Haw Chu, Shuolong Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of Anomalous Hall Effect in Bulk Single Crystals of n-type Cr-doped Sb$_{2}$Te$_{3}$ Magnetic Topological Insulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03141v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The exploration of topological Dirac surface states is significant in the realms of condensed matter physics and future technological innovations. Among the materials garnering attention is Sb$_{2}$Te$_{3}$, a compound that theoretically exhibits topological insulating properties. However, its inherent p-type nature prevents the direct experimental verification of its Dirac surface state due to the Fermi level alignment with the valence band. In this study, by doping Cr atoms into Sb$_{2}$Te$_{3}$, n-type behavior is observed in the Hall resistance measurements. Remarkably, the Cr-doped Sb$_{2}$Te$_{3}$ not only shows ferromagnetism with a high transition temperature of approximately 170 K but also exhibits an anomalous Hall effect (AHE). The Cr doping also allows for a controlled method for Fermi level tuning into the band gap. These properties spotlight its potential as an n-type magnetic topological insulator (MTI) as well as a material candidate for the quantum anomalous Hall effect (QAHE), opening new avenues for applications in spintronics and quantum devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03141v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Sarikhani (Material Research Center, Missouri University of Science and Technology, Rolla, MO), Mathew Pollard (Department of Physics, Missouri University of Science and Technology, Rolla, MO), Jacob Cook (Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of Missouri, Columbia, MO), Sheng Qiu (Department of Physics, Missouri University of Science and Technology, Rolla, MO), Seng Huat Lee (Department of Physics, Missouri University of Science and Technology, Rolla, MO), Laleh Avazpour (Department of Physics, Missouri University of Science and Technology, Rolla, MO), Jack Crewse (Department of Physics, Missouri University of Science and Technology, Rolla, MO), William Fahrenholtz (Department of Materials Science and Engineering, Missouri University of Science and Technology, Rolla, MO), Guang Bian (Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of Missouri, Columbia, MO), Yew San Hor (Department of Physics, Missouri University of Science and Technology, Rolla, MO)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological band insulators without translational symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03208v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the research of the topological band phases, the conventional wisdom is to start from the crystalline translational symmetry systems. Nevertheless, the translational symmetry is not always a necessary condition for the energy bands. Here we propose a systematic method of constructing the topological band insulators without translational symmetry in the amorphous systems. By way of the isospectral reduction approach from spectral graph theory, we reduce the structural-disordered systems formed by different multi-atomic cells into the isospectral effective periodic systems with the energy-dependent hoppings and potentials. We identify the topological band insulating phases with extended bulk states and topological in-gap edge states by the topological invariants of the reduced systems, density of states, and the commutation of the transfer matrix. In addition, when the building blocks of the two multi-atomic cells have different number of the lattice sites, our numerical calculations demonstrate that the existences of the flat band and the macroscopic bound states in the continuum in the amorphous systems. Our findings uncover a new arena for the exploration of the topological band states beyond translational symmetry systems paradigm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03208v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuo Wang, Jing-Run Lin, Zheng-Wei Zuo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Organic altermagnets based in two-dimensional nanographene frameworks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03234</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03234v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Altermagnetism stands as a third type of collinear magnetic order, whose band structure combines a net zero magnetization with a non-relativistic spin-splitting caused by a broken time reversal symmetry. So far, the strategy to design platforms displaying altermagnetism has relied mostly on inorganic crystals with d-metals as spin centers, where a representative example is the two-dimensional square lattice with antiparallel D2h magnetic blocks related by a pi/2 rotation. Despite the fact that there is no strong requirement for the magnetic atoms to be metals, the construction of an altermagnetic framework with light elements like carbon is challenging due to symmetric constrictions. We show how it is possible to overcome this by including non-alternant rings in pi-conjugated nanographenes. More specifically, dibenzo[ef,kl]heptalene, an S = 1 pi-conjugated hydrocarbon consisting of a graph of two fused heptagons and hexagons, represents a suitable building block for an altermagnetic 2D crystal. In this work, we confirm this hypothesis with DFT calculations of the spin polarized band structure, presenting a spin compensated ground state with broken time reversal symmetry, and a d-wave symmetry of the first valence and conduction bands. Consistent results are obtained for covalent organic frameworks based on dibenzo[ef,kl]heptalene units connected by linkers, paving the way for the realization of organic altermagnetic materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03234v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ricardo Ortiz, Karol Struty\'nski, Manuel Melle-Franco</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microscopic Theory of Light-Induced Coherent Phonons Mediated by Quantum Geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03257v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Light-induced coherent phonons provide a powerful platform for ultrafast control of material properties. However, the microscopic theory and quantum geometric nature of this phenomenon remain underexplored. Here, we develop a fully quantum-mechanical framework based on Feynman diagrams to systematically describe the generation of coherent phonons by light. We identify a dominant second-order, double-resonant process in noncentrosymmetric semiconductors that efficiently couples light to both electronic and phononic excitations. Crucially, we uncover the quantum geometric origin, encoded in the electron-phonon coupling (EPC) shift vector and the EPC quantum geometric tensor. Applying our theory to ferroelectric BaTiO$_3$ and SnSe, we demonstrate the potential for light-induced modulation of ferroelectric polarization driven by coherent phonons. This work provides fundamental insights for designing efficient optical control strategies for both coherent phonons and ferroelectric polarization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03257v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaming Hu, Zhichao Guo, Wenbin Li, Hua Wang, Kai Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Berry Curvature of Low-Energy Excitons in Rhombohedral Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03290v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate low energy excitons in rhombohedral pentalayer graphene encapsulated by hexagonal boron nitride (hBN/R5G/hBN), focusing on the regime at the experimental twist angle $\theta = 0.77^\circ$ and with an applied electric field. We introduce a new low-energy two-band model of rhombohedral graphene that captures the band structure more accurately than previous models while keeping the number of parameters low. Using this model, we show that the centres of the exciton Wannier functions are displaced from the moir\'e unit cell origin by a quantised amount -- they are instead localised at $C_3$-symmetric points on the boundary. We also find that the exciton shift is electrically tunable: by varying the electric field strength, the exciton Wannier centre can be exchanged between inequivalent corners of the moir\'e unit cell. Our results suggest the possibility of detecting excitonic corner or edge modes, as well as novel excitonic crystal defect responses in hBN/R5G/hBN. Lastly, we find that the excitons in hBN/R5G/hBN inherit excitonic Berry curvature from the underlying electronic bands, enriching their semiclassical transport properties. Our results position rhombohedral graphene as a compelling tunable platform for probing exciton topology in moir\'e materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03290v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henry Davenport, Frank Schindler, Johannes Knolle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic systems with Bose-Hubbard interactions: Effects of bias on particles on a 1D lattice and random comb</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03344</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03344v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Driven non-equilibrium lattice models have wide-ranging applications in contexts such as mass transport, traffic flow, and transport in biological systems. In this work, we investigate the steady-state properties of a one-dimensional lattice system that allows multiple particle occupancy on each site. The particles undergo stochastic nearest-neighbor jumps influenced by both a directional bias and on-site repulsive interactions. With periodic boundary conditions, we observe a non-monotonic dependence of inter-site correlation functions on the interaction strength. At large interaction strengths, the particle current exhibits a periodic dependence on density, accompanied by the formation of ordered stacks of particles. In contrast, with open boundary conditions, the system displays step-like density profiles reminiscent of those in tilted Bose-Hubbard systems, and a regime with a macroscopic number of empty sites followed by a steep parameter-dependent increase in density. Our results highlight how the interplay between drive, interaction, and boundary conditions leads to distinctive signatures on the current and density profiles in the steady state in different regimes.} {We also study the problem on a random comb, a simple model of a disordered system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03344v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Swastik Majumder, Mustansir Barma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Wye-Delta to Cross-Square Recursion Configurations in Graphene-Based Quantum Hall Arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03347</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03347v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In electrical metrology, the quantum Hall effect is accessed at the Landau level filling factor {\nu} = 2 plateau to define and disseminate the unit of electrical resistance (ohm). The robustness of the plateau is only exhibited at this Landau level filling factor and thus places a constraint on the quantized resistances that are accessible when constructing quantized Hall array resistance standards (QHARS) using epitaxial graphene on SiC. To overcome devices constrained by using Hall elements in series or in parallel, this work approaches the fabrication of a cross-square network configuration, which is similar to but departs slightly from conventional wye-delta designs and achieves significantly higher effective quantized resistance outputs. Furthermore, the use of pseudofractal-like recursion amplifies the ability to reach high resistances. QHARS devices designed as the ones here are shown to achieve an effective resistance of 55.81 M$\Omega$ in one configuration and 27.61 G$\Omega$ in another, with a hypothetically projected 317.95 T$\Omega$ that could be accessed with more specialized equipment. Teraohmmeter measurements reveal the limits of conventional wet cryogenic systems due to resistance leakage. Ultimately, this work builds on the capability of realizing exceptionally high-value quantum resistance standards.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03347v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ngoc Thanh Mai Tran, Marta Musso, Dominick S. Scaletta, Wei-Chen Lin, Valery Ortiz Jimenez, Dean G. Jarrett, Massimo Ortolano, Curt A. Richter, Chi-Te Liang, David B. Newell, Albert F. Rigosi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Engineering subgap states in superconductors by altermagnetism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03364</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03364v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the realization and control of subgap states by tailored altermagnetic fields on unconventional superconductors. When the symmetries of altermagnetism and unconventional superconductivity align, we demonstrate the emergence of bulk zero-energy flat bands, giving rise to a zero-bias conductance peak. The symmetry and strength of $d$- and $g$-wave altermagnets strongly affect the surface Andreev states from $d$-wave and chiral $d$- and $p$-wave superconductors. As a result, distinct types of subgap states are realized, including curved and flat bands, that can be detected by tunneling spectroscopy. Furthermore, we find that the altermagnetism-induced subgap states give rise to a large spin conductance at zero net magnetization which helps identify the strength of the underlying altermagnetism and superconductivity. Our results offer a solid route for designing and manipulating subgap states in superconducting systems, which can be useful for functionalizing superconducting spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03364v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bo Lu, Phillip Mercebach, Pablo Burset, Keiji Yada, Jorge Cayao, Yukio Tanaka, Yuri Fukaya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interstitial oxygen order and its competition with superconductivity in La$_2$PrNi$_2$O$_{7+\delta}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03414v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High-temperature superconductivity in bilayer nickelate La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ under pressure has attracted significant interest in condensed matter physics. While early samples exhibited limited superconducting volume fractions, Pr substitution for La enabled bulk superconductivity in polycrystals under pressure and enhanced transition temperatures in thin films at ambient pressure. Beyond rare-earth doping, moderate oxygen or ozone annealing improves superconductivity by mitigating oxygen vacancies, whereas high-pressure oxygen annealing leads to a trivial, non-superconducting metallic state across all pressure regimes. These findings highlight the need to elucidate both the individual and combined effects of Pr doping and oxygen stoichiometry in modulating superconductivity in bilayer nickelates. Here, using multislice electron ptychography and electron energy-loss spectroscopy, we investigate the structural and electronic properties of as-grown La$_2$PrNi$_2$O$_7$ and high-pressure-oxygen-annealed La$_2$PrNi$_2$O$_{7+\delta}$ polycrystals. We find that Pr dopants preferentially occupy outer La sites, effectively eliminating inner-apical oxygen vacancies and ensuring near-stoichiometry in as-grown La$_2$PrNi$_2$O$_7$ that is bulk-superconducting under pressure. In contrast, high-pressure oxygen annealing induces a striped interstitial oxygen order, introducing quasi-1D lattice potentials and excess hole carriers into p-d hybridized orbitals, ultimately suppressing superconductivity. This behavior starkly contrasts with cuprate superconductors, where similar interstitial oxygen ordering enhances superconductivity instead. Our findings reveal a competition between striped interstitial oxygen order and superconductivity in bilayer nickelates, offering key insights into their distinct pairing mechanisms and providing a roadmap for designing more robust superconducting phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03414v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zehao Dong, Gang Wang, Ningning Wang, Wen-Han Dong, Lin Gu, Yong Xu, Jinguang Cheng, Zhen Chen, Yayu Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry-breaking-induced topology in FeSe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03427</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03427v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: FeSe has been one of the most intensively studied iron-based superconductors over the past two decades, exhibiting a wide range of phenomena such as unconventional superconductivity, nematic order, magnetism, orbital-selective correlations, and structural phase transitions. While topologically non-trivial phases have been identified in certain cases - such as Te-doped FeSe and monolayer FeSe - topology in bulk FeSe has largely remained unexplored. In this work, we propose a new route to realize topological phases directly in bulk FeSe. We demonstrate that breaking the in-plane $C_4$ rotational symmetry, thereby lowering the crystal symmetry, can drive FeSe into a strong topological insulating phase. To support this, we perform density functional theory calculations and analyze the band structure using topological quantum chemistry and symmetry-based indicators. Our results show that both uniaxial strain and the structural transition to the orthorhombic low-temperature phase lead to non-trivial band topology. Moreover, incorporating electronic correlations through dynamical mean field theory reveals that the topological characteristics near the Fermi level remain robust, as the relevant bands experience only moderate renormalization. These findings highlight strain as a promising mechanism to induce topological phases in FeSe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03427v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikel Garc\'ia-D\'iez, Jonas B. Profe, Augustin Davignon, Steffen Backes, Roser Valent\'i, Maia G. Vergniory</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chirality transfer in lyotropic twist-bend nematics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03544</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03544v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using molecular simulations and classical density functional theory, we study the liquid-crystalline phase behaviour of a series of bent rod-like mesogens with a controlled degree of chirality introduced through a twist at the centre of the particle. In the achiral limit, isotropic, uniaxial nematic, twist-bend nematic and smectic phases form as the packing fraction increases. On introducing chirality, the symmetry between the right- and left-handed twist-bend phases is broken. The phase with the same-handedness as the particles quickly becomes overwhelmingly favoured as the magnitude of the particle twist is increased, because the particles are then able to better follow the helical director field lines in the twist-bend phase and pack more efficiently. By contrast, the cholesteric phase is predicted to have the opposite handedness to that of the particle due to the relatively weakly-twisted nature of the particles. That the cholesteric and twist-bend phases have opposite handedness illustrates the differences in the mechanisms of chirality transfer in the two phases. We also found that doping a system of achiral mesogens with a small fraction of chiral particles led to selection of the twist-bend phase with the same chirality as the particle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03544v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna Ashkinazi, Hemani Chhabra, Anouar El Moumane, Maxime M. C. Tortora, Jonathan P. K. Doye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement-Induced Entanglement in Conformal Field Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02788</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02788v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Local measurements can radically reshape patterns of many-body entanglement, especially in long-range entangled quantum-critical states. Yet, analytical results addressing the effects of measurements on many-body states remain scarce, and measurements are often approximated as forcing specific measurement outcomes. We study measurement-induced entanglement (MIE) in Tomonaga-Luttinger liquids, a broad family of 1+1d quantum critical states described at low energies by compact free boson conformal field theories (CFT). Measuring the local charge operator, we show that the MIE is entirely universal, conformally invariant, and depends on the operator content of the CFT. Using a replica-trick to address the randomness of the measurement outcomes, we compute the MIE exactly for Tomonaga-Luttinger liquids, in very good agreement with matrix-product state calculations. We show that the MIE for physical quantum measurements is fundamentally different from the entanglement induced by forcing measurement outcomes, and has a natural interpretation in terms of Born averaging over conformally-invariant boundary conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02788v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kabir Khanna, Romain Vasseur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong electron-electron interactions in a dilute weakly-localized metal near a metal-to-insulator transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02793</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02793v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Because it is easily switched from insulator to metal either via chemical doping or electrical gating, silicon is at the core of modern information technology and remains a candidate platform for quantum computing. The metal-to-insulator transition in this material has therefore been one of the most studied phenomena in condensed matter physics, and has been revisited with considerable profit each time a new fabrication technology has been introduced. Here we take advantage of recent advances in creating ultra-thin layers of Bohr-atom-like dopants to realize the two-dimensional disordered Hubbard model at half-filling and its metal-to-insulator transition (MIT) as a function of mean distance between atoms. We use gas-phase dosing of dopant precursor molecules on silicon to create arsenic and phosphorus $\delta$-layers as thin as 0.4~nm and as dilute as 10$^{13}$~cm$^{-2}$. On approaching the insulating state, the conventional weak localization effects, prevalent at high dopant densities and due to orbital motion of the electrons in the plane, become dominated by electron-electron interaction contributions which obey a paramagnetic Zeeman scaling law. The latter make a negative contribution to the conductance, and thus cannot be interpreted in terms of an emergent Kondo regime near the MIT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02793v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicol\`o D'Anna, Jamie Bragg, Aidan G. McConnell, Procopios C. Constantinou, Juerong Li, Taylor J. Z. Stock, Steven R. Schofield, Neil J. Curson, Y. Soh, Marek Bartkowiak, Simon Gerber, Markus M\"uller, Guy Matmon, Gabriel Aeppli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological invariants and topological charges in photonic systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03302</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03302v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Topology in photonics comes in two distinct flavors: global and local. Global topology considers invariants that are obtained by integrating over the energy band, whereas local topology considers defects, typically vortices, in the far-field emission. These topologies are described by a wide range of models built in both real and momentum space, which are connected only by computationally expensive numerical methods that lack physical intuition. Here we propose a general framework based on a real-space Hamiltonian capable of describing electric field as a vector in both near- and far fields, allowing us to bridge between topological defects in the far-field and global topological invariants. The proposed Hamiltonian is constructed from the symmetry-representations of the lattice, is deformable to both atomic localized-mode (tight-binding) and photonic delocalized-mode (long-range) limits, and allows for independent control over the energies of eigenmodes of different symmetries at high-symmetry points of the Brillouin zone. This symmetry-based approach enables the design of structures with almost arbitrary topological properties and is not limited to photonic systems, but could apply to any system with engineered real-space couplings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03302v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kristian Arjas, Grazia Salerno, P\"aivi T\"orm\"a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>All Photonic Isolator using Atomically Thin (2D) Bismuth Telluride (Bi2Te3)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03319v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study demonstrates that two-dimensional (2D) Bi2Te3 exhibits strong light-matter interaction, enabling a broadband Kerr nonlinear optical response. This characteristic is advantageous for nonreciprocal light propagation in passive photonic isolators. Using Spatial Self-Phase Modulation (SSPM) spectroscopy, self-induced diffraction patterns in the far field were observed at excitation wavelengths of 650 nm, 532 nm, and 405 nm to calculate the nonlinear refractive index (n2) and the third-order nonlinear optical susceptibility (chi^(3)) of the synthesized 2D Bi2Te3.
  The results show that 2D Bi2Te3 possesses a significantly higher nonlinear refractive index than graphene. The laser-induced hole coherence effect is responsible for the large magnitude of the third-order nonlinear susceptibility. Surface engineering techniques were also employed to enhance the response speed of the photonic system.
  Complementary ab initio simulations were performed to gain further insight into the observed nonlinear behavior. Leveraging the strong Kerr nonlinearity of 2D Bi2Te3, a nonlinear photonic isolator that breaks time-reversal symmetry and enables unidirectional light propagation was demonstrated. This work establishes Bi2Te3 as a novel 2D material for nonlinear photonics, expanding its potential applications in detectors, modulators, and optical switches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03319v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saswata Goswami, Bruno Ipaves, Juan Gomez Quispe, Caique Campos de Oliveira, Surbhi Slathia, Abhijith M. B, Varinder Pal, Christiano J. S. de Matos, Samit K. Ray, Douglas S. Galvao, Pedro A. S. Autreto, Chandra Sekhar Tiwary</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin transport revealed by the spin quantum geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02257v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the framework of \textit{spin quantum geometry}, which is fundamentally linked to the spin degree of freedom of Bloch electrons and incorporates both the spin quantum geometric tensor (QGT) and the recently introduced Zeeman QGT, to elucidate the spin transport. We show that the spin and Zeeman QGTs, respectively, provide a unified framework for revealing known spin currents, such as the intrinsic spin Hall effect, and spin magnetization, such as the Edelstein effect, of Bloch electrons under an electric field. In addition, we predict the linear displacement spin Hall effect, wherein an AC electric field induces a transverse spin current in insulating systems. Furthermore, we propose two novel nonlinear spin responses: the nonlinear Drude spin current (NDSC) and the nonlinear Drude spin magnetization (NDSM), both of which exhibit a quadratic dependence on the relaxation time, like the nonlinear Drude charge current, and are governed by the \textit{spin quantum geometry}. Finally, we evaluate the NDSC and NDSM with Dirac models of topological insulators and find that, in the moderately dirty regime, the NDSC and NDSM can exceed their respective nonlinear intrinsic counterparts, which have recently garnered significant interest in spintronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02257v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Longjun Xiang, Hao Jin, Jian Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Chiral Superconductivity Mediated by Intervalley Antiferromagnetic Fluctuations in Twisted Bilayer WSe$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.16114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.16114v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Motivated by the recent observations of superconductivity in twisted bilayer WSe$_2$ (tWSe$_2$), we theoretically investigate the superconductivity driven by electronic mechanism. We first demonstrate that the multi-band screened Coulomb interaction within the random phase approximation is insufficient to induce observable pairing instability. Nevertheless, by further including the intervalley antiferromagnetic fluctuations, the pairing interaction is substantially enhanced, yielding superconductivity with critical temperature $T_c$ of hundreds of millikelvin at van Hove singularities. The predicted $T_c$ increases with increasing the displacement field and corresponds to a doubly-degenerate $d$-wave-like pairing, which evolves into topological chiral $d \pm id$ superconductor below $T_c$. The interplay between superconductivity and intervalley antiferromagnetism results in a phase diagram consistent with experimental observations.These findings establish intervalley fluctuations as the primary pairing glue in tWSe$_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.16114v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Qin, Wen-Xuan Qiu, Fengcheng Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay between altermagnetism and topological superconductivity on an unconventional superconducting platform</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05451</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05451v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a theoretical model to investigate the interplay between altermagnetism and $p$-wave superconductivity, with a particular focus on topological phase transitions in a two-dimensional (2D) $p$-wave superconductor, considering both chiral and helical phases. Our study reveals that the emergence of helical and chiral Majorana states can be tuned by the amplitude of a $d-$wave altermagnetic order parameter, with the outcome depending on the nature of the superconducting state. In the helical superconductor, such an altermagnet can induce a topological phase transition into a gapless topological superconductor hosting Majorana flat edge modes. On the other hand, in the chiral superconductor, the topological transition takes place between a topologically nontrivial gapped phase and a gapless nodal-line superconductor, where the Bogoliubov quasiparticle bands intersect at an isolated line in momentum space. Remarkably, we show that when such an altermagnet is coupled to a mixed-pairing superconductor, with both chiral and helical components, a hybrid topological phase emerges, featuring dispersive Majorana edge modes that coexist with nearly flat Majorana edge states. Our findings therefore establish a novel platform for controlling and manipulating Majorana modes in unconventional superconductors with vanishing total magnetization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05451v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/4318-ttvf</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 054503 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pritam Chatterjee, Vladimir Juri\v{c}i\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological magnons and domain walls in twisted bilayer MoTe$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11010v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We theoretically investigate the magnetic excitations in the quantum anomalous Hall insulator phase of twisted bilayer MoTe$_2$ at a hole filling factor of $\nu=1$, focusing on magnon and domain wall excitations. Using a generalized interacting Kane-Mele model, we obtain the quantum anomalous Hall insualtor ground state with spin polarization. The magnon spectrum is then computed via the Bethe-Salpeter equation, revealing two low-energy topological magnon bands with opposite Chern numbers. To further explore the magnon topology, we construct a tight-binding model for the magnon bands, which is analogous to the Haldane model. We also calculate the energy cost of domain walls that separate regions with opposite Chern numbers and bind chiral edge states. Finally, we propose an effective spin model that describes both magnon and domain wall excitations, incorporating Heisenberg spin interactions and Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interactions. The coupling constants in this model are determined from the numerical results for magnons and domain walls. This model accounts for the Ising anisotropy of the system, captures the magnon topology, and allows for the estimation of the magnetic ordering temperature. Our findings provide a comprehensive analysis of magnetic excitations in twisted MoTe$_2$ and offer new insights into collective excitations in moir\'e systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11010v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/sl5k-c825</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Xuan Qiu, Fengcheng Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fully ergodic simulations using radial updates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01575</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.01575v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A sensible application of the Hybrid Monte Carlo (HMC) method is often hindered by the presence of large - or even infinite - potential barriers. These potential barriers separate the configuration space into distinct sectors and can lead to ergodicity violations that bias measurements. In this work, we address this problem by augmenting HMC with a multiplicative Metropolis-Hastings update in a so-called ''radial direction'' of the fields which enables crossing the potential barriers and ensures ergodicity of the sampling algorithm at comparably low computational cost. We demonstrate the algorithm on a simple toy model and show how it can be applied to the fermionic Hubbard model describing physics ranging from an exactly-solvable two-site system to the $C_{20}H_{12}$ perylene molecule. Our numerical results show that the radial updates successfully remove ergodicity violations, while simultaneously reducing autocorrelation times.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.01575v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/9zst-bvmk</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 045134 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Finn L. Temmen, Evan Berkowitz, Anthony Kennedy, Thomas Luu, Johann Ostmeyer, Xinhao Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Room-Temperature Pauli Spin Blockade and Current Rectification in 15-13-15 Armchair Graphene Nanoribbon Heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01662</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01662v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this study, we investigate the electronic structures of 13-11-13 and 15-13-15 armchair graphene nanoribbon (AGNR) superlattices (SLs) using a tight-binding model. We demonstrate that the conduction and valence subbands of 15-13-15 AGNR SLs can be accurately described by the Su-Schrieffer-Heeger model, with topologically protected interface states emerging at the junctions between 15-AGNR and 13-AGNR segments. These interface states enable the formation of quantum dot arrays with energy levels well separated from bulk states, making them promising candidates for high-temperature solid-state quantum processors. For 15-13-15 AGNRH segments, we observe both localized zigzag edge states and topologically protected interface states under longitudinal electric fields, with the latter providing efficient tunneling channels in contrast to the less conductive edge states. We further explore nonlinear charge transport through these interface states under Pauli spin blockade, showing that tunneling current spectra reveal charge stability diagrams and Coulomb blockade oscillations, consistent with experimental findings in other serial double quantum dot systems. Additionally, we examine the impact of orbital offsets on tunneling current rectification and demonstrate that significant current rectification is achieved over a wide temperature range when level broadening is optimized. These results highlight the potential of 15-13-15 AGNRHs for robust spin-current conversion and applications in quantum devices, offering advantages over other proposed structures due to precise tunability of key parameters via bottom-up synthesis techniques and the ease of two-gate electrode integration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01662v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David M T Kuo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Moir\'e Systems: a review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05620</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05620v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This review synthesizes recent advancements in the study of moir\'e magnetism. This emerging field, at the intersection of twistronics, topology, and strongly correlated systems, explores novel phenomena that arise when moir\'e potentials influence the magnetism of two-dimensional systems. The manuscript presents recent advances highlighting the interfacial incongruity as a novel mechanism for regulating the magnetism of two-dimensional materials and for the manifestation of various phenomena in twisted and mismatched magnetic two-dimensional interfaces. The manuscript addresses seminal and recent experimental and theoretical advances associated with both small- and large-period magnetic moir\'e lattices, including novel magnetic phases, low-energy and topological magnetic excitations, magnetic and electronic transport, optical properties, phase transitions, and prospective applications of these materials. Moir\'e magnetism signifies a promising frontier for manipulating complex quantum states in quantum matter. The ongoing advances in this field are poised to impact condensed matter physics, materials science, and quantum information science.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05620v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-648X/adf483</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys.: Condens. Matter 37 323001 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Paula Mellado</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic and ferroelectric phase diagram of twisted CrI$_3$ layers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12324</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.12324v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Twisting layers provide a rich ore for exotic physics in low dimensions. Despite the abundant discoveries of twistronics from the aspect of electronic structures, ferroic moir\'e textures are more plain and thus less concerned. Rigid lattice models are straightforward which can give a rough but intuitional description in most cases. However, taking CrI$_3$ as a model system, here we will demonstrate that the interlayer stacking potential can spontaneously lead to structural relaxation, which plays a vital role to understand the ferroicity in the twisted superlattices. The magnetic ground state is sensitive to the stacking mode and twisting angles, which can be seriously affected by the structural relaxation. In particular, the expected magnetic bubbles are annihilated in its bilayer. In contrast, due to topological protection, the ferroelectric vortices are more robust to structural relaxation, as well as twisting angle and thickness.Due to the universal existence of spontaneous structural relaxation in twisted superlattices, our work may lead to a general revisitation of emerging physics of twistronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.12324v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/bwwv-f247</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review Letters 135, 066701 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Haoshen Ye, Shuai Dong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous charge density wave in altermagnetism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15429v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Exploring the intricate interplay between magnetism and charge density waves has long been a fundamental pursuit at the forefront of condensed matter research. In this letter, based on symmetry analysis and first-principles calculations, we propose for the first time that anomalous charge density wave can be realized in two-dimensional altermagnetic WO. The anomalous charge density wave is characterized by three key features: (i) Unlike conventional charge density wave, whose stabilization is driven by the opening of a gap near the Fermi level, the anomalous charge density wave is stabilized by the occupied states with energies shifting lower far away from the Fermi level; (ii) the anomalous charge density wave increases the density of states near the Fermi level and then enhances-rather than diminishes-the metallicity of materials; (iii) altermagnetism plays a crucial role in stabilizing anomalous charge density wave. Thus, our work offers a pathway for exploring both the realization and the underlying mechanisms of anomalous charge density waves in magnetic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15429v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zi-Hao Ding, Lei Wang, Zhen-Feng Ouyang, Jingsi Qiao, Ze-Feng Gao, Wei Ji, Kai Liu, Peng-Jie Guo, Zhong-Yi Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Light-induced Odd-parity Magnetism in Conventional Collinear Antiferromagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.20705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.20705v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent studies have drawn growing attention on non-relativistic odd-parity magnetism in the wake of altermagnets. Nevertheless, odd-parity spin splitting is often believed to appear in non-collinear magnetic configurations. Here, using symmetry arguments and effective model analysis, we show that Floquet engineering offers a universal strategy for achieving odd-parity magnetism in two-dimensional (2D) collinear antiferromagnets under irradiation of periodic driving light fields such as circularly polarized light, elliptically polarized light, and bicircular light. A comprehensive classification of potential candidates for collinear monolayer or bilayer antiferromagnets is established. Strikingly, the light-induced odd-parity spin splitting can be flexibly controlled by adjusting the crystalline symmetry or the polarization state of incident light, enabling the reversal or conversion of spin-splitting. By combining first-principles calculations and Floquet theorem, we present illustrative examples of 2D collinear antiferromagnetic (AFM) materials to verify the light-induced odd-parity magnetism. Our work not only offers a powerful approach for uniquely achieving odd-parity spin-splitting with high tunability, but also expands the potential of Floquet engineering in designing unconventional compensated magnetism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.20705v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shengpu Huang, Zheng Qin, Fangyang Zhan, Dong-Hui Xu, Da-Shuai Ma, Rui Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
