<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 04:00:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Excitonic correlations in the system of gated metallic wires with the applied Zeeman magnetic field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19880</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19880v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We have studied the electron-electron interactions in the system composed of two metallic wires, placed in the external magnetic and electric fields. The interactions between the electrons in the wires have been taken into account within the usual Hubbard model. We have considered both half-filling and partial-filling limits for the occupation of the atomic lattice sites. We show the existence of the excitonic pairing in this low-dimensional system and calculate the excitonic order parameter in different electron-electron interaction regime, magnetic field and temperature. We demonstrate that the usual Hubbard-$U$ interaction leads to strong electron localization which enhance the local antiferromagnetic order in the system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19880v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0202826</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Appl. Phys., 135, 224302 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>V. Apinyan, T. Kope\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Canted antiferromagnetism and excitonic order in gated double-layer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19881</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19881v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the effects of the electron-electron interactions on the excitonic properties and charge-density modulations in the AB stacked double-layer (DL) graphene, placed in the external gate-potential $V$. The coexistence of the canted antiferromagnetic order and excitonic pairing gap has been studied with the help of the generalized Hubbard model. We calculate the chemical potential $\mu$, the average charge density difference between the layers $\delta{\bar{n}}$, the antiferromagnetic gap-function $\Delta_{\rm AFM}$ and the excitonic order parameters $\Delta_{\sigma}$ in the zero temperature limit. We found that the excitonic pairing order parameter has a larger energy scale than the canted antiferromagnetic gap-function. The charge neutrality, in the DL graphene system, occurs only in the absence of the external gate-potential $V$. Moreover, we have shown that the values of the antiferromagnetic gap-function $\Delta_{\rm AFM}$ and excitonic order parameter $\Delta_{\sigma}$ are always increasing at the large values of inter-layer Coulomb interaction, while they are decreasing for large values of the applied gate-potential $V$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19881v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.108.075147</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B, 108, 075147 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>V. Apinyan, T. K. Kope\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Hall to Chiral Spin Liquid transition in a Triangular Lattice Hofstadter-Hubbard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19907v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the weak interaction integer quantum Hall (IQH) phase, the intermediate interaction phase identified as a chiral spin liquid (CSL) and the transition between them in the triangular lattice Hofstadter-Hubbard model at a density of one electron per site in an orbital magnetic field corresponding to one-quarter flux per plaquette. Our primary tool is the finite system density matrix renormalization group (DMRG) method with both interaction-strength scan and fixed interaction techniques for cylinders of circumference 3, 5, and 7 and lengths up to 240. For the IQH phase, we use single particle exact diagonalization to clarify finite size effects, including an excess charge on the edges of our cylinders, and the limitations of entanglement spectra degeneracies on small circumference cylinders. For both phases, we use DMRG to study the entanglement spectra, the entanglement entropy, and the effect of flux insertion on charge and spin pumping, all of which show key differences between the two phases. To study the transition, we use interaction-strength scans extending between the two phases, and apply a scaling data collapse of a bond-dimerization order parameter to extract critical exponents. We also extract critical behavior from the divergence of correlation lengths on the IQH side, measuring decay away from edges of both the dimerization order parameter and transverse edge currents. The critical behavior and exponents are consistent with an Ising transition in 1+1 dimensions. Finally, we obtain excited states in various quantum number sectors finding that the gap to a charge neutral momentum $\pi$ excitation corresponding to fluctuations of the dimerization order parameter closes in the vicinity of the critical point but gaps to other excitations remain large.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19907v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cesar A. Gallegos, Rafael M. Magaldi, Andrew Millis, Steven R. White</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dimensionality-Changing Transition from a Non-Fermi Liquid to a Spin-Solid in a Multichannel Kondo Lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19937</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19937v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A multichannel Kondo system, where a single quantum spin couples to multiple channels of an electronic bath, provides one of the simplest examples of a zero-dimensional non-Fermi liquid. It is natural to ask: what happens when an extensive number of such systems are coupled together? A simple renormalization group argument implies that in a chain of SU(N) multichannel quantum systems, where each spin is coupled to its own bath of K channels, the individual spins dynamically decouple at low energy when N&gt;K, resulting in a 'sliding' non-Fermi liquid. Using Quantum Monte Carlo (QMC) simulations, we find evidences of a continuous, 'dimensionality-changing' phase transition out of this non-Fermi liquid into a valence-bond solid phase as the intersite coupling is increased. Remarkably, at the critical point, correlations exhibit a power-law behavior even along the direction in which the spins are coupled, indicating the breakdown of dynamical decoupling at the transition. We also develop an RG scheme to understand the universal aspects of this transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19937v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon Martin, Marcin Raczkowski, Fakher F. Assaad, Tarun Grover</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum geometry and impurity sensitivity of superconductors without time-reversal symmetry: application to rhombohedral graphene and altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19943</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19943v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Analyzing the consequences of the quantum geometry induced by the momentum dependence of Bloch states has emerged as a very rich and active field in condensed matter physics. For instance, for the superfluid stiffness or the pairing mechanism, these geometric aspects can play an important role. We here demonstrate that quantum geometry can also be essential for the disorder sensitivity of a superconductor, in particular when time-reversal symmetry is broken in the normal-state Bloch Hamiltonian. We derive a general expression for the behavior of the critical temperature $T_c$ involving weighted (anti-)commutators of the superconducting order parameter and impurity matrix elements, which includes both wave-function effects and kinetic pair breaking due to broken time-reversal symmetry in the dispersion. We analyze how the former effects lead to "quantum geometric pair breaking", where any superconductor becomes susceptible to microscopically non-magnetic impurities, and formally relate it to the maximum possible localization of two-particle Wannier states. Further, in the presence of kinetic pair breaking, impurities can also enhance pairing, leading to an overall more complex, non-monotonic behavior of $T_c$ with impurity concentration. We also analyze the fate of finite-momentum pairing. Our results are directly relevant to rhombohedral graphene, twisted MoTe$_2$, and superconducting altermagnets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19943v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Denis Sedov, Mathias S. Scheurer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Domain wall induced topological Hall effect in the chiral-lattice ferromagnet Fe$_x$TaS$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20181</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20181v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic topology and its associated emergent phenomena are central to realizing intriguing quantum states and spintronics functionalities. Designing spin textures to achieve strong and distinct electrical responses remains a significant challenge. Layered transition metal dichalcogenides offer a versatile platform for tailoring structural and magnetic properties, enabling access to a wide spectrum of topological magnetic states. Here, we report a domain-wall-driven, large, and tunable topological Hall effect (THE) in a non-centrosymmetric intercalated transition metal dichalcogenides series Fe$_x$TaS$_2$. By systematically varying the Fe intercalation level, we exert precise control over the magnetic ground states, allowing manipulation of the topological Hall effect. Real-space magnetic force microscopy (MFM) provides direct evidence of periodic magnetic stripe domain formation, confirming the microscopic origin of the observed topological transport phenomena. Our findings establish a promising way for tuning the topology of domains to generate substantial electromagnetic responses in layered magnetic materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20181v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sk Jamaluddin, Warit Nisaiyok, Yu Zhang, Hari Bhandari, Brian A. Francisco, Peter E. Siegfried, Fehmi Sami Yasin, Tianyi Wang, Abhijeet Nayak, Mohamed El Gazzah, Resham Babu Regmi, June Ho Yeo, Liuyan Zhao, J. F. Mitchell, Yong-Tao Cui, Nirmal J. Ghimire</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kondo breakdown induced by the non-Hermitian complex hybridization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20186v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently, a non-Hermitian Anderson impurity model with one-body loss has been studied in [Phys. Rev. B 111, 125157 (2025)}], and it has been demonstrated that the renormalization effect generated by strong correlations counterintuitively changes the nature of dissipation into an emergent many-body dissipation that causes a Kondo breakdown. In a closely related context, it is also known that two-body loss in a non-Hermitian Kondo model triggers the Kondo breakdown. To elucidate the essence of these phenomena, we study the Anderson impurity model with a non-Hermitian complex hybridization as an effective model that provides a simple understanding of the Kondo breakdown. Using the slave-boson mean-field theory, we show that this model can explain the Kondo breakdown with a single complex parameter. Furthermore, we provide the exact Bethe ansatz solutions that support the results obtained by the slave-boson mean-field theory. Finally, we point out that the Lehmann representation for the non-Hermitian Green function cannot be obtained by the analytic continuation to the complex energy upon the Kondo breakdown, where the analyticity of the non-Hermitian Green function in the half-complex-$\omega$ plane no longer holds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20186v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazuki Yamamoto, Masaya Nakagawa, Norio Kawakami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Soft Phonon Charge-Density Wave Formation in the Kagome Metal KV$_3$Sb$_5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20230v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A range of of unusual emergent behaviors have been reported in the charge-density wave (CDW) state of the $A$V$_3$Sb$_5$ ($A=~$K, Rb, Cs) kagome metals, including a CDW formation process without soft phonons, which points to an unconventional CDW mechanism. Here, we use inelastic x-ray scattering to show that the CDW in KV$_3$Sb$_5$ forms via phonons that soften to zero energy at the CDW ordering vector ($L$-point) around $T_{\rm CDW}=78$~K. These soft phonons exhibit a remarkable in-plane anisotropy, extending over a much larger momentum range along $L$-$A$ relative to $L$-$H$, which leads to diffuse scattering common among $A$V$_3$Sb$_5$. Using first-principles calculations, we find that the momentum-dependent electron-phonon coupling (EPC) is peaked at $L$ and exhibits the same in-plane anisotropy as the phonon softening. Conversely, the electronic susceptibility is not peaked at $L$ and shows the opposite in-plane anisotropy. Our findings favor momentum-dependent EPC as the driving mechanism of the CDW in KV$_3$Sb$_5$, with a CDW formation process similar to that of transition metal dichalcogenides.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20230v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifan Wang, Chenchao Xu, Zhimian Wu, Huachen Rao, Zhaoyang Shan, Yi Liu, Guanghan Cao, Michael Smidman, Ming Shi, Huiqiu Yuan, Tao Wu, Xianhui Chen, Chao Cao, Yu Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent Massless Dirac Fermions in Moir\'e Bands of Bilayer Graphene/hBN Superlattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20309</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20309v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A superlattice of multilayer graphene and hBN has proven to be a promising pathway for engineering electronic band structures and topologies. In this work, we experimentally demonstrate the role of hBN alignment in inducing topological band reconstruction in bilayer graphene (BLG) superlattices. Our study establishes that while the primary band retains its massive chiral naure, the secondary bands host massless, chiral fermions. Magnetotransport measurements, including Quantum Hall, temperature-dependent Shubnikov-de Haas oscillations, and Berry phase analysis, confirm the distinct topological nature of these bands. A significantly reduced Fermi velocity in the moir\'{e} secondary band indicates band flattening induced by the moir\'{e} potential. Our study provides a pathway for controlling topological quantum transport in BLG/hBN superlattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20309v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohit Kumar Jat, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Aveek bid</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sub-10 nm Quantification of Spin and Orbital Magnetic Moment Across the Metamagnetic Phase Transition in FeRh Using EMCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20523</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20523v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Electron magnetic circular dichroism (EMCD) in transmission electron microscopy (TEM) enables element-specific measurement of spin and orbital magnetic moments, analogous to X-ray magnetic circular dichroism (XMCD). While the EMCD technique offers unmatched spatial resolution, its quantitative accuracy remains under scrutiny, particularly in beam-splitter geometries with convergent probes. Here, we systematically evaluate the limits of quantitative EMCD analysis using the first-order magnetostructural transition in the functional phase-change material FeRh as a tunable magnetic reference. Unlike previous EMCD studies primarily focused on elemental ferromagnets such as Fe, we demonstrate its applicability to a correlated material exhibiting coupled structural and magnetic order. We demonstrate that the extracted orbital-to-spin moment ratio ($m_\text{L}/m_\text{S}$) remains consistent with XMCD benchmarks for TEM probes down to approximately 6 nm, thereby establishing the validity range for reliable quantification. For nm-sized probes with higher convergence angles, we observe an enhanced $m_\text{L}/m_\text{S}$, which we attribute to a combination of instrumental factors and sensitivity to nanoscale heterogeneity within the probed volume. Our results confirm that EMCD provides quantitative agreement with macroscale techniques under suitable conditions, while uniquely enabling spatially confined measurements of local magnetic moments in functional magnetic materials, and allowing the study of interfacial, defect-mediated, or phase-separated magnetism that is inaccessible to photon-based methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20523v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Hajdu\v{c}ek, Veronica Leccese, J\'an Rusz, Jon Ander Arregi, Alexey Sapozhnik, J\'achym \v{S}tindl, Francesco Barantani, Paolo Cattaneo, Antoine Andrieux, Vojt\v{e}ch Uhl\'i\v{r}, Fabrizio Carbone, Thomas LaGrange</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local Density of States as a Probe of Multifractality in Quasiperiodic Moir\'e Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20575</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20575v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quasiperiodic moir\'e materials provide a new platform for realizing critical electronic states, yet a direct and experimentally practical method to characterize this criticality has been lacking. We show that a multifractal analysis of the local density of states (LDOS), accessible via scanning tunneling microscopy, offers an unambiguous signature of criticality from a single experimental sample. Applying this approach to a one-dimensional quasiperiodic model, a stringent test case due to its fractal energy spectrum, we find a clear distinction between the broad singularity spectra $f\left(\alpha\right)$ of critical states and the point-like spectra of extended states. We further demonstrate that these multifractal signatures remain robust over a wide range of energy broadenings relevant to experiments. Our results establish a model-independent, experimentally feasible framework for identifying and probing multifractality in the growing family of quasiperiodic and moir\'e materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20575v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ricardo Oliveira, Nicolau Sobrosa, Pedro Ribeiro, Bruno Amorim, Eduardo V. Castro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Angular dependence and powder average of resonant inelastic X-ray scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20731</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20731v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Resonant Inelastic X-ray scattering (RIXS) is a synchrotron-based spectroscopy that has seen growing interest across a range of scientific disciplines beyond fundamental physics. The interpretation of experimental RIXS data requires theoretical calculations based on the Kramers-Heisenberg formula. However, due to the dependence of RIXS on both the incident and scattered photon properties, a tractable treatment of the angular dependence in this formula has been lacking. In this work, within the electric dipole approximation, we determine the number of fundamental spectra contributing to the RIXS cross-section for all crystallographic point groups. We then derive a general expression for the RIXS cross-section of isotropic samples such as un-textured powders, homogeneous glasses or liquids, explicitly accounting for the polarization and propagation directions of both the incident and scattered photons. Simplified forms of the RIXS expressions are subsequently obtained for most common point groups. Finally, we demonstrate the applicability of our formalism through a case study of uranium 3d4f RIXS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20731v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Myrtille O. J. Y Hunault, Timothy G. Burrow, Fabien Besnard, Am\'elie Juhin, Christian Brouder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous Hall effect in rhombohedral graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20804</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20804v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by recent experiments on rhombohedral stacked multilayer graphene and the observation of the anomalous Hall effect in a spontaneous spin-valley polarized quarter metal state, we calculate the anomalous Hall conductivity for this system in the presence of two types of impurities: weak and dense as well as sparse and strong. Our calculation of $\sigma_{xy}$ is based on the Kubo-Streda diagrammatic approach. In a model with Gaussian disorder applicable to weak dense impurities, this involves all non-crossing diagrams (intrinsic, side-jump and Gaussian skew-scattering contributions) and additionally diagrams with two intersecting impurities, X and $\Psi$, representing diffractive skew-scattering processes. A "Mercedes star" diagram (non-Gaussian skew scattering) is furthermore included to treat in the case of strong, sparse impurities. We supplement our asymptotically exact analytical solutions for an isotropic model without warping effects by semi-numerical calculations accounting perturbatively for warping, which plays a crucial role in the low-energy band structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20804v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vera Mikheeva, Daniele Guerci, Daniel Kaplan, Elio J. K\"onig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charge-density waves and stripes in quarter metals of graphene heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20816</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20816v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by recent experiments, here we identify valley-coherent charge-density wave (VC-CDW) order in the non-degenerate quarter-metal for the entire family of chirally-stacked $n$ layer graphene, encompassing rhombohedral multi-layer, Bernal bilayer, and monolayer cousins. Besides the hallmark broken translational symmetry, yielding a modulated charge-density over an enlarged unit-cell with a characteristic $2{\bf K}$ periodicity, where $\pm {\bf K}$ are the valley momenta, this phase lacks the three-fold ($C_3$) rotational symmetry but only for even integer $n$. The VC-CDW then represents a stripe order, as observed in hexalayer graphene [arXiv:2504.05129], but preserves the $C_3$ symmetry for odd $n$ as observed in trilayer graphene [Nat. Phys. 20, 1413 (2024) and arXiv: 2411.11163]. From a universal Clifford algebraic argument, we establish that the VC-CDW and an anomalous Hall order can lift the residual valley degeneracy of an antiferromagnetically ordered spin-polarized half-metal, when these systems are subject to perpendicular displacement fields, with only the latter one displaying a hysteresis in off-diagonal resistivity, as observed in all the systems with $2 \leq n \leq 6$. We showcase a confluence of VC-CDW and anomalous Hall orders within the quarter-metal, generically displaying a regime of coexistence, separating the pure phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20816v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sk Asrap Murshed, Bitan Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single Sr Atoms in Optical Tweezer Arrays for Quantum Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19816</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19816v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report on the realization of a platform for trapping and manipulating individual $^{88}$Sr atoms in optical tweezers. A first cooling stage based on a blue magneto-optical trap (MOT) operating on the $^1S_0$ -&gt; $^1P_1$ transition at 461 nm enables us to trap approximately $4\times 10^6$ atoms at a temperature of 8 mK. Further cooling is achieved in a narrow-line red MOT using the $^1S_0$ -&gt; $^3P_1$ intercombination transition at 689 nm, bringing $4\times 10^5$ atoms down to 5 uK and reaching a density of $\approx 10^{10}$ cm$^{-3}$. Atoms are then loaded into 813 nm tweezer arrays generated by crossed acousto-optic deflectors and tightly focused onto the atoms with a high-numerical-aperture objective. Through light-assisted collision processes we achieve the collisional blockade, which leads to single-atom occupancy with a probability of about $50\%$. The trapped atoms are detected via fluorescence imaging with a fidelity of $99.986(6)\%$, while maintaining a survival probability of $97(1)\%$. The release-and-recapture measurement provides a temperature of $12.92(5)$ uK for the atoms in the tweezers, and the ultra-high-vacuum environment ensures a vacuum lifetime higher than 7 minutes. These results demonstrate a robust alkaline-earth tweezer platform that combines efficient loading, cooling, and high-fidelity detection, providing the essential building blocks for scalable quantum simulation and quantum information processing with Sr atoms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19816v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Veronica Giardini, Luca Guariento, Andrea Fantini, Shawn Storm, Massimo Inguscio, Jacopo Catani, Giacomo Cappellini, Vladislav Gavryusev, Leonardo Fallani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling non-Hermitian band structures with non-Bloch supercells</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20160</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20160v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Real-valued band structures are foundational to analyzing periodic systems within the Hermitian description and have been experimentally well-established over recent decades. In contrast, non-Hermitian systems exhibit complex band structures where both energy and momentum have imaginary parts, underpinning phenomena like the non-Hermitian skin effect and anomalous bulk-boundary correspondence that defy conventional Bloch theory. Experimentally mapping these complex bands-relating complex momentum to complex energy-and identifying their associated eigenstates is crucial for understanding these systems but remains a significant challenge. Here, we introduce a non-Bloch supercell framework designed to overcome this challenge by decoupling Bloch phase control from the imaginary part of momentum. Our method combines an exponent-flattening protocol with twisted boundary conditions, enabling system-size-independent control of imaginary momentum while preserving high-resolution Bloch phase sampling. Implemented in programmable one- and two-dimensional acoustic crystals, our approach acquires momentum-resolved complex energy surfaces and biorthogonal eigenmodes by Green's function measurements.Data obtained using this framework accurately predict open-boundary spectra and eigenstates, findings we verify through separate open-geometry experiments. Our work provides a broadly applicable experimental toolkit for exploring non-Hermitian band geometry and topology in diverse engineered classical and quantum platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20160v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jia-Xin Zhong, Jing Lin, Kai Chen, Jing Lu, Kun Ding, Yun Jing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theta-term in Russian Doll Model: phase structure, quantum metric and BPS multifractality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20758</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20758v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the phase structure of the deterministic and disordered versions of the Russian Doll Model (RDM), which is a generalization of Richardson model of superconductivity in a finite system with time-reversal symmetry breaking parameter $\theta$. It is one of the simplest examples of the cyclic RG where $\log N$ plays the role of the RG time. The deterministic model is integrable and shares the same Bethe Ansatz (BA) equations with the inhomogeneous twisted XXX spin chain. We analyze the quantum metric, the Berry curvature, and the fractal dimension in the sector with a single Cooper pair. A rich phase structure in the $(\theta,\gamma)$ parameter plane is found, where $\gamma \log N$ quantifies the hopping term.
  For the deterministic RDM we clearly identify the extended domain of non-ergodic multifractal phase on the $(\theta,\gamma)$ parameter plane supporting the reentrance transitions between the localized, ergodic, and multifractal phases. We find the pattern of phase transitions in the global charge $Q(\theta,\gamma)$, which arises from the BA equation. In particular, in the multifractal phase in the deterministic model $Q(\gamma)$ exhibits the analogue of "charge concentration" and fortuity phenomena discussed in the context of black hole microstates at finite $N$. The BA equations in RDM exactly coincide with the equations defining the ground states in the theory on the worldvolume of the vortex strings in $N_F=2N_C$ ${\cal N}=2$ SQCD at a strong coupling point $\frac{1}{g_{YM}^2}=0$ with identification $\theta_{RDM}= \theta_{4D}-\pi$. We conjecture that the Hamiltonian of the RDM model describes the mixing in particular 2d-4d BPS sector of the Hilbert space. Our findings provide an example of the BPS multifractality regime for the probe operator in the sector of Hilbert space, and we comment on the possible application to dense QCD with $\theta$ term.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20758v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Gorsky, Ilya Lyubimov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kitaev-Heisenberg exchange on $t_{2g}^5e_g^2$ cobaltate platform</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12742</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12742v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The detection of considerable spin frustration in honeycomb cobalt oxide compounds indicates the presence of sizable Kitaev interactions in these systems, enlarging the pool of Kitaev spin liquid candidates. Several key questions remain to be answered, such as the magnitude of Kitaev couplings in cobaltates and how to engineer those, by either chemical or physical means. Analyzing the quantum chemistry of interacting magnetic moments in Na$_3$Co$_2$SbO$_6$, a representative $LS$-coupled $t_{2g}^5e_g^2$ Co$^{2+}$ oxide, we find that the Kitaev and off-diagonal $\Gamma$ interactions are substantial and antiferromagnetic but somewhat weaker than the Heisenberg contribution. Except $\Gamma'$, all nearest-neighbor couplings are mainly determined by Coulomb exchange, different from current representations of anisotropic interaction terms. This highlights the limits of existing anisotropic models and the need for systematic wave-function quantum chemical studies to clarify exchange mechanisms in Kitaev-Heisenberg magnets and the way of tuning intersite couplings towards the Kitaev spin liquid ground state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12742v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pritam Bhattacharyya, Abdul Basit, Thorben Petersen, Stephan Rachel, Satoshi Nishimoto, Liviu Hozoi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interleaved bond frustration in a triangular lattice antiferromagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04203</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04203v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Frustration of long-range order via lattice geometries serves to amplify fluctuations of the order parameter and generate unconventional ground states that are highly sensitive to perturbations. Traditionally, this concept of geometric frustration is used to engineer unconventional magnetic states in a variety of materials; however, the charge degree of freedom and bond order can be similarly frustrated. Finding materials that host both frustrated magnetic and bond networks holds promise for engineering structural and magnetic states with the potential of coupling to one another via either the magnetic sector (via magnetic field) or via the lattice sector (via strain). In this paper, we identify an unusual instance of this coexistence in the triangular lattice antiferromagnetic compounds $Ln$Cd$_3$P$_3$ ($Ln$ = La, Ce, Pr, and Nd). These compounds feature two-dimensional planes of unique trigonal-planar CdP$_3$ units that manifest an underlying bond instability with its long-range ordering frustrated via emergent kagome ice bond correlations. Our results establish $Ln$Cd$_3$P$_3$ as a rare class of materials where frustrated magnetism across a tunable rare-earth triangular network is embedded within a dopable semiconductor with a frustrated bond order instability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04203v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41563-025-02380-x</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>S. J. Gomez Alvarado, J. R. Chamorro, D. Rout, J. Hielscher, Sarah Schwarz, Caeli Benyacko, M. B. Stone, V. Ovidiu Garlea, A. R. Jackson, G. Pokharel, R. Gomez, B. R. Ortiz, Suchismita Sarker, L. Kautzsch, L. C. Gallington, R. Seshadri, Stephen D. Wilson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photoinduced twist and untwist of moir\'e superlattices in TMDC heterobilayers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11452</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11452v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Two-dimensional moir\'e materials are formed by artificially stacking atomically thin monolayers. A wealth of correlated and topological quantum phases can be engineered via precise choice of stacking geometry. These designer electronic properties depend crucially on interlayer coupling and atomic registry. An important open question is how atomic registry responds on ultrafast timescales to optical excitation and whether the moir\'e geometry can be dynamically reconfigured to tune emergent phenomena in real time. Here we show that femtosecond photoexcitation drives a coherent twist-untwist motion of the moir\'e superlattice in $2^\circ$ and $57^\circ$ twisted WSe$_2$/MoSe$_2$ heterobilayers, resolved directly by ultrafast electron diffraction. Upon above-band-gap photoexcitation, the moir\'e superlattice diffraction features are enhanced within 1 ps and subsequently suppressed several picoseconds after, deviating markedly from typical photoinduced lattice heating. Kinetic diffraction analysis, supported by simulations of the sample dynamics, indicates a peak-to-trough local twist angle modulation of $0.6^\circ$, correlated with a sub-THz frequency moir\'e phonon. This motion is driven by ultrafast charge transfer that transiently increases interlayer attraction. Our results could lead to ultrafast control of moir\'e periodic lattice distortions and, by extension, the local moir\'e potential that shapes excitons, polarons, and correlation-driven behaviors</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11452v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. J. R. Duncan, A. C. Johnson, I. Maity, A. Rubio, M. Gordon, A. C. Bartnik, M. Kaemingk, W. H. Li, M. B. Andorf, C. A. Pennington, I. V. Bazarov, M. W. Tate, D. A. Muller, J. Thom-Levy, S. M. Gruner, A . M. Lindenberg, F. Liu, J. M. Maxson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Longitudinal magnon transport properties in the easy-axis XXZ Heisenberg ferromagnet on the face-centered cubic lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04082v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a detailed investigation of longitudinal magneto-thermal transport in the $S=1/2$ ferromagnetic XXZ model with easy-axis exchange anisotropy ($\Delta&gt;1$) on a face-centered cubic lattice consisting of four sublattices. We employ linear spin-wave theory and the Kubo formalism to evaluate the longitudinal spin and thermal conductivities, both of which exhibit activated temperature dependence in the low-temperature regime, and to determine their magnetic-field dependence. Our analysis indicates that a magnon gap is crucial for ensuring the convergence of these conductivities. Furthermore, by examining the ratio of thermal conductivity to spin conductivity, we identify an analog of the Wiedemann-Franz law for magnon transport at low temperatures. Finally, we demonstrate that these results can be generalized to systems with arbitrary spin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04082v5</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jmmm.2025.173608</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JMMM 635, 173608 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>M. R. Parymuda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flat-band thermodynamics reveals enhanced performance across Otto, Carnot, and Stirling cycles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16525</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.16525v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Magic-angle twisted bilayer graphene (MATBG) exhibits remarkable electronic properties under external magnetic fields, notably the emergence of flat Landau levels. In this study, we present a comprehensive analysis of MATBG's operational phase diagram under three distinct quantum thermodynamic cycles, i.e., Quantum Otto Cycle (QOC), Quantum Carnot Cycle (QCC), and Quantum Stirling Cycle (QSC). Employing the continuum eight-band model, we evaluate the thermodynamic performance of MATBG across multiple operational modes: heat engine, refrigerator, cold pump, and Joule pump, and benchmark it against other graphene systems such as monolayer graphene, AB-Bernal stacked bilayer graphene, and non-magic-angle twisted bilayer graphene. Our findings reveal that MATBG demonstrates superior heat engine performance in QSC, while achieving high efficiency albeit with reduced work output in QOC. Even though the performance of MATBG as a cold pump or refrigerator is modest in QOC and QSC, it shows notable improvement as a refrigerator in QCC. Additionally, we identify a highly reversible Joule pump mode in both QSC and QOC under strict adiabaticity, underscoring the unique thermodynamic behavior of MATBG.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.16525v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/cjlz-lrd6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review A (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hadi Mohammed Soufy, Colin Benjamin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mesoscale variations of chemical and electronic landscape on the surface of Weyl semimetal Co$_3$Sn$_2$S$_2$ visualized by ARPES and XPS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01826</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01826v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The multiple crystalline terminations in magnetic Weyl semimetal Co$_3$Sn$_2$S$_2$ display distinct topological and trivial surface states, which have successfully been distinguished experimentally. However, a model of pure terminations is known to be inadequate because these surfaces exhibit a high degree of spatial heterogeneity and point disorder. Here we perform a spectromicroscopy study of the surface chemistry and surface electronic structure using photoemission measurements in combination with first-principles calculations of core levels. We identify an intermediate region with properties distinct from both the sulfur and tin terminations, and demonstrate that the spectral features in this region can be associated with a disordered termination with a varying density of surface tin vacancies. This work establishes heuristics for identifying variable surface disorder using photoemission, an important prerequisite to experimentally establishing the behavior of momentum-space topological surface features subject to variable surface disorder on a single cleave.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01826v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sudheer Anand Sreedhar, Matthew Staab, Mingkun Chen, Robert Prater, Zihao Shen, Giuseppina Conti, Ittai Sidilkover, Zhenghong Wu, Eli Rotenberg, Aaron Bostwick, Chris Jozwiak, Hadas Soifer, Slavomir Nemsak, Sergey Y. Savrasov, Vsevolod Ivanov, Valentin Taufour, Inna M. Vishik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital altermagnetism on the kagome lattice and possible application to $A$V$_3$Sb$_5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26596</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.26596v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Altermagnets, which encompass a broad landscape of materials, are compensated collinear magnetic phases in which the antiparallel magnetic moments are related by a crystalline rotation. Here, we argue that collinear altermagnetic-like states can also be realized in lattices with an odd number of sublattices, provided that the electronic interactions promote non-uniform magnetic moments. We demonstrate this idea for a kagome metal whose band filling places the Fermi level close to the van Hove singularity. Combining phenomenological and microscopic modeling, we show that the intertwined charge density-wave and loop-current instabilities of this model lead to a wide parameter range in which orbital ferromagnetic, antiferromagnetic, and altermagnetic phases emerge inside the charge-ordered state. In the presence of spin-orbit coupling, their electronic structures display the usual spin-split fingerprints associated with the three types of collinear magnetic order. We discuss the possible realization of orbital altermagnetic phases in the $A$V$_3$Sb$_5$ family of kagome metals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.26596v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anzumaan R. Chakraborty, Fan Yang, Turan Birol, Rafael M. Fernandes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixed Quantum-Classical Methods for Polaron Spectral Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13365</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13365v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, using two distinct semiclassical approaches, namely the mean-field Ehrenfest (MFE) method and the mapping approach to surface hopping (MASH), we investigate the spectral function of a single charge interacting with phonons on a lattice. This quantity is relevant for the description of angle-resolved photoemission experiments. Focusing on the one-dimensional Holstein model, we compare the performance of these approaches across a range of coupling strengths and lattice sizes, exposing the relative strengths and weaknesses of each. We demonstrate that these approaches can be efficiently applied with reasonable accuracy to ab initio polaron models. Our work provides a route to the calculation of spectral properties in realistic electron-phonon-coupled systems in a computationally inexpensive manner with encouraging accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13365v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0281529</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Haimi Nguyen, Arkajit Mandal, Ankit Mahajan, David R. Reichman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mechanism of the electrochemical hydrogenation of graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19505</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19505v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The electrochemical hydrogenation of graphene induces a robust and reversible conductor-insulator transition, of strong interest in logic-and-memory applications. However, its mechanism remains unknown. Here we show that it proceeds as a reduction reaction in which proton adsorption competes with the formation of H2 molecules via an Eley-Rideal process. Graphene's electrochemical hydrogenation is up to $10^6$ times faster than alternative hydrogenation methods and is fully reversible via the oxidative desorption of protons. We demonstrate that the proton reduction rate in defect-free graphene can be enhanced by an order of magnitude by the introduction of nanoscale corrugations in its lattice, and that the substitution of protons for deuterons results both in lower potentials for the hydrogenation process and in a more stable compound. Our results pave the way to investigating the chemisorption of ions in 2D materials at high electric fields, opening a new avenue to control these materials' electronic properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19505v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Y. -C. Soong, H. Li, Y. Fu, J. Tong, S. Huang, X. Zhang, E. Griffin, E. Hoenig, M. Alhashmi, Y. Li, D. Bahamon, J. Zhong, A. Summerfield, R. N. Costa Filho, C. Sevik, R. Gorbachev, E. C. Neyts, L. F. Vega, F. M. Peeters, M. Lozada-Hidalgo</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
