<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 04:00:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Time-reversal positivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06226</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06226v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a new analytical tool called time-reversal positivity. It is an analogue of the Majorana reflection positivity in time-reversal symmetric case. This new time-reversal positivity can fully explain the relationship between time-reversal symmetry and the sign-free property in quantum Monte Carlo simulations. Using a cone-theoretical method, we show the ground state uniqueness for the time-reversal symmetric non-hermitian Hubbard model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06226v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhong-Chao Wei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconductivity of Incoherent Electrons near the Relativistic Mott Transition in Twisted Dirac Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06313v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate that superconductivity driven by strong quantum-critical fluctuations can emerge near relativistic Mott transitions in twisted two-dimensional materials, taking on a remarkably rich character. In twisted double-bilayer WSe$_2$, all time-reversal-even, gap-opening collective modes promote pairing, whereas time-reversal-odd modes do not. In a Dirac model of twisted bilayer graphene, the Gross-Neveu transition into inter-valley-coherent insulators gives rise to a spectrum of degenerate and nearly degenerate superconducting states. More generally, we show that the richer the Dirac structure, the more readily pairs can form. A crucial ingredient of the theory is that critical fluctuations render the electronic states strongly incoherent, allowing attractive pairing channels to overcome the bare Dirac semi-metal behavior. Finally, we demonstrate a direct relation between boson-mediated pairing and the formation of charge-carrying skyrmionic excitations in the proximate insulating state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06313v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Veronika C. Stangier, Mathias S. Scheurer, Daniel E. Sheehy, J\"org Schmalian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hund's coupling assisted orbital-selective superconductivity in Ba1-xKxFe2As2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06435</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06435v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: While the superconducting transition temperature of hole-doped Ba_{1-x}K_{x}Fe_{2}As_{2} decreases past optimal doping, superconductivity does not completely disappear even for the fully doped KFe_{2}As_{2} compound. In fact, superconductivity is robust through a Lifshitz transition where electron bands become hole-like around the zone corner at around x=0.7, thus challenging the conventional understanding of superconductivity in iron-based systems. High-resolution angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy is used to investigate the superconducting gap structure, as well as the normal state electronic structure, around optimal doping and across the Lifshitz transition. Our findings reveal a largely orbital-dependent superconducting gap structure, where the more strongly correlated d_{xy} band has a vanishing superconducting gap at higher doping, aligning with the Hund's metal behavior observed in the normal state. Notably, the superconducting gap on the d_{xy} band disappears before the Lifshitz transition, suggesting that the Fermi surface topology may play a secondary role. We discuss how these results point to orbital-selective superconducting pairing and how strong correlations via Hund's coupling may shape superconducting gap structures in iron-based and other multiorbital superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06435v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elena Corbae, Rong Zhang, Cong Li, Kunihiro Kihou, Chul-Ho Lee, Makoto Hashimoto, Thomas Devereaux, Oscar Tjernberg, Egor Babaev, Dung-Hai Lee, Vadim Grinenko, Donghui Lu, Zhi-Xun Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kekul\'e Superconductivity in Twisted Magic Angle Bilayer Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06451</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06451v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by recent scanning tunneling microscopy experiments which report Kekul\'e ordering in the twisted graphene family, we develop a microscopic theory of superconductivity, specifically for the bi-layer case. This involves an intra-valley, finite-momentum pair-density wave (PDW) which naturally incorporates a Kekul\'e distortion into the superconducting phase. The PDW state displays three central features: (i) it spontaneously breaks $C_3$ rotational symmetry, producing nematic order, and (ii) it possesses a large gap-to-critical-temperature ratio. Moreover, (iii) it yields a quasi-particle density of states having a V-like shape (with a finite value at zero energy) which transitions to a fully gapped, U-shaped spectrum with increasing attraction. These characteristics, including consistency with an allowed Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless transition, align with key experimental signatures in the twisted graphene family where the U-V transition is observed in the tri-layer case. We find the paired state with a modest interaction strength is near to a BEC-like regime, as appears consistent with the observed extremely short coherence lengths. Together, these results establish a microscopic intra-valley Kekul\'e PDW state as an essential ingredient towards understanding unconventional superconductivity in twisted graphene.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06451v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ke Wang, K. Levin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mechanistic insights into hydrogen reduction of multicomponent oxides via in-situ high-energy X-ray diffraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06455</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06455v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Co-reduction of multicomponent oxides with hydrogen provides a carbon-neutral approach toward sustainable alloy design. Herein, we investigate the hydrogen-based direct reduction, using in-situ high-energy X-ray diffraction of two precursor variants: mechanically mixed powders and pre-sintered oxide mixtures, targeting an equiatomic CoFeMnNi alloy. We find distinct reduction pathways and microstructure evolution depending on initial precursors. Mixed powders at 700 {\deg}C are reduced to body-centered-cubic, face-centered-cubic, and MnO phases via halite, spinel, and Mn3O4 intermediates, whereas the pre-sintered material directly transforms into a mixture of metallic and oxide phases. The post-reduction microstructures are also different: mixed oxides show loosely packed morphology, whereas pre-sintered material reveals metallic nanoparticles supported on nanoporous MnO. The formation of nanoporous metallic networks is strongly governed by the precursor state, highlighting the role of initial precursors on the final microstructure. This precursor design strategy offers a single-step route to nanoporous alloys with potential applications in catalysis and energy technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06455v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shiv Shankar, Barak Ratzker, Claudio Pistidda, Dierk Raabe, Yan Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Twisted locality-preserving automorphisms, anomaly index, and generalized Lieb-Schultz-Mattis theorems with anti-unitary symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06555</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06555v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Symmetries and their anomalies are powerful tools to understand quantum matter. In this work, for quantum spin chains, we define twisted locality-preserving automorphisms and their Gross-Nesme-Vogts-Werner indices, which provide a unified framework to describe both unitary and anti-unitary symmetries, on-site and non-on-site symmetries, and internal and translation symmetries. For a symmetry $G$ with actions given by twisted locality-preserving automorphisms, we give a microscopic definition of its anomaly index, which is an element in $H^3_\varphi(G; U(1))$, where the subscript $\varphi$ means that anti-unitary elements of $G$ act on $U(1)$ by complex conjugation. We show that an anomalous symmetry leads to multiple Lieb-Schultz-Matttis-type theorems. In particular, any state with an anomalous symmetry must either have long-range correlation or violate the entanglement area law. Based on this theorem, we further deduce that any state with an anomalous symmetry must have long-range entanglement, and any Hamiltonian that has an anomalous symmetry cannot have a unique gapped symmetric ground state, as long as the interactions in the Hamiltonian decay fast enough as the range of the interaction increases. For Hamiltonians with only two-spin interactions, the last theorem holds if the interactions decay faster than $1/r^2$, where $r$ is the distance between the two interacting spins. We demonstrate these general theorems in various concrete examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06555v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruizhi Liu, Jinmin Yi, Liujun Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Hall Effect in PrSb$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06570</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06570v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: PrSb$_2$ exhibits a charge-density wave (CDW) transition at $T_\mathrm{CDW} = 100$ K and antiferromagnetic (AFM) ordering at $T_\mathrm{N} = 5$ K at ambient pressure. Hall resistivity measurements revealed an anomalous feature within the AFM state, which was attributed to the topological Hall effect (THE), ruling out contributions from the ordinary and anomalous Hall effects. Significantly, the THE anomaly diminished with increasing pressure and almost vanished as the CDW transition was suppressed near the critical pressure $P_c$ = 1.0 GPa. These findings suggest a relationship between the CDW order and the appearance of the THE in PrSb$_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06570v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.7566/JPSJ.94.113703</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. 94, 113703 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shingo Araki, Hinata Izumida, Kazuto Akiba, Tatsuo C. Kobayashi, Takashi Kambe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic ultrafast edge photocurrent dynamics in WTe$_2$ driven by broken crystal symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06618</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06618v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Directional photocurrents in two-dimensional materials arise from broken crystal symmetry, offering pathways to high-speed, bias-free photodetection beyond conventional devices. Tungsten ditelluride (WTe$_2$), a type-II Weyl semimetal, exhibits robust symmetry-breaking-induced edge photocurrents from competing nonlinear optical and photothermoelectric (PTE) mechanisms, whose intrinsic dynamics have remained experimentally inaccessible. Here, we directly resolve sub-picosecond edge photocurrent dynamics in WTe$_2$ through ohmic contacts over temperatures from 300 K to 4 K. We demonstrate ultrafast optical-to-electrical conversion with a 3 dB bandwidth of $\sim$250 GHz and reveal picosecond-timescale switching of the net photocurrent direction below 150 K, linked to a Lifshitz transition. This transient bipolar response arises from non-equilibrium Seebeck effects due to asymmetric cooling of hot electrons and holes. These findings reveal previously hidden ultrafast dynamics in symmetry-engineered materials, offering new strategies to disentangle competing photocurrent mechanisms and enabling the development of self-powered, ultrafast optoelectronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06618v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subhashri Chatterjee, Katsumasa Yoshioka, Taro Wakamura, Vasili Perebeinos, Norio Kumada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasiparticle Description of Angle-Resolved Photoemission Spectroscopy for SrCuO2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06693</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06693v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: SrCuO2 has long been considered a near-archetypal realization of a quasi one dimensional (1D) system of interacting electrons with short-range interactions. Within this framework, experimental observations - interpreted through the lens of the 1D Hubbard model-suggest that electron and hole excitations decay into two types of (unphysical) collective bosonic modes: spinons, which carry the spin degree of freedom, and holons, which carry the charge degree of freedom. This model, known as spin-charge separation, is most directly evidenced by angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES), where a photo-induced hole decays into a continuum of these excitations. Here we present an alternative perspective grounded in first-principles, self-consistent, and parameter-free many-body perturbation theory. In this revised quasiparticle framework, ARPES can be understood as a one-body effect arising from mild disorder in a long-range antiferromagnetic ground state. the emergence of the so-called spinon branch arises naturally from spin disorder, the anomalous line widths are accurately captured, and we provide a compelling explanation for the spectral weight observed at the non-magnetic zone boundary. This reinterpretation provides a unified explanation for key experimental signatures previously attributed to spin-charge separation, including features observed in optical conductivity. Additionally, we show that SrCuO2 exhibits a nontrivial interchain coupling that significantly influences both its one-particle and two-particle spectral functions. By comparing the spectral features of SrCuO2 with those of La2CuO4, we argue that SrCuO2 shares notable similarities with the two-dimensional cuprates - both being rooted in a common CuO4 plaquette-based molecular orbital framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06693v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dimitar Pashov, Casey Eichstaedt, Swagata Acharya, Mark van Schilfgaarde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modular Reactor for In Situ X-ray Scattering, Spectroscopy, and ATR-IR Studies of Solvothermal Nanoparticle Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06770</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06770v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding the chemical processes that occur during the solvothermal synthesis of functional nanomaterials is essential for their rational design and optimization for specific applications. However, these processes remain poorly understood, primarily due to the limitations of conventional ex situ characterization techniques and the technical challenges associated with in situ studies, particularly the design and implementation of suitable reactors. Here, we present a versatile cell suitable for in situ X-ray scattering, X-ray spectroscopy, and infrared spectroscopy studies performed during solvothermal synthesis under autoclave-like, inert conditions. The reactor enables precise control of the temperature between -20 C and 200 C, pressures up to 8 bar, magnetic stirring, and injection of gas or liquids. The reactor's capabilities are demonstrated by comprehensively studying the solvothermal synthesis of magnetite nanoparticles from iron acetylacetonate in benzyl alcohol through in situ X-ray scattering and spectroscopy, and ATR-IR spectroscopy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06770v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sani Y. Harouna-Mayer, Melike Gumus Akcaalan, Jagadesh Kopula Kesavan, Tjark R. L. Groene, Lars Klemeyer, Sarah-Alexandra Hussak, Lukas Grote, a Davide Derelli, Francesco Caddeo, Cecilia Zito, Paul St\"utzle, Dorota Speer, Ann-Christin Dippel, Blanka Detlefs, Yannik Appiarius, Axel Jacobi von Wangelin, Dorota Koziej</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ground state magnetic structure of Mn3Sn</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06808</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06808v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We use spherical neutron polarimetry to determine the ground state magnetic structure of Mn3Sn. We find that Mn3Sn adopts an inverse triangular structure with spins parallel to &lt;100&gt; (Type III) rather than spins parallel to &lt;110&gt; (Type IV). Density functional theory calculations reveal no energy difference between these two structures, suggesting that the selection is caused by subtle effects such as sixth-order anisotropy. Partial control of the magnetic domain population through a moderate magnetic field is key to distinguish between the two models. We find that three of the six domains are approximately equally populated, while the others have negligible population. Upon entering the low temperature incommensurate phase, the domain structure is lost. The domains decouple from the magnetic field, and can therefore not be controlled by any known method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06808v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeppe Jon Cederholm, Zhian Xu, Yanfeng Guo, Martin Ovesen, Thomas Olsen, Kristine M. L. Krighaar, Chrystalla Knekna, Jian Rui Soh, Youngro Lee, Navid Qureshi, Jose Alberto Rodriguez Velamazan, Eric Ressouche, Andrew T. Boothroyd, Henrik Jacobsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Field-Induced SIT in Disordered 2D Electron systems: The case of amorphous Indium-Oxide thin films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06894v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The phenomenon of field-induced superconductor to insulator transition (SIT) in disordered 2D electron systems has been a subject of controversy since its discovery in the early 1990s. Here we present a phenomenological quantitative theory of this phenomenon which is not based exclusively on the boson-vortex duality used commonly in the field. Within a new low-temperature framework of the time-dependent Ginzburg-Landau (TDGL) functional approach to superconducting fluctuations we propose and develop a scenario in which bosons of Cooper-pair fluctuations (CPFs) condense and localize in real-space mesoscopic puddles under increasing magnetic field due to diminishing stiffness of the fluctuation modes at low temperatures in a broad range of momentum space. Quantum tunneled CPFs relieving the condensed mesoscopic puddles, which consequently pair break into fermionic quasi-particle excitations, dominate the thermally activated inter-puddles transport. The spatially shrinking puddles of CPFs, embedded in expanding normal-state regions, upon further increasing field, suppress the quasi-particle excitation gap and so lead to high-field negative magneto-resistance (MR). Application to amorphous Indium-Oxide thin films shows good quantitative agreement with experimental sheet resistance data. In particular, in agreement with the experiment at low temperatures (i.e. well below the quantum tunneling pair breaking "temperature"), the sheet resistance isotherms are predicted to show a single crossing point at a quantum critical field not far below the MR peak.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06894v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tsofar Maniv, Vladimir Zhuravlev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncovering domain morphology in an unconventional magnet with scanning diamond quantum magnetometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06895</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06895v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Unconventional magnetic materials including non-collinear antiferromagnets, p-wave magnets and altermagnets, are an emerging frontier for quantum spintronics and hybrid quantum devices. Critical to the application of these materials is control over the magnetic domain state, as their unique, symmetry-driven properties vanish in a multi-domain limit. However, the mechanisms governing domain formation in materials with compensated local moments remain poorly understood. In this work, we examine the ferrimagnetic to non-collinear antiferromagnetic phase transition of Mn3NiN using scanning nitrogen-vacancy centre magnetometry. We provide nanoscale mapping of the magnetic domain evolution on cooling and correlate the local stray fields with global magnetometry and anomalous Hall effect measurements. We observe the formation of a disordered, dendritic domain structure whose roughness is quantified using its fractal dimension. The fractal dimension steadily increases on cooling through the transition, saturating at a value of ~ 1.55 in the non-collinear phase, but the domain area distribution does not show any significant changes. We show this behaviour cannot be explained by the balance of demagnetisation energy and domain wall energy, and conclude elastic contributions and defects are a critical factor to explain the domain size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06895v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Freya Johnson (Cavendish Laboratory, University of Cambridge), Jan Zemen (Faculty of Electrical Engineering, Czech Technical University in Prague), Helena Knowles (Cavendish Laboratory, University of Cambridge), Lesley F. Cohen (Department of Physics, Blackett Laboratory, Imperial College London)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic-Field-Induced Geometric Response of Mean-Field Projectors: Streda Formula and Orbital Magnetization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07001</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07001v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the magnetic-field response of interacting electron systems within mean-field theory using perturbation theory. We show that the linear response of the mean-field density-matrix to a weak magnetic field is purely geometric: it depends only on wavefunction derivatives, the Berry connections linking the occupied and unoccupied subspaces, and is independent of the interaction potential and the quasiparticle dispersion. This leads to compact, gauge-invariant projector expressions for both the St\v{r}eda formula and the formula for orbital magnetization. Our calculation explicitly elucidates the role of exchange and self-consistency in defining current vertices for orbital magnetization calculations. Our work establishes a direct connection between mean-field theory, quantum geometry and the non-interacting topological band theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07001v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jihang Zhu, Chunli Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous strain-dependent thermal conductivity in superelastic screw-dislocated graphites</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07075</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07075v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The design of strain-stable, or even strain-enhanced thermal transport materials is critical for stable operation of high-performance electronic devices. However, most nanomaterials suffer from strain-induced degradation, with even minor tensile strains markedly reducing thermal conductivity. Here, we demonstrate that screw-dislocated graphites (SDGs), recently identified as topological semimetals, display an unusual increase in cross-plane thermal conductivity under both tensile and compressive strains, revealed by high-accuracy machine-learning-potential-driven non-equilibrium molecular dynamics. Notably, SDGs exhibit over 100% enhancement under tensile strains up to 80% along the dislocation axis, arising from strain-induced increase in dislocation interface tilt angle that elongates the effective heat transfer paths. Their thermal conductivity surpasses multilayer graphene by an order of magnitude. An analytical model is further derived linking thermal conductivity to dislocation number and strain, offering a predictive framework for designing strain-tunable screwdislocated structures. These findings highlight SDGs as a promising platform for high-performance electronic and wearable devices with tunable thermal properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07075v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Li, Zhiqiang Zhao, Zhuhua Zhang, Yong-Wei Zhang, Jin-Wu Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tangent space Krylov computation of real-frequency spectral functions: Influence of density-assisted hopping on 2D Mott physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07279</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07279v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a tangent-space Krylov (TaSK) method for efficient computation of zero-temperature real-frequency spectral functions on top of ground state (GS) matrix product states (MPS) obtained from the Density Matrix Renormalization Group. It relies on projecting resolvents to the tangent space of the GS-MPS, where they can be efficiently represented using Krylov space techniques. This allows for a direct computation of spectral weights and their corresponding positions on the real-frequency axis. We demonstrate the accuracy and efficiency of the TaSK approach by showcasing spectral data for various models. These include the 1D Haldane-Shastry and Heisenberg models as benchmarks. As an interesting application, we study the Hubbard model on a cylinder at half-filling, augmented by a density-assisted hopping (DAH) term. We find that DAH leads to particle-hole asymmetric single-particle mobilities and lifetimes in the resulting Mott insulator, and identify the responsible scattering processes. Further, we find that DAH influences the dispersion of Green's function zeros beyond its range, which has a frustrating effect on the Mott insulator studied here.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07279v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleksandra Kovalska, Jan von Delft, Andreas Gleis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scattering of a Dirac particle by a Berry phase domain wall</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12848</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.12848v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Massless Dirac particles are characterized by an effective pseudospin-momentum locking, which is the origin of the peculiar scattering properties of Dirac particles through potential barriers. This pseudospin-momentum locking also governs the quantum geometric properties (such as the Berry phase and Berry curvature) of Dirac particles. In the present work, we demonstrate that a domain wall separating two regions with distinct quantum geometric properties can serve as an alternative to potential barriers. Specifically, using the three-band $\alpha-T_3$ model of two-dimensional Dirac particles, we show that a Berry phase domain wall results in partial reflection and transmission of the Dirac particles, despite the fact that the incident and refracted momenta are identical.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.12848v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/9gt4-3pwl</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 155402 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lassaad Mandhour, Farah Bouhadida, Fr\'ed\'eric Pi\'echon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fe contribution to the magnetic anisotropy of $L{1_0}$-ordered FePt thin films studied by angle-dependent x-ray magnetic circular dichroism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24385v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Among magnetic thin films with perpendicular magnetic anisotropy (PMA), $L1_0$-ordered FePt has attracted significant attention because of its exceptionally strong PMA. However, the microscopic origin of its strong PMA has not been elucidated experimentally. We have investigated the contribution of the Fe $3d$ electrons to its magnetic anisotropy energy by angle-dependent x-ray magnetic circular dichroism at the Fe $L_{2,3}$ edge. By this technique, one can deduce the magnetic dipole moment $m_\text{T}$, which represents the anisotropic spatial distribution of spin-polarized electrons, and the orbital moment anisotropy (OMA) of Fe $3d$ electrons. Detected finite $m_\text{T}$ indicates that the spin-polarized Fe $3d$ electrons are distributed preferentially in the out-of-plane direction of the films. This $m_\text{T}$ of Fe overwhelms the positive contribution of OMA to PMA, and reduces the PMA of $L1_0$-ordered FePt thin films, consistent with a previous first-principles calculation. The present result implies that a large positive contribution of the non-magnetic element Pt rather than Fe governs the PMA of $L1_0$-ordered FePt thin films.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24385v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0283193</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Appl. Phys. Lett. 127, 142406 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Goro Shibata, Keisuke Ikeda, Takeshi Seki, Shoya Sakamoto, Yosuke Nonaka, Zhendong Chi, Yuxuan Wan, Masahiro Suzuki, Tsuneharu Koide, Hiroki Wadati, Koki Takanashi, Atsushi Fujimori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frequency as a Clock: Synchronization and Intrinsic Recovery in Graphene Transistor Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08728</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08728v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Hysteresis and memory effects in graphene field-effect transistors (GFETs) offer unique opportunities for neuromorphic computing, sensing, and memory applications, yet their physical origins remain debated due to competing volatile and nonvolatile interpretations. Here, we present a unified dynamic model that captures the essential physics of the GFET response under periodic gate modulation, accounting for both intrinsic relaxation processes and externally driven charge transfer. By modeling non-equilibrium carrier dynamics as a competition between injection and reabsorption rates, we uncover two distinct regimes: one governed by intrinsic, frequency-independent relaxation and another exhibiting frequency-locked behavior where the response is tied to the external drive. This distinction resolves apparent nonvolatile effects and explains loop invariance in floating-gate structures via displacement current-driven charge injection. Our framework predicts the evolution of the hysteresis loop shape, amplitude, and direction across a wide range of driving conditions, offering a versatile tool for interpreting experimental results and guiding the design of next-generation graphene-based electronic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08728v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor Lopez-Richard, Igor Ricardo Filgueira e Silva, Gabriel L. Rodrigues, Rafael Furlan de Oliveira, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Alisson R. Cadore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resonant current-in-plane spin-torque diode effect in magnet$-$normal metal bilayers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08428v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Via the spin-Hall effect and its inverse, in-plane charge currents in a normal metal$-$ferromagnet (N$|$F) bilayer can be used to excite and detect magnetization dynamics in F. Using a magneto-electric circuit approach, we here consider the current response to quadratic order in the applied electric field, which is resonantly enhanced for driving frequencies close to frequencies of coherent magnetization modes. Our theory can be applied to bilayers with a magnetic insulator or with a magnetic metal. It focuses on the contribution of coherent magnetization dynamics to spin currents collinear with the equilibrium magnetization direction, but also takes into account relaxation of spin accumulation via spin currents carried by incoherent magnons and conduction electrons in F.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08428v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ulli Gems, Oliver Franke, Piet W. Brouwer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Refined spin Hamiltonian on the Cairo pentagonal lattice of Bi2Fe4O9</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04793</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04793v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The frustrated magnet Bi2Fe4O9 has been reported to exhibit complex spin dynamics coexisting with conventional spin wave excitations. The magnetic Fe3+ (S = 5/2) ions are arranged into a distorted two-dimensional Cairo pentagonal lattice with weak couplings between the layers, developing long-ranged non-collinear antiferromagnetic order below 245 K. In order to enable studies and modelling of the complex dynamics close to TN, we have reexamined the magnetic excitations across the complete energy scale (0 &lt; E &lt; 90 meV) at 10 K. We discover two distinct gaps, which can be explained by introducing, respectively, easy axis and easy plane anisotropy on the two unequivalent Fe-sites. We develop a refined spin Hamiltonian that accurately accounts for the dispersion of essentially all spin-wave branches across the full spectral range, except around 40 meV, where a splitting and dispersion are observed. We propose that this mode is derived from phonon hybridization. Polarisation analysis shows that the system has magnetic anisotropic fluctuations, consistent with our model. A continuum of scattering is observed above the spin wave branches and is found to principally be explained by an instrumental resolution effect. The full experimental mapping of the excitation spectrum and the refined spin Hamiltonian provides a foundation for future quantitative studies of spin waves coexisting with unconventional magnetic fluctuations in this frustrated magnet found at higher temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04793v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emma Y. Lenander, Frida B. Nielsen, Jakob Lass, Ursula B. Hansen, Kristine M. L. Krighaar, Asbj{\o}rn Preuss, Tobias Weber, Mechthild Enderle, Henrik Jacobsen, Uwe Stuhr, Ryoichi Kajimoto, Mitsutaka Nakamura, Manfred Burianek, Andrea Kirsch, Henrik M. R{\o}nnow, Kim Lefmann, Pascale P. Deen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum work statistics across a critical point: full crossover from sudden quench to the adiabatic limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01601v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: When an external parameter drives a system across a quantum phase transition at a finite rate, work is performed on the system and entropy is dissipated, due to the creation of excitations via the Kibble-Zurek mechanism. Although both the adiabatic and sudden-quench limits have been studied in detail, the quantum work statistics along the crossover connecting these limits has largely been an open question. Here we obtain exact scaling functions for the work statistics along the full crossover from adiabatic to sudden-quench limits for critical quantum impurity problems, by combining linear response theory, conformal field theory, and the numerical renormalization group. These predictions can be tested in charge-multichannel Kondo quantum dot devices, where the dissipated work corresponds to the creation of nontrivial excitations such as Majorana fermions or Fibonacci anyons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01601v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/vn83-mt2v</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 130402(2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zhanyu Ma, Andrew K. Mitchell, Eran Sela</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
