<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 05:00:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Floquet-engineered Valley Topology with Anisotropic Response in 1T'-WSe2 and Janus WSeTe monolayers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17661</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17661v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Valley topology has emerged as a key concept for realizing new classes of quantum states. Here, we investigate Floquet-engineered topological phase transitions in anisotropic 1T'-WSe2 and its Janus derivative WSeTe monolayers, which exhibit valley-degenerate and valley-polarized characteristics, respectively. In 1T'-WSe2, a single topological-phase-transition (TPT) occurs from the quantum-spin-Hall state (QSH) to the quantum anomalous Hall (QAH) state, involving one spin channel at both valleys simultaneously. In contrast, Janus WSeTe undergoes a two-stage Floquet-driven TPT that occurs within a single valley and sequentially involves two spin components. The intermediate phase manifests as a valley-polarized QAH (vp-QAH) state with a finite valley Chern number, while the final phase evolves into a high-Chern-number QAH state with distinct valley gaps. Furthermore, an in-plane anisotropic response of the TPTs is predicted under oblique light incidence, reflecting the intrinsic low-symmetry nature of the lattice. These findings provide a comprehensive understanding of Floquet-engineered valley-based topological properties and offer guidance for designing light-controllable valleytronic and topological devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17661v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhe Li, Haijun Cao, Lijuan Li, Huixia Fu, Mengxue Guan, Sheng Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Functional renormalization with interaction flows: A single-boson exchange perspective and application to electron-phonon systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17697</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17697v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The functional renormalization group (fRG) is acknowledged as a powerful tool in quantum many-body physics and beyond. On the technical side, conventional implementations of the fRG rely on regulators for bare propagators only. Starting from Schwinger--Dyson and Bethe--Salpeter equations, we develop here an fRG formulation where both bare propagators and bare interactions can be dressed with regulators. The approach thus obtained is a generalization of the multiloop fRG recently introduced for many-fermion systems. Using the single-boson exchange decomposition, we show that the underlying flow equations are simply interpreted as adding a regulator to the bosonic propagator and that such an extension scarcely changes the original structure of the flow equations. Overall, we provide a framework for implementing approaches that cannot be realized with conventional fRG methods, such as temperature flows for models with retarded interactions. For concrete applications, we analyze the loop convergence of our scheme against conventional cutoff schemes for the Hubbard atom and the Anderson impurity model. Finally, we devise a new temperature-flow scheme that implements a cutoff in both the propagator and the bare interaction, and demonstrate its validity on a model of an Anderson impurity coupled to a phonon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17697v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aiman Al-Eryani, Marcel Gievers, Kilian Fraboulet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Appraising the absolute limits of nanotubes and nanospheres to preserve high-pressure materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17868</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17868v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Matter under high pressure often exhibits attractive properties, which, unfortunately, are typically irretrievable when released to ambient conditions. Intuitively, nanostructure engineering might provide a promising route to contain high-pressure phase of materials because of the exceptional mechanical strength at nanoscale. However, there is no available theoretical model that can analyze this possibility, not to mention to quantitatively evaluate the pressure-bearing capability of nano-cavities. Here, a physical model is proposed to appraise the absolute theoretical limit of various nanotubes/nanospheres to preserve high-pressure materials to ambient conditions. By incorporating with first-principles calculations, we screen and select four types of representative nanomaterials: graphene, hexagonal boron nitride (h-BN), biphenylene, and {\gamma}-graphyne, and perform systematic investigations. The results indicate that nanotube/nanosphere of graphene exhibits the best pressure-bearing capability, followed by h-BN, biphenylene and {\gamma}-graphyne. Our model reveals that the structure with the largest average binding energy per bond and the highest density of bonds will have the highest absolute limit to contain pressure materials, while electron/hole doping and interlayer interactions have minor effects. Our finding suggests that one can utilize nanotube/nanosphere with multiple layers to retrieve compressed material with higher pressures. For example, a single layer graphene sphere can retrieve compressed LaH10 with a volume size of 26 nm3 that corresponding to a pressure of 170 GPa and with a near room temperature superconductor transition of Tc=250 K. Similarly, in order to retrieve the metastable atomic hydrogen or molecular metallic hydrogen at about 250 GPa, it requires only three layers of a nanosphere to contain a volume size of 173 nm^3.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17868v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acsami.5c13946</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces 17, 60985-60996 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yin L. Xu, Guang F. Yang, Yi Sun, Hong X. Song, Yu S. Huang, Hao Wang, Xiao Z. Yan, Hua Y. Geng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hexagonal polymorphism induced structural disorder and dielectric anomalies of Ca/Mn modified BaTiO3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17940v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work involves the local structural investigation of the samples using Extended X-ray Absorption Spectra (EXAFS) analysis to investigate structural changes due to the Ca and Mn-modified BaTiO3. TEM investigation of the crystal structure reveals the coexistence of the tetragonal and hexagonal phases of BaTiO3. Band gap modification and Urbach tail variation in UV-DRS measurements reveal a reduction of band gap from UV to Visible range (3.2 eV to 2 eV). This band gap change is correlated with the valence band modification observed in PES measurements due to localised defects in the material, and supported by theoretical Density of States calculations. The electron localisation function calculation is used to analyse the changes in the localised electron density near the dopant atoms. It reveals the local expansion and contraction of the lattice surrounding the dopant atom. All these structural modifications lead to variations in the dielectric properties and diffusive nature of the phase transition. The defect-induced structural modifications, multiple phase coexistence, band gap variations and dielectric properties are explored and correlated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17940v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. Maneesha, Dilip Sasmal, Rakhi Saha, Kiran Baraik, Soma Banik, R. Mittal, Mayanak K. Gupta, Abdelkrim Mekki, Khalil Harrabi, Somaditya Sen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2D-RIXS: Resonant inelastic x-ray scattering microscopy with high energy and spatial resolutions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17966</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17966v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A two-dimensional resonant inelastic x-ray scattering (2D-RIXS) microscopy system has been developed at the beamline BL02U of NanoTerasu. The instrument combines a Wolter type-I mirror for spatial imaging with a varied-line-spacing grating spectrometer, simultaneously achieving micrometer-scale spatial resolution and ultrahigh energy resolution in the soft x-ray regime. Test chart measurements confirm a vertical spatial resolution of 1.0 um near the field-of-view center, and the horizontal resolution determined by the incident beam footprint is 0.8 um. RIXS imaging capabilities have been demonstrated by the measurements of a patterned NanoTerasu logo and exfoliated NiPS${}_3$ nanoflakes, highlighting its efficiency in locating specific microscale regions within inhomogeneous samples. These results establish 2D-RIXS microscopy as a position-sensitive probe of elementary excitations in quantum materials and functional devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17966v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kohei Yamamoto, Hakuto Suzuki, Jun Miyawaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Density functional theory for core-level X-ray absorption</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.17969v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish a rigorous density functional theory (DFT) framework for core-level X-ray absorption spectroscopy (XAS) by formulating a constrained search for core-excited states based on the Gunnarsson-Lundqvist theorem. Within this framework, the explicit-core Delta SCF scheme enables shift-free absolute edge alignment and a consistent treatment of L/M edges with spin-orbit-resolved projectors. In addition, by exploiting dipole selection rules, we recast the evaluation of the dipole matrix elements, which otherwise requires many independent Slater determinant calculations, into a compact single determinant form. This reduces the computational scaling from $\mathcal{O}(N^4)$ to $\mathcal{O}(N^3)$, where $N$ is the number of electrons, without introducing additional approximations. Across representative C, B, O, and Li K-edge benchmarks in molecules and solids, the method reproduces line shapes, polarization anisotropies, and absolute onsets without empirical shifts, providing a robust and scalable route to quantitatively reliable XAS simulations within DFT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.17969v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seokkyu An, Taisuke Ozaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Many-body electronic structure in pyrochlore superconductor CsBi2 and spin liquid Pr2Ir2O7</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18059</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18059v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The pyrochlore lattice materials can exhibit geometrical frustration, while the related many-body electronic states remain elusive. In this work, we performed scanning tunneling microscopy measurements on the pyrochlore superconductor CsBi2 and spin liquid Pr2Ir2O7 at 0.3 K. For the first time, we obtained atomically resolved images of their (111) surfaces, revealing a hexagonal lattice or a kagome lattice. Tunneling spectroscopy in CsBi2 reveals a nearly fully opened superconductivity gap. The ratio of 2{\Delta}/kBTC = 4.7 suggests relatively strong coupling superconductivity, as compared with that in kagome superconductors AV3Sb5 (A = K, Rb, Cs). In contrast to the previous study categorizing CsBi2 as a type-I superconductor, the applied magnetic field induces a hexagonal vortex lattice in which each vortex core exhibits an intriguing three-fold symmetry state. In Pr2Ir2O7, we observed a spatially homogeneous Kondo-lattice resonance, which is compared with that in the kagome Kondo-lattice material CsCr6Sb6. We further discover that the Kondo resonance exhibits a spatial modulation with three-fold symmetry, and the applied magnetic field induces a Zeeman splitting of the Kondo resonance with intriguing atomic site dependence. We discuss the relations of these many-body electronic phenomena with the pyrochlore lattice geometry and its charge or spin frustration. Our systematic observations offer atomic-scale insights into the many-body electronic structures of the geometrically frustrated pyrochlore superconductors and spin liquids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18059v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Song, Guowei Liu, Hanbin Deng, Tianyu Yang, Yongkai Li, Xiao-Yu Yan, Ruoxing Liao, Qianming Wang, Jiayu Xu, Chao Yan, Yuanyuan Zhao, Hailang Qin, Da Wang, Wenchuan Jing, Dawei Shen, Kosuke Nakayama, Takafumi Sato, Chandan Setty, Desheng Wu, Boqing Song, Tianping Ying, Zhaoming Tian, Akito Sakai, Satoru Nakatsuji, Harish Kumar, Christine A. Kuntscher, Zhiwei Wang, Qi-Kun Xue, Jia-Xin Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of two-dimensional nonlocal screening on mobility of electrons in transition-metal dichalcogenide monolayers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18147</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18147v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A new mechanism for charge carrier scattering in transition-metal dichalcogenide monolayers is proposed on the basis of the theory of two-dimensional nonlocal screening developed for the dielectric function of thin-layer insulating materials (P. Cudazzo et al. PRB 84, 085406 (2011)). The expressions for the transport relaxation time and for the electron mobility are obtained for electrons scattering on Coulomb impurity centers in monolayers of transition-metal dichalcogenide on various substrates. It is found that taking nonlocal screening into account increases the mobility of electrons by several times. Although the value of the mobility decreases with increasing temperature, the relative enhancement due to nonlocal screening grows 6-9 times at room temperature, in the case of SiO$_2$ substrate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18147v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aram Manaselyan, Vram Mughnetsyan, Anna Asatryan, Albert Kirakosyan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tuning Breakdown-to-Coercive Field Ratio in Ultra-Thin Al1-xScxN Films via Reactive Nitrogen Atmosphere</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18160</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18160v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Al1-xScxN has attracted significant interest due to its large remnant polarization and low processing temperature when compared to other ferroelectric material systems. However, device dielectric failure before ferroelectric switching remains a critical limitation for AlScN-based memory devices. With the continuing trend toward device miniaturization, expanding the operating window is essential for next-generation memory development. In this work, we optimized the breakdown field (EBD) and coercive field (EC) in ultra-thin Al1-xScxN films by controlling defect density via adjustment of nitrogen gas flow during sputter deposition. The characteristic breakdown field, EBD, was evaluated using Weibull statistics, yielding optimal characteristic breakdown fields of 12.47 MV/cm (EBD+) and -12.63 MV/cm (EBD-) for samples deposited under 27.5 sccm N2 flow. The minimum EC was achieved at a nitrogen flow of 25 sccm and increased for higher gas flows, a trend that is opposite to previous reports in much thicker films. The highest EBD over EC ratio of 2.25 occurred at 27.5 sccm, effectively expanding the operational window. Using a combination of X-ray diffraction and photoluminescence spectroscopy to study changes in crystal orientation and defects, device performance can be tuned by controlling the point defect concentration in the ultra-thin film via adjusting the sputtering N2 process gas flow rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18160v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yinuo Zhang, Walter J. Smith, Giovanni Esteves, Eric A. Stach, Thomas E. Beechem, Roy H. Olsson III</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparison of the Electronic Structures of V$X_3$ ($X$ = Br, and I) using High-resolution X-ray Scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18168</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18168v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Transition-metal halides V$X_3$ ($X$ = Br and I) have emerged as promising candidates for two dimensional spintronic and quantum applications due to their layer-dependent magnetism and tunable electronic states. However, experimental insights into their ground state electronic structures remain limited. Here, we present a comprehensive investigation of V$X_3$ using high resolution resonant inelastic x-ray scattering (RIXS) combined with ligand field multiplet calculations. The RIXS spectra reveal distinct $dd$ and charge-transfer excitations, allowing precise determination of electronic structure parameters, including the crystal field splitting, trigonal distortion, and Racah parameters. The determined parameters showed clear variation, indicating an increase in covalency from Br to I. The trigonal distortion parameters $\Delta_{D_{3d}}$ were determined to be -0.096 eV in VBr$_3$ and 0.07 eV in VI$_3$, indicating a sign opposition between the two compounds, reflecting good agreement with experimental RIXS data. Cluster model calculations yield a high-spin V$^{3+}$ $(S = 1)$ configuration, with an $e'^2_g$ ground state in VBr$_3$ and an $e'^1_ga^1_{1g}$ ground state in VI$_3$, consistent with trigonal elongation and compression, respectively. Our findings provide the most complete experimental determination of the low energy electronic structure in V$X_3$, offering valuable insights for designing 2D magnetic and spintronic materials based on vanadium halides.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18168v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chamini S. Pathiraja, Deniz Wong, Christian Schulz, Yi-De Chuang, Yu-Cheng Shao, Byron Freelon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Engineering the Magnetocaloric Effect in Nd$T_4$B</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18195v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive study of the magnetocaloric effect (MCE) in the Nd$T_4$B system where $T$ = Fe, Co, and Ni. These compounds are ferromagnetic kagome materials with tunable ordering temperatures, transition width, and magnetic moments depending on the choice of transition metal. Thus, they are good candidates for investigating the MCE. We characterize the MCE using standard metrics and construct ternary phase diagrams as functions of Fe, Co, and Ni concentrations. Using these phase diagrams, we engineer the composition NdFe$_{1.15}$Co$_{0.46}$Ni$_{2.39}$B to maximize the MCE. Interestingly, the Nd$T_4$B system shows a notable entropy change over a wide temperature range ($\sim$10 to 650 K), and particular compositions have notable MCEs spanning hundreds of Kelvin, making this a suitable system to study for technologies used in a wide range of temperatures. In a few cases, we observe a two-peak MCE. These two transitions, releasing comparable entropy, provide an interesting platform to study for applications in multi-stage cooling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18195v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kyle W. Fruhling, Enrique O. Gonz\'alez Delgado, Siddharth Nandanwar, Xiaohan Yao, Zafer Turgut, Michael A. Susner, Fazel Tafti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Possibilities of the X-ray Diffraction Data Processing Method for Detecting Reflections with Intensity Below the Background Noise Component</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18311</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18311v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The values of the signal-to-noise ratio are determined, at which the method of processing X-ray diffraction data reveals reflections with intensity less than the noise component of the background. The possibilities of the method are demonstrated on weak reflections of $\alpha$-quartz. The method of processing X-ray diffraction data makes it possible to increase the possibilities of X-ray phase analysis in determining the qualitative phase composition of multiphase materials with a small (down to $0.1$ wt. \%) content of several (up to eight) phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18311v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/S0885715624000241</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Powder Diffraction 39 132-143 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>S. V. Gabielkov, I. V. Zhyganiuk, A. D. Skorbun, V. G. Kudlai, B. S. Savchenko, P. E. Parkhomchuk, S. O. Chikolovets</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-space formulation of the Chern invariant and topological phases in a disordered Chern insulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18332</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18332v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we formulate the real-space Chern number in a supercell framework. In this framework, the overlap matrix between two corners of the Brillouin zone (BZ) is derived from diagonalizing the real-space Hamiltonian with periodic boundary conditions. The pass-ordered product of overlap matrices around the BZ boundary forms a Wilson loop, and defines the Chern number in real space. It is analytically shown that the real-space Chern number is quantized at integers for large enough systems and coincides with the Bott index used in the previous studies. The formulation is greatly simplified for the former so that it makes numerical computations more efficient. The real-space formula is used to numerically elucidate topological phases in a disordered Chern insulator. The Chern insulator is modeled by dimensional extension of the Rice-Mele (RM) model consisting of two sublattices, and is disordered by including a random onsite potential. As disorder strength increases, the nontrivial-to-trivial phase transition takes place for normal disorder with no sublattice polarization. By contrast, the phase diagram is almost unaffected by polarized disorder, indicating that nontrivial topology persists against disorder. These observations are supported by the linear conductance and the density of bulk states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18332v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kiminori Hattori, Shinji Nakata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of topological phases without crystalline counterparts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18357</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18357v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Topological phases have been extensively studied primarily in crystalline systems with translational symmetry. Recent theoretical studies, however, have demonstrated the existence of topological phases in quasicrystals that are absent in crystals. Despite numerous experimental observations of topological phases in various crystalline systems, observing these phases without crystalline counterparts remains challenging due to very complex models. Here, we design a practically realizable tight-binding model with nearest-neighbor hopping on the Ammann-Beenker quasicrystalline lattice. This model respects eight-fold rotational and chiral symmetries, resulting in a higher-order topological phase with eight zero-energy corner modes that have no crystalline counterparts. We experimentally explore the topological phase in an acoustic quasicrystal. Surprisingly, we also discover symmetry-protected zero-energy modes near the center of the quasicrystal in a topologically trivial phase, a phenomenon not seen in crystals. We further experimentally observe these modes in a topologically trivial acoustic quasicrystal. Our work represents the first experimental observation of topological phases in quasicrystals without crystalline counterparts, paving the way for the study of exotic topological physics in quasicrystals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18357v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mou Yan, Yu-Liang Tao, Yichong Hu, Zhenxing Cui, Jiong-Hao Wang, Gang Chen, Yong Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High accuracy Spin Hall Effect Induced Spin Accumulation detection in MOKE Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18443v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Charge to spin (orbital) momentum conversion phenomena enclose great potential for advancing applications in spin/orbitronics. Although current-induced magnetic moment accumulation is crucial both for fundamental understanding and practical applications, direct quantifications are scarce. Optical polarization measurements, namely magneto-optical Kerr rotation (MOKE) ($\theta_K$), have been used to get direct evidence of magnetic accumulation perpendicular to a current flow density ($J$) in late transition metals (Pt) as well as in light transition elements (Ti, Cr), and used to conclude evidence of spin or orbital momentum accumulation. However, discrepancies of the reported $\theta_K/J$ values, exceeding one order of magnitude, together with early claims that conventional MOKE experiments were not a suitable tool, is prompting revisions of methods and results. Here, we report on a new methodology for MOKE measurements that solves known bottlenecks. We obtain a sensitivity of $(354 \pm 27)$ nV/nrad and use the designed protocol to measure $|\theta_K^S/J| = (7.92 \pm 1.94)$ nrad/$(10^7$ A/cm$^2)$ and $|\theta_K^P/J| = (6.89 \pm 1.74)$ nrad/$(10^7$ A/cm$^2)$ in a 50 nm thick Pt bar for S and P polarized incident light, respectively.The extracted value of $|\theta_K^S/J|$ is significantly smaller, about a 7-fold reduction, than previous results on a nominally identical device. Given that differences in the microstructure of Pt films cannot account for such large discrepancy, this implies that experimental procedures and models should be revised accordingly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18443v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emanuele Longo, Josep Fontcuberta, Paolo Vavassori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Light-engineered Multichannel Quantum Anomalous Hall Effect in High-order Topological Plumbene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18520</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18520v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Floquet engineering severs as a forceful technique for uncovering high Chern numbers of quantum anomalous Hall (QAH) states with feasible tunability in high-order topologically insulating plumbene, which is readily accessible for experimental investigations. Under the irradiation of righthanded circularly polarized light, we predict a three-stage topological phase transition in plumbene, whether it is in a free-standing form or grown on h-BN. Initially, a metallic state evolves into a K(K')-valley-based QAH state with a Chern number of -8, which then decreases to -6 after the valley gap closes. Finally, a band inversion occurs at the $\Gamma$ point, resulting in a multichannel QAH state with C = -3. The trigonal warping model accounts for both K(K')-valley-based and $\Gamma$-pointbased QAH states. Additionally, growing plumbene on a non-van-der-Waals substrate eliminates the K(K')-valley-based topology, leaving only the $\Gamma$-point-based QAH state with C = +3. Our findings propose the tunability of various high Chern numbers derived from high-order topological insulators, aiming to advance the next-generation dissipationless electronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18520v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhe Li, Fangyang Zhan, Haijun Cao, Jingjing Cao, Huisheng Zhang, Sheng Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ab initio modeling of resonant inelastic x-ray scattering from Ca2RuO4</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18526v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The single-layered perovskite Ca$_2$RuO$_4$, characterized by a 4$d^4$ electron configuration, has been studied from first principles using density functional theory (DFT) using the generalized gradient approximation, with inclusion of strong on-site Coulomb interactions and spin-orbit coupling (GGA+SO+$U$), in the framework of the fully relativistic, spin-polarized Dirac linear muffin-tin orbital (LMTO) band-structure method. This approach enabled a comprehensive investigation of the electronic structure of Ca$_2$RuO$_4$ through the modeling of relevant spectra obtained from synchrotron-based techniques widely used to probe electronic properties, with a primary focus on resonant inelastic X-ray scattering (RIXS) at the Ru $L_3$ and O $K$ edges. The calculated spectra were thoroughly analyzed with available experimental data reported in the literature. The good agreement between our results and experimental observations for Ca$_2$RuO$_4$ enables a conclusive interpretation of key features in the spectra obtained from the aforementioned techniques. Consequently, this enables us to describe its electronic properties and to establish a solid theoretical approach suitable for routine modeling of spectra, particularly from RIXS, aimed at characterizing the electronic structure and properties of similar or more complex strongly correlated, technologically relevant materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18526v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. A. Kukusta (G.V. Kurdyumov Institute for Metal Physics of the N.A.S. of Ukraine, Kyiv, Ukraine), L. V. Bekenov (G.V. Kurdyumov Institute for Metal Physics of the N.A.S. of Ukraine, Kyiv, Ukraine), P. F. Perndorfer (Institute for Theoretical Physics, Johannes Kepler University, Linz, Austria, Department of Engineering and Computer Sciences, Hamburg University of Applied Sciences, Hamburg, Germany), D. V. Vyalikh (Donostia International Physics Center, IKERBASQUE, Basque Foundation for Science, Bilbao, Spain), P. A. Buczek (Department of Engineering and Computer Sciences, Hamburg University of Applied Sciences, Hamburg, Germany), A. Ernst (Institute for Theoretical Physics, Johannes Kepler University, Linz, Austria, Max Planck Institute of Microstructure Physics, Halle), V. N. Antonov (G.V. Kurdyumov Institute for Metal Physics of the N.A.S. of Ukraine, Kyiv, Ukraine, Max Planck Institute for Solid State Research, Stuttgart, Germany)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Competition between charge-density-wave and superconducting orders on eight-leg square Hubbard cylinders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18644</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18644v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The issue of whether $d$-wave superconductivity (SC) occurs in the square-lattice Hubbard model with $U$ of order of the bandwidth has been one of the most debated issues to emerge from the study of high temperature SC. Here, we report variational results on eight-leg cylinders with next-nearest-neighbor hopping in the range $-0.5 t \leq t'\leq 0.25 t$ with $U = 8t$ and $12t$ and doped hole concentrations $\delta=1/12$ and $1/8$. For $t'\leq 0$, the ground-state appears to be a charge-density wave (CDW) of one sort or another with SC correlations that are extremely short-ranged. In contrast, in some cases, the local magnetic order has a correlation length greater than half the cylinder width - suggestive that magnetic order might also arise in the 2D limit. For $t'&gt;0$, our results depend more strongly on boundary conditions (periodic vs antiperiodic), making it still harder to correctly guess whether SC or CDW correlations dominate in the 2D limit. These results were obtained employing matrix-product states with bond dimensions large enough that energy differences as small as $10^{-3}t$ per site can be resolved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18644v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hong-Chen Jiang, Thomas P. Devereaux, Steven A. Kivelson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microscopic parameters of a type-II superconductor measured by small-angle neutron scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18736v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A necessary condition for understanding and predicting the properties of any material is knowledge of microscopic parameters which control these properties. In superconductors these parameters are the radius of the orbital motion of electrons bound in Cooper pairs $R_0$ and the radius of the field-induced currents $r_i$ caused by precession of the pairs; one more parameter, associated with $r_i$, is the number density of Cooper pairs $n_{cp}$. In this communication we report on the first measurements of these parameters in a type-II superconductor (niobium) by SANS (small-angle neutron scattering). Other approaches potentially applicable for measuring the microscopic parameters are considered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18736v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Alba Venero, A. -M. Valente-Feliciano, O. O. Bernal, V. Kozhevnikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strain-induced Berry phase in chiral superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18753</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18753v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the topology of the order parameter in the intermediate phase between the superconducting and time-reversal symmetry breaking transitions of a $p_x+ip_y$ superconductor under strain. The application of in-plane strain reduces the underlying crystal symmetry and lifts the degeneracy of the critical temperature between the $p_x$ and $p_y$ orbitals, resulting in a Dirac cone structure in the thermodynamic phase diagram. When the strain is varied adiabatically along a closed path enclosing the Dirac cone, the order parameter acquires a Berry phase of $\pi$, which originates from a half rotation of the superconducting gap function. This half rotation leaves a topological signature in the superfluid stiffness tensor, making it directly observable through the geometry of vortices and the upper critical field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18753v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Canon Sun, Marcel Franz, Joseph Maciejko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting Linear Dichroism with Atomic Resolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18796</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18796v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: X-ray linear dichroism has been pivotal for probing electronic anisotropies, but its inherent limited spatial resolution precludes atomic-scale investigations of orbital polarization. Here we introduce a versatile electron linear dichroism methodology in scanning transmission electron microscopy that overcomes these constraints. By exploiting momentum-transfer-dependent electron energy-loss spectroscopy with an atomic-sized probe, we directly visualize orbital occupation at individual atomic columns in real space. Using strained La0.7Sr0.3MnO3 thin films as a model system, we resolve the Mn-3d eg orbital polarization with sub-angstrom precision. We show that compressive strain stabilizes 3z2-r2 occupation while tensile strain favors x2-y2. These results validate our approach against established X-ray measurements while achieving the ultimate single atomic-column sensitivity. We further demonstrate two optimized signal extraction protocols that adapt to experimental constraints without compromising sensitivity. This generalizable platform opens unprecedented opportunities to study symmetry-breaking phenomena at individual defects, interfaces, and in quantum materials where atomic-scale electronic anisotropy governs emergent functionality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18796v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roger Guzman, J\'an Rusz, Ang Li, Juan Carlos Idrobo, Wu Zhou, Jaume Gazquez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of Dicke cooperativity between strongly coupled phonons and crystal-field excitations in a rare-earth orthoferrite</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18862</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18862v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Collective interactions between localized electronic excitations and the crystal lattice are central to many emergent phenomena in materials, including ferroelectricity and quantum magnetism. Despite its importance, the scaling behavior of such cooperativity remains largely unexplored. Here, we report the direct observation of Dicke-type cooperativity arising from the coupled phonons and non-degenerate crystal-field transitions (CFE), namely a pseudo-Jahn-Teller effect1, in the rare-earth orthoferrite, ErFeO3. Using magneto-Raman spectroscopy, we uncover strongly coupled spin, lattice, and orbital excitations. By varying the temperature, we identify the phonon-CFE coupling strength scales as sqrt(N), where N represents the effective ground-state population, which is a hallmark of Dicke cooperativity. Our findings verified the cooperative nature of the interaction between local Jahn-Teller ions and long-range phonons, offering a pathway for tailoring electronic and vibrational properties of materials through population control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18862v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fangliang Wu, Xiaoxuan Ma, Zhongwei Zhang, Motoaki Bamba, Jian Sun, Yuan Wan, Shixun Cao, Qi Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Giant Domain Walls and Intrinsic Heterogeneity in 214 Cuprate Superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18938</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18938v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The intricate interplay of structural, charge and spin orders in layered cuprates leads to emergent phenomena, most notably high-temperature superconductivity. However, there is growing awareness that both the structure and electronic ordering that underpin them are not fully homogeneous. Here, we employ scanning three-dimensional X-ray diffraction to spatially resolve structural distortions in La$_{1.675}$Eu$_{0.2}$Sr$_{0.125}$CuO$_{4}$, a prototypical system that exhibits a strong competition between superconductivity and charge density wave order, across its low-temperature orthorhombic to tetragonal phase transition. We uncover two forms of intrinsic microstructural heterogeneity: at 300 K, we reveal remarkably wide tetragonal-like domain wall regions within the nominally orthorhombic crystal structure, and, upon cooling to 100 K, a fine microstructure of orthorhombic-like stripes embedded within the tetragonal matrix emerges. This spatially resolved view directly defines the microstructural architecture of phase coexistence in this system, demonstrating how structural distortions generate intrinsic heterogeneity that shapes the balance between superconductivity and charge density wave order as constrained by the restrictive orthorhombic and tetragonal structures, offering a pathway to control correlated phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18938v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark S. Senn, Evie Ladbrook, Jon Wright</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Web of Non-invertible Dualities for (2+1) Dimensional Models with Subsystem Symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18969v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We extend non-invertible duality concepts from one-dimensional systems to two spatial dimensions by constructing a web of non-invertible dualities for lattice models with subsystem symmetries. For the $\mathbb{Z}_2 \times \mathbb{Z}_2$ subsystem symmetry on the square lattice, we build two complementary dualities: a map that sends spontaneous subsystem symmetry-broken (SSSB) phases to the trivial phase (the analogue of the Kramers-Wannier (KW) duality in 1+1D), and a generalized subsystem Kennedy-Tasaki (KT) transformation that maps SSSB phases to subsystem symmetry-protected topological (SSPT) phases while leaving the trivial phase invariant. These dualities are boundary-sensitive. On open lattices, both subsystem KW and KT transformations act as unitary, invertible operators. In particular, the KT map not only matches the bulk Hamiltonians of the dual phases but also carries the spontaneous ground-state degeneracy of the SSSB phase onto the protected boundary degeneracy of the SSPT phase. On closed manifolds, however, both maps become intrinsically non-unitary and non-invertible when restricted to the original Hilbert space. We demonstrate this non-invertibility via ground-state degeneracy matching (in two copies of the Xu-Moore/Ising-plaquette model), analysis of symmetry-twist sectors mapping, and the fusion algebra of the duality operator. Enlarging the Hilbert space to include twisted sectors allows the subsystem KW map to be formulated as a projective unitary preserving quantum transition probabilities, consistent with generalized Wigner-theorem-based constructions. We also show that the KT map faithfully transmits the algebraic content of bulk and edge invariants diagnosing strong SSPT order: although strictly local SSPT repair operators map to highly nonlocal objects in the dual SSSB phase, the essential commutation algebra and the bulk-edge correspondence remain intact.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18969v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Avijit Maity, Vikram Tripathi, Andriy H. Nevidomskyy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Al$_{1-x}$Hf$_{x}$N Thin Films with Enhanced Piezoelectric Responses for GHz Surface Acoustic Wave Devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18970</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18970v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ternary compounds obtained by alloying wurtzite AlN with transition metals have emerged as promising materials with significantly enhanced piezoelectric characteristics relative to binary AlN. The increased electromechanical coupling in these compounds boosts the performance of high-frequency acoustic devices. So far, progress has largely focused on Al$_{1-x}$Sc$_x$N, which is costly and poorly compatible with complementary metal-oxide-semiconductor (CMOS) technologies. Here, we investigate aluminum hafnium nitride (Al$_{1-x}$Hf$_{x}$N) as a scalable and potentially CMOS-compatible alternative to Al$_{1-x}$Sc$_x$N. Using reactive co-sputtering on both Si and sapphire substrates, we demonstrate wurtzite Al$_{1-x}$Hf$_{x}$N thin films ($x \leq 0.17$) with strong $c$-axis texture and nearly isotropic lattice expansion upon Hf incorporation. X-ray absorption spectroscopy indicates cross-gap hybridization between N 2$p$ and Hf 5$d$ states, which can enhance the Born effective charge and, thereby, the piezoelectric response. Correspondingly, we observe a nearly two-fold enhancement in the piezoelectric coefficient, $d_{33}$, relative to AlN, despite increasing structural disorder in Al$_{1-x}$Hf$_{x}$N. Building on this finding, we demonstrate Al$_{1-x}$Hf$_{x}$N GHz surface acoustic wave (SAW) resonators that exhibit enhanced performance, as well as efficient excitation of bulk acoustic waves with low propagation losses. These results establish Al$_{1-x}$Hf$_{x}$N as a promising platform for next-generation high-frequency electromechanical devices, with prospects for further piezoelectric enhancements through improved epitaxy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18970v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laura I. Wagner, Verena Streibel, Esperanza Luna, Katarina S. Flashar, Walid Anders, Nicole Volkmer, Doreen Steffen, Frans Munnik, Tsedenia A. Zewdie, Saswati Santra, Ian D. Sharp, Mingyun Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clustering-Enhanced Time- and Angle-Resolved Photoemission Study of LaTe$_3$: Absence of a Photoinduced Secondary CDW in the Electronic Structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18974</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18974v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Optical control offers a compelling route for tailoring material properties on an ultrafast time scale. Ordered states such as charge density waves (CDWs) can be transiently melted by an ultrafast light excitation. This is also the case for the rare-earth tritelluride LaTe$_3$, a prototypical CDW compound. For this material it has recently been reported that the suppression of the primary CDW allows the transient formation of a second CDW, whose wave vector is orthogonal to the primary one. This creates the intriguing scenario where light enables switching between two distinct ordered phases of the material. While the second CDW has so far been observed by structural techniques, it remains an open question how the interplay of the two CDW phases is reflected in the material's electronic structure. We investigate this via time- and angle-resolved photoemission measurements of LaTe$_3$. The complex Fermi contour is probed using a FeSuMa analyzer, which records the photoemission intensity of the entire Fermi contour at once. The dynamics revealed by the FeSuMa analyzer are complemented by measurements using a conventional hemispherical electron analyzer. We combine conventional data analysis with $k$-means clustering, an unsupervised machine learning technique, demonstrating its strong potential for disentangling large datasets. While we do not find any features that cannot be explained by the melting and re-establishment of the primary CDW, distinct dynamics and coherent oscillations are observed in the different branches of the Fermi contour.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18974v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gesa-R. Siemann, Davide Curcio, Anders S. Mortensen, Charlotte E. Sanders, Yu Zhang, Jennifer Rigden, Paulina Majchrzak, Deepnarayan Biswas, Emma Springate, Ratnadwip Singha, Leslie M. Schoop, Philip Hofmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Combined Theoretical and Experimental Study of Oxygen Vacancies in Co$_3$O$_4$ for Liquid-Phase Oxidation Catalysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19060</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19060v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the present work, we investigate oxygen vacancies (V$_\mathrm{O}$) in Co$_3$O$_4$, both in the bulk phase and under liquid-phase ethylene glycol oxidation, by combining theoretical and experimental techniques. Density functional theory calculations for bulk Co$_3$O$_4$ show that introducing an oxygen vacancy reduces two adjacent Co$^{3+}$ ions to Co$^{2+}$ and narrows the band gap. The newly formed Co$^{2+}$ ions adopt high-spin configurations in distorted octahedral sites and remain stable in this state in ab initio molecular dynamics simulations at $300$ K. Computed O and Co K-edge X-ray absorption spectra for ideal and vacancy-containing Co$_3$O$_4$ show excellent agreement with the experimental data and serve as references to analyze the liquid-phase ethylene glycol oxidation. The comparison with experimental O K-edge spectra of fresh and post-reaction catalysts shows that fresh samples resemble the vacancy-containing reference, whereas post-reaction spectra shift toward the ideal reference. These results suggest that under liquid-phase ethylene glycol oxidation conditions, Co$_3$O$_4$ becomes more oxidized rather than reduced, by refilling preexisting oxygen vacancies. This is further supported by the observation that higher O$_2$ pressures increase the conversion and that the catalyst remains stable and active over several cycles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19060v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amir Omranpour, Lea K\"ammerer, Catalina Leiva-Leroy, Anna Rabe, Takuma Sato, Soma Salamon, Joachim Landers, Benedikt Eggert, Eugen Weschke, Jean Pascal Fandr\'e, Ashwani Kumar, Harun T\"uys\"uz, Martin Muhler, Heiko Wende, J\"org Behler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Expansion of Momentum Space and Full 2$\pi$ Solid Angle Photoelectron Collection in Laser-Based Angle-Resolved Photoemission Spectroscopy by Applying Sample Bias</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19064</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19064v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) directly probes the energy and momentum of electrons in quantum materials, but conventional setups capture only a small fraction of the full 2$\pi$ solid angle. This limitation is acute in laser-based ARPES, where the low photon energy restricts momentum space despite ultrahigh resolution. Here we present systematic studies of bias ARPES, where applying a sample bias expands the accessible momentum range and enables full 2$\pi$ solid angle collection in two dimension using our 6.994 eV laser source. An analytical conversion relation is established and validated to accurately map the detector angle to the emission angle and the electron momentum in two dimensions. A precise approach is developed to determine the sample work function which is critical in the angle-momentum conversion of the bias ARPES experiments. Energy and angular resolutions are preserved under biases up to 100 V, and minimizing beam size is shown to be crucial. The technique is effective both near normal and off-normal geometries, allowing flexible Brillouin zone access with lower biases. Bias ARPES thus elevates laser ARPES to a new level, extending momentum coverage while retaining high resolution, and is applicable across a broad photon-energy range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19064v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taimin Miao, Yu Xu, Bo Liang, Wenpei Zhu, Neng Cai, Mingkai Xu, Di Wu, Hongze Gu, Wenjin Mao, Shenjin Zhang, Fengfeng Zhang, Feng Yang, Zhimin Wang, Qinjun Peng, Zuyan Xu, Zhihai Zhu, Xintong Li, Hanqing Mao, Lin Zhao, Guodong Liu, X. J. Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-Flux Skyrmions: Anomalous Electron Dynamics and Spin-Hall Currents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19239v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a topologically distinct skyrmion, termed a spin-flux skyrmion, which shares the same real-space magnetization profile as a conventional skyrmion but differs fundamentally in its underlying topological structure. This distinction originates from the path traced by its rotation matrices within the doubly connected SO(3) group manifold, leading to a nontrivial spinor phase of $e^{i\pi}$ upon encircling the texture. Using an explicit SU(2) gauge field formalism, we derive the emergent magnetic field components generated by both conventional and spin-flux skyrmions. While conventional skyrmions exhibit a dominant $\sigma_z$ component with weak dipolar $\sigma_x, \sigma_y$ contributions, spin-flux skyrmions possess an additional monopolar $\sigma_x$ component that yields a finite average emergent field for a finite density of skyrmions. This nontrivial component introduces a nontrivial term in the Hall conductivity, enabling a direct explanation of experimental Hall resistivity anomalies that cannot be accounted for by conventional skyrmions alone. Moreover, we show that this additional term couples to the in-plane spin polarization of conduction electrons, providing a further tunable handle to control the transverse Hall response.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19239v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sandip Bera, Sajeev John</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is the signature of a trion in photoemission?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19280</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19280v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent advances in time- and angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (tr-ARPES) allow for the probing of multiparticle excited-states in reciprocal space. While neutral two-particle excitations (excitons) have been observed in tr-ARPES, signatures of trions -- three-quasiparticle bound states -- have only been probed via optical spectroscopy. Here, we develop a generic theory for the ARPES signature of trions in the model system of a monolayer transition metal dichalcogenide (TMD). We simulate the ARPES signals of both positively and negatively charged trions and show that the interaction of the residual holes, or electron and hole, lead to large energy shifts, on the order of the exciton binding energy, compared to the exciton signal. For positive trions, the additional momentum degree of freedom of the residual particles removes any strict lower bound on the photoemission energy, leading to distinctive asymmetric spectral features. For negative trions, the photoemission process causes the tr-ARPES spectrum to reproduce inverted images of the exciton band structure for multiple exciton states, encompassing both spin-allowed and spin-forbidden states, providing a direct momentum-resolved probe of both trion and exciton physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19280v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinyuan Wu, Zachary H. Withers, Thomas K. Allison, Diana Y. Qiu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diagnosis of mixed-state topological phases in strongly correlated systems via disorder parameters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19311</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19311v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Characterizing topological phases for strongly interacting fermions in the mixed-state regime remains a major challenge. Here we introduce a general and numerically efficient framework to diagnose mixed-state topological phases in strongly interacting systems via the disorder parameter (DP) of the U(1) charge operator. Specifically, from the finite-size scaling of the second derivative of the DP generating function, we introduce the topological scaling indicator, which exhibits a characteristic linear scaling with the system's linear dimension for topological phases, a signature that vanishes upon transition into a topologically trivial phase. Crucially, we develop an efficient determinant Quantum Monte Carlo algorithm that facilitates the evaluation of this indicator in interacting systems. We apply our approach to two paradigmatic models: for the Kane-Mele-Hubbard model, we successfully map the interaction-driven transition from a quantum spin Hall insulator to a trivial Mott insulator. Furthermore, our method circumvents the limitations imposed by the severe sign problem in the Haldane-Hubbard model, enabling robust identification of the quantum anomalous Hall phase at accessible temperatures. This work provides a powerful and accessible tool for the numerical exploration of topological phenomena in interacting mixed states, opening a pathway to study systems previously inaccessible due to computational obstacles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19311v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shao-Hang Shi, Xiao-Qi Sun, Zi-Xiang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-throughput validation of phase formability and simulation accuracy of Cantor alloys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19335</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19335v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High-throughput methods enable accelerated discovery of novel materials in complex systems such as high-entropy alloys, which exhibit intricate phase stability across vast compositional spaces. Computational approaches, including Density Functional Theory (DFT) and calculation of phase diagrams (CALPHAD), facilitate screening of phase formability as a function of composition and temperature. However, the integration of computational predictions with experimental validation remains challenging in high-throughput studies. In this work, we introduce a quantitative confidence metric to assess the agreement between predictions and experimental observations, providing a quantitative measure of the confidence of machine learning models trained on either DFT or CALPHAD input in accounting for experimental evidence. The experimental dataset was generated via high-throughput in-situ synchrotron X-ray diffraction on compositionally varied FeNiMnCr alloy libraries, heated from room temperature to ~1000 {\deg}C. Agreement between the observed and predicted phases was evaluated using either temperature-independent phase classification or a model that incorporates a temperature-dependent probability of phase formation. This integrated approach demonstrates where strong overall agreement between computation and experiment exists, while also identifying key discrepancies, particularly in FCC/BCC predictions at Mn-rich regions to inform future model refinement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19335v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Changjun Cheng, Daniel Persaud, Kangming Li, Michael J. Moorehead, Natalie Page, Christian Lavoie, Beatriz Diaz Moreno, Adrien Couet, Samuel E Lofland, Jason Hattrick-Simpers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kondo screening and random-singlet formation in highly disordered systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19389</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19389v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a minimal model to capture the anomalous low-temperature thermodynamics of doped semiconductors, such as Si:P, across the metal-insulator transition. We consider pairs of local magnetic moments coupled to a highly disordered, non-interacting electronic bath that undergoes a metal-insulator transition with increasing doping. Using a large-$\mathcal{N}$ variational approach, we capture both the inhomogeneous local Fermi-liquid and the insulating random-singlet phase, and find that the local moment susceptibility exhibits a robust power-law behavior, $\chi(T) \propto T^{-\alpha}$, with $\alpha$ evolving smoothly with doping before saturating in the metal. Our results highlight the competition between Kondo screening and random-singlet formation as the key ingredient in constructing a complete theory for the low-temperature behavior of strongly disordered interacting systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19389v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas G. Rabelo, Igor C. Almeida, Eduardo Miranda, Vladimir Dobrosavljevi\'c, Eric C. Andrade</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral spin liquid instability of the Kitaev honeycomb model with crystallographic defects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19409v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the spin-1/2 Kitaev honeycomb gapless spin liquid in the presence of Stone-Wales-type local lattice defects with odd-sided plaquettes. While the clean Kitaev model has no finite-temperature phase transitions, we find that introducing a finite defect density $n_d\approx 10^{-4}$--$10^{-2}$ produces a true phase transition with a sizeable $T_c \approx 2 n_d$ in units of the Kitaev exchange. The resulting non-Abelian chiral quantum spin liquid exhibits scalar spin chirality and electron orbital magnetization which peak near lattice defects. This disorder-driven instability relies on an emergent long range ferromagnetic interaction $r^{-\gamma}$ ($\gamma \approx 2.7$) between defect chiralities, mediated by the nearly-gapless fermions, with implications for topology generation in Dirac cones with fluctuating mass terms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19409v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arnab Seth, Fay Borhani, Itamar Kimchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong Energy Dependent Transition Radiation in a Photonic Crystal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18863</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18863v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Radiation of a charged particle crossing an alternating stack of slabs in the optical region is considered. Both disordered and periodic stacks are investigated. It is shown that for special type of alternating disordered and periodic stacks the radiation problem can be solved exactly for backward and forward Brewster observation angles. Strong $N^2$ dependence of radiation intensity on slab number is re-established in special case of the disordered stack. This leads to strong directivity either on forward or on backward Brewster angles depending on the type of stack randomness. In certain type of periodic photonic crystal, a strong energy dependence $E^4$ for relativistic particles of the radiation intensity, observed at Brewster's angle is found. Further increment of particle energy leads to saturation. The band structure of the corresponding photonic crystal (PhC) has a behavior, analogous to the Dirac cones in graphene. We suggest this special type $1D$ photonic crystal for application as a detector of relativistic particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18863v1</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Gareyan, Zh. Gevorkian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximate resolution convolution function for fitting a dispersion gap measured on a triple-axis spectrometer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19144</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19144v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present an analytic convoluted-gap function, eq. 11 in the manuscript, for fitting dispersion gaps measured on triple-axis spectrometers (TAS). At the gap, the instrumental resolution skews the signal, producing a high-energy tail that complicates fitting. Our function assumes an instrumental $Q$-resolution with two equal wide and one narrow direction (typical of focused TAS instruments), and a parabolic dispersion at the gap, which is exact for quadratic and accurate for linear dispersions if the resolution is moderate. We demonstrate, that our function outperforms previous methods of fitting a gap, by giving a better fit and more accurate gap determination, seen in figure 4. Here, the anti-ferromagnetically gapped material; MnF$_2$ is simulated in a double-focusing TAS instrument. We also tested our function on experimental data on MnF$_2$ from a TAS-like instrument, where we reproduce the gap size from previous accurate experimentally determined measurements. The function is simple to implement, converges reliably, and we recommend its use for future gap fitting on TAS data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19144v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emma Y. Lenander, Silas B. Schack, Kim Lefmann, Henrik M. R{\o}nnow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synchronized Aharonov-Bohm Motifs via Engineered Dissipation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19219</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19219v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The interplay between external gauge fields and lattice geometry can induce extreme localization dynamics through complete destructive interference. We show that combining this flux-induced localization with engineered dissipation leads to robust spin synchronization in rotationally symmetric spin geometries, referred to as Aharonov-Bohm motifs, with cyclic symmetries of any order. The synchronized dynamics is independent of initial conditions and features entanglement among spins within each motif. We further demonstrate that multiple motifs can fully synchronize when coupled, which is achieved by applying additional collective dissipation acting on all intra-motif spins. These results reveal a direct connection between flux-induced localization, dissipative engineering, and collective quantum synchronization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19219v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher W. W\"achtler, Gloria Platero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin Excitations and Flat Electronic Bands in a Cr-based Kagome Superconductor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05293</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05293v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the quest for topology- and correlation-driven quantum states, kagome lattice materials have garnered significant interest for their band structures, featuring flat bands (FBs) from the quantum destructive interference of the electronic wavefunction. Tuning an FB to the chemical potential could induce electronic instabilities and emergent orders. Despite extensive studies, direct evidence of FBs tuned to the chemical potential and their role in emergent orders in bulk materials remains lacking. Using angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy, resonant inelastic X-ray scattering, and density functional theory, we show that the low-energy structure of the Cr-based kagome metal superconductor {\Cr} is dominated by FBs at the Fermi level. We also observe low-energy magnetic excitations evolving across the low-temperature transition, largely consistent with the FB shift. Our results suggest that the low-temperature order contains a magnetic origin and that the kagome FBs may play a role in the emergence of this order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05293v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41467-025-62298-5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nat Commun 16, 7573 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zehao Wang, Yucheng Guo, Hsiao Yu Huang, Fang Xie, Yuefei Huang, Bin Gao, Ji Seop Oh, Han Wu, Jun Okamoto, Ganesha Channagowdra, Chien Te Chen, Feng Ye, Xingye Lu, Zhaoyu Liu, Zheng Ren, Yuan Fang, Yiming Wang, Ananya Biswas, Yichen Zhang, Ziqin Yue, Cheng Hu, Chris Jozwiak, Aaron Bostwick, Eli Rotenberg, Makoto Hashimoto, Donghui Lu, Junichiro Kono, Jiun Haw Chu, Boris I Yakobson, Robert J Birgeneau, Guang Han Cao, Atsushi Fujimori, Di Jing Huang, Qimiao Si, Ming Yi, Pengcheng Dai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global and Local Topological Crystalline Markers for Rotation-Symmetric Insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02985</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.02985v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Crystalline symmetry can be used to predict bulk and surface properties of topological phases. For non-interacting cases, symmetry-eigenvalue analysis of Bloch states at high symmetry points in the Brillouin zone simplifies the calculation of topological quantities. However, when open boundaries are present, and only the point group part of the symmetry group remains, it is unclear how to utilize crystalline symmetries to diagnose band topology. In this work, we introduce topological crystalline markers to characterize bulk topology in $C_n$-symmetric ($n=2,3,4,6$) crystalline insulators and superconductors with and without translation symmetry. These markers are expressed using a crystalline symmetry operator and the ground state projector, and are defined locally in position space. First, we provide a general method to calculate topological markers in periodic systems with an arbitrary number of unit cells. This includes cases where momentum quantization does not span all necessary high-symmetry points for computing the topological quantities, which we address using twisted boundary conditions. Second, we map these markers to the Chern number, bulk polarization, and sector charge for two-dimensional $C_n$-symmetric insulators in symmetry classes A, AI, AII, and superconductors in class D. Finally, we show how to numerically calculate the markers in finite-size systems with translation-symmetry (and even rotation-symmetry) breaking defects, and how to diagnose the bulk topology from the marker. Our results demonstrate how to compute bulk topological crystalline invariants locally in position space, thereby providing broader scope to diagnosing bulk crystalline topology that works even in inhomogeneous systems where there is no global rotation symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.02985v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/1sw2-qkpw</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 094204 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Saavanth Velury, Yoonseok Hwang, Taylor L. Hughes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring Hall voltage and Hall resistance in an atom-based quantum simulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09744</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09744v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the Hall effect, a voltage drop develops perpendicularly to the current flow in the presence of a magnetic field, leading to a transverse Hall resistance. Recent developments with quantum simulators have unveiled strongly correlated and universal manifestations of the Hall effect. However, a direct measurement of the Hall voltage and of the Hall resistance in a non-electronic system of strongly interacting fermions was not achieved to date. Here, we demonstrate a technique for measuring the Hall voltage in a neutral-atom-based quantum simulator. From that we provide the first direct measurement of the Hall resistance in a cold-atom analogue of a solid-state Hall bar and study its dependence on the carrier density, along with theoretical analyses. Our work closes a major gap between analogue quantum simulations and measurements performed in solid-state systems, providing a key tool for the exploration of the Hall effect in highly tunable and strongly correlated systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09744v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41467-025-65083-6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nat. Commun. 16, 10247 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>T. -W. Zhou, T. Beller, G. Masini, J. Parravicini, G. Cappellini, C. Repellin, T. Giamarchi, J. Catani, M. Filippone, L. Fallani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distinct topological excitonic insulators characterized by quantum geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09305</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09305v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Theintertwining of electron-hole correlation and nontrivial topology is known to give rise to exotic topological
  excitonic insulators. Here, we show that the involvement of quantum geometry can characterize more exotic
  excitonic phases exhibiting physical properties that are not influenced by their topology but by geometry.
  Starting from a topological band insulator and gradually reducing the band gap, many-body interaction can
  initially generate a p + ip-wave and then an s-wave excitonic insulator. Interestingly, they bear the same Chern
  number but exhibit completely different spin textures and magneto-optical Kerr responses, reflecting the intricate
  geometric distinctions in their wave functions. We also propose to enhance the correlation effect via Floquet
  engineering, which provides a systematic way to realize these topological excitonic insulators and their phase
  transitions in the nonequilibrium steady states. Our results demonstrate correlated phenomena characterized by
  quantum geometry, beyond the conventional topological classifications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09305v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/18dk-tr69</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Zhuowei Liu, Rui Wang, Baigeng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Incommensurate spin fluctuations and competing pairing symmetries in La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05254</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05254v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The recent discovery of superconductivity in the bilayer Ruddlesden-Popper nickelate La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ under high pressure has generated much interest in the superconducting pairing mechanism of nickelates. Despite extensive work, the superconducting pairing symmetry in La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ remains unresolved, with conflicting results even for identical methods. We argue that different superconducting states in La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ are in close competition and highly sensitive to the choice of interaction parameters as well as pressure-induced changes in the electronic structure. Our study uses a multi-orbital Hubbard model, incorporating all Ni $3d$ and O $2p$ states. We analyze the superconducting pairing mechanism of La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ within the random phase approximation and find a transition between $d$-wave and sign-changing $s$-wave pairing states as a function of pressure and interaction parameters, which is driven by spin fluctuations with different wave vectors. These spin fluctuations with incommensurate wave vectors cooperatively stabilize a superconducting order parameter with $d_{x^2-y^2}$ symmetry for realistic model parameters. Simultaneously, their competition may be responsible for the absence of magnetic order in La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$, demonstrating that magnetic frustration and superconducting pairing can arise from the same set of incommensurate spin fluctuations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05254v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/f6nj-34th</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 174519 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Han-Xiang Xu, Daniel Guterding</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electric field tunable coupling strength and quantum metric hot spots in a moir\'e flatband superconductor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06460</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06460v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Superconductivity in flatband systems has attracted tremendous attention in condensed matter physics. Alternating twisted multilayer graphene presents a compelling multiband system, with a coexistence of Dirac bands and flat bands, for exploring superconductivity. However, the roles of flat bands and dispersive bands played in determining the superconductivity remain elusive. Here, we focus on the alternating twisted quadralayer graphene to reveal unconventional superconducting behaviors by systematically quantifying individual contributions for both the dispersive bands and the flat bands. The superconductivity is robust, with a strong electrical field tunability, a maximum BKT transition temperature of 1.6 K, and high critical magnetic fields beyond the Pauli limit. By analyzing the Landau fan diagram at zero electric displacement fields, we disentangle Dirac bands and flat bands, revealing a Coulomb interaction-induced band broadening effect. We further quantify the electric-field-dependent evolution of the critical temperature and coherence length, and estimate the flat-band Fermi velocity and superfluid stiffness via critical current measurements. Our results demonstrate an electric field tunable coupling strength within the superconducting phase, revealing unconventional properties with vanishing Fermi velocity and large superfluid stiffness. These phenomena, attributed to substantial quantum metric contributions mediated by Dirac band hybridization, offer new insights into the mechanisms underlying unconventional flatband superconductivity in moir\'e systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06460v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Le Liu, Yu Hong, Chengping Zhang, Jundong Zhu, Jingwei Dong, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Luojun Du, Dongxia Shi, Kam Tuen Law, Guangyu Zhang, Wei Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inhomogeneity, Fluctuations, and Gap Filling in Overdoped Cuprates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20861</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20861v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Several recent experiments have challenged the premise that cuprate high-temperature superconductors approach conventional Landau-BCS behavior in the high-doping limit. We argue, based on an analysis of their superconducting spectra, that anomalous properties seen in the most-studied overdoped cuprates require a pairing interaction that is strongly inhomogeneous on nm length scales. This is consistent with recent proposals that the "strange-metal" phase above $T_c$ in the same doping range arises from a spatially random interaction. We show, via mean-field Bogoliubov-de Gennes (BdG) calculations and time-dependent Ginzburg-Landau (TDGL) simulations, that key features of the observed tunneling spectra are reproduced when both inhomogeneity and thermal phase fluctuations are accounted for. In accord with experiments, BdG calculations find that low-$T$ spectra are highly inhomogeneous and exhibit a low-energy spectral shoulder and broad coherence peaks. However, the spectral gap in this approach becomes homogeneous at high $T$, in contrast to experiments. This is resolved when thermal fluctuations are included; in this case, global phase coherence is lost at the superconducting $T_c$ via a broadened BKT transition, while robust phase-coherent superconducting islands persist well above $T_c$. The local spectrum remains inhomogeneous at $T_c$, and the gap is found to fill instead of close with increasing temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20861v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/x1m7-bs95</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Res. 7, 043201 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Antonio Sulangi, Willem Farmilo, Andreas Kreisel, Mainak Pal, W. A. Atkinson, P. J. Hirschfeld</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Importance of bond exchange in MnC structural stability and half-metallic ferromagnetism: a comprehensive density functional benchmark study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23116</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23116v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently, a first successful synthesis of the unknown bulk manganese monocarbide (MnC) has been reported. Suggested as a potential superhard material, the compound is found to crystallize in the zincblende (B3) structure. In the present work, we report an exhaustive density functional investigation on structural, electronic and magnetic properties of MnC, using different levels of exchange-correlation approximations. We show that SCAN meta-GGA and PBE0r hybrid functional outperform GGA-PBEsol, HSE06 hybrid functional and the mean field DFT+$U$+$V$; in predicting correctly the experimental zincblende structure as the groundstate one. It is demonstrated that the bond exchange plays a crucial role in this stabilization. At theoretical equilibrium, hybrid functionals (PBE0r and HSE06) lead to a metallic behavior of MnC. Semilocal ones (PBEsol and SCAN) and mean field DFT+$U$+$V$, however, predict two opposite kinds of half-metallic ferromagnetism; opening a debate on the origin and the nature this behavior. If the latter is confirmed experimentally, MnC could be for importance as a spintronic material.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23116v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abdesalem Houari, Peter Bloechl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prethermalization of light and matter in cavity-coupled Rydberg arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.06267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.06267v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explore the dynamics of two-dimensional Rydberg atom arrays coupled to a single-mode optical cavity, employing nonequilibrium diagrammatic techniques to capture nonlinearities and fluctuations beyond mean-field theory. We discover a novel prethermalization regime driven by the interplay between short-range Rydberg interactions and long-range photon-mediated interactions. In this regime, matter and light equilibrate at distinct - and in some cases opposite - effective temperatures, resembling the original concept of prethermalization from particle physics. Our results establish strongly correlated AMO platforms as tools to investigate fundamental questions in statistical mechanics, including quantum thermalization in higher-dimensional systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.06267v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/gqjz-tyqg</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 210402 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Aleksandr N. Mikheev, Hossein Hosseinabadi, Jamir Marino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electric field tunable magnetoexcitons in Xenes-hBN-TMDC, Xenes-hBN-BP, and Xenes-hBN-TMTC heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.19063v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we propose novel van der Waals (vdW) heterostructures composed of Xenes, transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDCs), phosphorene, and transition metal trichalcogenides (TMTCs), which are separated by insulating hexagonal boron nitride (hBN) layers. We investigate theoretically the behavior of Rydberg indirect excitons in Xenes-hBN-TMDC, Xenes-hBN-BP, and Xenes-hBN-TMTC heterostructures, subject to parallel external electric and magnetic fields that are oriented perpendicular to the layers. By incorporating both isotropic and anisotropic materials, we demonstrate that excitonic properties can be effectively tuned through the external field strengths and the heterostructure design.
  Our results show that the exciton reduced mass and the binding energy increase with the electric field strength, while enhanced dielectric screening from additional hBN layers reduces the binding energy. Anisotropic materials exhibit distinct excitonic responses, including variations in diamagnetic behavior. Moreover, the diamagnetic energy contributions and coefficients decrease with stronger electric fields but increase with the number of hBN layers. Finally, we explore the potential of time-periodic electric fields with Floquet band-structure engineering. These findings provide a comprehensive framework for controlling excitonic phenomena in low-dimensional materials, enabling the design of advanced optoelectronic and quantum devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.19063v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0281960</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Appl. Phys. 138, 174302 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Roman Ya. Kezerashvili, Anastasia Spiridonova, Klaus Ziegler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Majoranas with a twist: Tunable Majorana zero modes in altermagnetic heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.00119</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.00119v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Altermagnetism provides new routes to realize Majorana zero modes with vanishing net magnetization. We consider a recently proposed heterostructure consisting of a semiconducting wire on top of an altermagnet and with proximity-induced superconductivity. We demonstrate that rotating the wire serves as a tuning knob to induce the topological phase. For $d$-, $g$- and $i$-wave altermagnetic pairing, we derive angle-dependent topological gap-closing conditions. We derive symmetry constraints on angles where the induced altermagnetism must vanish, which we verify by explicit models. Our results imply that a bent or curved wire realizes a spatially-dependent topological invariant with Majorana zero modes pinned to positions where the topological invariant changes. This provides a new experimental set-up whereby a single wire can host both topologically trivial and nontrivial regimes without $in$ $situ$ tuning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.00119v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/p79l-rty6</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Hadjipaschalis, Sayed Ali Akbar Ghorashi, Jennifer Cano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quench spectroscopy for Lieb-Liniger bosons in the presence of harmonic trap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07699</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07699v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quench spectroscopy has emerged as a novel and powerful technique for probing the energy spectrum of various quantum phases for quantum systems from out-of-equilibrium dynamics. While its efficacy has been demonstrated in the homogeneous systems theoretically, most experimental setups feature a confining potential, such as a harmonic trap, which complicates the practical implementations. In this work, we experimentally probe the quench spectroscopy for one-dimensional bosons in optical lattices with the presence of a harmonic trap, and comparing our results with the density matrix renormalization group simulation. For the Mott insulator phase, although a gap is still observed, the band signal is broadened along the frequency space and cut at the half Brillouin zone, which can be explained by the nearest-neighbor tunneling excitations under harmonic confinement. Comparing with the superfluid spectrum, we can see a clear distinction between the two phases and find the inverse quench with larger amplitude yields the clearest spectrum. Our work offers pivotal insights into conducting quench spectroscopy effectively in practical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07699v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiachen Yu, Yuanzhe Hu, Wenhan Chen, Jianing Yang, Xuzong Chen, Hepeng Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nesting-driven ferromagnetism of itinerant electrons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.11614v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We theoretically investigate a model with electrons and holes whose Fermi surfaces are perfectly nested. The fermions are assumed to be interacting, both with each other and with the lattice. To suppress inhomogeneous states, a sufficiently strong long-range Coulomb repulsion is included into the model. Using the mean field approximation, one can demonstrate that in the absence of doping, the ground state of such a model is insulating and possesses a density-wave order, either SDW, or CDW. Upon doping, a finite ferromagnetic polarization emerges. It is argued that the mechanism driving the ferromagnetism is not of the Stoner type. A phase diagram of the model is constructed, and various properties of the ordered phases, such as half-metallicity and cone magnetic structure, are studied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.11614v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/kpdc-9p8m</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.B 112,(2025) 205129</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ya. I. Rodionov, A. V. Rozhkov, M. E. S. Beck, A. O. Sboychakov, K. I. Kugel, A. L. Rakhmanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic annihilation pathways of magnetic skyrmions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14365</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14365v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The investigation of magnetic solitons often relies on numerical modeling to determine key features such as stability, annihilation, nucleation, and motion. However, as soliton sizes approach atomic length scales, the accuracy of these predictions become increasingly sensitive to the details of the numerical model. Here, we study the annihilation of two-dimensional magnetic skyrmions using a pseudospectral approach and compare its performance to that of conventional micromagnetic simulations. A central distinction between the models lies in their treatment of the exchange interaction, which governs the magnon dispersion relation and plays a crucial role to balance the uniaxial anisotropy to stabilise skyrmions. We demonstrate that both the choice of model and spatial discretisation significantly influence the skyrmion dynamics and the magnetic field required for annihilation. The pseudospectral model provides a consistent description across length scales and captures complex behaviours such as skyrmion breathing on its path to annihilation. Our results have direct implications in the state-of-the-art modeling of skyrmions and other two-dimensional textures and will impact the modeling of three-dimensional textures such as hopfions. More broadly, our approach will contribute to the development seamless multiscale model and optimization machine learning approaches for material discovery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14365v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Copus, Ezio Iacocca</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fluctuation-induced Hall-like lateral forces in a chiral-gain environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14754v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Here, we demonstrate that vacuum fluctuations can induce lateral forces on a small particle positioned near a translation-invariant uniform non-Hermitian substrate with chiral gain. This type of non-Hermitian response can be engineered by biasing a low-symmetry conductor with a static electric field and is rooted in the quantum geometry of the material through the Berry curvature dipole. The chiral-gain material acts as an active medium for a particular circular polarisation handedness, while serving as a passive, dissipative medium for the other polarisation handedness. Owing to the nonreciprocity and gain characteristics, momentum is continuously exchanged in a preferred direction parallel to the surface between the test particle and the surrounding electromagnetic field, giving rise to lateral forces. Interestingly, the force can be viewed as a fluctuation-induced drag analogous to a Hall force. Indeed, although the gain is driven by an electric current, the resulting force acts perpendicular to the bias -- unlike conventional current-drag effects. This effect stems from the skewed propagation characteristics of surface modes and gain-momentum locking. Our theory reveals a Hall-like asymmetry in the field correlations and establishes a novel link between quantum geometry and fluctuation-induced phenomena, offering new possibilities for nanoscale control via tailored electromagnetic environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14754v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daigo Oue, M\'ario G. Silveirinha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient $GW$ band structure calculations using Gaussian basis functions and application to atomically thin transition-metal dichalcogenides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18411</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18411v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a $GW$ space-time algorithm for periodic systems in a Gaussian basis including spin-orbit coupling. We employ lattice summation to compute the irreducible density response and the self-energy, while we employ $k$-point sampling for computing the screened Coulomb interaction. Our algorithm enables accurate and computationally efficient quasiparticle band structure calculations for atomically thin transition-metal dichalcogenides. For monolayer MoS$_\text{2}$, MoSe$_\text{2}$, WS$_\text{2}$, and WSe$_\text{2}$, computed $GW$ band gaps agree on average within 50 meV with plane-wave-based reference calculations. $G_0W_0$ band structures are obtained in less than two days on a laptop (Intel i5, 192 GB RAM) or in less than 30 minutes using 1024 cores. Overall, our work provides an efficient and scalable framework for $GW$ calculations on atomically thin materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18411v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/v4zv-1pf9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 205130 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>R\'emi Pasquier, Mar\'ia Camarasa-G\'omez, Anna-Sophia Hehn, Daniel Hernang\'omez-P\'erez, Jan Wilhelm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Field-free Superconducting Diode Effect and Topological Fulde-Ferrell Superconductivity in Altermagnetic Shiba Chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21446</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.21446v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The superconducting diode effect (SDE), characterized by a directional asymmetry in the critical supercurrents, typically requires external magnetic fields to break time-reversal symmetry -- posing challenges for scalability and device integration. Here, we demonstrate a field-free realization of the SDE in a helical Shiba chain proximitized by a $d$-wave altermagnet. Using a self-consistent Bogoliubov-de Gennes approach, we uncover a topological Fulde-Ferrell (FF) superconducting state that hosts tunable Majorana zero modes at the chain ends. The Cooper pair momentum is directly controlled by an externally injected supercurrent providing an experimentally accessible tuning parameter for driving and manipulating the topological FF phase. This state is stabilized by the interplay between the exchange coupling of magnetic adatoms and the induced altermagnetic spin splitting. Crucially, the same topological FF phase supports strong nonreciprocal supercurrents, achieving diode efficiencies exceeding $45\%$ without applied magnetic fields. The $d$-wave altermagnet plays a dual role: it intrinsically breaks time-reversal symmetry, enabling topological superconductivity, and introduces inversion symmetry breaking via momentum-dependent spin-splitting, driving the field-free SDE in a junction-free architecture. Our results establish the Shiba chain-altermagnet heterostructure as a promising platform for realizing topological superconducting devices with efficient, intrinsic superconducting diode functionality -- offering a scalable pathway towards dissipationless quantum technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.21446v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dibyendu Samanta, Sudeep Kumar Ghosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graphene-based quantum heterospin graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23360</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.23360v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate from first principles a variety of low-dimensional open quantum spin systems based on magnetic nanographene structures that contain spin-1/2 and spin-1 triangulenes and/or olympicenes. These graphene nanostructures behave as localized spins and can be effectively described by a quantum bilinear-biquadratic Heisenberg Hamiltonian, for which we will compute the energy spectrum and the quantum numbers associated with the low-energy eigenstates. We propose the experimental realization of antiferromagnetic alternating spin chains using these graphene nanostructures, which result in ferrimagnetic systems whose ground state spin and degeneracy depend on the length of the chain. We identify a double degeneracy in the total spin quantum number $S$ of the first excited state in three-leg spin graphs (3-LSGs) and other heterospin nanostructures, which depends on both the number of sites and the spin species, and originates from the swapping transformation symmetry of the Hamiltonian. Numerical simulations indicate that this degeneracy remains largely robust for $N=7$ spin-1 3-LSGs under realistic perturbations present in experimental conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.23360v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/v3fm-lvsh</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 174428 - Published 24 November, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel Mart\'inez-Carracedo, Amador Garc\'ia-Fuente, L\'aszl\'o Oroszl\'any, L\'aszl\'o Szunyogh, Jaime Ferrer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Clarification on Quantum-Metric-Induced Nonlinear Transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02088v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Over the years, Berry curvature, which is associated with the imaginary part of the quantum geometric tensor, has profoundly impacted many branches of physics. Recently, quantum metric, the real part of the quantum geometric tensor, has been recognized as indispensable in comprehensively characterizing the intrinsic properties of condensed matter systems. The intrinsic second-order nonlinear conductivity induced by the quantum metric has attracted significant recent interest. However, its expression varies across the literature. Here, we reconcile this discrepancy by systematically examining the nonlinear conductivity using the standard perturbation theory, the wave packet dynamics, and the Luttinger-Kohn approach. Moreover, inspired by the Dirac model, we propose a toy model that suppresses the Berry-curvature-induced nonlinear transport, making it suitable for studying the quantum-metric-induced nonlinear conductivity. This work provides a clearer and more unified understanding of the quantum-metric contributions to nonlinear transport. It also establishes a solid foundation for future theoretical developments and experimental explorations in this highly active and rapidly evolving field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02088v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/advs.202514818</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Adv. Sci. 2025, e14818</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xiao-Bin Qiang, Tianyu Liu, Zi-Xuan Gao, Hai-Zhou Lu, X. C. Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin structures and phase diagrams of the spin-$\frac{5}{2}$ triangular-lattice antiferromagnet Na$_2$BaMn(PO$_4$)$_2$ under magnetic field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21021</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.21021v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We combine single-crystal neutron diffraction studies and Monte Carlo simulations to determine the spin structures and finite-temperature phase diagram of the spin-5/2 triangular-lattice antiferromagnet Na$_2$BaMn(PO$_4$)$_2$ in magnetic field. With the application of a magnetic field in two different directions, namely along the $c$-axis and in the $ab$-plane of the trigonal symmetry, we track the evolution of the spin structure through changes of the magnetic propagation vector. We account for these results with a minimal Heisenberg Hamiltonian that includes easy-axis anisotropy and weak, frustrated interlayer couplings in addition to intralayer exchange. Guided by representation analysis, we refine symmetry-allowed modes to the measured intensities and obtain the spin structures for all field-induced phases, which we compare quantitatively with simulated configurations. Taken together, our measurements and simulations show that frustrated interlayer exchange -- rather than purely 2D physics -- organizes the unexpectedly rich field-induced phases of Na$_2$BaMn(PO$_4$)$_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.21021v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/kszh-m6bf</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 174429 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>N. Biniskos, F. J. dos Santos, M. Stekiel, K. Schmalzl, E. Ressouche, D. Svit\'ak, A. Labh, M. Vali\v{s}ka, N. Marzari, P. \v{C}erm\'ak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry-enforced Moir\'e Topology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.06906v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Topological flat bands in two-dimensional (2D) moir\'e materials have emerged as promising platforms for exploring the interplay between topology and correlation effects. However, realistic calculations of moir\'e band topology using density functional theory (DFT) are computationally inefficient due to the large number of atoms in a single moir\'e unit cell. In this work, we propose a systematic scheme to predict the topology of moir\'e bands from atomic symmetry data and moir\'e symmetry group, both of which can be efficiently extracted from DFT. Specifically, for $\Gamma$-valley electron gases, we find that certain combinations of atomic symmetry data and moir\'e symmetry groups can enforce nontrivial band topology in the low-energy moir\'e bands, as long as the moir\'e band gap is smaller than the atomic band splitting at the moir\'e Brillouin zone boundary. This symmetry-enforced nontrivial moir\'e topology, including both topological insulators and topological semimetals, is robust against various material-specific details such as the precise form and strength of the moir\'e potential or the exact twist angle. By exhaustively scanning all 2D atomic symmetry data and moir\'e symmetry groups, we identify 197 combinations that can yield symmetry-enforced nontrivial moir\'e topology, and we verify one such combination using a moir\'e model with cubic Rashba spin-orbit coupling. By screening the existing 2D material database, we currently identify 92 monolayer materials with (i) the low-energy bands near $\Gamma$ and (ii) the atomic symmetry data that belong to those combinations. Our approach is generalizable to other valleys and provides a useful guideline for experimental efforts to discover and design new topologically nontrivial moir\'e materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.06906v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunzhe Liu, Ethan Angerhofer, Kaijie Yang, Chao-Xing Liu, Jiabin Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General ab initio framework for chiral phonons induced by electronic order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09253v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Conventional ab initio methods fail to describe the emergence of chiral phonons driven by electronic ordering. Here, we develop an ab initio framework, grounded in molecular Berry curvature (MBC), that captures electronic-order-driven symmetry breaking in lattice dynamics and is applicable to both insulating and metallic magnets. Using Co$_3$Sn$_2$S$_2$ as a model system, we show that the MBC term simultaneously breaks time-reversal and mirror symmetries, enabling a quantitative reproduction of the experimentally observed phonon splittings. The analysis uncovers distinct microscopic origins for the $E_g$ and $E_u$ modes: the $E_g$ splitting is governed by MBC and is accurately described by our first-principles scheme, whereas the $E_u$ splitting is enhanced by the Fano resonance, consistent with its asymmetric spectral profile. Leveraging this framework, we further predict several candidates with chiral-phonon splitting. Our results establish a predictive route for identifying and understanding phonon magnetism, chiral phonons, and related Hall-type lattice responses from first principles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09253v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuai Zhang, Mengqi Wang, Tiantian Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hopper Growth of Higher-Order Topological Insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09875</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09875v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding crystal growth and morphology is a fundamental issue in condensed matter physics. While crystal morphology due to the distribution and dynamics of the diffusion field has been intensively studied, how the intrinsic material properties affect crystal morphology remains unclear. In this Letter, we demonstrate that higher-order topological phases can give rise to hopper-shaped crystal morphologies through an unconventional mechanism originating from topological electronic states. We quantitatively show this connection by analyzing both the fractal dimension $D_f$ and the fractal dimension of coastlines $D_{f,c}$. When we compare the crystals in the trivial and topological phases with the same $D_{f}$ in the case of relatively rapid crystal growth, the former is in the dendritic shape, while the latter is in the hopper shape, quantified by the smaller $D_{f,c}$ in the topological phase. We reveal the microscopic origin of this anomalous growth in the higher-order topological phase, and find that it leads to the stepwise-depressed morphology characteristic of hopper crystals. Our theory uncovers a fundamental link between hopper crystals and higher-order topological phases, offering unconventional insight into crystal morphology governed by topological electronic states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09875v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yutaro Tanaka, Shuai Zhang, Tiantian Zhang, Shuichi Murakami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-Throughput Quantification of Altermagnetic Band Splitting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14729</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14729v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Altermagnetism represents a recently established class of collinear magnetism that combines zero net magnetization with momentum-dependent spin polarization, enabled by symmetry constraints rather than spin-orbit coupling. This distinctive behavior gives rise to sizable spin splitting even in materials composed of light, earth-abundant elements, offering promising prospects for next-generation spintronics applications. Despite growing theoretical and experimental interest, the discovery of altermagnetic materials remains limited due to the complexity of magnetic symmetry and the inefficiency of conventional approaches. Here, we present a comprehensive high-throughput screening of the entire MAGNDATA database, integrating symmetry analysis with spin-polarized density functional theory (DFT) calculations to identify and characterize altermagnetic candidates. Our workflow uncovers 173 materials exhibiting significant spin splitting ($\geq 50$ meV within $\pm 3$ eV of the Fermi level), spanning both metallic and semiconducting systems. Crucially, our momentum-resolved analysis reveals that the spin splitting varies strongly across the Brillouin zone, and that the maximal splitting tends to occur away from the high-symmetry paths, a result that directly informs and guides future photoemission experiments. By expanding the catalog of known altermagnets and elucidating the symmetry-protected origins of spin splitting, this work lays a robust foundation for future experimental and theoretical advances in spintronics and quantum materials discovery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14729v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Sufyan, Brahim Marfoua, J. Andreas Larsson, Erik van Loon, Rickard Armiento</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Fermi liquid behaviour of CDW instabilities in fractionally-filled moir\'e flatbands</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15996</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.15996v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Spin- and valley-polarized fractionally-filled moir\'e flatbands are known to host emergent Fermi-liquid phases, when analyzed with the help of a dual description in terms of holes. The dominant Coulomb interactions in an almost flatband endow the fermions with a nontrivial dispersion, when the system is described in terms of the hole operators (rather than the particle operators). In particular, for one-fourth filling, the Fermi surface takes a quasi-triangular shape, which brings about the possibility of charge-density-wave (CDW) ordering in the ground state, characterized by the nesting vectors ($ \mathbf{Q}_n $). The $\mathbf{Q}_n$'s connect antipodal points of the Fermi surface (designated as hot-spots) and are found to belong to the space of reciprocal vectors of the underlying honeycomb structure. The resulting CDW order can be described in terms of instabilities caused by bosonic fields with momenta centred at $\lbrace \mathbf{Q}_n \rbrace $, coupling with the fermions residing in the vicinity of a pair of antipodal hot-spots. When there is a transition from a Fermi liquid to a CDW state, the bosons become massless (or critical), effectuating a non-Fermi liquid behaviour. We set out to identify such non-Fermi liquid phases after constructing a minimal effective action.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.15996v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ipsita Mandal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-Axis Dynamic Locking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18476</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.18476v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The all-electrical realization of highly spin-polarized charge currents and their efficient conversion into pure spin currents remains a fundamental challenge in spintronics. Here, we report a spin-axis dynamic locking (SADL) effect in altermagnets that pins the spin polarization to the crystalline axes: an in-plane electric field along one principal axis drives a fully spin-up charge current, whereas along the orthogonal axis, it generates an equal spin-down current. Consequently, applying an electric field diagonally yields a transverse pure spin current with 100% charge-to-spin conversion efficiency. Mechanistically, SADL originates in a distinctive tent state characterized by alternating spin-split flat bands and orthogonal Fermi-surface lines. High-throughput first-principles screening confirms SADL in broad materials (e.g., 2D Cr2WSe4 monolayer and a synthesized three-dimensional compound, (BaF)2Mn2Se2O). Our work thus opens a route to ultra-low-power, reconfigurable spintronic devices where the spin states are governed solely by electric field orientation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.18476v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lv Zhiheng, Cai Jiangtao, Ma Dengpan, Xing Yan, Liu Zhifeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Casimir Stabilization of Fluctuating Electronic Nematic Order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.05088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.05088v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Vacuum cavity control of quantum materials is the engineering of quantum materials systems through electromagnetic zero-point fluctuations. In this work we articulate a generic mechanism for vacuum optical control of correlated electronic order: Casimir control, where the zero-point energy of the electromagnetic continuum, the Casimir energy, depends on the properties of the material system. To assess the experimental viability of this mechanism we focus on the Casimir stabilization of fluctuating nematic order. In nematic Fermi liquids, different orientations of the electronic order are often energetically degenerate. Thus, while local domains of fixed orientation may form, thermal disordering inhibits long range order. By engineering the electromagnetic environment of the electronic system, however, we show that the Casimir energy can be used as a tool to preferentially stabilize particular orientations of the nematic order. As a concrete example, we examine the interplay between a birefringent crystal -- which sources an anisotropic electromagnetic environment -- and a quantum Hall stripe system, an archetypal nematic Fermi fluid. We show that for experimentally feasible setups, the anisotropy induced by the orientation dependent Casimir energy can be $10^4$ times larger than other mechanisms known to stabilize quantum Hall stripes. This finding convincingly implies that our setting may be realized with currently available experimental technology. Having demonstrated that the Casimir energy can be used to stabilize fluctuating nematic order, we close by discussing the implications for recent terahertz cavity experiments on quantum Hall stripes, as well as pave the road towards broader Casimir control of competing correlated electronic phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.05088v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ola Carlsson, Sambuddha Chattopadhyay, Jonathan B. Curtis, Frieder Lindel, Lorenzo Graziotto, J\'er\^ome Faist, Eugene Demler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-dimensional superconducting diode effect in topological insulator/superconductor heterostructure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09921</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09921v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The superconducting diode effect (SDE) is characterized by the nonreciprocity of Cooper-pair motion with respect to current direction. In three-dimensional (3D) materials, SDE results in a critical current that varies with direction, making the effect distinctly observable: the material exhibits superconductivity in one direction while behaving as a resistive metal in the opposite direction. However, in genuinely two-dimensional (2D) materials, the critical current density is theoretically zero, leaving the manifestation of SDE in the 2D limit an intriguing challenge. Here, we present the observation of SDE in a heterostructure composed of the topological insulator Bi$_2$Te$_3$ and the iron based superconductor Fe(Se,Te) $-$a candidate for topological superconductor$-$ where superconductivity is confined to the 2D limit. The observed I-V characteristics reveal nonreciprocity in the vortex-creep regime, where finite voltages arise due to the two-dimensional nature of superconductivity. Furthermore, our 2D film demonstrates abrupt voltage jumps, influenced by both the current flow direction and the transverse magnetic field direction. This behavior resembles that of 3D materials but, in this case, is driven by the vortex-flow instability, as illustrated by voltage controlled S-shaped I-V curves. These results underscore the pivotal role of vortex dynamics in SDE and provide new insights into the interplay between symmetry breaking and two-dimensionality in topological insulator/superconductor systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09921v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soma Nagahama, Yuki Sato, Minoru Kawamura, Ilya Belopolski, Ryutaro Yoshimi, Atsushi Tsukazaki, Naoya Kanazawa, Kei S Takahashi, Masashi Kawasaki, Yoshinori Tokura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Field-Enhanced Graphene Superconductivity with Record Pauli-Limit Violation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.10873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.10873v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Spin-polarized superconductors offer a rare platform for studying electronic correlations, but few candidate systems have been experimentally confirmed to date. Here, we report the observation of a spin-polarized superconducting state, denoted SC5, in WSe2-proximitized rhombohedral trilayer graphene. At in-plane magnetic field B|| = 0 T, SC5 has a critical temperature of 68 mK and an out-of-plane critical magnetic field of only 12 mT. Surprisingly, these values are significantly enhanced as B|| increases, and the superconductivity persists to B|| = 8.8 T. This value corresponds to a record-high Pauli-limit violation ratio of at least 80 among all superconductors, while the true critical field is beyond the limit of our instrument. We conclude that SC5 experiences a canting crossover from Ising-type to spin-polarized superconductor with increased B||.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.10873v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jixiang Yang, Omid Sharifi Sedeh, Chiho Yoon, Shenyong Ye, Henok Weldeyesus, Armel Cotten, Tonghang Han, Zhengguang Lu, Zach Hadjri, Junseok Seo, Lihan Shi, Emily Aitken, Prayoga P Liong, Zhenghan Wu, Mingchi Xu, Christian Scheller, Mingyang Zheng, Rasul Gazizulin, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Dominique Laroche, Mingda Li, Fan Zhang, Dominik M. Zumb\"uhl, Long Ju</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three Types of Non-Fermi-Liquid Fixed Point for a Triplet Quantum Impurity in a Cubic Metal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15163</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15163v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In cubic metals, a local, magnetic moment with a triplet ground state coupled to $\Gamma_8$ conduction electrons can give rise to various non-Fermi liquid (NFL) quantum critical behaviors. To date, only those exchange couplings have been studied that are spherically symmetric already in the high-temperature, local moment regime. Namely, only the effects of potential scattering, dipolar spin exchange, i.e. Kondo, and quadrupolar exchange couplings were considered, and two types of NFL fixed points have been identified. However, in cubic symmetry, six independent exchange couplings can be present in the Hamiltonian: in addition to the spherically symmetric potential scattering and Kondo exchange, there are four independent, spherical-symmetry-breaking Hamiltonian terms: two quadrupolar-quadrupolar, a dipolar-octupolar and a quadrupolar-octupolar exchange interaction, where the first/second element of the compound adjectives refers to the impurity/conduction-electron transitions. While all of them flow to fixed points where rotational invariance is recovered, I found that one of the quadrupolar-quadrupolar couplings flows to a previously unidentified NFL fixed point. I derive the exchange couplings allowed by cubic symmetry, solve them with the numerical renormalization group, and present three types of NFL excitation spectrum$-$one of which is novel, at least in the context of a quantum impurity with a triplet ground state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15163v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna I. T\'oth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond the Lowest Landau Level: Unlocking More Robust Fractional States Using Flat Chern Bands with Higher Vortexability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22831v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Enhancing the many-body gap of a fractional state is crucial for realizing robust fractional excitations. For fractional Chern insulators, existing studies suggest that making flat Chern bands closely resemble the lowest Landau level (LLL) seems to maximize the excitation gap, providing an apparently optimal platform. In this work, we demonstrate that deforming away from the LLL limit can, in fact, produce substantially larger FQH gaps. Using moir\'e flat bands with strongly non-Landau-level wavefunctions, we show that the gap can exceed that of the LLL by more than two orders of magnitude for short-range interactions and by factors of two to three for long-range interactions. This enhancement is generic across Abelian FCI states and follows a universal enhancement factor within each hierarchy. Using the Landau level framework, we identify the amplification of pseudopotentials as the microscopic origin of the observed enhancement. This finding demonstrates that pseudopotential engineering can substantially strengthen fractional topological phases. We further examined non-Abelian states and found that, within finite-size resolution, this wavefunction construction method can also be used to manipulate and enhance the gap for certain interaction parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22831v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yitong Zhang, Siddhartha Sarkar, Xiaohan Wan, Daniel E. Parker, Shi-Zeng Lin, Kai Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\mathbb{Z}_2$ Universality of the Mott Transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25845</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25845v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We demonstrate that the Mott transition exhibits universal scaling as a consequence of the breaking of a $\mathbb{Z}_2$ symmetry in momentum space. A direct consequence of this discrete symmetry breaking is the charge or Mott gap itself. From extensive numerics, we proffer that it is the charge compressibility that acts as the underlying order parameter as it is zero in the insulator and non-zero in the metallic state. Additionally, the Widom line (temperature of the extremum of the compressibility) obeys a universal scaling of $T_m=0.39U$ deep into the insulating state directly from $Z_2$ universality. Furthermore, the temperature at which the second derivative of the compressibility has a minimum is independent of lattice geometry, exhibiting a universal scaling of $|U-U_c|^\alpha$ where $\alpha\approx 1$. Finally, our computational approach reproduces the key features of the doping dependence of the compressibility demonstrated in recent cold-atom quantum simulators of the Hubbard model, thereby corroborating our conclusions on $\mathbb{Z}_2$ universality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25845v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinchao Zhao, Peizhi Mai, Gaurav Tenkila, Philip W. Phillips</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The parent state in kagome metals and superconductors: Chiral-nematic Fermi liquid state</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09402v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The kagome metals and superconductors hosting rich correlated and topological electronic states have captivated quantum materials research. These states are triggered by an unconventional chiral charge density wave (CDW) wherein a chiral superconductivity emerges at low temperatures, yet the origin of this chiral CDW order, the parent state, is unresolved. Here, we report the discovery of a parent chiral-nematic Fermi liquid state in kagome metals and superconductors. We use spectroscopic-imaging scanning tunneling microscopy to study Ti-doped CsV3Sb5 where the CDW is suppressed, and find that multiorbital Fermi surfaces break all mirror reflections and exhibit handedness. We observe the chiral low-energy quasiparticle dispersions, providing direct evidence for a chiral-nematic electronic structure. We further observe the direct transition from the parent state to a chiral-nematic superconducting state. Moreover, in the samples with chiral CDW, we also observe the residual chiral-nematic QPI features, demonstrating that the CDW-triggered exotic states descend from the chiral-nematic Fermi liquid. Our findings not only provide a plausible chiral-nematic parent state, but also establish a new conceptual framework for exploring the emergence and consequences of such exotic quantum phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09402v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zihao Huang, Zhan Wang, Hengxing Tan, Zhen Zhao, Chengmin Shen, Haitao Yang, Bent Weber, Binghai Yan, Hui Chen, Ziqiang Wang, Hong-Jun Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractional Chern Insulators Transition in Non-ideal Flat Bands of Twisted Mono-bilayer Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12231</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12231v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Fractional Chern insulators (FCIs) in ideal flat bands with Chern number $C$ are commonly understood as color-entangled states constructed from $C$ copies of the lowest Landau level. In realistic moir\'e systems, however, the band geometry is generally non-ideal, and the mechanism that stabilizes such FCIs remains unclear. Using twisted monolayer-bilayer graphene as a platform, we find two FCIs separated by a continuous transition driven by a geometric instability of the Bloch wave functions.Below the transition, the target $C=2$ conduction band is geometrically stable, and the resulting fractional phase is naturally described by the Halperin-$(112)$ state. Above the transition, the system is geometrically unstable, entering a Laughlin-$1/3$ phase that persists despite further degradation of standard quantum-geometry indicators. To account for this unconventional phenomenon, we propose a color-separation mechanism beyond global geometric indicators: in the geometrically unstable regime, interactions hybridize electronic states near the $K$ point and generate an emergent ideal color component that supports the FCI. We corroborate this picture by applying a weak perpendicular magnetic field that acts as a "color separator," directly visualizing the ideal subcomponent in the single-particle level. Together, these results establish mechanisms which non-ideal flat bands stabilize FCIs, substantially enlarging their viable parameter space and clarifying the role of quantum geometry in strongly correlated topological phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12231v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Moru Song, Kai Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structural phase transitions in the van der Waals ferromagnets Fe$_x$Pd$_{y}$Te$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.15584v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Here, we provide a detailed study of the crystal structure and physical properties of the recently discovered vdW ferromagnet FePd$_2$Te$_2$. We find this compound has a relatively wide width of formation, and grow single crystals with compositions Fe$_x$Pd$_{y}$Te$_2$ where $x$ ranges from 0.9 to 1.1 and $y$ from 1.8 to 2.5, respectively. Temperature-dependent X-ray diffraction and transport measurements reveal that a first-order structural transition occurs in the range of $T$ = 360-420 K. Above the transition, the compounds with Pd fraction $y&gt;2$ adopt a disordered derivative of the tetragonal FeTe structure, with the Fe layer showing mixed Fe/Pd occupancy and the extra Pd atoms partially occupying interstitial sites. Below 370 K, the structure is incommensurately modulated. For $y&lt;2$, the composition Fe$_{1.1}$Pd$_{1.8}$Te$_2$ has monoclinic symmetry at room temperature that is consistent with the reported structure of FePd$_2$Te$_2$. This phase undergoes a structural transition at 420 K for which the high temperature structure is yet to be determined; however, based on the similarities with the $y &gt; 2$ compounds, we speculate that this composition also adopts a tetragonal structure above 420\,K. All compounds investigated in the Fe$_x$Pd$_{y}$Te$_2$ series show metallic behavior, with magnetic characterization indicating that they are easy-plane, hard, ferromagnets with $T_C$ spanning 98--180 K. Both the critical temperature for the structural transition and the Curie temperature are moderately suppressed with increasing Pd fraction $y$ and corresponding decreasing Fe fraction $x$, indicating that synthetic control over $x$ and $y$ paves way for the further exploration of these compounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.15584v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafaela F. S. Penacchio, Siham Mohamed, S\'ergio L. Morelh\~ao, Sergey L. Bud'ko, Paul C. Canfield, Tyler J. Slade</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synthesis and optical characterization of Mn-doped ZnS nanocrystalline thin films prepared via chemical bath deposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16167</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.16167v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Manganese-doped zinc sulfide nanocrystalline thin films were synthesized using a low-temperature chemical bath deposition and deposited on glass substrates for controlled durations using triethanolamine (TEA) as a complexing and capping agent. After deposition, the films were annealed at 200 degrees Celsius and characterized by X-ray diffraction (XRD), SEM, and UV-Vis spectroscopy. XRD patterns confirmed the formation of nanocrystalline cubic zinc blende ZnS with an average crystallite size of approximately 37 nm. Optical measurements revealed strong transparency in the visible region, blue-shifted absorption edges due to quantum confinement, and a band gap value of approximately 3.70 eV. Mn incorporation resulted in a slight red shift of the absorption edge, attributed to particle growth and sp-d exchange interactions. These results demonstrate that Mn doping modifies the optical response of ZnS while preserving its crystalline structure, suggesting its suitability for optoelectronic and photovoltaic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.16167v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Himal Pokhrel, Urvashi Verma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Room-temperature valley-selective emission in Si-MoSe2 heterostructures enabled by high-quality-factor chiroptical cavities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09806v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Transition metal dichalcogenides possess valley pseudospin, enabling coupling between photon spin and electron spin for classical and quantum information processing. However, rapid valley-dephasing processes have impeded the development of scalable, high-performance valleytronic devices operating at room temperature. Here we demonstrate that a chiral resonant metasurface can enable room-temperature valley-selective emission in MoSe2 monolayers independent of excitation polarization. This platform provides circular eigen-polarization states with a high quality factor (Q-factor) and strong chiral near-field enhancement. The fabricated Si chiral metasurfaces exhibit chiroptical resonances with Q-factors up to 450 at visible wavelengths. We reveal degrees of circular polarization (DOP) reaching a record high of 0.5 at room temperature. Our measurements show that the high DOP can be attributed to the significantly increased chiroptical local density of states, which enhances valley-specific radiative transition rates by a factor of ~13. Our work could facilitate the development of ultracompact chiral classical and quantum light sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09806v4</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Feng Pan, Xin Li, Amalya C. Johnson, Scott Dhuey, Ashley Saunders, Meng-Xia Hu, Jefferson P. Dixon, Sahil Dagli, Sze-Cheung Lau, Tingting Weng, Chih-Yi Chen, Jun-Hao Zeng, Rajas Apte, Tony F. Heinz, Fang Liu, Zi-Lan Deng, Jennifer A. Dionne</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fortuity in SYK Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06902</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06902v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the fortuity phenomenon in supersymmetric Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev (SYK) models. For generic choices of couplings, all the BPS states in the $\mathcal{N}=2$ SUSY SYK model are fortuitous. The SYK models reveal an intimate connection between fortuity and the Schwarzian description of supersymmetric black holes, reflected in a sharp feature of $R$-charge concentration - microscopically, all the fortuitous states are concentrated in particular charge sectors. We propose that both $R$-charge concentration and the random matrix behavior near the BPS states are key properties of a generic $q$-local supercharge and formulate these as a supercharge chaos conjecture. We expect supercharge chaos to hold universally for supercharges in holographic CFTs near their fortuitous states, potentially providing a microscopic interpretation for the charge constraints of supersymmetric black holes.
  We also construct SYK models that contain both fortuitous states and monotonous states and contrast their properties, providing further evidence that monotonous states are less chaotic than fortuitous states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06902v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chi-Ming Chang, Yiming Chen, Bik Soon Sia, Zhenbin Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information-theoretic principle of emergent 1-form symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17572v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Higher-form symmetries act on sub-dimensional spatial manifolds of a quantum system. They can emerge as an exact symmetry at low energies even when they are explicitly broken at the microscopic level, making them difficult to characterize. In this work, we propose that the emergence of 1-form symmetries is information-theoretic in nature, precisely characterized by the preservation of information about how quantum states transform under the symmetry. As a consequence, the loss of the emergent 1-form symmetry is an information-theoretic transition which we argue to be revealed from the long-range entanglement in the ensemble of post-measurement states. We analytically determine the regimes in which a 1-form symmetry emerges in product states on one- and two-dimensional lattices. In analytically intractable regimes, we demonstrate how to efficiently detect 1-form symmetries with a global quantum error correction (QEC) decoder and numerically examine the information-theoretic transition of the 1-form symmetry, including systems with $\mathbb{Z}_2$ topological order. As a practical application of our framework, we show that once the 1-form symmetry is detected to exist, a topological quantum phase transition characterized by the spontaneous breaking of the 1-form symmetry can be accurately determined by a disorder parameter. We further argue that our proposed theory for emergent 1-form symmetries offers new perspectives on particle condensation and suggests sharp information-theoretic phase boundaries between Higgs and confining regimes in the $\mathbb{Z}_2$ lattice gauge theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17572v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Jie Liu, Wen-Tao Xu, Frank Pollmann, Michael Knap</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-Phonon Relaxation of Boron-Vacancy Centers in Two-Dimensional Boron Nitride Polytypes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00154</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.00154v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2D) materials hosting color centers and spin defects are emerging as key platforms for quantum technologies. However, the impact of reduced dimensionality on the spin-lattice relaxation time ($T_1$) of embedded defect spins -- critical for quantum applications -- remains largely unexplored. In this study, we present a systematic first-principles investigation of the negatively charged boron-vacancy (V$_{\text{B}}^-$) defect in monolayer boron nitride (BN), as well as in AA$^\prime$-stacked hexagonal BN (hBN) and ABC-stacked rhombohedral BN (rBN). Our results reveal that the $T_1$ times of V$_{\text{B}}^-$ in monolayer BN and hBN are nearly identical at room temperature. Surprisingly, despite the symmetry reduction in rBN opening additional spin relaxation channels, V$_{\text{B}}^-$ exhibits a longer $T_1$ compared to hBN. We attribute this effect to the stiffer out-of-plane phonon modes in rBN, which activate spin-phonon relaxation at reduced strength. These findings suggest that V$_{\text{B}}^-$ in rBN offers enhanced spin coherence properties, making it a promising candidate for quantum technology applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.00154v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/gqfq-5rb4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, L201407 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nasrin Estaji, Ismaeil Abdolhosseini Sarsari, Gerg\H{o} Thiering, Adam Gali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General theory of perturbation of infinite resistor networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18654</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18654v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The effective resistance between any two nodes in a perturbed resistor network is determined by removing multiple bonds from an infinite resistor lattice. We have developed an efficient method for calculating the Green operator of the Laplacian for such perturbed networks, which is directly related to the two-point resistance. Unlike the recursive techniques that remove bonds one at a time, our approach handles all bond modifications simultaneously. To demonstrate the versatility of our method, several analytical and numerical examples are presented. In addition, we computed bond current distributions to gain deeper insight into the nature of resistor perturbations. We emphasize that our method has a broad range of applications, including condensed matter physics describing the quantum mechanical effects of impurities in crystal lattices, recently emerging topoelectronics, the study of vibrations in spring networks, and problems involving random walks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18654v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J\'ozsef Cserti, Gyula D\'avid</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Scaling Laws for Deep Regression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.10000v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Neural scaling laws--power-law relationships between generalization errors and characteristics of deep learning models--are vital tools for developing reliable models while managing limited resources. Although the success of large language models highlights the importance of these laws, their application to deep regression models remains largely unexplored. Here, we empirically investigate neural scaling laws in deep regression using a parameter estimation model for twisted van der Waals magnets. We observe power-law relationships between the loss and both training dataset size and model capacity across a wide range of values, employing various architectures--including fully connected networks, residual networks, and vision transformers. Furthermore, the scaling exponents governing these relationships range from 1 to 2, with specific values depending on the regressed parameters and model details. The consistent scaling behaviors and their large scaling exponents suggest that the performance of deep regression models can improve substantially with increasing data size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.10000v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tilen Cadez, Kyoung-Min Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computational complexity of Berry phase estimation in topological phases of matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13423</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13423v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Berry phase is a fundamental quantity in the classification of topological phases of matter. In this paper, we present a new quantum algorithm and several complexity-theoretical results for the Berry phase estimation (BPE) problems. Our new quantum algorithm achieves BPE in a more general setting than previously known quantum algorithms, with a theoretical guarantee. For the complexity-theoretic results, we consider three cases. First, we prove $\mathsf{BQP}$-completeness when we are given a guiding state that has a large overlap with the ground state. This result establishes an exponential quantum speedup for estimating the Berry phase. Second, we prove $\mathsf{dUQMA}$-completeness when we have $\textit{a priori}$ bound for ground state energy. Here, $\mathsf{dUQMA}$ is a variant of the unique witness version of $\mathsf{QMA}$ (i.e., $\mathsf{UQMA}$), which we introduce in this paper, and this class precisely captures the complexity of BPE without the known guiding state. Remarkably, this problem turned out to be the first natural problem contained in both $\mathsf{UQMA}$ and $\mathsf{co}$-$\mathsf{UQMA}$. Third, we show $\mathsf{P}^{\mathsf{dUQMA[log]}}$-hardness and containment in $\mathsf{P}^{\mathsf{PGQMA[log]}}$ when we have no additional assumption. These results advance the role of quantum computing in the study of topological phases of matter and provide a pathway for clarifying the connection between topological phases of matter and computational complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13423v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryu Hayakawa, Kazuki Sakamoto, Chusei Kiumi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Haag Duality for 2D Quantum Spin Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23734v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Haag duality is a fundamental locality property introduced in the pioneering formulation of algebraic quantum field theory by Haag and Kastler in the 1960s. Since then, it has played a central role, most notably in the classification of superselection sectors by Doplicher, Haag, and Roberts in the 1970s. Over the past two decades, this concept has migrated from its relativistic origins to quantum spin systems, becoming a cornerstone of the operator-algebraic approach to the long-standing problem of classifying two-dimensional topological quantum phases of matter. In physics, it is widely conjectured that such phases are classified by their emergent anyons, a view supported by exactly solvable models exemplifying all known non-chiral phases: Kitaev's quantum double models, Levin-Wen string-net models, and their slight generalizations. In these models, elementary excitations behave as quasi-particles, namely anyons, whose fusion and braiding properties form a tensor category expected to characterize the phase of matter. A major open problem was to derive the emergence of anyons and the stability of their fusion and braiding beyond these solvable models. Recently, it has been shown that a weaker, phase-stable form of Haag duality resolves these questions. However, rigorous proofs of Haag duality in two dimensions were previously restricted to systems exhibiting abelian anyons. In this work, we establish Haag duality for a broad class of tensor network models based on $C^*$-weak Hopf algebras, encompassing all Kitaev quantum double and Levin-Wen string-net models, and expected to include all non-chiral topological quantum phases of matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23734v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoshiko Ogata, David P\'erez-Garc\'ia, Alberto Ruiz-de-Alarc\'on</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perfect Particle Transmission through Duality Defects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26780</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26780v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study wavepackets that propagate across (a) topological interfaces in quantum spin systems exhibiting non-invertible symmetries and (b) duality defects coupling dual theories. We demonstrate that the transmission is always perfect, and that a particle traversing the interface is converted into a nonlocal string-like excitation. We give a systematic way of constructing such a defect by identifying its Hilbert space with the virtual bond dimension of the matrix product operator representing defect lines. Our work both gives an operational meaning to topological interfaces, and provides a lattice analogue of recent results solving the monopole paradox in quantum field theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26780v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Atsushi Ueda, Vic Vander Linden, Laurens Lootens, Jutho Haegeman, Paul Fendley, Frank Verstraete</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
