<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat</link>
    <description>cond-mat updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 04:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Observing Differential Spin Currents by Resonant Inelastic X-ray Scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05796</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.05796v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Controlling spin currents, i.e., the flow of spin angular momentum, in small magnetic devices is the principal objective of spin electronics, a main contender for future energy efficient information technologies. Surprisingly, a pure spin current has never been measured directly since the associated electric stray fields and/or shifts in the non-equilibrium spin-dependent distribution functions are too small for conventional experimental detection methods optimized for charge transport. Here we report that resonant inelastic x-ray scattering (RIXS) can bridge this gap by measuring the spin current carried by magnons -- the quanta of the spin wave excitations of the magnetic order -- in the presence of temperature gradients across a magnetic insulator. This is possible due to the sensitivity of the momentum- and energy-resolved RIXS intensity to minute changes in the magnon distribution under non-equilibrium conditions. We use the Boltzmann equation in the relaxation time approximation to extract transport parameters, such as the magnon lifetime at finite momentum, essential for the realization of magnon spintronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.05796v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanhong Gu, Joseph Barker, Jiemin Li, Takashi Kikkawa, Fernando Camino, Kim Kisslinger, John Sinsheimer, Lukas Lienhard, Jackson J. Bauer, Caroline A. Ross, Dmitri N. Basov, Eiji Saitoh, Jonathan Pelliciari, Gerrit E. W. Bauer, Valentina Bisogni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of Spin Current Generation by Elastic Waves in $f$-wave Altermagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.06027v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We theoretically investigate the mechanism of spin current generation induced by elastic waves in nonrelativistic magnets referred to as altermagnets. By analyzing an $f$-wave altermagnet formed by a three-sublattice noncollinear antiferromagnetic structure breaking the spatial inversion symmetry on a two-dimensional triangular lattice within the linear response theory, we show that the nonrelativistic antisymmetric spin-split band structure can give rise to spin current generation when either longitudinal or transverse elastic wave is applied. We find that the momentum dependence of the antisymmetric spin splitting leads to a characteristic direction-dependent spin current response. We also compare the present nonrelativistic magnetic-order-driven mechanism with the relativistic one in a nonmagnetic Rashba system. These findings highlight the potential of invesion-symmetry-breaking altermagnets as a spin current generator driven by elasticity without relying on the relativistic spin-orbit coupling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.06027v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ken Uchino, Yuuki Ogawa, Satoru Hayami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological bound states in a lattice of rings with nearest-neighbour interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06272</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.06272v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study interaction-induced bound states in a system of ultracold bosons loaded into the states with orbital angular momentum in a one-dimensional staggered lattice of rings. We consider the hard-core limit and strong nearest-neighbour interactions such that two particles in next neighbouring sites are bound. Focusing on the manifold of such bound states, we have derived the corresponding effective model for doublons. With orbital angular momentum $l=1$, the original physical system is described as a Creutz ladder by using the circulations as a synthetic dimension, and the effective model obtained consists of two Su-Schrieffer-Heeger (SSH) chains and two Bose-Hubbard chains. Therefore, the system can exhibit topologically protected edge states. In a structure that alternates $l=1$ and $l=0$ states, the original system can be mapped to a diamond chain. In this case, the effective doublon model corresponds to a Creutz ladder with extra vertical hoppings between legs and can be mapped to two SSH chains if all the couplings in the original system are equal. Tuning spatially the amplitude of the couplings destroys the inversion symmetry of these SSH chains, but enables the appearance of multiple flat bands.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.06272v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunjia Zhai, Ayaka Usui, Anselmo M. Marques, Ricardo G. Dias, Ver\`onica Ahufinger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiorbital character of the density wave instability in La$_4$Ni$_3$O$_{10}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06440</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.06440v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ruddlesden-Popper nickelates exhibit high-temperature superconductivity closely intertwined with charge and spin density wave order. However, fundamental questions persist regarding the interplay between the associated density wave (DW) fluctuations and superconductivity, as well as the orbital character and symmetry underlying the DW instabilities. Here we utilize polarized Raman scattering to investigate the phononic and electronic Raman responses of the trilayer nickelate La$_4$Ni$_3$O$_{10}$ across its concomitant charge and spin density wave transitions. In addition to distinct phonon anomalies occurring below the transition temperature, we observe a depletion of continuum spectral weight up to 114 meV and a pronounced peak centered at this energy. By combining momentum-selective information from polarized electronic Raman scattering with model calculations involving both Ni-3$d_{x^2 - y^2}$ and Ni-3$d_{z^2}$ orbitals, we identify 114 meV as the energy scale $2\Delta_\mathrm{DW}$ of the DW gap, characterized by incoherent opening and non-mean-field behavior. Furthermore, the model calculations reveal that the corresponding $2\Delta_\mathrm{DW}$ peak exhibits a multiorbital origin, thus shedding light on the nature of the DW instabilities in La$_4$Ni$_3$O$_{10}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.06440v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Suthar, V. Sundaramurthy, M. Bejas, Congcong Le, P. Puphal, P. Sosa-Lizama, A. Schulz, J. Nuss, M. Isobe, P. A. van Aken, Y. E. Suyolcu, M. Minola, A. P. Schnyder, Xianxin Wu, B. Keimer, G. Khaliullin, A. Greco, M. Hepting</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetization-induced reordering of ground states phase diagram in a two-component Bose-Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.06442v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the influence of non-zero magnetization on the ground-state phase diagram of the two-component Bose-Hubbard model. Employing a mean-field theoretical framework, both analytically and numerically, we demonstrate that positions and sizes of specific phases on the diagram are magnetization dependent. In particular, non-zero magnetization introduces different Mott insulator phase boundaries for each of the two components. This effect leads to the emergence of a hybrid phase characterized by the coexistence of superfluid in one of the components and Mott insulator in the another one. Our findings highlight the important role of a conserved quantities, which is magnetization here, in reshaping the phase landscape, significantly influencing the stability and emergence of distinct quantum phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.06442v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oskar Stachowiak, Hubert Dunikowski, Emilia Witkowska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of momentum dependent charge density wave gap in EuTe4</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.06464v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The occurrence of charge density wave (CDW) phenomena, particularly in low dimensional rare-earth chalcogenides, has attracted substantial research interest. Among these materials, EuTe4, which features multiple Te layers and a single Eu-Te layer, serves as a promising platform to study the interplay between CDW order and 4f electron configurations, including magnetism. In this study, First principles based density functional theory (DFT) calculations were carried out to investigate the electronic band structure modifications arising from CDW modulation. Angle resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) revealed the emergence of a CDW gap at the Fermi level, as well as hybridization induced gap features at lower binding energies. The low lying CDW gap reaches its maximum along the Gamma-Y high-symmetry direction and a minimum along GX reflecting the anisotropic nature of the electronic structure. We also performed low temperature heat capacity measurements in applied magnetic fields near the Neel temperature (TN ~ 6.9 K) to construct the magnetic phase diagram of EuTe4. This study provides valuable insight into the directional dependent evolution of the Fermi surface nesting induced CDW ordering, along with other observed gap openings within this system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.06464v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Iftakhar Bin Elius, Nathan Valadez, Gyanendra Dhakal, Volodymyr Buturlim, Sabin Regmi, Dante James, Peter Radanovich, Matthew Yankowitz, Tetiana Romanova, Andrzej Ptok, Krzysztof Gofryk, Dariusz Kaczorowski, Madhab Neupane</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4D operando X-ray nano-holo-tomography reveals multiscale chemomechanics in Silicon-Graphite anode</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.06413v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Linking electrode microstructure to electrochemical performance is essential for optimizing Li-ion batteries. However, this requires mechanistic 4D observations at ultimate spatio-temporal scales, which remains elusive. Here we demonstrate the use of operando synchrotron X-ray nano-holo-tomography combined with Digital Volume Correlation to track chemomechanical dynamics at both particle (local) and electrode (averaged) scales. Quantitative scale-bridging image analysis is applied to a high-capacity silicon-graphite anode during its formation cycle. Our findings reveal that local diffusion properties, graphite particle morphology and position in the electrode, distance to silicon clusters, surface contact with electrolyte and mechanical deformations, all have a direct impact on the local electrochemical activity and irreversibility - but these parameters are not equally important. Particularly, we identify fast diffusion channels that play a key role and counterbalance intrinsic depth-dependent reaction heterogeneities due to ionic/electronic diffusion limitations. The various structural factors that determine Gr-Si battery performance beyond ensemble properties are classified using a scale of influence, providing a practical framework for the optimization of materials and electrode manufacturing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.06413v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor Vanpeene, Olga Stamati, Francois Cadiou, Quentin Jacquet, Julie Villanova, Sandrine Lyonnard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bipartite Fluctuations of Critical Fermi Surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04331</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04331v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Fluctuations of conserved quantities within a subsystem are non-local observables that provide unique insights into quantum many-body systems. In this paper, we study bipartite charge (and spin) fluctuations across interaction-driven ``metal-insulator transitions'' out of Landau Fermi liquids. The ``charge insulators'' include a class of non-Fermi-liquid states of fractionalized degrees of freedom, such as compressible composite Fermi liquids (for spinless electrons) and incompressible spin-liquid Mott insulators (for spin-$1/2$ electrons). We find that charge fluctuations $F$ exhibit distinct leading-order scalings across the transition: $F \sim L\log(L)$ in Landau Fermi liquids and $F \sim L$ in charge insulators, where $L$ is the linear size of the subsystem. In composite Fermi liquids, under certain conditions, we also identify a universal constant term $-f(\theta)|\sigma_{xy}|/(2\pi)$ when the subsystem geometry contains a sharp corner, where $f(\theta)$ denotes a function of the corner angle, and $\sigma_{xy}$ is the Hall conductivity. At the critical point, provided the transition is continuous, the leading scaling $F\sim L$ is accompanied by a subleading universal corner contribution $-\log(L)f(\theta)C_{\rho}/2$ with the same angle dependence $f(\theta)$, and the universal coefficient $C_{\rho}$ is directly related to the predicted universal jumps in longitudinal and Hall resistivities. These results establish fluctuation-transport relations, paving the way for numerical and experimental studies of unconventional quantum criticalities in metals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04331v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/dflw-rksw</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. X 15, 031035 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xiao-Chuan Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charge ordering and spontaneous topological Hall effect in bilayer skyrmion crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.04520</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.04520v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Magnetic skyrmion crystals with zero net skyrmion charge and zero topological Hall response are interesting candidate phases which can occur at a vanishing magnetic field in centrosymmetric systems. We study a minimal bilayer model of skyrmion crystals having opposite chirality and topological charge in the two layers, and show that it can host nearly flat electronic bands with quasi-uniform Berry curvature and quantum metric. Using Hartree-Fock theory, we show that weak to moderate short-range electron interactions induce two distinct types of symmetry breaking patterns depending on the band dispersion: an intra-unit-cell charge density modulation from Chern band mixing or a layer-imbalanced phase with a nonzero ferroelectric polarization. Both phases break inversion symmetry leading to a spontaneous and large net topological Hall effect, with the phase diagram tunable by external electric fields. Our results may be relevant to centrosymmetric skyrmion materials such as Gd$_2$PdSi$_3$ and Gd$_3$Ru$_4$Al$_{12}$ as well as artificially engineered heterostructures. We also discuss its relation to recent work on twisted transition metal dichalcogenide bilayers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.04520v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.115115</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, 115115, 5 March, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Hardy, Anjishnu Bose, Tanmay Grover, Arun Paramekanti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coulomb-driven Momentum Space Condensation in Rhombohedral Hexalayer Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.09954v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In systems of strongly correlated electrons, the emergence of spontaneous symmetry breaking serves as a defining hallmark of the underlying many-body physics. Here, we report the discovery of an unprecedented emerging order in rhombohedral hexalayer graphene, defined by the intertwinement of rotational, time-reversal, and inversion symmetry breaking. The link between these broken symmetries is uncovered through angle-resolved transport measurements. The spontaneous breaking of rotational symmetry is identified by the Curie-Weiss behavior in the temperature-dependent onset of transport anisotropy. Most remarkably, the nematic transition, defined by the cusp of transport anisotropy, coincides with the emergence of the anomalous Hall effect in both the linear and nonlinear regimes. Our findings provide unambiguous experimental evidence of spontaneous condensation in momentum space, a phenomenon previously proposed to arise from a Coulomb-driven flocking effect. Together, these observations establish electronic anisotropy as a fundamental organizing principle in the landscape of intertwined electronic orders in strongly correlated two-dimensional systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.09954v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erin Morissette, Peiyu Qin, K. Watanabe, T. Taniguchi, J. I. A. Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Striped Superconductor in Rhombohedral Hexalayer Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05129</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.05129v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The nature of a superconductor is fundamentally determined by the symmetries broken in its order parameter. Here, we report an exceptionally exotic superconducting phase in rhombohedral hexalayer graphene that simultaneously breaks rotational, translational, and time-reversal symmetries. We show that superconductivity emerges from a quarter-metallic state and is accompanied by the onset of stripe charge order. This unique intertwinement is revealed by angle-resolved transport measurements, which demonstrate dissipationless current confined to a single principal axis-forming one-dimensional-like superconducting channels -- while the orthogonal direction remains resistive down to the lowest temperatures. The formation of stripe order is marked by a first-order melting transition, evidenced by pronounced thermal hysteresis upon warming and cooling. In addition, magnetic-field-induced switching between superconducting states -- reminiscent of behavior previously observed in rhombohedral tetra- and pentalayer graphene -- signals time-reversal symmetry breaking. Collectively, these observations reveal a previously unrecognized quantum phase: a chiral superconductor embedded within a stripe-ordered anomalous Hall state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.05129v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erin Morissette, Peiyu Qin, Hai-Tian Wu, Naiyuan J. Zhang, Ron Q. Nguyen, K. Watanabe, T. Taniguchi, J. I. A. Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unconventional Altermagnetism in Quasicrystals: A Hyperspatial Projective Construction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01564v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Altermagnetism, a novel magnetic phase characterized by symmetry-protected, momentum-dependent spin splitting and collinear compensated magnetic moments, has thus far been explored primarily in periodic crystals. In this Letter, we extend the concept of altermagnetism to quasicrystals -- aperiodic systems with long-range order and noncrystallographic rotational symmetries. Using a hyperspatial projection framework, we construct decorated Ammann-Beenker and Penrose quasicrystalline lattices with inequivalent sublattices and investigate a Hubbard model with anisotropic hopping. We demonstrate that interaction-induced N\'eel order on such lattices gives rise to alternating spin-polarized spectral functions that reflect the underlying quasicrystalline symmetry, revealing the emergence of unconventional $g$-wave (octagonal) and $h$-wave (decagonal) altermagnetism. Our symmetry analysis and low-energy effective theory further reveal unconventional altermagnetic spin splitting, which is compatible with quasicrystalline rotational symmetry. Our work shows that quasicrystals provide a fertile ground for realizing unconventional altermagnetic phases beyond crystallographic constraints, offering a platform for novel magnetisms and transport phenomena unique to quasiperiodic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01564v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiming Li, Mingxiang Pan, Jun Leng, Yuxiao Chen, Huaqing Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
